<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A15515">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Cobbler's Prophecy <date type="creation_date">1590</date></title>
        <author>Wilson, Robert</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A15515.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The coblers prophesie. Written by Robert Wilson. Gent.</title>
            <author>Wilson, Robert, d. 1600.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>27 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2005 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99847078</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 25781.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 124.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">12088</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15515</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The coblers prophesie. Written by Robert Wilson. Gent.</title>
            <author>Wilson, Robert, d. 1600.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[56] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>By Iohn Danter for Cuthbert Burbie: and are to be sold at his shop nere the Royall-Exchange,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1594.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Mostly in verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-G4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A" with rows of ornaments; the last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A15515-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A15515-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A15515-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <p xml:id="A15515-e100040">The cobblers prophesy.</p>
        <p xml:id="A15515-e100050">Written by Robert Wilson. gent.</p>
        <p xml:id="A15515-e100060">Printed at London by John Danter for Cuthbert Burbie: and are to be sold at his shop near the Royal-exchange. 1594.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A15515-e100070">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A15515-e100080">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>The cobblers prophesy.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e100090">Enter Jupiter and Juno, Mars and Venus, Apollo, after him, Bacchus, Vulcan limping, and after all Diana wringing her hands: they pass by, while on the stage Mercury from one end Ceres from another meet.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100100" who="A15515-ceres">
          <speaker>Ceres.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100110">Fresh Maia's son, fine witcrafts greatest god,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100120">Herald of heaven, soul charming Mercury:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100130">Tell, for thou wit'st, why these celestial powers</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100140">Are thus assembled in Boeotia. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100150" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mercury:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100160">Plenty's rich Queen, cheerer of fainting souls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100170">Whose altars are adorned with ripened sheaves. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100180">Know that security chief nurse of sin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100190">Hath bred contempt in all Boeotia. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100200">The old are scorned of the wanton young,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100210">Unhallowed hands, and hearts impurer far,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100220">Rend down the altars sacred to the gods. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100230"><pb facs="4"/>Heaven is long suffering, and eternal powers</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100240">Are full of pity to perversest men:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100250">Which made the awful ruler of the rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100260">Summon this meeting of the heavenly states:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100270">The first was Jupiter, Juno with him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100280">Next Mars and Venus, him I know you knew not,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100290">His harness is converted to soft silk ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100300">His wars are only wantonings with her,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100310">That scandalizeth heaven and heaps world's hate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100320">Apollo next, than Bacchus belly-god,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100330">And horned Vulcan forger of heaven's fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100340">The last poor Cynthia making woeful moan,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100350">That she is left sweet virgin post alone. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100360">I am but messenger, and must not denounce</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100370">Till the high senate of the gods decree it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100380">But sacred Ceres, if I may divine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100390">In heaven shall Venus vaunt but little time. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100400" who="A15515-ceres">
          <speaker>Ceres:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100410">So pleased it mighty Jove the doom were just,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100420">Amongst that holy train what needs there lust. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100430" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mercury:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100440">I see a sort of wondering gazing eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100450">That do await the end of this conceit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100460">Whom Mercury with waving of his rod,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100470">And holy spells enjoins to sit and see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100480">Th'effectual working of a prophecy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100490" who="A15515-ceres">
          <speaker>Ceres:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100500">And Ceres sheds her sweetest sweets in plenty,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e100510">Cast comfets.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100520">That while ye stay their pleasure may content ye. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100530">Now do I leave thee Mercury, and will into take my place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100540">Do what thou canst in wanton lusts disgrace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100550" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mercury:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100560">Ceres I will, and now I am alone</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100570">Will I advise me of a messenger</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100580">That will not faint: will not said I? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100590">Nay shall not faint sent forth by Mercury. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100600">I am resolved, the next I meet with be it he or she,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100610">To do this message shall be sent by me. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e100620">Enter Raph cobbler with his stool, his implements and shoes,<pb facs="4"/> and sitting on his stool, falls to sing,</stage>
          <floatingText xml:id="A15515-e100630">
            <body xml:id="A15515-e100640">
              <div type="song" xml:id="A15515-e100650">
                <l xml:id="A15515-e100660">Heigh down down a down a down,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e100670">Heigh down down a down a,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e100680">Our beauty is the bravest lass in all the town a ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e100690">For beauty's sweet sake, I sleep when I should wake,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e100700">She is so nut brown a. </l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e100710">Her cheeks so red as a cherry, do make my heart full merry ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e100720">So that I cannot choose in cobling of my shoes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e100730">But sing heigh derry derry down derry. </l>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e100740">Zelota his wife within.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100750" who="A15515-zelota">
          <speaker>Zelota:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100760">Go too Raph you'll still be singing love songs it's your fashion. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100770" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100780">Content yourself wife, 'tis my own recantation,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100790">No love song neither, but a carol in beauty's condemnation</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100800" who="A15515-zelota">
          <speaker>Ze:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100810">Well year best leave singing and fall to work by and by</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100820">While I to buy meat for our dinner to market do hie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100830" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>R:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100840">And you were best leave your scolding to, and get you away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100850" who="A15515-zelota">
          <speaker>Z:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100860">And I come to you Raph, I'll course ye as I did a Saturday</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100870" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>R:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100880">Course me snown, I would thou durst come out of door,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100890">And thou dost I'll knock thee on the head thou arrant thou.</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100900">Was not this lustily spoken? I warrant she dare not come out</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e100910">Enter Zelota ▪</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100920" who="A15515-zelota">
          <speaker>Ze:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100930">I'll see what you'll do, where are ye goodman lout? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e100940">He creeps under the stool.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100950" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Ra:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100960">O nobody tell her that I am under the stool. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100970" who="A15515-zelota">
          <speaker>Ze:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e100980">Where's this prating ass, this dizzardly fool. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e100990" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101000">Why here I am dame, let's see what thou canst say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101010">Bestir your distaff, do the worst ye may. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101020" who="A15515-zelota">
          <speaker>Ze:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101030">Alas that ever I was born to see this sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101040">My Raph is transformed to a wicked spright. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101050" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Ra:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101060">She lies i'faith, I am here under the stool. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101070" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101080">Let me alone Raph, hold thy peace thou fool ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101090">I am a sprite indeed, a fiend which will pursue thee still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101100">Until I take a full revenge of all thy proffered ill ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101110">And for thy former dealings to thy husband hath been bad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101120">I charm thee and inchant thee quean,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101130">Thou henceforth shalt be mad:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101140"><pb facs="5"/> and never shall thy foolish brain cut off this frantic fit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101150">Till with thy hand unwillingly thou murder do commit. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e101160">He charmes her with his rod.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101170" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Rap:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101180">Nay she is mad enough already,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101190">For she will do nothing with me but fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101200">And ye make her more mad, she'll kill me out right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101210" who="A15515-zelota">
          <speaker>Zel:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101220">Make me mad Raph, no faith Raph,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101230">Though thou be a devil and a spright,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101240">Ne'er toll the bell, I'll not be gossip,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101250">The child shall not be christened tonight . </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101260">Go to the backhouse for the boy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101270">Bid the tankard bring the conduit home. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101280">I'll buy no plum porridge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101290">I'll not be made such a mome. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101300">And because thou hast a fine rod Raph,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101310">I'll look in thy purse by and by:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101320">And if thou have any money in it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101330">We'll drink the devil dry, devil dry, etc. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e101340">Here she runs about the stage snatching at every thing she sees.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101350" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101360">Out of doubt she is mad indeed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101370">See what a coil she doth keep,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101380" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101390">Raph she shall trouble none of us, I'll charm her fast asleep . </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101400" who="A15515-zelota">
          <speaker>Zel:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101410">Come Raph, let's go sleep, for thou must mend</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101420">Queen Guiniver's shoes tomorrow. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101430">I have a pillow of my own, I'll neither beg nor borrow. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e101440">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101450" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101460">So sleep thy fill, now Raph come forth to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101470" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101480">Come forth quoth he marry God bless us.</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101490">Now you have made my wife mad what shall become of me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101500" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mar:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101510">Fear not come forth, I mean no hurt to thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101520" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Rap:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101530">Well I'll trust you for once, what say ye. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101540" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101550">Raph hie thee home, and thou shalt find upon thy bed</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101560">Attire that for a prophet's suit shall stand thee in good stead</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101570">A prophet thou must be and leave thy work a while. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101580" who="A15515-raphe">
          <pb facs="5"/>
          <speaker>Raph</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101590">A prophet speaker? Ha, ha, ha, here's a coil. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101600">What are you, I pray? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101610" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101620">I am Mercury the messenger of the gods. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101630" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101640">And I am Raph cobbler, twixt us there is some odds. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101650">But hear ye God markedy, have you th'authority</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101660">To take a free man of his company,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101670">And hinder him to be your prophet speaker,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101680">And when ye set him a work give him nothing for his labour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101690" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101700">I must charm him asleep, or he will still be prating. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101710">I'll please thee well, I pray thee Raph sit down. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101720" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101730">Now I am set, would I had a pot of ale. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e101740" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101750">We will have twain, but first attend my tale. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e101760">He charmes him with his rod asleep.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101770">Not far hence standeth Mars his court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e101780">To whom thus see thou say,</l>
          <floatingText xml:id="A15515-e101790">
            <body xml:id="A15515-e101800">
              <div type="prophecy" xml:id="A15515-e101810">
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101820">Mars though thou be a cock of the game,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101830">That wontst to crow by day,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101840">And with thy sharpened spurs</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101850">The craven cock's didst kill and slay:</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101860">Sith now thou dost but prune thy wings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101870">And make thy feathers gay:</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101880">A dunghill cock that crows by night,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101890">Shall slily thee betray,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101900">And tread thy hen, and for a time</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101910">Shall carry her away. </l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101920">And she by him shall hatch a chick,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101930">This country to decay. </l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101940">And for this pretty pullet's name</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101950">Thou shalt the better learn:</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101960">When thou shalt only letters five</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101970">Within one name discern,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101980">Three vowels and two consonants,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e101990">Which vowels if thou scan,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e102000">Doth sound that which to every pace</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e102010">Conducteth every man. </l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e102020"><pb facs="6"/>Then call to mind this prophecy,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e102030">For that's the bastard's name:</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e102040">Then rouse thyself, then reach thy sword,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e102050">And win thy wonted fame. </l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e102060">Now Raph awake, for I have done</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e102070">The task for which I came. </l>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e102080">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e102090">Raph stretches himself, and wakes.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102100" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102110">Heigh ho, wake quoth you, I think 'tis time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102120">For I have slept soundly:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102130">And methought in my sleep this was God Markedy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102140">That had chanted my wife mad for good cause why. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102150">Above methought I saw God shebiter,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102160">That mar'lously did frown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102170">With a dart of fire in his hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102180">Ready to throw it down. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102190">Below methought there were false knaves</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102200">Walking like honest men very craftily:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102210">And few or none could be plainly seen</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102220">To thrive in the world by honesty. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102230">Methought I saw one that was wondrous fat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102240">Pick two men's purses while they were striving for a gnat. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102250">And some that dwelled in streets were large and fair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102260">Kept back shops to utter their baddest ware. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102270">What meddle I with trades? Men masters and maids,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102280">Yea and wives too and all are too too bad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102290">Be judged by my wife, that was never well till she ran mad. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102300">But oh the baker, how he played false with the balance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102310">And ran away from the takers talons. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102320">The brewer was as bad, the butcher as ill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102330">For it's their trick to blow up lean meat with a quill ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102340">And with the stroke a butcher gave an ox</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102350">That loud bellowing did make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102360">I lost sight of all the other tricks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102370">And so suddenly did wake. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102380">But now must Raph trudge about his prophetation,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102390">Faith ye shall hear me troll it out after my fashion. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e102400">Exit.</stage>
        <pb facs="6"/>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e102410">Enter sateros a soldier, and contempt naming himself content. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102420" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102430">Thus have I served in my prince's wars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102440">Against the Persian and the Asian powers:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102450">The coal-black Moor that revels in the straits</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102460">Have I repelled with my loss of blood. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102470">My scars are witness of my hard escapes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102480">My wrinkles in my face (Made old by care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102490">When yet my years are in their chiefest prime)</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102500">Are glasses of my grief, lights of my languor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102510">That live disgraced, and have deserved honour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102520" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Cont:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102530">I am the admiredst in Boeotia,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102540">By honouring me thou shalt obtain preferment. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102550" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102560">Unto the gods and prince do soldiers honour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102570">And wert thou one of these, I would adore thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102580" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Cont:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102590">I am of power more than all the gods</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102600">To sit and rule the hearts of all degrees. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102610">They have in me content, as thou shalt see</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102620">A present instance in these entring men. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e102630">Enter Emnius a courtier, with him a scholar, and a country gentleman.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102640" who="A15515-countrygentleman">
          <speaker>Contr:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102650">Haile to contents divinest excellence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102660" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102670">Content our sweetest good, we do salute thee ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102680" who="A15515-courtier">
          <speaker>Courtier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102690">Though last I am not least in duteous kindness</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102700">To thee content although thou be no god,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102710">Yet greater in account than all of them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102720" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e102730">But if ye knew his name were Olygoros, which signifieth contempt, you would not mistake him, and name him content.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102740" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Cont:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e102750">O mas. scholar be patient, for though you like not my name, you love my nature: and therefore gentlemen forward with the discourse intended at our last meeting: and in that conference this gentleman a soldier, I presume will make one.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102760" who="A15515-courtier">
          <speaker>Courtier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e102770">Being a soldier, his company is fit for any honest gentleman, and therefore welcome into our company.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102780" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e102790">I thank you sir.</p>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e102800"><gap extent="2" unit="pages" xml:id="A15515-e102810" n="6-b-3450"/><pb facs="7"/>May say to you with some surplusage: my wood they bring me home, my hay and corn in harvest: their cattle, servants, sons, and selves, are at my command.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102820" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102830">O iure, quaque iniuria. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102840" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102850">Nay and you speak Latin, reach me my last. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102860">Hark ye mas. scholar, hark ye. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102870">The time shall come not long before the doom,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102880">That in despite of room,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102890">Lat in shall lack,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102900">And greek shall beg with a wallet at his back. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102910">For all are not sober that goes in black. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102920">Go too scholar, there's a learning for your knack. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102930" who="A15515-countrygentleman">
          <speaker>Contr:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e102940">At my list can I rack their rends, set them to fines, bind them to forfeits, force them to what I please. If I build, they be my labourers: if bargain, on them I build: and for my good look they are content to endure any travel.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e102950" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102960">But for all this ill and wrong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102970">Mark the cobbler's song. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102980">The high hill and the deep ditch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e102990">Which ye digged to make yourselves rich,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103000">The chimneys so many, and alms not any,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103010">The widows woeful cries,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103020">And babes in street that lies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103030">The bitter sweat and pain</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103040">That tenants poor sustain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103050">Will turn to your bane I tell ye plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103060">When burning fire shall rain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103070">And fill with botch and blain</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103080">The sinew and each vain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103090">Then these poor that cry,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103100">Being lifted up on high,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103110">When you are all forlorn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103120">Shall laugh you loud to scorn. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103130">Then where will be the scholar's allegories,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103140">Where the lawyer with his dilatories,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103150">Where the courtier with his bravery,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103160"><pb facs="7"/> and the money monging mate with all his knavery ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103170">Bethink me can I nowhere else,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103180">But in hell where dives dwells. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103190">But I see ye care not yet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103200">And think these words for me unfit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103210">And guess I speak for lack of wit:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103220">Stand aside, stand aside, for I am disposed to spit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103230" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Cont:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103240">Be quiet cobbler, let's hear the scholar speak!</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103250" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103260">I give him retority: to it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103270" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103280">What the courtier dreamingly possesses, the country gentleman with curses, and the soldier with cares: I quietly enjoy without control. In my study I contemplate what can be done in battles, and with my pen hurt more than thousands do with pikes, I strike him that sees me not.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103290" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103300">I thought you were a proper man of your hands to come behind one.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103310" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103320">I see the height of heaven.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103330" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103340">But thou makest no haste thither.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103350" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103360">I view the depth of hell.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103370" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103380">Is there any room in hell for cursed wives and cobbler's shops.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103390" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103400">Content is my landlord, peace and quiet are my companions, I am not with the courtier bound to dance attendance; nor with the countryman bind I others to attend on me. I possess pleasure more than mortal, and my contemplation is only of the life immortal.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103410" who="A15515-courtier">
          <speaker>Courtier:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103420">But you would be glad to creep in credit in the court scholar, and not be curious of the means, for all your coyness.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103430" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103440">I will not acquaint you sir with my intent, for they are fools that in secret affairs are too familiar, know this, that I intend to await occasion.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103450" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103460">Faith master scholar yet it stands not with your protestation.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103470" who="A15515-country_gentleman">
          <speaker>Country gentleman:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103480">Nor with you soldier to be thus blunt after your rude fashion.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103490" who="A15515-soldier">
          <pb facs="8"/>
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103500">Alas sir, you must needs be excellent: for Piers and plain your poor tenants pray for ye: their bread and cheese is seldom denied to any, when your small beer is scarce common to many. You know what will be made of a fat ox as well as the grazier, of the tallow as well as the butcher, of a tod of wool as well as the stapler.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103510" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <speaker>Country-gentleman</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103520">What hath any man to do what I do with mine own?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103530" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>S.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103540">I all's thine own that comes in thy hands.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103550" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <speaker>Country-gentleman</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103560">Sir you would make enough of it in yours to.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103570" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103580">I master courtier, that's to deal as you do.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103590" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103600">This soldier is as rough as if he were in the field ▪</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103610" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103620">Where you would be as tame.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103630" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Cont:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103640">Has a proud heart though a beggar's habit.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103650" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103660">Where I frequent this habit serves my turn: and as goodly a sight were it to see you there in your silks, as the scholar skirmishing in his long gown, or the country gentleman riding on a fat ox with a mole spade on his neck.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103670" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103680">What, riding running, braving, bralling,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103690">I see ye pass not for a prophet's calling:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103700">Therefore I will not be so mad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103710">To cast pearls to swine so bad. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103720" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Cont:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103730">Prithee Raph stay a little. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103740" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103750">Little little seeing God, I shall see you in a spittle. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e103760">Ex.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103770" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Con:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103780">Your disputation being done gentlemen, which hath highly contented me? what will ye now do?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103790" who="A15515-emnius">
          <speaker>Emn:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103800">Marry we will all to the eighteen pence ordinary, how say ye gentlemen?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103810" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <speaker>Country-gentleman</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103820">No sir, not I, 'tis too dear by my faith. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103830" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103840">Why you shall be my guest for this once. How say you master soldier?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103850" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103860">No sir I must turn one of your meals into three. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103870">And every one a sufficient banquet for me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103880" who="A15515-courtier">
          <speaker>Courtier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103890">Faith and you had kept your news until now, ye should have been my guest ▪ for your talk would have served well for the table.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103900" who="A15515-soldier">
          <pb facs="8"/>
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e103910">That's a practice of thine own art: it makes thy company born withal, where otherwise thou wert no fit guest, for tales at some tables are as good as testerns.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103920" who="A15515-courtier">
          <speaker>Courtier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103930">Nay then I perceive ye grow choleric, come sirs,</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e103940">They proffer to go in.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103950" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Cont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103960">Why gentlemen, no farewell to your little God. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103970" who="A15515-all_voices">
          <speaker>All three:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e103980">Suffice it without vain ceremonies we show ourselves dutiful. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e103990" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Con:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104000">'Tis enough, fare ye well. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e104010">Exeunt courtier, scholar, country.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104020" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Contempt:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104030">Now soldier, what wilt thou do? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104040" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104050">Faith sir as I may. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104060" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Cont:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e104070">Wilt thou serve me, and do as I will thee, and thou shalt not want.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104080" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e104090">No: for if thy name be contempt as the scholar said, I abhor and defy thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104100" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Con:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e104110">Even as the child doth wormseed hid in raisins, which of itself he cannot brook: so thou canst not abide my name, but lovest my nature: for proof, wanting living rail'st on the city, griev'st at the country, yea grudgest at the King himself: thou sayest thou art going to thy patron Mars with a supplication for bettering thy estate, and how, by war: where how many rapes, wrongs and murders are committed, thyself be judge, all which thou esteemest not off, so thy own want be supplied.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104120" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104130">Contempt herein thou reasonest like thyself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104140">Base minded men I know there are in field,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104150">That do delight in murder, rape and blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104160">As there are tares in corn and weeds with flowers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104170">And envious snakes among the fleeting fish:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104180">But for the noble soldier, he is just</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104190">To punish wrongs, protect the innocent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104200">Weaken the tyrant ▪ and confirm the right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104210">Want cannot make him basely mutinous,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104220">Wealth cannot make him proudly insolent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104230">In honourable thoughts dwell his content,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104240">And he is foe to all that love contempt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104250" who="A15515-contempt">
          <pb facs="9"/>
          <speaker>Contempt:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104260">Then sateros thou art no mate for me</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e104270">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104280" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104290">No, Upstarted scorners are fit slaves for thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e104300">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e104310">Enter Clio, Melpomine, and Thalia: Clio with a penknife, Melpomine being idle, Thalia writing. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104320" who="A15515-thalia">
          <speaker>Thalia:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104330">Clio a pen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104340" who="A15515-clio">
          <speaker>Clio:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104350">Both pen and quill I miss. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104360" who="A15515-thalia">
          <speaker>Thalia:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104370">One ostrich pen yet in my penner is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104380">Quickly take that and make a pen for me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104390" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Melpomine:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e104400">The feathers of a gluttonous bird show what the wearers be.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104410" who="A15515-thalia">
          <speaker>Thalia:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104420">Melpomene lend me a pen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104430" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Melpom:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104440">Mine pierce too hard for your writing. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e104450">Enter Raph cobbler.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104460" who="A15515-thalia">
          <speaker>Thalia:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104470">Quickly a pen, ha, ha, fond foolish men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104480" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104490">Fool? no fool neither though none of the wisest dame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104500">But a prophet one of Merlin's kind I am. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104510" who="A15515-unassigned">
          <speaker>Mil:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104520">Art thou a prophet, what's thy name? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104530" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104540">Raph Cob </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104550" who="A15515-clio">
          <speaker>Clio:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104560">●er, speak out. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104570" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104580">Ye ha' it i'faith. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104590" who="A15515-thalia">
          <speaker>Thal:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104600">A pen a pen in haste,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104610">That I may write this pageant ere it be past. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104620" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e104630">Comes there a pageant by, I'll stand out of the green men's way for burning my vestment.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104640" who="A15515-thalia">
          <speaker>Thal:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104650">A pen good Clio, fie how ye make me stay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104660" who="A15515-clio">
          <speaker>Clio:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104670">Make shift awhile you shall have this straight way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104680" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104690">If I had a pen as I have none,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104700">For I use no such tool,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104710">Thou shouldst have none an it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104720">For at my first coming thou calld'st me fool. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104730" who="A15515-thalia">
          <speaker>Tha:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104740">A pen a pen, it will be gone incontinent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104750" who="A15515-clio">
          <speaker>Clio:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104760">Hold there's thy pen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104770" who="A15515-raphe">
          <pb facs="9"/>
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e104780">But are you the gods of the scriveners, that you make pens so fast trow we.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e104790">Enter soldier.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104800" who="A15515-clio">
          <speaker>Clio:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104810">O sisters shift we are betrayed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104820">Another man I see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104830" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104840">A silly man at your command,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104850">Be not afraid of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104860" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e104870">No, no, 'tis the soldier, he'll do ye no hurt I warrant ye.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104880" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Melpom:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104890">To see a man come in this place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104900">It is so strange to us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104910">As we are to be held excused,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104920">That are amazed thus. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104930">But art thou a soldier? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104940" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104950">Yea lady. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104960" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Mel:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104970">The better welcome unto me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e104980" who="A15515-thalia">
          <speaker>Tha:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e104990">Not so to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105000" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105010">And what am I? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105020" who="A15515-thalia">
          <speaker>Tha:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105030">Be whist a while, I'll tell thee by and by. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105040" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105050">That's some mends yet for calling of me fool. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105060" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e105070">Thanks ladies for your courtesies, but the sight of three such goddesses on the sudden, hath driven me into certain muses.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105080" who="A15515-echo">
          <speaker>Echo:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105090">Certain muses. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105100" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105110">Especially being alone so solitary in this wood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105120" who="A15515-echo">
          <speaker>Echo:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105130">In this wood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105140" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105150">Hark soldier somebody mocks thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105160" who="A15515-echo">
          <speaker>Echo:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105170">Mocks thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105180" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105190">Mocks me much. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105200" who="A15515-echo">
          <speaker>Echo:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105210">Much. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105220" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105230">Hold thy peace good Raph. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105240" who="A15515-echo">
          <speaker>Echo:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105250">Good Raph. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105260" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105270">Raph, that's my name indeed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105280">But how shall I call thee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105290" who="A15515-echo">
          <speaker>Eccho:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105300">I call thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105310" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e105320">Dost thou: mass and I'll come to thee, and<pb facs="10"/> I knew where thou art.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105330" who="A15515-echo">
          <speaker>Echo:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105340">Thou art. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105350" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e105360">Art: faith and thou be as pretty a wench as any of these three, my mad wife shall never know that I play a mad part.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105370" who="A15515-echo">
          <speaker>Echo:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105380">Part. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105390" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105400">Part: I'll come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105410" who="A15515-echo">
          <speaker>Echo:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105420">Come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105430" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105440">Faith and I will, have at thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e105450">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105460" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Mel:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e105470">Thus are we well rid of one that would have troubled our talk and this artificial echo, hath told thee what we are: certain muses dwelling in this wood, in number twice so many more as we be here.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105480" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e105490">Your names good ladies?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105500" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Melp:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105510">Mine Melpomene, hers Clio, this that writes Thalia. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105520" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105530">Might I without offence entreat three things,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105540">I should be greatly bound. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105550" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Melp:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e105560">We will not deny thee three things, that can participate to thee thousands.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105570" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e105580">First would I request of this lady, whether she write with this ostrich quill of purpose, or for want of other.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105590" who="A15515-thalia">
          <speaker>Tha:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e105600">Somewhat for want, but especially of purpose: the men which now do minister me matter to write, are near of the nature of the ostrich: who having the body of a bird, hath the head of a beast: she is greedy, devouring and digesting all things, and builds her nest in sand: so are my worldlings, bodied and feathered as birds to fly to heaven, but headed as beasts to imagine beastly things on earth: down to the which their camels necks do draw their very noses: greedy are they devouring the orphans right, and digesting the widow's wrongs, foolish, forgetful and froward, building their nest on sand, which the wind of heaven's wrath or water of worldly affliction doth scatter and wash away. Thus art thou answered for the first, demand the rest.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105610" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>So ▪</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105620">Next ladies why do you twain stand idle,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105630">And let Thalia take the pain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105640" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105650">On gears and gests the world is only set,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105660"><pb facs="10"/> for me there is no work no tragic scene,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105670">Battles are done, the people live in rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105680">They shed no tears but are secure passed mean. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105690" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105700">Why lend you not Thalia then some pens? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105710" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Mel:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105720">My pens are too too sharp to fit her style,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105730">I shall have time to use them in a while. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105740" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105750">But gentle Clio, methinks your ink is dry. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105760" who="A15515-clio">
          <speaker>Cleo:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105770">It may be well, I have done writing I,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105780" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105790">What did you register when you did write? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105800" who="A15515-clio">
          <speaker>Clio:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105810">The works of famous Kings, and sacred priests,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105820">The honourable acts of leaders brave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105830">The deeds of Codri, and Horatij. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105840">The love Lycurgus bore to Spartans state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105850">The lives of ancient sages and their saws,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105860">Their memorable works, their worthy laws. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105870">Now there is no such thing for to indite</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105880">But toys, that fits Thalia for to write. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105890" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105900">A heavy tale good lady you unfold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105910">Are there no worthy things to write as were of old. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105920" who="A15515-clio">
          <speaker>Cleo:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105930">Yes divers princes make good laws,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105940">But most men over slip them. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105950">And divers dying give good gifts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e105960">But their executors nip them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105970" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Mel:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e105980">Tisiphone is stepping to the stage, and she hath sworn to whip them.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e105990" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106000">The third and last thing I require is if you can:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106010">Show me the mighty mats his court. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106020" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Mel:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106030">Walk hence a slight shoot up the hill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106040">And thou shalt see his castle wall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106050" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106060">Ladies the gifts that I can give,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106070">Is humbly thrice to thank you all. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e106080">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106090" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Mel:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106100">Farewell poor soldier. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106110" who="A15515-clio">
          <speaker>Clio:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e106120">Thalia now we are alone, tell us what pageant 'twas you called for pens even now so hastily, to end?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106130" who="A15515-thalia">
          <speaker>Tha:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106140">'Twas thus: you know the gods long since sent down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106150">Pleasure from heaven to comfort men on earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106160"><pb facs="11"/> pleasure abused in country court and town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106170">By speeches, gestures, and dishonest mirth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106180">Made humble suit that he to heaven might pass</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106190">Again, from world where he so wronged was. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106200">His suit obtained, and ready he to climb,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106210">Sorrow comes sneaking and performs his deed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106220">Snatches his robe, and ever since that time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106230">'Tis pain that masks disguised in pleasure's weed ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106240">The pageant's thus, with cost and cunning trim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106250">That worldlings welcome pain in steed of him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106260">Loath was I that penned one jot of this should go,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106270">Because I smile to see for weal, how sweetly men swill woe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106280" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Melpo:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106290">Woe is the first word I must write, beginning where you end. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106300">I have ink enough and pens good store. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106310" who="A15515-clio">
          <speaker>Clio:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106320">Perhaps the world will mend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106330" who="A15515-melpomene">
          <speaker>Mel:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106340">I would it would. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106350" who="A15515-clio">
          <speaker>Clio:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106360">Why if it should you fail in your account. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106370" who="A15515-thalia">
          <speaker>Thalia:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106380">Then you perhaps will have some work. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106390" who="A15515-clio">
          <speaker>Clio:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106400">Tush come let's mount the mount. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e106410">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e106420">Enter Raph cobbler whooping. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106430" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Ra:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e106440">Waha how, wa how, holla how whoop: did nobody see the mocking sprite, I am sure I have followed her up and down all this day crying and calling while my throat is hoarse again. I'll conjure her too but 'tis in vain, for knowledge hath knocked that in the brain, but be it devil or be it spright, I'll call again to have a sight. Ya ha how: nay I'll call again.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e106450">Enter Charon.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106460" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>Charon:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106470">Again, I and again too, I trow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106480">What night and day no rest but row? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106490">Come if thou wilt go over Styx,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106500">For if thou stay a while I think,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106510">There will come so many my boat will sink,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106520" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Ra:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106530">Over Styx i and over stones,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106540">Here's a question for the nonce,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106550">Why what art thou I pray thee tell? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106560" who="A15515-charon">
          <pb facs="11"/>
          <speaker>C:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106570">Why Charon ferryman of hell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106580" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Ra:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106590">Why what a devil do I with thee? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106600">Three or four within: a boat, a boat, a boat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106610" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>C:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106620">Hark what a coil they keep, come if thou wilt to hell with me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106630" who="A15515-small_voice">
          <speaker>A small voice:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106640">A boat, a boat, a boat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106650" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Ra:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106660">This should be the voice of a woman, comes women thither too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106670" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>C:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106680">Why men and women every hour, I know not what to do. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106690" who="A15515-great_voice">
          <speaker>A great voice:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106700">A boat, a boat, a boat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106710" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Ra:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106720">This should be the voice of some great man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106730" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>C:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106740">Why Popes and prelates, princes and judges more than I number can,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106750">But the covetous misers they fret me to the gall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106760">I think they bring their money to hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106770">For they weigh the devil and all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106780" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Ra:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106790">Mas and may well be, for there's little money stirring on the earth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106800" who="A15515-hasty_voice">
          <speaker>A voice hastily:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106810">Charon a boat, a boat, I'll pay thee well for thy hire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106820" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>C:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106830">Why what art thou that mak'st such haste? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106840" who="A15515-voice">
          <speaker>Voice:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106850">The ghost of a grey friar. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106860">So troubled with nuns as never friar was,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106870">Therefore good Charon let me be first,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106880">That over the ford shall pass. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106890" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>C:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106900">Come sirrah, thou hearst what 'a calling they keep wilt thou go? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106910" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Ra:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106920">Why Charon this calling makes thee mad I guess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106930">Why I am no spirit but living Raph,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106940">And God Markedy sends me of business. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106950" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106960">Tush, if thou be sent of God, we cannot hold thee farewell. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e106970">Enter Codrus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e106980" who="A15515-codrus">
          <speaker>Codr:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e106990">Yet gentle Charon carry me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107000" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107010">Thee? Why what art thou, that living suest to go to hell? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107020" who="A15515-codrus">
          <speaker>Codrus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107030">The wretchedst man of wretches most that in this wretched world doth dwell:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107040"><pb facs="12"/> despised, disdained, starved, whipped and scorned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107050">Pressed through despair myself to quell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107060">I therefore covet to behold if greater torment be in hell:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107070">All the voices, a boat, a boat, a boat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107080" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>Cha:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107090">I come, I come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107100" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Rap:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107110">Nay I prithee let them tarry and hearken to the poor. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107120" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>Cha:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107130">Codrus I cannot help thee now, and yet I wish thee well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107140">There's scarcely room enough for rich,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107150">So that no poor can come to hell. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107160">But when the ditch is digged down as clean as is the wall</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107170">That parted hell and purgatory, then if thou chance to call:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107180">Because I see as thou art poor thou art impatient,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107190">To carry thee quickly unto hell Codrus I'll be content. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107200">And now the time will not be long, for there's commission gone ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107210">For workmen, that have power to make Elysium and limbo one,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107220">And there are shipwrights sent for too, to build me up a bigger boat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107230">A boat said I? nay a whole hulk:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107240">And that the same may safely float,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107250">Cocytus, Lethe, Phlegecon</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107260">Shall all be digged into Styx:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107270">For where one wont to come to hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107280">I tell thee now comes five or six. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107290">For ignorance that wont to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107300">Is wilful blindness now become. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107310">So thou must come when room is made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107320">I tell thee yet there is no room. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107330" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107340">I pray thee tell me one thing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107350" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107360">That I will Raph what's the matter? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107370" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Rap:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107380">Charon why doth thy face look so black, and thou use somuch the water? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107390" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>Cha:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107400">O, night was my mother, this is her mark,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107410">I cannot wash it off. Codrus farewell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107420" who="A15515-cobbler">
          <speaker>Co:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107430">Charon adieu. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e107440">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107450" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Ra:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107460">Boatsman? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107470" who="A15515-charon">
          <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107480">Hagh. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e107490">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107500" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Ra:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107510">There's a scoff, that's a waterman indeed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107520"><pb facs="12"/>Well I must to God Mars for all this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107530">I would I could meet my soldier again. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e107540">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e107550">Enter Emnius courtier solus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107560" who="A15515-emnius">
          <speaker>Emn:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107570">Even as the eagle soars against the sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107580">And spite of Phoebus shine, pries in his face:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107590">Even as the swordfish meets the mighty whale,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107600">And puts the hugy monster to disgrace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107610">So Emnius thoughts intending to aspire</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107620">Sore 'gainst the sun, and fleet in wrathful ire:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107630">The Duke the sun that dazzles Emnius eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107640">The Duke the hugy whale that overbears me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107650">But I will gaze and blind him too ere long,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107660">And play the swordfish though he little fears me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107670">The less suspected sooner shall I strike him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107680">And this my reason is for I mislike him</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107690">His daughter with enticing words is won mine own,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107700">But I disdain her were she fairer far:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107710">Tush 'tis for rule I cast and princely throne,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107720">The state of prince, brighter than brightest star. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107730">And who doth hinder Emnius but the Duke? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107740">And therefore who should perish but the Duke? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107750">Shortly a solemn hunting he intends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107760">And who but I is put in chiefest trust? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107770">Well I'll be trusty if my Pistol hold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107780">In love and kingdoms Jove will prove unjust. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107790">He dead, I wed his heir and only daughter,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107800">And so shall win a crown by one man's slaughter. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107810">Suppose he have been kind, liberal and free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107820">Why I confess it, but it's my desire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107830">To be as able to bestow as he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107840">And till I can my heart consumes in fire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107850">Oh sovereign glory, chiefest earthly good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107860">A crown! to which who would not wade through blood. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107870">Then ruthless of his life do I resolve. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107880"><pb facs="13"/>To wait my time till I have wrought his end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107890">He dies, the Duke shall die, and Emnius' reign,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107900">Were he my father or a dearer friend. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107910">Tears shall not hinder, prayers shall not entreat me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107920">But in his throne by blood I soon will seat me. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e107930">Enter soldier, Raph, Mars his lame porter in rusty armour, and a broken bill, the herald with a pencil and colours.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e107940" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107950">Art thou one of God Mars his train? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107960">Alas good father thou art lame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107970">To be a soldier far unlusty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107980">Thy beard is grey thy armour rusty ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e107990">Thy bill I think be broken too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108000" who="A15515-porter">
          <speaker>Porter:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108010">Friend make not thou so much ado,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108020">My lameness comes by war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108030">My armours rustiness comes by peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108040">A maimed soldier made Mars his porter,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108050">Lo this am I: now questioning cease. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108060" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108070">And what are you? A painter with your pencil and your colours brave? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108080" who="A15515-herald">
          <speaker>Herald</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108090">No painter but a herald sirrah to decipher a gentleman from a knave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108100" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108110">Pray sir, can ye gentleman and knave it both in one man, and ye can sir, I pray you do it in me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108120" who="A15515-herald">
          <speaker>Herald</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108130">Indeed I cannot in thyself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108140">For all is knave that is in thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108150" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108160">Sing one two and three, sing after me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108170">And so shall we right well agree. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108180" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108190">Sir take no heed what he doth say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108200">His foolish humour you do see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108210">But tell me pray are you a herald. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108220" who="A15515-herald">
          <speaker>Herald</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108230">I am. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108240" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108250">I should have rather took you to have been,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108260">Appelles' prentice, you were with colours so provided. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108270"><pb facs="13"/>In ancient times have heralds been esteemed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108280">And held companions for the greatest Kings. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108290">Augustus Caesar made a law, so did Antonius too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108300">That without heralds grave advice princes should nothing do. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108310" who="A15515-herald">
          <speaker>Herald</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108320">Well then was then, these times are as they be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108330">We now are fain to wait who grows to wealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108340">And come to bear some office in a town. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108350">And we for money help them unto arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108360">For what cannot the golden tempter do? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108370" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108380">A lamentable thing it is, but tell us I entreat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108390">Where might we find adored Mars. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108400" who="A15515-herald">
          <speaker>Herald</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108410">From hence sir you to Venus' court must pass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108420">Adown the hill, the way is steep, smooth, sleek as any glass ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108430">Go by the door of dalliance, and if you there him miss</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108440">Ask niceness for she best can tell where her fair lady is? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108450">Both day and night the doors are ope,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108460">The strongest closet door is but of feathers made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108470">Rush boldly in, stand not to ask and never be afraid. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108480" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108490">At Venus' court sir do you say that Mars is to be found? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108500" who="A15515-porter">
          <speaker>Porter</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108510">Gentleman we have told ye truth although unto our hearts it be a wound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108520">For searching as we bid you sir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108530">No doubt a wondrous hap,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108540">But you shall find God Mars asleep ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108550">On lady Venus' lap. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108560">This one thing more, you cannot come</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108570">The way you thither pass:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108580">'Tis dangerous, the hills too sleep and slippery all as glass. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108590">Take this of me, the fairest way from Venus' court is beggary. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108600">There are more ways, but they are worse and threaten more extremity. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108610" who="A15515-herald">
          <speaker>Herald</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108620">I that's for such as thither pass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108630">Of pleasure and of will:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108640">But these for other purpose go,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108650">Doubt therefore sir no ill. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108660" who="A15515-soldier">
          <pb facs="14"/>
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108670">I thank you both that have us warned by your skill. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108680" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Ra:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108690">I and I'll end with a prophecy for your good will:</l>
          <floatingText xml:id="A15515-e108700">
            <body xml:id="A15515-e108710">
              <div type="prophecy" xml:id="A15515-e108720">
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108730">You think it is a pleasant jest,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108740">To tell the times of peace and rest,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108750">But he that lives to ninety nine,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108760">Into the hundreds shall decline,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108770">Then shall they speak of a strange time:</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108780">For it will be a wondrous thing,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108790">To see a carter lodge with a King. </l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108800">Town's shall be unpeopled seen,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108810">And markets made upon the green:</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108820">This will be as true I tell ye all,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108830">As cobblers use the thread and nawl. </l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108840">And so because that all men are but mortar,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e108850">I leave the paltry herald and the porter. </l>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108860" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108870">I pray thee come away, gentlemen with thanks I take my leave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108880" who="A15515-herald">
          <speaker>Herald</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108890">Adieu good sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108900" who="A15515-porter">
          <speaker>Porter</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108910">Farewell unto you both. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e108920">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e108930">Enter contempt and Venus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108940" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Con:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108950">Come lady love, now bore we Mars, thou mine I thine beloved. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e108960" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108970">Ah my contempt it will be spied too soon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108980">So shall our pleasures have a bitter end. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e108990">Provide some place for I am big with child,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109000">And clean undone if Mars my guilt espy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109010" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Cont:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109020">Sweet Venus be assured, I have that care</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109030">But you perchance will coily scorn the place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109040" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109050">What its some abbey or a nunnery? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109060" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Con:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109070">No they abound with much hypocrisy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109080" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Ven:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109090">Is it a gentleman's or a farmer's house? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109100" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Con:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109110">Too much resort would there bewray your being. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109120" who="A15515-venus">
          <pb facs="14"/>
          <speaker>Ve.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109130">Some husbandman's, some inn, some cleanly alehouse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109140" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Con:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109150">Neither of these, a spittle lovely love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109160" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Ven:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109170">What where foul lazars and loathed lepors lie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109180">Their stink will choked thy Venus and her babe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109190" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Cont:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109200">Why gentle Venus I entreat ye be not over nice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109210">What think ye as the proverb goes that beggars have no lice? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109220">Proctors themselves in every spittle house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109230">Have things as neat, as men of more account. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109240" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Ven:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109250">But I have seen even very mean men's wives,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109260">Against their childbirth so provide for,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109270">As all their husband's wealth was scarce the worth</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109280">Of the fine linen used in that month. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109290">And shall not Venus' be as kindly used. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109300" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Con:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109310">It must be as we may, I'll go provided</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109320">And spy my time slyly to steal thee hence. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e109330">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109340" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109350">Away for Mars is come,</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e109360">Enter Mars.</stage>
        <l xml:id="A15515-e109370">Welcome God Mars, where hath my love been all this while? </l>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109380" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109390">Walking about th' garden time for to beguile. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109400">Whereas between niceness your maid and newfangle your man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109410">I heard such sport as for your part, would you had been there then. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109420">Quoth niceness to new fangle thou art such a Jack,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109430">That thou devisest forty fashions for my ladies back. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109440">And thou quoth he art so possessed with every fantike toy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109450">That following of my lady's humour thou dost make her coy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109460">For once a day for fashion's sake my lady must be sick,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109470">No meat but mutton or at most the pinion of a chick,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109480">Today her own hair best becomes which yellow is as gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109490">A periwigs better for tomorrow, blacker to behold. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109500">Today in pumps and chevril gloves, to walk she will be bold. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109510">Tomorrow cuffs and countenance for fear of catching cold. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109520">Now is she barefaced to be seen, straight on her muffler goes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109530">Now is she huffed up to the crown, straight nulled to the nose. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109540">These seven years trust me better sport I heard not to my mind ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109550">The dialogue done, then down came I my lady love to find. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109560" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109570">And thou hast found her all alone, half sickly by ill hap</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109580"><pb facs="15"/> sit for a while Mars and lay thy head upon my lap,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109590">I see my folks behind my back have much good talk of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109600" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109610">And so they have. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109620" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109630">They are too idle: soft Mars do you see,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109640" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109650">I see some saucy mates press in: now sirs what would you have? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109660" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109670">Be not offended sir, we seek God Mars. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109680" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109690">Why and Mars have you found sir, what's your will with him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109700" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109710">Are you he I cry you mercy, I promise you I took you for a morris dancer you are so trim. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109720" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109730">What says the villain? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109740" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sa:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e109750">If thou be Mars, the cause which makes me doubt, is that I see thy body leapt in soft silk which was wont to be clad in hard steel, and thy head so childishly laid on a woman's lap. Pardon I humbly beseech thee, the plainness of thy poor servant, and vouchsafe to read my poor petition.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e109760">He delivers the petition, Mars takes and reads it, mean while Venus speaks.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109770" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109780">Rough shaped soldier enemy to love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109790">Why dost thou thirst so much for bloody war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109800">Wherein the strong man by a stronger quelled,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109810">Or reached far off by dastard darters arm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109820">Breathes forth his spirit with a bootless cry,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109830">Leaving behind his earth's anatomy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109840">By war the infant trampled under steeds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109850">Holds to his mother out his feeble hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109860">And she is ravished while her youngling bleeds. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109870">Yet to abide death's stroke doth quaking stand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109880">The twice forced virgin like the wounded lamb,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109890">Dejected at the mercy of the wolf,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109900">Holds up her throat in vain to bloody men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109910">That will not kill her while her beauty stayeth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109920">But stab her when her tears her fair decayeth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109930">Away thou bloody man, vex not my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109940">By war true love is hindered and undone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109950"><pb facs="15"/> and ladies' laps left empty of their loves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109960">Whose heads did beautify their tender knees. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109970" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e109980">You need not plain your laps full enough:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e109990" who="A15515-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110000">Fair Venus be propitious I will fight</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110010">To maintain true love and defend the right,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110020" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110030">On that condition soldier I am won,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110040">Receive this favour, Mars let it be done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110050" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e110060">Sateros, I have received thy supplication, and sorrow I cannot as I would give thee immediate comfort. If I should oppose myself against the gods, they would soon set fire on my seat, six double us there are, three at liberty, three imprisoned, and one their keeper: at liberty, wiliness, wrong and wantonness, in prison, are war wreak and woe, their keeper is wonder; who once giving way to liberty for those he holds; shall set thee and thy fellows on work: in mean time go thou to the Duke of Booetia, commend us to him, when he can he will employ thee I am sure, let that be thy answer for this time, and so good sateros be contented.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110070" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110080">I humbly take my leave adored Mars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110090">Prove a good night raven Venus I entreat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110100" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110110">Farewell poor soldier wear that for my sake ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110120" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sa:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110130">Of both your godheads duteous leave I take. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110140" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110150">And when go you sir? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110160" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Rahh:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110170">Who I? Good lord there hangs a matter by. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110180" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110190">Why what are you? get gone or I will send thee gone ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110200" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110210">I pray you bear a while, gentle master mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110220">And you shall hear my in speech I warrant? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110230" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110240">Go too sir fool, let's hear what you can say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110250" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110260">And shall I warrant ye to your cost my lady Do-little ▪</l>
          <floatingText xml:id="A15515-e110270">
            <body xml:id="A15515-e110280">
              <div type="prophecy" xml:id="A15515-e110290">
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110300">Mars though thou be a cock of the game,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110310">That wontst to crow by day,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110320">And with thy sharpened spurs</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110330">The craven cock's didst kill and slay:</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110340">Sith now thou dost but prune thy wings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110350">And make thy feathers gay:</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110360"><pb facs="16"/> a dunghill cock that crows by night,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110370">Shall slily thee betray,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110380">And tread thy hen, and for a time</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110390">Shall carry her away. </l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110400">And she by him shall hatch a chick,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110410">This country to decay. </l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110420">And for this pretty pullet's name</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110430">Thou shalt the better learn:</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110440">When thou shalt only letters find</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110450">Within one name discern,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110460">Three vowels and two consonants,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110470">Which vowels if thou scan,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110480">Doth sound that which to every place</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110490">Conducteth every man. </l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110500">Then call to mind this prophecy,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110510">For that's the bastard's name:</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110520">Then rouse thyself, then reach thy sword,</l>
                <l xml:id="A15515-e110530">And win thy wonted fame. </l>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110540">Now have I done the task for which I came,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110550">And so farewell fine master and nice dame. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e110560">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e110570">Mars rises in a rage, Venus offers to stay him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110580" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110590">A dunghill cock to tread my hen? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110600">Break forth ye angry powers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110610">And fill the world with bloodshed and with rage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110620" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110630">My lord, my love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110640" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110650">Venus I am abused. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110660" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110670">Why will ye trust a fool when he shall speak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110680">And take his words to be as oracles? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110690" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110700">But he hath touched me near, and I'll revenge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110710" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110720">Ay me! </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110730">Revenge true lovers wrongs immortal powers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110740">And ne'er let lady trust a soldier. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e110750">Make as if she swounds.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110760" who="A15515-mars">
          <pb facs="16"/>
          <speaker>Mars.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110770">Why faintest thou Venus? why art thou distressed? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110780">Look up my love, speak Venus, speak to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110790" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110800">Nay let me die, sith Mars hath wronged me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110810" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110820">Thou hast not wronged me, Mars believes it not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110830" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110840">Yes, yes, base cobblers utter oracles,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110850">And all are sooth fast words against poor love,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110860" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110870">I will believe no words, they are all false:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110880">Only my Venus is as bright as heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110890">And firmer than the poles that hold up heaven. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110900" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110910">Now comes your love too late, first have you slain</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110920">Her whom your honey words cannot recure again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110930" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110940">I will do penance on my knees to thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110950">And beg a kiss, that have been so unkind,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110960" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110970">And know you not, unkindness kills a woman? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e110980" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e110990">I know it doth? sweet forgive my fault:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111000" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111010">I will forgive ye now ye beg so hard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111020">But trust me next time I'll not be entreated. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111030" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Ma:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111040">Now hast thou cheered my drooping thoughts sweet love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111050">Let me lay down my head upon thy knee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111060">Sing one sweet song, thy voice will ravish me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111070" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111080">Folly come forth. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e111090">Enter Follie.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111100" who="A15515-folly">
          <speaker>Folly:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111110">Anon forsooth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111120" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111130">Bid niceness, new fangle, dalliance and the rest bring forth their music Mars intends to sleep. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111140" who="A15515-folly">
          <speaker>Folly:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111150">I will forsooth. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e111160">Exit Folly.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111170" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111180">I think in deed that I shall quickly sleep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111190">Especially with music and with song. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e111200">Enter Follie with a fife, niceness, new fangle, dalliance, and jealozie with instruments, they play while Venus sings.</stage>
        <floatingText xml:id="A15515-e111210">
          <body xml:id="A15515-e111220">
            <div type="song" xml:id="A15515-e111230">
              <l xml:id="A15515-e111240">Sweet are the thoughts that harbour full content,</l>
              <l xml:id="A15515-e111250">Delight full be the joys that know no care:</l>
              <l xml:id="A15515-e111260">The sleeps are sound that are from dreams exempt,</l>
              <l xml:id="A15515-e111270">Yet in chief sweets lies hid a secret snare,</l>
              <l xml:id="A15515-e111280"><pb facs="17"/> where love is watched by prying jealous eyes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A15515-e111290">It fits the loved to be wary wise. </l>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111300" who="A15515-folly">
          <speaker>Folly:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111310">Peep, peep, madam he is asleep ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e111320">Enter contempt, and kiss Venus. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e111330">Sing:</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111340" who="A15515-contempt">
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111350">Sleep on secure, let care not touch thy heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111360">Leave to love her, that longs to live in change,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111370">So wantoness deal, when they their fairs impart</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111380">Rome thou abroad for I intend to range:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111390">Yet wantoness learn to guide your ruling eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111400">As no suspect by gazing may arise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111410" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111420">Hold on your music, folly leave thy play,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111430">Come hither lay his head upon thy knee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111440">Fie what a loathed load was he to me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111450">Come my content, let's dance about the place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111460">And mock God Mars unto his sleepy face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111470" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Con:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111480">Venus agreed, play us a galliard. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e111490">Music plays, they dance, and leap over Mars, and making horns at every turn, at length leave him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111500" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111510">Why sings not Venus? her love I to hear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111520">Sweet let the fife be further from mine ear,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e111530">Follie holds still the fife,</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111540">Nay let the fife play, else the music fails. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e111550">Follie plays again.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111560">What still so near my ear, sweet Venus sing. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111570" who="A15515-unassigned">
          <speaker>Sing:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111580">Where is she? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111590">Out fool, what does my head upon thy knee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111600" who="A15515-folly">
          <speaker>Folly:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111610">Forsooth my mistress bid me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111620" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111630">Where's Venus, speak ye ribalds, harlots, fools,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111640">And never speak again except I see her:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111650">Mars is impatient, find out Venus soon. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e111660">Exeunt 〈◊〉.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111670">Or perish slaves, before my angry wrath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111680" who="A15515-folly">
          <speaker>Folly:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111690">Nay a lady, folly will live for all you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111700" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111710">Away ye fool, tell Venus of my rage. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111720"><pb facs="17"/>And bid her come to Mars that now begins,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111730">To doubt the cobbler's prophecy. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e111740">Exit follies</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e111750">Enter new fangle, and dalliance.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111760" who="A15515-newfangle">
          <speaker>New:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111770">My lord we cannot find her anywhere . </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111780" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111790">Hence villains, seek the garden, search each place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111800">Mars will not suffer such abhorred disgrace. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e111810">Enter Follie.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111820">Where's Venus' folly, prithee tell me fool? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111830" who="A15515-folly">
          <speaker>Folly:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111840">Forsooth she's run away wid a man called contempt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e111850" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111860">What hath contempt robbed mighty Mars of love? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111870">Hence fools and flatterers, fly you from my sight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111880">Mars with a kindled fire begins to burn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111890">Away ye hell hounds, ministers of shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111900">Vanish like smoke, for you are lighter far,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e111910">All run away.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111920">'Gainst wantonness proclaim I open war. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111930">Unconstant women I accuse your sex,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111940">Of folly, lightness, treachery and fraud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111950">You are the scum of ill, the scorn of good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111960">The plague of mankind, and the wrath of heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111970">The cause of envy, anger, murder, war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111980">By you the peopled towns are deserts made:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e111990">The deserts filled with horror and distress. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112000">You laugh hyena like, weep as the crocodile,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112010">One ruin brings your sorrow and your smile,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112020">Hold on in lightness, lust hath kindled fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112030">The trumpets clang and roaring noise of drums,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112040">Shall drown the echoes of your weeping cries,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112050">And powders smoke dim your enticing eyes. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112060">These wanton ornaments for maskers fit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112070">Will Mars leave off, and suit himself in steel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112080">And strumpet Venus with that vile contempt. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112090"><pb facs="18"/>I will pursue unto the depth of hell. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112100">Away with pity, welcome ire and rage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112110">Which naught but Venus' ruin shall assuage. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e112120">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e112130">Enter the Duke, sateros, the scholar, and Raph cobbler,</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112140" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112150">Well do I like your reasoning gentlemen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112160">You for your learning, Sateros for act,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112170">The learned is preferred, the soldier shall not want,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112180">But sateros, ye must forbear a while,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112190">I cannot yet employ ye as I would:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112200">Mean time attend the court you shall have pay</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112210">To my ability and your content. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112220" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112230">Thanks to your highness. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112240" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112250">Scholar lead him in. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112260">Be kind to him he is a soldier. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112270">Attend upon us to our hunting sateros,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112280">We must have pleasant war anon with beasts. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e112290">Withdraw sateros and scholar ▪</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112300" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112310">When will these fellows make an end. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112320" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112330">Depart my friends, I have a little business</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112340">With this poor man that doth attend to speak with me. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e112350">Exeunt scholar and sateros ▪</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112360">Fellow what is it thou wilt now reveal? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112370" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112380">You are the Duke of all this land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112390">And this I wish ye understand;</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112400">That princes give to many bred</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112410">Which wish them shorter by the head. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112420">You have a courtier Emnius named, whose flattering tongue hath many blamed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112430">He lowteth low doth fawn and kneel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112440">Your worthy meaning for to feel. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112450"><pb facs="18"/>And quaintly roams your person nigh, willing to see it fall and die. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112460">You have a daughter fair and trim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112470">He loveth her and she loves him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112480">Yet as the fox doth win the kid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112490">So are his secret treasons hid:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112500">He dares not once his passions move,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112510">For fear your highness should reprove. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112520">Yet is it not your daughter dear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112530">That he desires so fair and clear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112540">He coveteth your dignity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112550">And therefore this intendeth he. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112560">Today you mean to hunt in wood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112570">And for he doth pretend no good:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112580">He hath with shot intended ill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112590">And means your noble grace to kill:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112600">I that desire for to explain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112610">The manner of your grace's pain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112620">Give counsel ere the deed be done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112630">That you may all deceiving shun:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112640">I see that Emnius cometh nigh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112650">My protestation quickly try. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112660">And if you find as I have said,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112670">That you should be by him betrayed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112680">Remember Raph the cobbling knave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112690">You warning of this mischief gave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112700">So leave I you to search the slave. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e112710">Exit</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e112720">Enter Emnius the courtier.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112730" who="A15515-emnius">
          <speaker>Emnius:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112740">My honourable lord, the train attends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112750">All things are ready for your highness' sport:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112760">And I am sent from other of estate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112770">To pray your grace to haste your wonted presence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112780" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112790">Emnius they must attend a while,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112800">For I have secrets to impart with thee:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112810" who="A15515-emnius">
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <speaker>Emnius:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112820">Say on my honourable lord to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112830" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112840">Thou know'st we must unto the wood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112850" who="A15515-emnius">
          <speaker>Emnius.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112860">True my most gracious lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112870" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112880">Suppose there were a traitorous foe of mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112890">What wouldst thou do to rid me from my fear? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112900" who="A15515-emnius">
          <speaker>Emnius:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112910">Die on the traitor, and prepare his grave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112920">Before he should one thought of comfort have. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112930" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112940">But tell me Emnius, didst thou see a tree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112950">That bore fair fruit delighting to the eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112960">And by the straightness of the trunk they grow too high ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112970">Wouldst thou oppose thyself against the tree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e112980">And work the downfall ere the fall should be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e112990" who="A15515-emnius">
          <speaker>Emnius.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113000">I would regard no height to claim the fruit</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113010">That should content me, but attempt to climb</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113020">The highest top of height, or fall to death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113030">Alone and naked to obtain my will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113040" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113050">I am right joyous you are so resolved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113060">Such courtiers should become a noble prince. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113070">But tell me Emnius had I any foe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113080">That secretly attempted my distress,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113090">What secret weapon have ye to prevent? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113100" who="A15515-emnius">
          <speaker>Emnius.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113110">Only my sword my lord, that is my rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113120">My resolution to defend your grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113130" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113140">And have you not a dag to help me too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113150" who="A15515-emnius">
          <speaker>Emnius:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113160">A dag my lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113170" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113180">I manned deny it not,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113190">I know ye have a dag prepared for me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113200" who="A15515-emnius">
          <speaker>Emn:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113210">I have a dag not for your majesty. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e113220">The Duke takes it from him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113230" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113240">Yes Emnius pour thyself into thyself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113250">And let thy own eyes be thy hearts true witness.</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113260">Wearest thou this dag to injure any beast? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113270">Bearest thou these bullets for a foeman's life? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113280">Or art thou bent against thy loyal lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113290">To reave his life that gives thee life and breath? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113300" who="A15515-emnius">
          <speaker>Em:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113310">'Gainst beasts my lord doth Emnius like to deal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113320">He is not so beastly and abominate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113330"><pb facs="19"/> as he delights to joy in treachery,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113340" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113350">So smiles hyena, when she will be guile,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113360">And so with tears deceives the crocodile. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113370">Are not these tools prepared for my end? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113380">Speak ill intending man, ah Emnius? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113390">Have I for this maintained thy estate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113400">Afforded all the favours I could yield,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113410">To be rewarded with ingratitude,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113420">With murder, treachery, and these attempts? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113430">And all in hope to win my realm and child. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113440">I will not show thy sin unto the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113450">But as thou didst intend, so shalt thou fall. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e113460">Emnius kneels down.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113470">Receive thy death, desertful man of death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113480">And perish all thy treacherous thoughts with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113490" who="A15515-emnius">
          <speaker>Em:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113500">Welcome my death, desertful I confess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113510">Heavens pardon my intent, your highness bless. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e113520">The Duke raises him up.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113530" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113540">Heaven's pardon thy intent, and so do I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113550">Be true hereafter, now thou shalt not die. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113560">Come follow us Emnius, learn to know this lore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113570">Murder of meanest men brings shame, of princes more. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e113580">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113590" who="A15515-emnius">
          <speaker>Em:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113600">O that same cobbling rogue that raving runs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113610">And madding aims at every hid intent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113620">Revealed this practice, but I'll stab the slave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113630">And he once dead the Duke's death will I have. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e113640">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e113650">Enter Mercury with a trumpet sounding, and two of Venus' waiting maids, the one named Ru, the other Ina, Ina bearing a child.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113660" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e113670">Be it known unto all people, that whereas Venus alias lust, hath long challenged a pre-eminence in heaven, and been adored with the name of a goddess, the synod of the gods being assembled, in regard of her adulteries with Mars, discovered<pb facs="20"/> by Phoebus, when in the face of heaven, they both were taken in an iron net: wherein her wrong to Vulcan was apparent; and since that, many other escapes considered. But lastly and most especially, her public adultery she hath committed with that base monster contempt they have all consented, and to this decree firmed; that no more shall Venus possess the title of a goddess, but be utterly excluded the compass of heaven: and it shall be taken as great indignity to the gods to give Venus any other title than the detested name of lust, or strumpet Venus: and whosoever shall adore contempt or entertain him, shall be reputed an enemy to the gods. More, it is decreed that war shall be raised against Booetia, and victory shall not fall on their side, till the cabin of contempt be consumed with fire. Given at Olimpus by Jupiter and the celestial synod.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113680" who="A15515-ru">
          <speaker>Ru:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113690">Ill tidings for my lady these. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113700" who="A15515-ina">
          <speaker>Ina:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113710">Ill news poor babe for thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113720" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113730">What who are these? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113740">I take ye to be two of Venus' virgins, are ye not? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113750" who="A15515-ru">
          <speaker>Ru:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113760">Faith she is a pure virgin indeed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113770">For the child she had by Venus' chaplin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113780">Is a big boy and follows the father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113790" who="A15515-ina">
          <speaker>Ina:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113800">And so are you a maid too, are ye not? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113810">For the girl you had by Mars his captain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113820">She's dead, and troubles not the mother. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113830" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113840">Then I perceive ye be both maids for the most part,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113850" who="A15515-ru">
          <speaker>Ru.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113860">Well for our maidenheads it skill not much. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113870">For in the world I know are many such. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113880" who="A15515-ina">
          <speaker>Ina:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113890">I Mercury I pray let that go,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113900">We are fair Venus' maids, no more but so. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113910">And in our lady's cause we do entreat</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113920">To know, if that be true thou didst proclaim? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113930">Or was it spoken but of policy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113940">To fright us whom thou knewest to be her maids. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113950" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113960">As true as neither of you both are maids</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113970">So true it is, that I have uttered. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e113980">The sentence is set down, Venus exiled,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e113990" who="A15515-ina">
          <pb facs="20"/>
          <speaker>Ina:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114000">Aim poor babe for thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114010" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114020">Whose child is that you bear so tenderly? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114030" who="A15515-ru">
          <speaker>Ru:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114040">My lady's child, begotten by contempt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114050" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114060">O is it so, and whether bear you it? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114070" who="A15515-ina">
          <speaker>Ina:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114080">To nurse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114090" who="A15515-mor">
          <speaker>Mor:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114100">To whom? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114110" who="A15515-ru">
          <speaker>Ru:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114120">Unto security. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114130" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114140">Is it a boy or girl, I pray ye tell? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114150" who="A15515-ina">
          <speaker>Ina:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114160">A girl it is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114170" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114180">Who were the godmothers? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114190" who="A15515-ru">
          <speaker>Ru:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114200">We two are they. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114210" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114220">Your names I crave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114230" who="A15515-ru">
          <speaker>Ru:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114240">Mine Ru and hers is Ina. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114250" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114260">And whether name I pray ye bears the girl? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114270" who="A15515-ina">
          <speaker>Ina:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114280">Both hers and mine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114290" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114300">And who is godfather? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114310" who="A15515-ru">
          <speaker>Ru:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114320">Ingratitude that is likewise the grandfather. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114330" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114340">Ruina otherwise called ruin the child,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114350">Contempt the father, Venus alias lust the mother,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114360">Ru and Ina the godmothers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114370">Ingratitude the godfather and grandfather,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114380">And security the nurse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114390">Here's a brood that all Booetia shall curse. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114400">Well damsels hie you hence, for one is coming nigh</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114410">Will tread your young one under foot. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114420" who="A15515-ina">
          <speaker>Ina:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114430">'Tis Mars, oh let us fly. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e114440">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e114450">Enter Mars in Armour ▪</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114460" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mar:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114470">Now Mars thou seemest like thyself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114480">Thy women's weeds cast off,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114490">Which made thee be in heaven a scorn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114500">On earth a common scoff. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114510" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114520">O Mercury how am I bound to thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114530">That blazest forth this strumpets just reproof? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114540">O could I find the harlot or her brood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114550"><pb facs="21"/> I would revenge me of indignities:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114560">Now Mercury, I mind a prophecy</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114570">A simple fellow brought me on a day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114580">When wantoning upon her knee I lay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114590">How that a craven cock should tread my hen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114600">And she should hatch a chick this country to decay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114610">The bastard's name he told me too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114620">But it was riddle-wise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114630">Help me to search it Mercury,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114640">I know thee quick and wise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114650">When I should only in a word</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114660">Five letters just discern</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114670">Three vowels and two consonants,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114680">The name I soon should learn:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114690">But those same vowels he did bid ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114700">That I should duly scan,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114710">And they would signify the way</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114720">That guideth every man. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114730">Hast thou not heard of such a thing? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114740" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114750">Yes, and did send that prophesy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114760">And even as thou camest hither</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114770">The bastard and the godmothers</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114780">Were in this place together. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114790" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114800">Were they in deed, where are they now? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114810">I'll search, I'll follow them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114820" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114830">Be patient Mars, they will be quickly found ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114840">Ruina is the bastard's name. R.n. the consonants,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114850">V. I. and A. the vowels be, and via is the way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114860" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114870">Now have I found it Mercury, thou hast resolved me</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114880">I will raise war, I will avenged be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114890">Go with me Mercury, thou my revenge shalt see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114900" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114910">I will go and do my best for thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e114920">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e114930">Enter the Duke, scholar, cobbler.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e114940" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114950">'Tis true o Duke, that I do say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114960"><pb facs="21"/> he still would make thy life away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114970">He is too frolic and too lusty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114980">Thou too simple and too trusty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e114990">Wars shall in thy land begin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115000">For pride, contempt, and other sin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115010">Nothing shall appease heaven's ire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115020">Till the cabin of contempt be set on fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115030">And wantonness with lewd desire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115040">Be trampled under foot as mire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115050">The cobbler has no more to say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115060">But for the people's sins, good princes oft are ta'en away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115070" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115080">Well, God a mercy fellow, go thou in. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e115090">Ex. Raph.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115100" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115110">He raves my lord, it's ill advised of you</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115120">To suffer him so near your princely excellence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115130" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115140">His presence breeds me no offence. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e115150">A cry within help, murder, murder, Raph comes running out, Ennius after him with his dagger drawn, after Ennius Zelota the cobbler's wife, who snatches the dagger from Ennius, and runs raving.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115160" who="A15515-zelota">
          <speaker>Ze:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115170">What Raph, Raph, so fine you will not know your wife</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115180">What a gilden sword and a silver knife? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115190">There, there Raph put it up. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e115200">She stabs Ennius, and he falls dead.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e115210">She stands again suddenly amazed.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115220">Why so? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115230">What so? Why where am I? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115240" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115250">Faith where ye ha' made a fair piece of work. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115260" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Worser;</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115270">Lay hold on them, what violence is this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115280">To have one murdered even before our presence? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115290" who="A15515-scholar">
          <pb facs="22"/>
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e115300">What cause hadst thou to kill this gentleman?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115310" who="A15515-zelota">
          <speaker>Zel:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e115320">None in the world, I never knew him I.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115330" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e115340">No faith she's mad, and has been ever since I was a prophet, and cause she saw a dagger without a sheath, she even put it up in his belly.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115350" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115360">Why what acquaintance hast thou with this woman? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115370" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e115380">O lord sir, she has been acquainted with me a great while, with mine ears, with every part of me, why 'tis my wife.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115390" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115400">The likelier may it like your grace of his consent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115410">'Twere good they both did suffer punishment. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115420" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115430">Commit them both, but she has long been mad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115440">It may be heaven reserved her to this end. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115450" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115460">Come sirrah, you and your wife must go to ward,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115470">Till you be tried for clearness or consent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115480" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115490">O sir, whether you will I am content,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115500">God Markedy has served me prettily,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115510">Has made my wife mad, and said she should not be well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115520">Till by her hand a traitor fell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115530">And I must even be hanged for company. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e115540">Exeunt with the cobbler and his wife some bear out Ennius' body.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115550" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115560">I do not guess the woman guilty of this crime,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115570">But the just heavens in their severity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115580">Have wrought this wreak for Ennius' treachery. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e115590">Enter scholar and messenger.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115600" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115610">Here is a messenger my gracious lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115620">That brings ill tidings to your quiet state. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115630" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115640">What are they fellow, let us hear them speak. Spare not</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115650" who="A15515-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115660">The Argives and the men of Thessaly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115670">With mighty powers are come upon your coast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115680">They burn, waste, spoil, kill, murder, make no spare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115690">Of feeble age, or harmless infant youth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115700">They vow to triumph in Booetia,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115710">And make your highness' vassal to their will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115720">They threaten mightily, their power is mighty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115730"><pb facs="22"/> the people fall before them as the flowering grass</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115740">The mower with his sith cuts in the mead,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115750">Help your poor people, and defend your state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115760">Else you, they, it, will soon be ruinated. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115770" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115780">I will provide as far as heavenly powers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115790">And our abilities shall give consents;</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115800">I'll to the temple and pour forth my prayers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115810">Meanwhile let sateros be called for,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115820">To muster up the people with all speed,</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e115830">Exit Duke.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115840" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115850">Now see I that this simple witted man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115860">This poor plain cobbler truly did divine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115870">The gods when we refuse the common means</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115880">Sent by their oracles and learned priests,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115890">Raise up some man contemptible and vile,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115900">In whom they breathe the pureness of their spirits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115910">And make him bold to speak and prophesy. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e115920">Enter sateros the soldier.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115930">Welcome friend sateros, you are fitly come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115940">The Duke intends that you shall lead to field</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115950">The powers of Boaetia 'gainst his foes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115960">Are you prepared, and willingly resolved? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e115970" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115980">Why you sir by your pen can do as well</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e115990">I know 'tis nothing but facsimile. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116000" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116010">Soldier, stand not on that, discharge your duty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116020">The country needs our service and our counsel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116030">I'll do my best, and do you your endeavour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116040">For public quiet and Booetias honour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116050" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat;</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116060">Well I forget your scorns given me in peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116070">And rate all envy at an humble price,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116080">I'll do my duty, do not you neglect,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116090">Arms will not art, art should not arms reject. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116100" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116110">A blessed concord, I will to the Duke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116120">And leave thee sateros to thy glorious war. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="23"/>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e116130">Enter hastily the country gentleman.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116140" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <speaker>Country-gentleman</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116150">O sir, I have been seeking ye all day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116160">And greatly do I praise my fortune thus to meet ye. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116170" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116180">In good time sir, be brief I pray.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116190" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <speaker>Count:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116200">You do remember me I hope.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116210" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116220">Not very well I promise ye.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116230" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <speaker>Country-gentleman</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116240">Lord sir, and you be advised, I was one of them that reasoned before contempt, when you defended war, another art, one the court, and I the country.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116250" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116260">I remember in deed such a reasoning, before that vile monster contempt, but you I have forgotten.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116270" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <speaker>Country-gentleman</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116280">O lord sir yes, by that token we went afterwards to the ordinary.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116290" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116300">True, true, now I call ye mind, by this token I was not able to reach commons, and so was cashiered out of your company.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116310" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <speaker>Country-gentleman</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116320">'Twas against my will i'faith: ye saw I was another man's guest.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116330" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116340">It's no great matter. But what's your business with me now, that you seek for me so hastily?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116350" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <speaker>Country-gentleman</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116360">Marry sir there is wars towards, do ye not hear on it?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116370" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116380">That's to too sure.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116390" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <speaker>Country-gentleman</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116400">And I fear by reason of my wealth I shall be chosen for a captain over some companies.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116410" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116420">And what of that?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116430" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <speaker>Country-gentleman</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116440">Why I have no skill, and therefore would hire you to serve in my place. I'll please ye well.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116450" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116460">The Duke wants men sir, and therefore must ye serve yourself, though not as a captain, yet in a place fitting your person. You offer me money, why man I'll deal kindly with ye, ye shall have some of me, bear take it, be not nice. In the Duke's name I charge ye with horse and furniture to be ready tomorrow by break of day, for the business asks speed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116470" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <pb facs="23"/>
          <speaker>Country-gentleman</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116480">But I hope ye will not deal so with me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116490" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116500">But I am sure I will, therefore dispatch on peril of your life.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116510" who="A15515-country-gentleman">
          <speaker>Country-gentleman</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116520">Why what alive is this, that such as I must serve? A shame on wars for me that ere they were.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e116530">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e116540">Enter Raph and other prisoners with weapons.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116550" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116560">Why now fellows, what are you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116570" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116580">What soldier, do not you know me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116590" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116600">Yes Raph but what are these?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116610" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116620">Faith certain pew-fellows of mine, that have been mewed up, and now the exclamation goes we shall have wars, we are all set at liberty, and sent to you to be trailed up.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116630" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116640">Why wert in prison?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116650" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116660"> i'faith I prophesied so long, that I had like to have been hanged. My wife killed the courtier man, that would have killed me and the Duke to, but I'll be a prophet no longer that's flat, after I have done being a soldier, I'll to cobbling again.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116670" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116680">So dost thou well: but fellow tell me why wert thou in.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116690" who="A15515-prisoner">
          <speaker>Prisoner</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116700">Faith sir for nothing but riding another man's horse.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116710" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116720">That was but a small matter.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116730" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116740">A thing of nothing, for when he had stolen him, he were as good ride him as lead him in his hand.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116750" who="A15515-priest">
          <speaker>Priest</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e116760">Faith that's even the truth on it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116770" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat;</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116780">I think you all have been of such condition ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116790">But now betake you to another course,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116800">The Duke hath given you life and liberty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116810">Where otherwise your deeds deserved death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116820">If now you do offend under my charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116830">Look for no favour but the martial law,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116840">Death on the next tree without all remission,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116850">And if ye like not this I will return ye</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116860"><pb facs="24"/> from whence ye came to bide the doom of law,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116870">Speak, will ye live and serve as true men should? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116880" who="A15515-all">
          <speaker>All:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116890">Ay, ay, I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116900" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116910">I am sure ye take me for none of they number. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116920" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116930">No Raph, thou shalt be still with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116940">I have an host of worthy soldiers</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116950">Ready to march, to them now will I go,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e116960">Heavens and good fortune quell our furious foe. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e116970">Sound drums, exeunt omnes. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e116980">Enter contempt, Venus following him, he pushing her from him twice or thrice.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e116990" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Cont;</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117000">Away thou strumpet, scandal of the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117010">Cause of my sorrow, author of thy shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117020">Follow me not, but wander where thou wilt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117030">In uncouth places loathed of the light,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117040">Fit shroud to hide thy lustful body in,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117050">Whose fair's distained with foul adulterous sin. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e117060" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Ven:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117070">Ah my content, prove not so much unkind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117080">To fly and leave thy love alone behind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117090">I will go with thee into hollow caves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117100">To desert to the dens of furious beasts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117110">I will descend with thee unto the grave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117120">Look on me love let me some comfort have. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117130">Contempt still turns from Venus. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117140">What not a word to comfort me in woe? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117150">No look to give my dying heart some life? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117160">Nothing but frowns, but lours, but scorns, disdains? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117170">Woe to my pleasures that have brought these pains. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117180">Have I for this set light the god of war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117190">Against whose frowns nor death nor heaven can stand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117200">Have I for this procured the angry gods</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117210">To make me exile from all blessedness. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117220">Have I for this lost honour and renown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117230">Become a scandal to the vulgar world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117240"><pb facs="24"/> and thus to be repaid▪ ah break my heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117250">Had all these evils fallen upon my head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117260">And millions of more harms than heaven could heap,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117270">Yet all were nothing, had not my content,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117280">Rewarded me thus vilely with contempt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e117290" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Con ▪</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117300">Shape of collusion, mirror of deceit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117310">Fair form with foul deformities defiled. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117320">Know that I am contempt in nature scornful,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117330">Foe to thy good, and fatal to thy life ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117340">That while I joyed in glory and account,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117350">Disdained all virtue, and contemned all vice. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117360">Good, bad ▪ were held with me of equal price. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117370">And now the waning of my greatness comes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117380">Occasioned by thy love, whom Mars aspected,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117390">And I that all despised am now rejected. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117400">For which I thee reject, disdain and hate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117410">Wishing thee die a death disconsolate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e117420" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117430">Yet once regard me as a thing regardless,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117440">Thou art the abjects wretch alive esteemed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117450">I worse than vileness in the world am deemed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117460">I scorned, thou hated, each like other being,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117470">Live we together void of other being. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e117480" who="A15515-contempt">
          <speaker>Con:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117490">Lightness of lightest things that vaunt of life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117500">Sprung from the frothy bubbles of the sea:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117510">Leave to solicit him that loathes thy looks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117520">Spitting upon thy faces painted pride</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117530">I will forsake thee, and in silence shroud</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117540">This loathed trunk despised and abhorred,</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e117550">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e117560">She offers to follow, he drives her back.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e117570" who="A15515-venus">
          <speaker>Venus:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117580">So flies the murderer from the mangled limbs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117590">Left limbless on the ground by his fell hand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117600">So runs the tiger from the bloodless prey,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117610">Which when his fell stomach is of hunger staunched. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117620">Thou murderer, tiger, glutted with my fair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117630"><pb facs="25"/> leav'st me forsaken, map of grief and care. ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117640">Oh what is beauty humbled to the base,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117650">That never had a care of civil thought? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117660">O what is favour in an obscure place? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117670">Like unto pearls that for the swine are bought:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117680">Beauty and favour where no virtue bides,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117690">Proves foul, deformed, and like a shadow glides. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117700">Ah that my woe could other women warn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117710">To love true wedlock or the virgin's life:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117720">For me too late, for them fit time to learn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117730">The honour of a maid and constant wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117740">One is adored by gods with holy rites,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117750">The last like lamps both earth and heaven lights. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117760">But the foul horror of a harlot's name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117770">Even of the lecher counted as a scorn:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117780">Whose forehead bears the mark of hateful shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117790">Of the lust-lover hated and forlorn. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117800">O such is Venus, so shall all such be</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117810">As use base lust, and foul adultery. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e117820">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e117830">Enter the Duke, his daughter, priest, and scholar: thou compass the stage, from one part let a smoke arise: at which place they all stay.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e117840" who="A15515-priest">
          <speaker>Priest</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117850">Immortal mover of this glorious frame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117860">That circles us about with wonder great,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117870">Receive the offerings of our humble hearts</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117880">And bodies prostrate on the lowly earth. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e117890">They all kneel down,</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117900">Our sins hath drawn the fury of thy wrath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117910">And turned our peace to misery and war:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117920">But if repentant souls may purchase grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117930">We crave it humbly, and intend to live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117940">Hereafter more reformed than we have done. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117950">For pride, we entertain humility:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117960">For our presumption, due obedience:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117970"><pb facs="25"/> love for contempt, and chastity for lust:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117980">The cabin of contempt doth burn with fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e117990">In which our sins are cast, and there consume. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118000">Hear us ye heavenly powers, help we require,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118010">And be propitious to the penitent. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e118020">Enter a messenger.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118030" who="A15515-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118040">Rise from the humble earth my noble lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118050">Rise up ye priests, princes, and people rise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118060">And hear the gladsome tidings I unfold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118070">Of happy peace and glorious victory. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e118080">They all rise and cast incense into the fire.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118090" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118100">For that sweet voice offered to us by man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118110">Cast sweetest incense into holy fires,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118120">And while they burn, tell on thy happy news,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118130">That we may bear and honour heavenly powers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118140" who="A15515-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118150">When sateros my lord had brought your power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118160">In view of our presuming enemies:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118170">And equal place was chosen for the field,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118180">He sent a herald, willing them restore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118190">The wrongs that in Booetia they had done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118200">And leave the country, turning to their home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118210">Or else resolve on doubtful chance of war. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118220">They proud, ambitious, covetous of gain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118230">Returned an answer filled with disdain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118240">Then was the signal given, and streamers red,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118250">Menacing blood on either side advanced. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118260">Drums, fifes, and trumpets drowned the cries of men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118270">That each where fell before their foemen's swords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118280">Mars there showed ruthless rage on either part,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118290">And murder ranged thorough every rank. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118300">Dust dimmed the sun's light, and the powders smoke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118310">Seemed like thick clouds in air congluminate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118320">Thus was seven hours consumed, and doubtful chance</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118330">Sometime with us, sometime with them abode:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118340">Till at the length our general gave charge</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118350">To found retreat, which made the hopeful foe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118360"><pb facs="26"/> pursue regardless our retiring bands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118370">That being knit together in firm rank,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118380">A fresh pursued their straggling followers. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118390">Then fell their glory like the ripened corn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118400">Before the sickle and the reapers hand:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118410">In brief, some fled, most slain, and many taken</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118420">Have left the honour to Booetia. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118430" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118440">To heavens and sateros return we thanks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118450">For thy reward receive this recompense:</l>
          <stage xml:id="A15515-e118460">The Duke gives him his upper garment.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118470">Ourselves will forward to salute our friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118480">That fought for honour of Booetia. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118490">Sound drum and trumpet notes triumphantly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118500">Heavens have the honour for this victory. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e118510">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e118520">Enter with drum and trumpet sateros lead between Mars and Mercury, Raph cobbler and his wife following, and other soldiers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118530" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118540">Thus sateros have we assisted thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118550">Our true sworn soldier, worthy man at arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118560">And the Booetian Duke hath heaven appeased,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118570">By firing false contempt and loathed lust. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118580">Mercury the son and messenger of Jove</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118590">With me shall pass unto my warlike house. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118600">Go thou unto the Duke with all thy train,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118610">That longs to see thee, and requite thy pain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118620" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118630">To mighty Mars and wary Mercury</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118640">Poor sateros gives thanks and vows his duty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118650" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118660">Are ye here i'faith? here's two on ye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118670">Raph cobbler may curse the time that here knew your company ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118680" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118690">What mine man? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118700" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e118710">I yours, what reason had you to make my wife mad? I and so mad to kill one? and then make me a prophet?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118720" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e118730">It was the secret judgement of the gods, sateros speak to the Duke to think on him, and to remit her fault.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118740" who="A15515-sateros">
          <pb facs="26"/>
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118750">It shall be done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118760" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118770">Is this the prophet? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118780" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118790">I that it is, that told you your own when 'twas. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118800" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118810">Sateros use him well. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118820" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e118830">Ne'er doubt you that: are ye remembered since ye told him, if ye set yourself against the gods they would drive you out of heaven.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118840" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118850">Well what of that? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118860" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15515-e118870">Faith at that time the world might well have afforded you a cart to ride in.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118880" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118890">Go too rap ▪ cease. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118900" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118910">Ay, ay, and great folk do amiss,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118920">Poor folk must hold their peace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118930" who="A15515-mercury">
          <speaker>Mer:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118940">Mars shall we hence? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118950" who="A15515-mars">
          <speaker>Mars:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e118960">Ay, farewell sateros. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e118970">Exeunt Mars and Mercury.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e118980">Enter with honour the Duke and his train.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e118990" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119000">Welcome brave soldier, welcome to you all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119010">Joy stops my words, I cannot speak my mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119020">But in this triumph pass we to the court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119030">Where you shall all receive your due deceits. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e119040" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119050">Thanks noble lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e119060" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119070">What shall I do then, and my wife? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e119080" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119090">I will provide for thee, and pardon her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e119100" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119110">Faith then farewell the court;</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119120">For now I'll not run and ride, nor no more abide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119130">But since my mad wife, has changed her mad life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119140">I'll even leave to be a prophet speaker,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119150">Take clouting leather and nawl, and fall to my old trade of the gentle craft the cobbler. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e119160" who="A15515-zelota">
          <speaker>Zelot:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119170">I Raph that will be fittest for us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e119180" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119190">Come sateros let me yet honour thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119200">To whom the heavens have given great victory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119210">And took in worth our worthless sacrifice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119220">Wherein contempt and lust with old ingratitude,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119230"><pb facs="27"/> have perished like fume that flies from fire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119240">March forward brave and worthy man at arms ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119250">Thy deeds shall be rewarded worthily:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119260">Embrace the scholar, live you two as friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119270">For arms and learning may not be at jar,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119280">Counsel prevents, counsel prevails in war. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e119290" who="A15515-sateros">
          <speaker>Sat:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119300">My thoughts are free from hate, let me not live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119310">When soldiers fail good letters to defend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e119320" who="A15515-scholar">
          <speaker>Scholar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119330">Let every scholar be a soldier's friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119340">As I am friend to thee and so will rest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e119350" who="A15515-raphe">
          <speaker>Raph:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119360">I so live, and ye are blessed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119370">How sayest thou zealot is not that life best. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15515-e119380" who="A15515-duke">
          <speaker>Duke:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119390">Then with due praise to heaven let us depart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15515-e119400">Our state supported both by arms and art. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15515-e119410">Exeunt.</stage>
        <closer xml:id="A15515-e119420">Fortuna crudelis.</closer>
        <trailer xml:id="A15515-e119430">Finis ▪</trailer>
        <pb facs="27"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A15515"><item xml:id="A15515-raphe" n="80">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-raphe</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">80</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-soldier" n="34">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-soldier</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">34</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-mercury" n="31">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-mercury</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">31</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-sateros" n="31">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-sateros</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">31</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-mars" n="30">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-mars</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">30</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-venus" n="28">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-venus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">28</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-duke" n="27">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-duke</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">27</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-contempt" n="25">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-contempt</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">25</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-scholar" n="19">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-scholar</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">19</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-charon" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-charon</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-melpomene" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-melpomene</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-country-gentleman" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-country-gentleman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-emnius" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-emnius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-clio" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-clio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-thalia" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-thalia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-zelota" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-zelota</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-echo" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-echo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-ina" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-ina</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-ru" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-ru</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-herald" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-herald</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-folly" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-folly</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-courtier" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-courtier</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-messenger" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-porter" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-porter</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-ceres" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-ceres</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-countrygentleman" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-countrygentleman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-priest" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-priest</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-codrus" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-codrus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-unassigned" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-cobbler" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-cobbler</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-all" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-voice" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-voice</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-newfangle" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-newfangle</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-prisoner" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-prisoner</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-country_gentleman" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-country_gentleman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-small_voice" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-small_voice</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-all_voices" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-all_voices</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-hasty_voice" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-hasty_voice</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-great_voice" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-great_voice</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15515-mor" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15515-mor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

