<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A19975">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Humor Out of Breath <date type="creation_date">1608</date></title>
        <author>Day, John</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Madeline Burg</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A19975.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Humour out of breath. A comedie diuers times latelie acted, by the Children of the Kings Reuells. Written by Iohn Day.</title>
            <author>Day, John, 1574-1640?</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>30 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2009 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99845070</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 6411.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 268.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">9946</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19975</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Humour out of breath. A comedie diuers times latelie acted, by the Children of the Kings Reuells. Written by Iohn Day.</title>
            <author>Day, John, 1574-1640?</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[56] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>[By Richard Bradock] for Iohn Helmes, and are to be sold at his shop in Saint Dunstons Church-yard in Fleet-street,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1608.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: [A]2 B-G4 H2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A19975-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A19975-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A19975-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A19975-e100040"><pb facs="1"/>Humour out of breath.</p>
        <p xml:id="A19975-e100050">A comedy divers times lately acted, by the children of the King's revels written by John day.</p>
        <p xml:id="A19975-e100060">Printed at London for John helms, and are to be sold at his shop in saint Dunston's churchyard in Fleetstreet, 1608.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A19975-e100070">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head><pb facs="2"/>To signior nobody.</head>
        <p xml:id="A19975-e100080">Worthless sir, I present you with these my unperfect labours, knowing that what defect in me or neglect in the printer hath left unperfect, judgement in you will wink at, if not think absolute. Being to turn a poor friendless child into the world, yet sufficiently featured too, had it been all of one man's getting, (Woe to the iniquity of time the whilst) my desire is to prefer him to your service: in which, as he shall be sure to get nothing, so likewise my hope is, he shall not lose much: for your bounty neither makes stranger's love you, nor your followers envy you: you are a patron worthy the sisterhood, I mean, the poor half dozen, for the three elders, they climb above my element: the sun, the moon, and the seven stars being scarce worthy the survey of their workings: I protest I had rather bestow my pains on your good worship for a brace of angels certain, then stand to the bounty of a better-mans purse-bearer, or a very good woman gentleman-usher: my reason is I cannot attend: your bis dat, qui citò stands so like a loadstone over your great gate, that I fear, 'twill draw all the iron-pated muse-mongers about the town in a short time to your patronage. For mine own part I had rather be yours volens, then be driven nolens: so till I meet you next at your great castle in Fish-street, I'll neither taste of your bounty, nor be drunk to your health.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A19975-e100090">
          <salute xml:id="A19975-e100100">One of your first followers,</salute>
          <signed xml:id="A19975-e100110">John day.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A19975-e100120">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A19975-e100130">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A19975-e100140">
          <pb facs="3"/>
          <head>Actʋs 1. Scaena. 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e100150">Enter Octavio Duke of Venice, Hippolito and Francisco his sons, Florimell his daughter: Hortensio and others attendants.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100160" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Octa.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100170">Sons, hopeful buds of fruitful Italy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100180">Having banished war which like a prodigal ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100190">Kept wasteful revels with our subjects' blood:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100200">Since proud Anthonio our arch-enemy</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100210">Is in his journey towards th'underworld,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100220">Or hovers in the shade of banishment;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100230">Let us in peace smile at our victory ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100240">And every breast pass his opinion</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100250">What pastime best becomes a conqueror. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100260" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100270">What sport but conquest for a conqueror,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100280">Then with our wounds undressed ▪ our steeds still reined,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100290">Branded with steel ere we wipe off the blood</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100300">Of conquered foes, let's with our shriller bugles</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100310">Summon the surly landlord of the forest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100320">The kingly lion to a bloody parley,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100330">Combat the heart, the leopard or the boar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100340">In single and adventurous hardiment:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100350">The spirit of mirth in manly action rests,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100360">Having quelled men let's now go conquer beasts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100370" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100380">Manly resolved; Hippolito's advice ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100390" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100400">Rather like soldiers, and Octavio's sons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100410">Let's throw a general challenge through the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100420">For a proud tourney, at the which ourselves</l>
            <pb facs="4"/>
            <pb facs="4"/>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100430"><pb facs="5"/> consorted with a hundred of our knights,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100440">Accoutred like so many gods of war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100450">Will keep the lists 'gainst all adventurers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100460">Which like the suns light figured in a star,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100470">Should be a brief epitome of war. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100480" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100490">Noble and royal, your opinion daughter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100500" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100510">Faith I shall anger soldiers, I would pour</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100520">Spirit of life ▪ aurum potabile</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100530">Into the jaws of chap-fallen scholarship,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100540">That have since amorous quid was exiled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100550">Lyen in a swoon, y' have many holds for war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100560">I would once view a garrison for wit:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100570">'Twere heavenly sport to see a train of scholars</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100580">Like old trained soldiers skirmish in the schools ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100590">Traverse their ergoes and discharge their jests</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100600">Like peals of smallshot, were this motion granted</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100610">Myself would be free woman of their hall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100620">And sit as sister at their festival. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100630" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100640">Have we not Padua</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100650" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100660">Yes, but the commanders</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100670">Deal with our graduates, as the general</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100680">Doth with his soldier, gives him place for favour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100690">Not for deserving, look into't yourself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100700">You have courts for tennis, and methinks 'twere meet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100710">Learning should not stand bawling in the street</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100720">For want of houseroom: o 'tis much unfit</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100730">Courtiers should be all pleasure and small wit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100740" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100750">All that you speak is but what we command</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100760" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100770">But officer's father cannot understand</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100780">Their lords at first: wert not a gallant sight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100790">To see wits army royal come from fight? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100800">Some crowned with gold, others with wreath of bays,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100810">And whilst they hold their solemn holidays,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100820">Music should like a lover court the skies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100830">And from the world wrest ringing plaudities. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100840" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100850">My sister would make a rare beggar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100860" who="A19975-francisco">
            <pb facs="5"/>
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e100870">True, she's parcel poet, parcel fiddler already, and they commonly sing three parts in one.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100880" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100890">Wrong neither art nor music, they are twins</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100900">Born and begotten in heat, your thought of both. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e100910" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100920">I think my lord that music is divine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100930">Whose sacred strains have power to combine</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100940">The soul and body; and it reason bears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100950">For it is said that the celestial spheres,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100960">Dance to Apollo's lyre whose sprightly fires</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100970">Have tamed rude beasts and charmed men's wild desires:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100980">The author was immortal, the first strings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e100990">Made by a King, therefore an art for Kings:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101000">The world's a body, every liberal art</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101010">A needful member, music the soul and heart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101020" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101030">Well for her sex hath Florimell discourse</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101040">Of heavenly music, and since all conclude</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101050">It is an art divine, we were too rude</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101060">Should we reject it, music, I take great pride,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101070">To hear soft music and thy shrill voice chide. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101080" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101090">To please your grace, though i want voice and skill,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101100">I'll show myself obedient to your will. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e101110">Sing.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101120" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101130">This would have done rare at a scholar's window,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101140">How do you like it father? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101150" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101160">Highly my boys, I relish all delight ,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101170">For when the fiery spirit of hot youth</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101180">Kept house within me, I was all delight:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101190">Then could I take my love, no love more fair</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101200">By the smooth hand, and gazing in love's air</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101210">Tell her her beauty beautified the sky,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101220">And that the sun stole lustre from her eye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101230" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e101240">I do admire to hear my princely father thus merrily discourse of trifling love.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101250" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101260">Nay more my boys, when i was at your years,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101270">I went a pilgrimage through Italy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101280">To find the shrine of some love-hallowed saint. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101290">Devote to beauty, I would pray for love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101300"><pb facs="6"/> desiring beauty I would sue for love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101310">Admiring beauty I would serve for love:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101320">Pray, sue, and serve, till beauty granted love. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101330">If she denied me, I would swear she granted,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101340">If she did swear that she could never love me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101350">Then would I swear she could not choose but love me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101360">Let her swear never so much, still have I sworn,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101370">Till she had said, I should not be forsworn. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101380" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101390">I marry brothers, here was cunning love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101400">Learn like good scholars, he'll make you wise in love:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101410">He was a man in love, were you such men,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101420">Then were you men indeed, but boys till then. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101430" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101440">To please my father, I'll inquest of beauty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101450">And never make return till I have found,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101460">A love so fair, so rich, so honourable,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101470">As fits the honour of Octavio's sons. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101480" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101490">The like (You pleased) vows young Hippolito. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101500" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101510">Do boys, and I will teach you how to choose them. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101520">Elect not amongst whole troops of courtly dames,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101530">For amongst many, some must needs be ill:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101540">The seld seen phoenix ever sits alone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101550">Jove courted Danae when she was alone:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101560">Alone my boys, that is the only way,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101570">Ladies yield that alone, they else say nay. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101580" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101590">An expert soldier; how shall they choose them father? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101600" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101610">If her bright eye dim not the diamond,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101620">Say it is bright, but brighter iems delight you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101630">If that her breath do not perfume the air;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101640">Say it is sweet, but sweeter sweets content you. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101650">If that her cheek compared to the lily,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101660">Make not the lily black with whiter whiteness;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101670">Say it is lily white, but black to white,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101680">When your cho●●e white must have such high exceeds. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101690" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101700">Father you do exceed things possible,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101710">Faith say how many ladies have you seen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101720">Much fairer than myself, in all your travail? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101730" who="A19975-octavio">
            <pb facs="6"/>
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101740">Should the crow teach me, then no lady fairer,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101750">If judgement tell me, than a many fairer:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101760">Thou art mine own, i must think well of thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101770">Yet Florimella many do excel thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101780" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101790">Should the crow teach, I am not all crowblack. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101800">Though judgement; i not all perfection black,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101810">Though you have seen ladies that dim the day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101820">Yet will i think myself as fair as they. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101830" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101840">Do Florimella, and I'll one day get,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101850">A husband for thee that shall think thee fair. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101860" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101870">And time i'faith, that pretty sport would be,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101880">Wive it for them, you shall not husband me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101890" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101900">Yet you will take my counsel in your choice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e101910" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101920">Yes, if I had not years enough to choose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101930">Would you direct me as you do your sons? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101940">With daughter take a man with such a nose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101950">With such an eye, with such a colour beard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101960">Thus big, thus tall, with all his teeth afore;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101970">Thus lipped, thus legged, thus handsome, thus apparelled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101980">Were not this pitiful! O pitiful:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e101990">Now by the soul of soul ▪ commanding love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102000">I will not stoop to such obedience,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102010">I must be bid to blush when I am kissed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102020">Bid my love welcome, and I thank you sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102030">With no indeed, I know not what love is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102040">I never heard so much of love before,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102050">I pray take heed, nay fie you go too far,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102060">With such a rabble of prescriptions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102070">As never maid of a conceiving spirit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102080">Will follow them, yet brothers go you on,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102090">Take you good counsel, Florimell will none. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e102100">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102110" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102120">I daughter? are you so experienced? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102130">An elder woman might have spoken less,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102140">Yet by your leave minion, I'll watch you so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102150">Your ay shall still be governed by my no. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102160">But come my sons take pattern of great Jove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102170"><pb facs="7"/> early ith' morning suit yourselves for love. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e102180">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e102190">Enter Anthonio Duke of Mantua, Hermia and Lucida his daughters, they with angels and he with a net.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102200" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102210">Go daughters with your angels to the brook,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102220">And see if any silver-coated fish,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102230">Will nibble at your worm-emboweled hooks:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102240">Deceive the watery subjects, yet the name</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102250">Of foul deceit methinks should fray them from you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102260">Alack, alack, I cannot blame the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102270">That in the world there is so much deceit;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102280">When this poor simple trade must use deceit. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102290">But with what conscience can i make this net,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102300">Within whose meshes all are caught that come:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102310">They cousin one at once, this cousins many,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102320">I will undo't it shall not cozen any. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102330">But daughters go practice that little sin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102340">I'll mend this great fault ere the fault begin. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102350">O cozening fortune how hast thou deceived me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102360">Turning me out a doors to banishment,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102370">And made another lord of Mantua. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102380">I that was lord now slave to misery. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102390" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102400">Take comfort yet dear father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102410" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Ant</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102420">Comfort? no:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102430">My breast's turned prison, my proud jailer woe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102440">Locks out all comfort: where's your valiant brother? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102450" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102460">All discontent like to a wounded lion</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102470">He forages the woods, daring proud fortune</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102480">At her best weapon, he accounts this smart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102490">As a slight hurt, but far off from the heart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102500" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102510">How holds his humour? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102520" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102530">The same fashion still:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102540">But somewhat sadder-coloured death may end</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102550">But never change him, see our words have raised him. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e102560">Enter Aspero.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102570" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e102580">Fitly applied for 'a wals like a ghost ▪ why how now son?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102590" who="A19975-aspero">
            <pb facs="7"/>
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102600">Peace. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102610" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102620">Brother. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102630" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102640">Good now peace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102650">Wake me not as you love me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102660" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102670">What asleep ? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102680" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e102690">Ay, in a most sweet sleep, blisters o'your tongues for waking me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102700" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102710">Thou forgettest thyself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102720" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e102730">I should not be a courtier else, methought i was at a strange wedding?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102740" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102750">Prithee what wedding? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102760" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102770">Of a young lawyer and old madam conscience. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102780" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102790">I scarce believe that. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102800" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e102810">Nor i neither, because it was a dream, but methought the young man doted on the old woman exceedingly.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102820" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102830">That was miraculous! did they live together? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102840" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e102850">In the country they did, and agreed passing well, all the long vacation, and but for two things he would have carried her up to the term with him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102860" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102870">What things were those? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102880" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e102890">One was, because her gown was of the old fashion, the other was cause he would not have her by when he took fees ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102900" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102910">His reason for that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102920" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e102930">For fear if a bribe had been offered, she being by he should have had the bad conscience to take it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102940" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102950">His wife and he lived together. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102960" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e102970">Conscience and the lawyer, as lovingly as men and their wives do, one flesh but neither meddle nor make one with another</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e102980" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e102990">Man and wife part, that's strange! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103000" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e103010">O lord sit, profit can part the soul and the body, and why not man and wife, now you have had my dream father, let me understand yours.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103020" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103030">How can he dream, that never sleeps my son ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103040" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e103050">O best of all: why, your whole world doth nothing but dream, your Machiavel he dreams of state, deposing Kings, grounding new monarchies: the lover he dreams of kisses, amorous embraces: the new-married wife dreams,<pb facs="8"/> that rid of her young husband she hugs her old love, and likes her dream well enough too: the country gentle woman dreams that when her first husband's dead, she marries a knight, and the name of lady sticks so in her mind, that she's never at hearts-ease till she get her husband dubbed; the captain, he dreams of oppressing the soldiers, devising stratagems, to keep his dream, and that dream wakes in the pate of Octavio your arch-enemy ▪ who is not content to hurl us into the whirlpool of banishment, but binds weights at our heels leaden poverty, to sink us to the very depth that we should never rise again.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103060" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103070">Then since all dream, let us dream of revenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103080" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e103090">I marry sister, that were a dream worth dreaming, and I'll sleep out my brains but I'll compass it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103100" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103110">Pretty content; we kill our foes in dreams. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103120" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103130">Uds foot, I'll do it waking then. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103140" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103150">Aspero. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103160" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103170">At counsel table. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103180" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103190">Hear me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103200" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103210">In his Duchess arms, 'twere base to go disguised,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103220">No, my revenge shall wear an open brow;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103230">I will not play the coward, kill him first</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103240">And send my challenge after; I'll make known</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103250">My name, and cause of coming, if I thought</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103260">Grief like a painter had so spoiled my visage</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103270">He could not know me, on my breast I'd write</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103280">Howe'er I am disfigured through woe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103290">I am the thing was made for Aspero. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103300">Speak not, I am as constant as the centre,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103310">Some fortune good or bad doth beckon me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103320">And I will run, bitter revenge tastes sweet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103330">If here on earth farewell, in heaven we'll meet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103340">Attendance sirrah, your low comedy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103350">Craves but few actors, we'll break company. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103360" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103370">As many blessings as the sea hath sands</l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e103380">Exit cum puero</stage>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103390">Attend thee in thine honourable journey:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103400">Come pretty maids we have not wrought today,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103410"><pb facs="8"/> or fish, or fast, our need must needs obey. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e103420">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e103430">Enter Hippolito, Francisco, Florimell, and page meeting them.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103440" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103450">Now sirrah what have you been about? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103460" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103470">About my living sit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103480" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103490">What's that? feeding? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103500" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103510">No sir, looking into the under-officers about the court. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103520" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103530">Canst get any living out of them? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103540" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e103550">Ay sir, my betters get good livings out of officers, and why not I? but to be plain, I have been seeking your good lordship.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103560" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e103570">But your boyship hath so sought us, that we have found you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103580" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103590">Will you sell your findings my lord? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103600" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103610">They are scarce worth giving. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103620" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e103630">Yes, a box to keep them in, for fear you lose them again.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103640" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e103650">And I were a man as I am no woman, I'd pepper your box for that jest.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103660" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103670">You jest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103680" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103690">In earnest la I would madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103700" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103710">Well sir, no more, here comes our royal father. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e103720">Enter Octavio, Hortensio, Flamineo, etc.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103730" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103740">How now my boys? provided for your journey? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103750">Beauty conduct you: what, attired like shepherds? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103760">I thought t'have seen you mounted on your steeds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103770">Whose fiery stomachs from their nostrils breathe</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103780">The smoke of courage, and whose wanton mouths</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103790">Do proudly play upon their iron bits:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103800">And you in stead of these poor weeds in robes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103810">Richer than that which Ariadne wrought,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103820">Or Cythara's aery-moving vestment. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103830">Thus should you seem like lovers suited thus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103840">You'd draw fair ladies' hearts into their eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103850"><pb facs="9"/> and strike the world dead with astonishment. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103860" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103870">Father such cost doth pass your sons revenues</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103880">We take example from immortal Jove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103890">Who like a shepherd would repair to love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103900" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103910">And gentle love conduct you both my sons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103920">Daughter go bring them onward in their way,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103930">Were not we called back by important business,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103940">We would not leave you thus: Hortensio</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103950">Is my disguise prepared, for i unknown</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103960">Will see how they behave themselves in love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103970" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e103980">'Tis done my lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e103990" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104000">Once more my boys adieu:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104010">He sends you forth that means to follow you. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e104020">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104030" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104040">Now brothers you must amongst these wenches,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104050">Faith for a wager which shall get the fairest? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104060" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104070">I'll gauge a 100. crowns mine proves the fairest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104080" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104090">A match, I'll venture twice so much of mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104100" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e104110">And I'll lay 'gainst you both, that both your loves get them when you can where you can, or how you can, shall not be able to compare with me in beauty.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104120" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104130">That wager I'll take for 'tis surely won. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104140" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104150">'Las thou art but a star to beauty's sun. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104160" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104170">Star me no stars, go you and stare for love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104180">I'll stay at home, and with my homely beauty</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104190">Purchase a love, shall think my looks as fair,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104200">As those fair loves that you shall fetch so far;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104210">But take your course, fate send you both fair luck. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104220" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104230">How if't be foul? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104240" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e104250">Nay if't be forked, you must bear it off with head and shoulders.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104260" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104270">O stale, that jest runs oth' lees. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104280" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e104290">You must consider 'tis drawn out of the bottom of my wit.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104300" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104310">O shallow wit, at the bottom so soon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104320" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104330">Deep enough to lay you in the mire. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104340" who="A19975-page">
            <pb facs="9"/>
            <speaker>Page.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104350">Or else 'tis shallow indeed, for they are foundered already,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104360">But I must play dun, and draw them all out o'th mire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104370">What's o'clock my lord? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104380" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104390">Which of them dost ask? thou seest they are two. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104400" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104410">What two are they madam? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104420" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104430">Why two fools. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104440" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e104450">Is it not passed two, doth it not come somewhat near three sister:</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104460" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e104470">Show pair royal and take't, but come my lord you have stood fooling long enough, will you about your business in good earnest?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104480" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104490">Indeed we will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104500" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e104510">And they are deeds you must trust too, for women will respect your words but slightly without deeds.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104520" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e104530">Why, are women called angels but because they delight in good deeds, and love heaven, but that it will not be won without them.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104540" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104550">They shall have deeds. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104560" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104570">Brother, and good deeds too:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104580">They are tongues that men must speak with when they woo. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104590" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104600">That tongue we'll practise, sister to love we leave you. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e104610">Exeunt brothers.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104620" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104630">Louers take heed least cunning love deceive you. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e104640">Exit with page.</stage>
          </sp>
          <trailer xml:id="A19975-e104650">Finis actus primi.</trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A19975-e104660">
          <head>Actus secundus.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e104670">Enter Octavio disguised, Hortensio Flamineo.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104680" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104690">No more; thus suited I'll attend my sons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104700">Impute it not to any ruffian vain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104710">But to a father's wakeful providence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104720">Lovers like bees are privileged to taste,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104730">All buds of beauty: should they chance to light</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104740">Upon some worthless weed I'll hinder it:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104750"><pb facs="10"/> the eyes of youth will now and then dwell there,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104760">Whereas they should not glance, this doubt I fear. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104770" who="A19975-flamineo">
            <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104780">And well advised my liege should they incline</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104790">To love not fitting their estates and births,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104800">You with your present counsel may prevent them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104810" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104820">That's my intent, and further in my absence</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104830">I leave my land and daughter to thy charge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104840">The girl is wanton, if she gad abroad</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104850">Restrain her, bound her in her chamber door;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104860">My word's thy warrant, let her know so much:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104870">Farewell, at home I leave my fear with thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104880">And follow doubt abroad. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104890" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104900">I'll careful be. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e104910">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104920" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e104930">Now to my business, I have a strange habit, and I must cut out an humour suitable to it, and humours are picked so near the bone, a man can scarce get humour enough to give a flea his breakfast, but I am a stale ruffian, my habit is brave, and so shall my humour be, and here comes one to give me earnest of it.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e104940">Enter Aspero and his boy.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104950" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104960">Send him a letter that I come to kill him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104970" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e104980">'Twere great valour but little policy my lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e104990" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105000">How long have you been a Matchevillian boy? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105010" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105020">Ever since I practised to play the knave my lord,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105030" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105040">Then policy and knavery are somewhat a kin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105050" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105060">As near, as penury and gentry, a degree and half removed no more.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105070" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105080">How came in the kindred twixt gentry and penury? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105090" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105100">Shall I tell you sir ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105110" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105120">First tell me what thou art? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105130" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105140">Lime and hair: plaster of Paris, kneaded together with rye dow and goats milk, I am of a hot constitution, wonot freeze.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105150" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105160">Thy profession. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105170" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105180">A fool or a knave choose you which. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105190" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105200">Then thou art fit for any gentleman's company. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105210" who="A19975-octavio">
            <pb facs="10"/>
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105220">True boy, for your sweet fool and your fine knave are like a pair of upright shoes, that gentlemen wear so long now of one foot, then of another, till they leave them never a good sole.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105230" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105240">That makes your fool and your knave have such bad soles; but what dost thou seek?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105250" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105260">Mine own undoing sir, service. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105270" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105280">Indeed service is like the common law, it undoes any one that follows it long, canst describe service?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105290" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105300">Yes, 'tis a vacant place, filled up with a complete knave, a miserable pandar, or an absolute beggar.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105310" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105320">Your opinion boy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105330" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105340">I say a servingman is an antecedent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105350" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105360">Because he sits before a cloak-bag. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105370" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105380">He is likewise a nominative case, and goes before his mistress.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105390" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105400">That's when the verb he goes before his mistress and he can agree together.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105410" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105420">If not, he turns accusative and follows his master. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105430" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105440">Wilt follow me fellow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105450" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105460">To a tavern, and thou wilt pay for my ordinary. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105470" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105480">My business is more serious, thou dost not know me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105490" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105500">Nor myself neither so long as I have maintenance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105510" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105520">Didst never hear of the wars betwixt Venice and Mantua.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105530" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105540">I cut some few of the Mantuans throats. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105550" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105560">And wert not a knave for't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105570" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105580">No, i was a Venetian commander, a great man: the reason of this question.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105590" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105600">Dost know the Duke of Venice? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105610" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105620">I am his right hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105630" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105640">Wilt do me a message to him ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105650" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105660">What is't? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105670" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105680">Tell him i hate him, my name's Aspero, has banished my father, usurps his Duke dome, and I come to be revenged.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105690" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105700">Anthonio's son? vesfoot haste any gold. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105710" who="A19975-aspero">
            <pb facs="11"/>
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105720">Thy reason. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105730" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105740">Shalt be revenged, give me money, I'll be thy snail and score out a silver path to his confusion.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105750" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105760">No, my revenge shall be like my father's wrongs in aperto lend me any honest aid.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105770" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e105780">Pax of honesty, it goes a-begging upon crutches, and can get relief out of few but scholars, I shall not kill him?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105790" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105800">I'd be thy death first. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105810" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105820">Yet you say you hate him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105830" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105840">Equal with my shame. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105850" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105860">Make him chew a bullet then. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105870" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105880">No, though my state with poverty be tainted,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105890">Mine acts and honour shall live still acquainted. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e105900" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105910">True moulded honour I admire the temper</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105920">Of thy mild patience, that not all the wrongs</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105930">I laid upon thee can enforce thy spleen</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105940">To foul requital, had thy coming ta'en</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105950">Any base level, it had cost thy life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105960">But being free and full of honour live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105970">Thy virtues teach me honour freely go,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105980">A secret friends worse than an open for:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e105990">You are too honest for my attendance, farewell sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106000" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106010">And thou too knavish for my employment. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106020">But here comes more company. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e106030">Enter Florimell and page.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106040" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106050">Boy, let your attendance wait further of ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106060">Under this shade i mean to take a sleep. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106070" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106080">And may you madam like a soldier sleep. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106090" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106100">How boy in alarms. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106110" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106120">No lady but in arms, and you had need of them too, for see the enemy comes down, shall I sound a parley ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106130" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106140">Peace wag. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106150" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106160">Peace, oh coward, offer peace and but two to two of them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106170" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106180">Boy dost know what gentleman it is? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106190" who="A19975-page">
            <pb facs="11"/>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106200">Gentle madam no, but he is a man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106210" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106220">Believe me boy he is a proper man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106230" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106240">Man is a proper name to a man, and so he may be a proper man.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106250" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106260">I love him he's a very proper man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106270" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106280">She loves him for his properties, and indeed many women love men only to make properties of them.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106290" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106300">Pray gentleman if no more, tell me where you were born. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106310" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106320">Fair virgin if so much, nowhere somewhere anywhere , where you would have me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106330" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106340">Faith I would have it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106350" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106360">Marry and you shall have it lady. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106370" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106380">What shall i have sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106390" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106400">Why a kiss. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106410" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106420">Nothing else: we courtiers ▪ count them trifles, not worth taking.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106430" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106440">Why then bestow one of me I'll take it most thankfully .</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106450" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106460">I will not stand with you for a trifle, sir pray where were you born?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106470" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106480">In Italy, but never yet in Venice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106490" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106500">You may in Venice, gentle sir adieu. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e106510">Exit .</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106520" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106530">Gentle lady thrice as much to you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106540" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106550">Farewell sweet heart. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e106560">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106570" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106580">God a mercy bagpudding. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106590" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106600">You may in Venice gentle sir adieu? this begets wonder. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106610" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106620">You're not wise then ▪ what do you take her for? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106630" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106640">Some great woman ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106650" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106660">Some woman great with child, be ruled, she's a pink board her.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106670" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106680">But how ▪ the means. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106690" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106700">Make but a shot of flattery at her broad side, and she'll strike sail presently.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106710" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106720">Flattery ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106730" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106740">I flattery, women are like fiddlers, speak them fair they'll play of any instrument.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106750" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106760">Ay, that they can play of ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106770" who="A19975-boy">
            <pb facs="12"/>
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106780">She's a butcher cannot play a little of all ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106790" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106800">And to common that will play too much of any, but come I'll use means to get her.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106810" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106820">Nay you must first have means to give her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106830" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106840">Why in the course of scholarship, the genitive case goes before the dative.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106850" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106860">The grammarians are fools that placed them so; for in rerum natura, the dative goes before the genitive, you must always give before you can get, lovers are fools, and fools must be liberal.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106870" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106880">Will not women respect a man for his good parts? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106890" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106900">Yes, some few; but all for his good gifts, a gentleman with his good gifts sit at the upper end of the table on a chair and a cushion, when a scholar with his good parts will be glad of a joint stool in the lobby with the chambermaids.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106910" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106920">I will have good gifts and show myself liberal to, though I beg for't.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106930" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e106940">I think that will be the end, for penury has ta'en a leaf of your pocket to keep court in this Christmas.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e106950" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106960">Well, howsoe'er , she's fair and courteous,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106970">And courteous fair, is a fair gift in ladies:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106980">She may be well descended, if she be,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e106990">She's fit for love, and why not then for me. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e107000">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107010" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e107020">And you be not fitted in Venice 'tis strange, for 'tis counted the best flesh shambles in Italy: but here's no notable coward, that having suffered wrong by a man, seeks to right himself of a woman.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e107030">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e107040">Enter Hippolito Francisco like shepherds, Octavio in disguise.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107050" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e107060">Look you sir, I am like an irish beggar, and an English burr, will stick close where I find a good nap, I must and will dwell with you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107070" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107080">What canst do:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107090" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e107100">Still aquavitæ, stamp crabs, and make mustard, I can do as much as all the men you keep ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107110" who="A19975-francisco">
            <pb facs="12"/>
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107120">Prithee what? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107130" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e107140">Why undo you, and twenty could do no more, but business, come my wits grow rusty for employment.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107150" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107160">Canst keep counsel ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107170" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107180">My mother was a midwife. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107190" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107200">Hast any skill in love? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107210" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e107220">I am one of Cupid's agents, have Ovid's ars amandi ad ungues, know 〈◊〉 and can apply remedium, and minister effectum to a hair, but why do you ask ▪ have you traversed an action in love's spiritual court ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107230" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107240">Not to dissemble, we have. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107250" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e107260">And without dissembling you'll never come out of it, but tell me true, are you in love already ▪ or have you the desire to be in love</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107270" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107280">Indeed I am in love to be in love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107290" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107300">And I desire to live in fond desire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107310">And yet I doubt to each blind fancy's f●e●. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107320" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107330">'Tis good to doubt, but 'tis not good to fear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107340">Yet still to doubt, will at the least prove fear;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107350">Doubt love, 'tis good, but 'tis not good to fear it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107360">Love hurts them most, that least of all come near it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107370" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107380">Then to doubt love is the next way to love ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107390" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107400">Doubtless it is if you misdoubt not love ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107410" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107420">Doubt and misdoubt? what difference is there here? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107430" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107440">Yes, much: when men misdoubt, 'tis said they fear ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107450" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107460">But is it good in love to be in doubt ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107470" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107480">No not in love, doubt then is 〈◊〉</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107490">'Tis good to doubt before you be in love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107500">Doubt counsels, how 〈◊〉 loves misery. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107510" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107520">Your doubtful counsel counsels us to love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107530" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107540">To equal love, I like experience speak. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107550" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107560">Experienced lover, you have spoken well. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107570" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107580">Experience wanting lovers, truth I tell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107590">Young wits be wife, in love live constant still,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107600">You need nor doubt good hap not misdoubt ill. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e107610">Enter Lucida and Hermonia with Angles.</stage>
          <p xml:id="A19975-e107620"><pb facs="13"/>And see your discourse has conjured up beauty in the likeness of two country-maids, but you shall not come in the circles of their arms if i can keep you out.</p>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107630" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107640">These are too mean for love, brother let's leave them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107650" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107660">What? speechless? will you make dumb virgins of them? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107670" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107680">O we are sons of a great father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107690" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e107700">So is the sun of heaven, yet he smiles on the bramble as well as the lily, kisses the check of a beggar as lovingly as a gentlewoman, and 'tis good to imitate, him 'tis good.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107710" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107720">Say sister, had we not fine sport today? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107730" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107740">We had, if death may be accounted play. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107750" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107760">Why 'tis accounted pleasure to kill fish. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107770" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107780">A pleasure nothing pleasant to the fish. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107790" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107800">Yet fishes were created to be killed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107810" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107820">Cruel creation then to have lives spilt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107830" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107840">Their bodies being food, maintain our breath. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107850" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107860">What bodies then have we to live by death? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107870" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107880">Come, come, you vainly argue, it is good. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107890" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107900">What is it good to kill? o god o god? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107910" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107920">If it be sin, than you yourself's a sinner. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107930" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107940">I thank proud fortune fort, my woes beginner. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107950" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e107960">Foot are ye not ashamed to stand by like idle ciphers, and such places of account void? and they had been rich offices and you poor courtiers, you would have been in them in half the time.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107970" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e107980">Though against stomach. —</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e107990" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108000">Nothing against stomach and you love me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108010" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108020">Fair maids if so ▪ you be you are well met. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108030" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108040">Shepherds or be what else you are well met. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108050" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108060">'Tis well, if that well met we be to you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108070" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108080">If not to us you are unto yourselves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108090" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108100">We did not meet, you saw us come together. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108110" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108120">Whatever we saw ▪ you yet ere you came hither. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108130" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108140">We did, we met in kindred, we are brothers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108150" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108160">So shepherds we did meet for we are sisters. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108170" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108180">Then sisters, let us brothers husbands be. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108190" who="A19975-hermia">
            <pb facs="13"/>
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108200">So brothers without our leaves you well may be. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108210" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108220">Say we desire to husband it with you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108230" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108240">Know we desire no husbands such as you ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108250" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108260">A shepherd is an honest trade of life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108270" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108280">Yet honest shepherd has with honest trade some strife. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108290" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108300">He seldom swears but by his honesty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108310" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108320">So honest men do too as well as he. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108330" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108340">But will you trust a shepherd when he vows,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108350" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108360">No never, if his oath be that he loves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108370" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108380">Yet if I swear, that needs must be mine oath,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108390" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108400">Swear not, for we are misbelievers both. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108410" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108420">Let us persuade you to believe we love you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108430" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108440">First we entreat you give us time to prove you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108450" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108460">Take time, mean time we'll praise ye to our powers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108470" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108480">O time, sometime shepherds have idle hours. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108490" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108500">I'll say thy cheek no natural beauty lacks,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108510" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108520">Good, if it had been spoke behind our backs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108530" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108540">I'll say this is the heaven of heavenly graces. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108550" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108560">O heaven, how they can flatters to our faces. Exeunt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108570" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108580">Brother the last is fairest in my eye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108590" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108600">I but the first brother is first in beauty ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108610" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108620">First in your choice, but not in beauty sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108630" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e108640">Come ye so near as choice: then 'tis time for me to stop for fear the music run too far out of tune, how now gallants? in dumps.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108650" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108660">No, but in love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108670" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108680">That's a dump, loves nothing but an Italian dump or a</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108690">French brawl. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108700" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108710">Methinks 'tis sweeter music. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108720" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e108730">And 'twere in tune I confess it, but you take your parts too low, you are treble courtiers, and will never agree with these country manikins, the music's too base, never meddle in't.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108740" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108750">Peace dotard, peace, thy sight of love is done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108760">Thou canst not see the glory of love's sun. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108770">Spent age with frosty clouds thy sight doth dim,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108780"><pb facs="14"/> that thou art blind to see and apt to sin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108790" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108800">Is it accounted sin to speak the truth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108810" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108820">And worse, when age spits poison against youth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108830" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108840">They do not fit your callings, let them go. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108850" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108860">Yet they are fair: we love, thou art love's foe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108870" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108880">I am your friend, and wish you from this love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108890" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e108900">Canst thou heave hills? than thou my thoughts mayst move ▪ but never else.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108910" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108920">Never! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108930" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108940">No never. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108950" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108960">Stay. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108970" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e108980">We are bound for love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e108990" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109000">Hate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109010" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109020">Hinder not our way. <stage xml:id="A19975-e109030">Exeunt brothers.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109040" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109050">I boys? will eagles eaglets turn to bastards. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109060">Then must i change my vain, and once more prove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109070">To teach you how to hate as well as love. <stage xml:id="A19975-e109080">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <trailer xml:id="A19975-e109090">Finis actus secundi.</trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A19975-e109100">
          <head>Actus tertius.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e109110">Enter page and Florimell ▪</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109120" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109130">Sweet honey candy madam, if it be no forfeit to tell tales out of Cupid's free school, tell what proficient your lover Aspero proves.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109140" who="A19975-unassigned">
            <speaker>Flo ▪</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109150">Now so love help me lot, a passing weak one and very unready.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109160" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109170">The better, for women would have their lovers unready to choose.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109180" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109190">Now ready you are to play the knave? but to Aspero</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109200" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109210">I do not think but there's good music in him, your tongue harps so much upon his name ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109220" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109230">I shall never forget him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109240" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109250">I'faith lady then I know what i know ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109260" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109270">What do you know I prey? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109280" who="A19975-page">
            <pb facs="14"/>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109290">Marry that if you never forget him, you shall ever remember him, was he never in your chamber ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109300" who="A19975-florimel">
            <speaker>Fio.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109310">Yes, but he showed himself the strangest fool: and by my troth lo. I am sorry for't to, i had as good an appetite to maintain discourse; but here 'a comes, if ever I choose a man by the fullness of his calf, or a cock by the crowing, look and the bashful fool do not blush already.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109320" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109330">You may do well to kiss him, and make him bold madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109340" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109350">Boy, go know what strange gentleman that is ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109360" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109370">Slid what a strange lady's this madam though I seem a stranger to you, i lay with one last night that's well acquainted with you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109380" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109390">Acquainted with me? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109400" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109410">And knows you, and loves you, and you love him, and have bestowed kind favours of him to.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109420" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109430">I bestow favours? what favours? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109440" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109450">Though 'twere but a trifle he took it as kindly as some would have done a kiss ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109460" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109470">Lord what a while this jest has been a brooding? and it proves but addle too now it is hatched.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109480" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109490">'Tis a pig of your own sow madam, and I hope your wit will bestow the nursing of it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109500" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109510">So it had need, I think 'tis like to have but a dry nurse of yours.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109520" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109530">O dry jest, all the wit in your head will scarce make sippits in't, what a ground? and such a fair landing place? get ashore, or be rank amongst fools for ever.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109540" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109550">And faith is't not pity such a proper man should keep company with a fool.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109560" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109570">I keep company with none but you lady. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109580" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109590">You keep mine against my will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109600" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109610">So do I the fools I protest; but take away yours, I'll soon shift away the fools.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109620" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109630">I have not seen a fool so handsomely shifted in Venice.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109640" who="A19975-aspero">
            <pb facs="15"/>
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109650">But come, shall the fool and you be friends? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109660" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109670">The fool and i? you're too familiar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109680" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109690">Why, i hope a fool may be a lady's familiar at all times ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109700" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109710">Come you're too saucy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109720" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109730">Indeed 'tis a fool's part of Jove to be in the sauce afore my</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109740">Lady; otherwise I am neither fool nor saucy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109750" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109760">Not, proud sir? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109770" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109780">Not, coy lady; come why should your tongue make so many false fires that never come from your heart: you love me, I know you love me, your spirit, your look, your countenance betrays it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109790" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109800">You jest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109810" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109820">In earnest you do, and you shall know't in earnest too, lend me this jewel.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109830" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109840">Jewel? away you sharking companion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109850" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109860">How? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109870" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109880">Wandering stravagant, that like a drone flies humming from one land to another.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109890" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109900">'Slight and thou hast any wit, now show her thy sting. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109910" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109920">And lightest upon every dairy maid and kitchen-wench. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109930" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109940">And now and then on a lady's lip as —</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109950" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e109960">You did of mine you would say, and i am heart sorry you can say it, and when by your buzzing flattery, you have sucked the smallest favour from them, you presently make wing for another.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109970" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e109980">Marry buz. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e109990" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110000">Double the zard and take the whole meaning for your labour.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110010" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110020">The buzzards wit's not so bald yet I trow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110030" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110040">A word in your ear, madam the buzzard will anger you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110050" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110060">With staying you do. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110070" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110080">With going I shall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110090" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110100">Away. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110110" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110120">I away, never entreat, 'tis too late, if you send after me, I will not come back, if you write to me, I will not answer, drown your eyes in tears, I will not wipe them, break your heart with<pb facs="15"/> sighs, i will not pity you: never look, signs cannot move me, if you speak, 'tis too late, if you entreat, 'tis bootless, if you hang upon me, 'tis needless, I offered love and you scorned it, my absence will be your death, and I am proud on't ▪</p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e110130">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110140" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110150">Is he gone boy? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110160" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110170">Yes faith madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110180" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110190">Clean out of sight? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110200" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110210">And out of mind to, or else you have not the mind of a true woman.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110220" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110230">Thou readest a false comment boy, call him again; yet do not, my heart shall break ere it bend.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110240" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110250">Or else it holds not the true temper of woman ▪ hood, but faith tell me madam, do you love him?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110260" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110270">As a Welshman doth toasted cheese, I cannot dine without him, he's my pillow I cannot sleep quietly without him; my rest, I cannot live without him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110280" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110290">O that he knew it lady. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110300" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110310">He does, he would never have left me else, he does</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110320" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110330">You called him fool, but methinks he proves a physician, has found the disease of your liver, by the complexion of your looks, but see he returns.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e110340">Enter Aspero meditating.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110350" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110360">And now methinks i loathe him more than I loved him ▪ go run for Hortensio my guardian, bid him come armed, thet's intent of treason tell him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110370" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110380">My lady cannot choose but dance well, she's so full of pretty changes.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e110390">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110400" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110410">I wonder you dare come in my sight, considering the wrong you did me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110420" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110430">I came I confess, but with no intent to see you i protest, and that shall be manifested by the shortness of my stay.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110440" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110450">'Tis too long and 'twere shorter than 'tis, will he not court me? not? nor speak to me neither? nay never ask pardon ▪ 'tis too late, we shall ha'you come to my window one of these mornings with<pb facs="16"/> music, but do not, my patience is to much out of tune, out of my sight I hate thee, worse than I loathe painting, I hate thee, out of my sight.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110460" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110470">Enough, will you be a quiet woman yet? will you, speak afore my resolve take strength? will you, do but say you are sorry I ask no mends but a kiss, kindly, come: shall I ha't?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110480" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110490">I'll kiss a toad first. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110500" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110510">You will, remember this another time, a toad you will: i know thou lovest me, and i see the pride of thy humour; I do, and thou shalt know I do; half an hour hence we shall have you weeping on your knees, with oh my Aspero would I had died when I rejected thee, but do, weep till i pity thee; a toad! I'll make thee creep on thy knees for a kiss.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110520" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110530">You will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110540" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110550">Thy bare knees, i will, and go without it to. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110560" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110570">Out humoured? O I would sell my part of immortality. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110580" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110590">But to touch my hand, thou wouldst, I know thou wouldst,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110600" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110610">O how spleen swells me? help Hortensio, creep a my knees? Hortensio. </p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e110620">Enter Hortensio with his man assistance.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110630" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110640">How fares my beauteous charge? weeping lady? the law shall fetch red water from his veins that hath drawn blood of your eyes, is this the traitor?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110650" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110660">Traitor? in thy disloyal throat thou liest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110670" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110680">O monstrous, a wish's you choked my lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110690" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110700">How! choked? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110710" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110720">I choked? for a wish's the traitor in your throat, and he's a very small traitor that is not able to choke a wiser man than your lordship.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110730" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110740">Down with him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110750" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110760">Ay, down with him, if he stick in your throat, and spare not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110770" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110780">Do not kill him, though he deserves death yet do not kill him, only disweapon him; so.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110790" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110800">But madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110810" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110820">I will not hear him, keep him; but keep him safe on your<pb facs="16"/> lives, if he get away or miscarry in prison: as I am heir of Venice I'll have your heads for't. <stage xml:id="A19975-e110830">They bind</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110840" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110850">I warn you madam, if irons will hold him.<stage xml:id="A19975-e110860">Him.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110870" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110880">Fie, fie, with a cord? here, bind him with my scarf, that will hold, and yet stand away, I'll do't myself, I cannot trust him with you, lest you should let him sometime scape free: besides, you cannot use him according to the quality of his offence, and because I'll glory in his bondage my chamber shall be his prison, let him have neither light meat nor drink, but what i provide him myself.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110890" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110900">Your will's a law, we obey it madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110910" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110920">She knows me sure; well, though my joys be thrall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110930">My comforts this, a speedy death ends all. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e110940">Exit with Hort. and ass.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110950" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e110960">O you are not gone then. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110970" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e110980">Here's a new kind of courting, never seen before i think.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e110990" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111000">He would anger me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111010" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111020">Nay you take a course, to anger him first i think. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111030" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e111040">Should i have let him go, (As I could no other way detain him in modesty) and he had set his love on some other, 'twould have fretted my heart strings asunder.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111050" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111060">Why did you set him so light then? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111070" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111080">Not for any hate, but in pride of my humour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111090" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e111100">Why did you command him close prisoner to your chamber.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111110" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e111120">That I may feed mine eye with the sight of him, and be sure no other beauty can rob me of his company: I will have't all, I will not lose an inch of him: and in this, I but imitate our Italian dames, who cause their friends to clap their jealous husbands in prison, that if they have occasion to use them within forty weeks and a day, they may surely know where to find them.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e111130">Exit.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111140" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e111150">If I had any knavery in me, as i am all honesty, I could make a notable scene of mirth betwixt these two amourists.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e111160">Enter</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e111170"><pb facs="17"/>Enter Antonio with a net.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111180" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111190">Early sorrow, art got up so soon? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111200">What? ere the sun ascendeth in the East? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111210">O what an early waker art thou grown? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111220">But cease discourse, and close unto thy work;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111230">Under this drooping myrtle will I sit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111240">And work a while upon my corded net;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111250">And as I work, record my sorrows past,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111260">Asking old time, how long my woes shall last:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111270">And first, but stay alas what do i see? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111280">Moist gum like tears, drop from this mournful tree</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111290">And see, it sticks like birdlime; 'twill not part;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111300">Sorrow is even such birdlime at my heart. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111310">Alas poor tree, dost thou want company? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111320">Thou dost, I see't, and i will weep with thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111330">Thy sorrows make thee dumb, and so shall mine. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111340">It shall be tongueless, and so seem like thine;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111350">Thus will I rest my head unto thy bark,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111360">Whilst my sighs tell my sorrows; hark tree, hark. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e111370">Enter Hippolito and Francisco.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111380" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e111390">Fie, fie, how heavy is light love in me?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111400" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e111410">How slow runs swift desire?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111420" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111430">This leaden air,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111440">This ponderous feather, merry melancholy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111450" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111460">This passion, which, but in passion</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111470">Hath not his perfect shape. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111480" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111490">And shapeless love</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111500">Hath in his watch of love o'erslept himself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111510" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111520">Then sleepy wakers, let these grave let's wander</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111530">And wait th'ascension of beauty's wonder:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111540">But stay, a man striving twixt life and death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111550" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111560">Nay then 'tis so, my heavenly love's gone by,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111570">And struck him dead with her love-darting eye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111580" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111590">If speech-bereaving love will let thee speak,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111600">Then speechless man, speak with the tongue of love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111610"><pb facs="17"/> and tell me, if thou sawest not Cynthia</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111620">Seeking Endymion in these flowery dales. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111630" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111640">Dales for Endymion and fair Cynthia fit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111650">But never heavenly goddess blessed this grove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111660">These woods are consecrate to grief, not love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111670" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111680">Out atheist, thou profan'st love's deity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111690">For, false-reporter, I in them have seen</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111700">A love that makes a negro of love's Queen:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111710">One that whenas the sun keeps holiday,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111720">Her beauty clads him in his best array,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111730" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111740">Now truly shepherd none such soiourn here</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111750">Please you survey the cell, go in and see,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111760">I'm hearst, and none but sorrow lies with me. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e111770">Enter Lucida.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111780" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e111790">Call you this sorrow's cave?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111800" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111810">Rather a cell,<stage xml:id="A19975-e111820">Enter Octavio and whisper with Antonio.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111830">Where pleasure grows, and none but angels dwell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111840" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111850">To what compare shall I compare thee to? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111860">Uncomparable beauty's paragon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111870" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111880">I will compare her beauty to the sun,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111890">For her bright lustre gives the morning light. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111900" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111910">I'll say she is like Cynthia when day's done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e111920">Or lady to the mistress of the night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111930" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e111940">O speak but to me, and i shall be blessed.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111950" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e111960">One smile would lay my jarring thoughts at rest.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e111970">Enter Hermia.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e111980" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e111990">How now fair sister? you are hard beset.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112000" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112010">Nymph.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112020" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112030">Goddess.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112040" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112050">Saint, once more, you're both well met.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112060" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112070">O she is fair.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112080" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112090">She fairer.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112100" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112110">Both more fair</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112120">Than rocks of pearl, or the chaste evening air. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112130" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112140">Say sweet, intend you not to fish today?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112150" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112160">No, shepherds, now fish do not bite but play.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112170" who="A19975-francisco">
            <pb facs="18"/>
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112180">What time, sweet love, keep fishes when they bite?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112190" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112200">Early ith' morning, or else late at night.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112210" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112220">Come, will you talk with me till time of fishing?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112230" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112240">My father, sir, will chide if I be missing.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112250" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112260">The match is made, they're even upon going.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112270" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112280">What should we do?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112290" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112300">Why as poor parents and dutiful servants should do, run amongst the bushes and catch flies.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112310" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112320">Stay forward daughters whether are ye going ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112330" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112340">Father, I think these shepherds come a-wooing .</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112350" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112360">A wooing daughters? ne'er imagine so:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112370">What man's so mad to marry grief and woe? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112380" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112390">Why where lives sad grief? here's all speaking joy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112400" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112410">O I would live and die with such annoy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112420" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112430">But they are poor, and poverty is despised:</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112440" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112450">No, they are fair, beauty is highly prized.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112460" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112470">'Twill be a match, they are beating the price already.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112480" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112490">They once were fair, sorrow from that hath changed them</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112500">They once knew wealth, but chance hath much estranged them,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112510" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112520">Have they been fair? what fairer than they are? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112530">Why 'tis not possible, this heavenly fair</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112540">Hath only in itself beauties exceed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112550">Oh then rich, fair, and only selves exceed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112560" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112570">Come daughters, and come shepherds, if you please,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112580">I'll lead you to the lodge of little ease,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112590">Where I will feast you with what cheer I may,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112600">Grief shall turn mirth, and keep high holiday. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e112610">Exit cumfiliabw.</stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e112620">The brothers going out Octavio stays them.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112630" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112640">A word with you, you mean to marry these wenches,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112650" who="A19975-ambo">
            <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112660">We do.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112670" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112680">And are going to contract yourselves.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112690" who="A19975-ambo">
            <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112700">We are.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112710" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112720">And what say you to this?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112730" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112740">God speed you: I would have you marry on saint Luke's day.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112750" who="A19975-francisco">
            <pb facs="18"/>
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112760">Why?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112770" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e112780">Because i would offer at your wedding.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112790" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112800">Come, thou'rt all envy, feed upon thy hate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112810">This day our quest of love shall terminate. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e112820">Exeunt manet Octavio,</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e112830" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112840">Not if I live, this malady of love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112850">Is grown so strong, it will not be driven out. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112860">To see the folly of a doting father;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112870">What toil I had to fashion them to love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112880">And how 'tis doubled to misfashion them. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112890">They shall not wed, yet how shall i prevent it? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112900">Fearing th'event I have forethought a means,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112910">And here it lies, swaggering becomes not age,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112920">Now like the fox, I'll go a pilgrimage. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112930">Frolic my boys, I come to mar your sport,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112940">Your country music must not play at court. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112950">But first, I'll write back to Hortensio</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112960">For apprehension of young Aspero:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112970">They have not yet dined, I'll bid myself their guest</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e112980">Religion beg? A fashion in request. <stage xml:id="A19975-e112990">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e113000">Enter Aspero and his boy.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113010" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113020">Art sure she hates me boy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113030" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113040">More than her death, i have been in her bosom sir, and this day she intends your execution.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113050" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113060">My execution! the reason of her hate?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113070" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113080">Her humour, nothing but a kind of strange cross humour in that you rejected her love.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113090" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113100">That's not capital.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113110" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113120">Not to cross a great ones humour? no treason more ▪ great personages humours are puritans, they'll as live endure the devil as soon as a cross, and can away with him better.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113130" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113140">I will submit, ask pardon on my knee.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113150" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113160">Is your proud humour come down i'faith, your high humour that would not stoop an inch of the knees; I'll help't up again, an't be but to uphold the jest; I must bring her as low ere I have done; oh base, i would rather lay my neck under the axe of her hate, than my sport under the feet of<pb facs="19"/> her humour; but be counselled, I'll teach you to prevent both, and perchance make her upstart humour stoop gallant too.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113170" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113180">I'll hold thee my best jewel and thou dost.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113190" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113200">And pawn me as poor lords do their jewels too, will you not? receive me; you shall counterfeit yourself dead.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113210" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113220">The life of that jest.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113230" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113240">It may be she dissembles all this while, loves you, and puts on this show of hate of purpose to humble you: she may, and I believe —</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113250" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113260">What?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113270" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113280">That most intelligencers are knaves, and some women dissemblers; being thought dead (As let me alone to buzz that into the credulous ear of the court) if she have any sparks of love, they'll kindle and flame bright through the cinders of her heart.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113290" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113300">If not,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113310" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113320">If not, 'twill be a means for your escape: I'll say you requested at your death to be buried at your native city: and what courtier, if a christian can deny that?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113330" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113340">I am all thine, my humour's thy patient.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113350" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113360">And if I do not kill it, I am not worthy to be your physician.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e113370">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e113380">Enter Florimell and her page.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113390" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113400">I marry lady; why now you credit your sex: a woman's honour or humour should be like a ship under sail, split her keel ere she veil. <stage xml:id="A19975-e113410">Enter boy.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113420" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113430">I'll split my heart ere my humour strike sail: here comes his page, how now boy? how doth your master.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113440" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113450">Well madam he.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113460" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113470">Well?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113480" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113490">Very well.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113500" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113510">Where is he?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113520" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113530">Where none of your proud sex will ever come, I think: in heaven.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113540" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113550">Is he dead?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113560" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113570">See madam, and seeing blush, and blushing shame, that your ungentle humour should be the death of so good and generous<pb facs="19"/> a spirit.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e113580">Discover Aspero lying on a table seeming dead.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113590" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e113600">My Aspero dead! </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e113610">Boy see madam, what a mutation</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113620" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113630">I see too much, and curse my proud humour that was the cause of it: Aspero, kind soul, proud sullen Florimell, disdainful humour, that in one minute hast eternally undone me: I would not kiss the living substance, that being dead dote on thy picture: o I loved thee ever with my soul: oh let me kiss this shroud of beauty: I would not accept thee living, that being dead on my knees adore thee: could kisses recover thee, I would dwell on thy lips: kneel till my knees grew to the ground, dear gentle Aspero she that procured thy death will die with thee,</p>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113640">And crave no heaven, but still to lie with thee.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e113650">Aspero starts up.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113660" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113670">I take you at your word lady:</p>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113680">Nay never recant, I have witness on't now: is your proud humour come down? could you not have said so at first? and saved me a labour of dying?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113690" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113700">Lives Aspero? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113710" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113720">Live quotha? 'sfoot what man would be so mad to lie in his cold grave alone, and may lie in a warm bed with such a beautiful wife as this will be? have I ta'en your humour napping i'faith?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113730" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113740">Am I o'er reached?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113750" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113760">In your humour madam, nothing else, and I am as proud on't.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113770" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113780">Do not flout me; and you do, I shall grow into my humour again.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113790" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113800">In jest.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113810" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113820">In earnest I shall, and then I know what I know.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113830" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113840">You may ▪ but and you do, I shall die again.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113850" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113860">In jest.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113870" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113880">Nay in earnest madam, and then —</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113890" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113900">No more, thou hast driven me clean out of conceit with my humour, I love thee, I confess it, shalt be my husband, I'll live<pb facs="20"/> with thee, thou art my life, and I'll die with thee.</p>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e113910">What more I mean is coated in my look,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e113920">If thou accept'st it, swear,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113930" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113940">I kiss the book.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113950" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113960">Boy, run to the master of my gondola, and will him attend me after supper at the garden stairs, I mean to take the evening air, tell him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e113970" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e113980">It shall be done madam. <stage xml:id="A19975-e113990">Exit.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114000" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114010">Nay if I say the word, it shall be done Aspero ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114020" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114030">Look to yourself my lord, I lay my life, my lady means to steal you away tonight .</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114040" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114050">Away? I'll call Hortensio, I'll not be accessary to your felony madam.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e114060">Enter Hortensio and his man assistance with a letter.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114070" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114080">The fool comes without calling.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114090" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114100">You shall know him by these signs.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114110" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114120">Good figure, very good figure, for as the house is found out by the sign, so must this traitor be scented out by the token, up with the first sign good assistance. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114130" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114140">A proper man without a beard.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114150" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114160">How? A proper man without a beard? we shall scarce find that sign in all Venice: for the properness of a man lives altogether in the fashion of his beard, good assistance the next.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114170" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114180">Fair spoken and well conditioned.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114190" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114200">More strange: you shall have many proper men fairs-poken, but not one amongst twenty well conditioned, but soft, this should be the house by the sign, I must pick it out of him by wit.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114210" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114220">As good say steal my lord, what marrowbone of wit is your judgement going to pick now?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114230" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114240">I must, like a wise justice of peace, pick treason out of this fellow.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114250" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114260">Treason?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114270" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114280">Ay, treason madam; know you this hand?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114290" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114300">My royal fathers:</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114310" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114320">Then whilst you and your father's letters talk together, let<pb facs="20"/> me examine this fellow: are you a proper man without a beard?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114330" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114340">My properness sir contents me: for my beard, indeed that was bitten the last great frost, and so were a number of justices of peace besides.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114350" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114360">'Tis rumoured about the court that your name is Aspero. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114370" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114380">I am called Aspero. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114390" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114400">Son to the Duke of Mantua that was.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114410" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114420">The Duke of Mantua's son that is.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114430" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114440">Then the Duke of Mantua has a traitor to his son, lay hands of him and to close prison with him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114450" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114460">Can he be closer than in my custody?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114470" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114480">I do not think so madam, but your father has imposed the trust upon me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114490" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114500">And dare not you trust me?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114510" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114520">With my head if you were my wife, but not with my profit, if you were my mother: will you along sir?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114530" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114540">With all my heart sir, see what your humour's come to now go my lord? as willingly as a slave from the galleys: for as I shall have a stronger prison, so i shall be sure of a kinder and a wiser jailer.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114550" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114560">Do you observe how he flouts you my lord? that I had been his keeper but one night longer ▪ but keep him close, if he escape (Though against thy will) as I am a maid,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114570" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114580">A maid against your will.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114590" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114600">Shalt pay as dear for't as thou didst for thy office.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114610" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114620">If he scape, hang me. <stage xml:id="A19975-e114630">Exit and as. with Aspero.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114640" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114650">I shall wish thee hanged, if he do not: treason! I may thank my peevish humour fort.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e114660">Enter page.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114670" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114680">Madam the gondola is ready.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114690" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114700">Thou bringst physic when the patient's dead boy: our jest's turned earnest.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114710" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114720">Is a dead in earnest?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114730" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114740">As good, or rather worse, he's buried quick.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114750" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114760">O madam, many a good thing has been buried quick and survived again, I would be buried quick myself, and I might<pb facs="21"/> choose my grave.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114770" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114780">He's buried in close prison boy, he's known for the Duke of Mantua's son, and by my father's letter attached for a traitor.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114790" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114800">Good gentleman, and I be not sorry for him: who is his keeper?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114810" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114820">The testy ass Hortensio. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114830" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114840">Uds foot let's enlarge him,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114850" who="A19975-unassigned">
            <speaker>Flo ▪</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114860">Not possible boy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114870" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114880">Not possible 〈◊〉 we'll cozen his keeper.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114890" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114900">We cannot.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114910" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114920">Cannot! we can: your father made a lord of him, but be ruled by me, his daughter shall make a fool of him: you are not the first woman has made a fool of a wiser lord than he is.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114930" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114940">Shall he be cozened?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e114950" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e114960">As palpably as at the lottery, my brains are in labour of the stratagem already.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e114970">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
          <trailer xml:id="A19975-e114980">Finis actus tertiis ▪</trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A19975-e114990">
          <head>Actus quartus.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e115000">Enter Anthonio, Francisco, Hippolito, Hermia, Lucida and Octavio disguised,</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115010" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115020">Sons of Octavio if your princely thoughts</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115030">Can stoop to such mean beauty, from this hand</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115040">Receive your wives, but should the Duke your father —</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115050" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115060">Fear not old man, he was the means that breathed this spirit into us.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115070" who="A19975-unassigned">
            <speaker>Hip ▪</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115080">Wood us to this course. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115090">But should he prove apostata, deny</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115100">Love which he first enforced us to profess,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115110">So firm are our inseparate affections,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115120">To win our love's weed lose the names of sons. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115130" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115140">Your father thanks you, but hot-sprighted you that,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115150">Take counsel from experience, ere ye tie</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115160">The Gordian knot which none but heaven can lose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115170"><pb facs="21"/> crave his consent: when an imperial hand</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115180">Shakes a weak shed, the building 〈…〉</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115190" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115200">Not stand? it shall: not Jove 〈…〉 the ground ▪ work for our love ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115210" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115220">Not Jove! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115230" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115240">Not Jove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115250">Should 'a speak 〈…〉</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115260">Our love admits no 〈…〉</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115270" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115280">Then to 〈…〉 your love is 〈…〉</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115290" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115300">As 〈…〉</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115310" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115320">As 〈…〉</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115330" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115340">And yours ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115350" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Herm.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115360">And ours,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115370" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Lucid.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115380">And ours,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115390" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115400">Then lend me all your hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115410">Whilst thus a father's tongue forbids the bands,<stage xml:id="A19975-e115420">Discovers himself</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115430">Forgetful boys, but most audacious traitor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115440">That durst in thought consent to wrong thy prince,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115450">Out of my fight; no land that calls me lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115460">Shall bear a weight so hateful as they self:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115470">Live ever banished, if (Three days expire)</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115480">Thou or these lustful strumpets. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115490" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115500">Father.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115510" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115520">Boys;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115530">If you be mine show't in obedience:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115540">If (Three days passed) you live within my dukedom,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115550">Thee as a slave I'll doom unto the galleys,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115560">And these thy brats as common prostitutes ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115570">Shall dry their lustful veins in the bordello</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115580">Come boys, to court; he that first 〈◊〉 lives,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115590">Will to your births provide you equal 〈◊〉</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115600" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115610">They have our loves.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115620" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115630">Our oaths.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115640" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115650">Our hearts and hands.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115660" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115670">Tut, lovers oaths, like toys writ down in 〈◊〉</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115680"><pb facs="22"/> are soon blown o'er, contracts are common wiles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115690">Tintangle fools, Jove himself sits and smiles</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115700">At lovers perjuries, bawd, strumpets hence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115710">My bosom's charged, give way to violence:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115720">Come do not mind them. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e115730">Exeunt Anth, and his daughters.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115740" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115750">How? not mind them father? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115760">When in your court you courted us to love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115770">You red another lecture, women then ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115780">Were angels. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115790" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115800">True, but that was before angels</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115810">Had power to make them devils; they were then</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115820">Fiends to themselves, and angels unto men. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115830">When upon Po thou findest a coal-black swan,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115840">Thou'st found a woman constant to a man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115850" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115860">And not afore?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115870" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e115880">Never afore.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115890" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115900">Your tongue</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115910">Unspeaks your former speech. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e115920" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115930">It doth; new themes</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115940">Must have new change of rhetoric; all streams</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115950">Flow not alike one way; when I spoke like a lover,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115960">It was to break you from your soldier's humour;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115970">Having made you lovers, ay, like envy, speak</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115980">To make you hate love; art still strives to break</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e115990">Bad to make better:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116000" who="A19975-brothers">
            <speaker>Brothers.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116010">You have your wish.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116020" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e116030">Then onward to the court,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e116040">Make us of love, as schoolboys do of sport. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e116050">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e116060">Enter Florimell and her page.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116070" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116080">Call out the jailer boy, yet do not; haste got a beard like Hortensio? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116090" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116100">Yes, madam, i have got his hair, if I could come as easily by his wit.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116110" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116120">Wouldst rob him of his wit?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116130" who="A19975-page">
            <pb facs="22"/>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116140">If I should, he could not hang me for ▪ 'tis not worth thirteen pence half penny ▪ but what shall I do with it?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116150" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116160">Put it on boy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116170" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116180">That shall i madam, oh forward age, I am a man already: how do you like me lady?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116190" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116200">Very ill, and my plot worse.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116210" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e116220">Then leave't of, if you be grounded in the plot,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e116230">You will but mar the comedy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116240" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116250">I purposed, thou in the habit of Hortensio, shouldst under pretence of removing Aspero to a new prison, have freed him out of the old one.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116260" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116270">Tut, i can tell you a trick, worth two of that: madam, your ear, take some care in the managing, and let me alone to prepare it.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e116280">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e116290">Enter Aspero and his boy.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116300" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116310">Udsfoot break prison my lord, 'tis but swimming the river.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116320" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116330">Break prison? 'twere both dishonour to my name, and treason to my love, what benefit were't for me to free my body, and leave my heart in bondage? I'll die, ere I'll harbour a disloyal thought.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116340" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116350">It bears no relish of disloyalty: being in prison you live as far from love as liberty: being abroad, you may by letters, or a thousand means purchase her company, and compass your content.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116360" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116370">Shalt be my lawyer boy and counsel me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116380" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116390">I'll look for my fee then.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116400" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116410">If thy counsel prospers.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116420" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116430">That's an exception lawyers never respect, but come my lord, leap, as we have risen together, we'll fall together,</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e116440">Enter Hort. Florimell and page.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116450" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116460">Blame me not love,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116470" who="A19975-unassigned">
            <speaker>Boy ▪</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116480">Udsfoot your jailer my lord ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116490" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116500">Am I prevented?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116510" who="A19975-boy">
            <pb facs="23"/>
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116520">Yes faith, there had been a counselor's fee cast away now.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116530" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116540">You have heard his usage lady, seen his lodging, and if it please you, you both may and shall confer with him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116550" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116560">Prithee call him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116570" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116580">My lord, your keeper hath brought a lady or two to see you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116590" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116600">To see me? why am I turned monster? doth he take money to show me? what doth 'a take a piece trow?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116610" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116620">Why how now gallant, not gone yet?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116630" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116640">Not, I thank you lady, and yet I was near't.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116650" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116660">How do you man?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116670" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116680">Musty for want of airing.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116690" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116700">We'll have you hanged out i'the fresh air, one of these mornings.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116710" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116720">You'd be glad to take me in then.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116730" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116740">Yes, when you had hanged abroad a little: but my lord Hortensio (For I think I must be your lady when all's done) what sport? I would be merry a purpose to make him mad; the room's private and fit for any exercise.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116750" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116760">Udsfoot to her, can a woman offer fairer for't?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116770" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116780">Why shall we go to span-counter madam?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116790" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116800">To span-counter, best ask her and she'll go to coits.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116810" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116820">No, I love some stirring exercise, my body's conditioned like the sun; it would never be out of motion.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116830" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e116840">I have't i'faith, when I was student in Padua,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e116850">We used a most ingenious pastime. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116860" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116870">The name my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116880" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e116890">I cannot give it a name equal to the merit. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e116900">'Tis vulgarly called blindman's buff. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116910" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116920">Blind man's buff? ha, ha, ha,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116930" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116940">Do you laugh at it?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116950" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116960">At the happiness of your wit my lord, that you should hit upon that sport, which of all other I delight in.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116970" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e116980">Will you hear an apology I made in the commendation of it?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e116990" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117000">We'll have the thing itself first; and as we like that, we'll<pb facs="23"/> hear your apology after: who shall be hoodwinked first?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117010" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117020">Who but the author?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117030" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117040">Ay, ay, none shall be blind but I; help of with my gown boy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117050" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117060">What shall we have to blind him?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117070" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117080">My scarf, take my scarf my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117090" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117100">There's a simple favour for you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117110" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117120">And most fit, for indeed nothing blinds lovers sooner than ladies' favours, but who shall blind me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117130" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117140">Marry that will I my lord, let me alone to blind you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117150" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117160">Good again; for who should blind men, but beauteous women? come sweet madam.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117170" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117180">But how if you take me? as I know that will be your aim,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117190" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117200">If i take you prisoner madam, you must either be hoodwinked yourself, or give your conqueror a kiss for your ransom.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117210" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117220">An easy ransom: I'll not be prisoner long, if a kiss will enlarge me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117230" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117240">Lord what scambling shift has he made for a kiss and cannot get in neither; a little higher, so, so, so, are you blind my lord?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117250" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117260">As a purblind poet: have amongst you blind harpers.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117270" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117280"> methinks he looks for all the world like God Cupid. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117290" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117300">Take heed of his dart madam, he comes upon you,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117310" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117320">He cannot come to fast, oh I am taken prisoner.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117330" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117340">Your ransom's but a kiss.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117350" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117360">Is that your law of arms?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117370" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117380">Yes madam, but I'll take it on your lips.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117390" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117400">My lips like faithful treasurers shall see it discharged.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117410" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117420">And here are my honest receivers to take it.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e117430">The page puts his pantofle to his lips, he kisses it.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117440" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117450">Am I freed now?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117460" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117470">As if you had served seven year for't: sweet kiss, rare lip.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117480" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117490">Has she not a sweet breath my lord?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117500" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117510">As perfume.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117520" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117530">And a soft lip?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117540" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117550">And smooth as velvet: I could scarce discern it from<pb facs="24"/> velvet: I'd pawn my office for the fellow on't, madam.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117560" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117570">Here.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117580" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117590">Here Aspero, on with this beard and gown: I think he follows me by the sent, his hat, so: a narrow miss i'faith my lord?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117600" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117610">Gone madam?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117620" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117630">Even upon going, one of you counterfeit my voice, there I deceived you my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117640" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117650">Have you deceived me madam?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117660" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117670">Not yet, but I will, and you look not the better to't, busy him till you think we are out of the court, and then follow us: you shall find us at the South port, now or never my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117680" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117690">Why then 'twill never be lady. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117700" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117710">Here.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117720" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117730">Where?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117740" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117750">Here.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117760" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117770">Scaped again?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117780" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117790">She's scaped indeed my lord, you may cast your cap after her, for I see you can do no other good upon her.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117800" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117810">What have I catched you?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117820" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117830">Kiss her and let her go.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117840" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117850">King's truce till I breathe a little.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117860" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117870">And you had need so, for I think you are almost out of breath, if you be not, you shall be, and that's as good, but breathe and spare not.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e117880">Enter Aspero like Hortensio, Florimell, and assistance on the upper stage.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117890" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117900">Did you ever converse with a more stranger dissolute, madam?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117910" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117920">Peremptory jack, jailer, as you respect your office, lay special watch that none of what degree soever have access to him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117930" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117940">Without me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117950" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117960">Or your signet.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117970" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e117980">Signet me no signets, your goldsmith's shop is like your swans nest, has a whole brood of signets, and all of a feather, and amongst many, one may be like another, let none enter upon the<pb facs="24"/> stage where Aspero plays the madam, without Hortensio. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e117990" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118000">Is he mad my lord?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118010" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118020">As the lord that gave all to his followers, and begged more for himself.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118030" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118040">If he call for me, tell him I scorn him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118050" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118060">If he counterfeit my voice (As mad fellows will counterfeit great men's hands, and their tongues too) rate him for't, threaten him with the whip.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118070" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118080">But come not at him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118090" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118100">If he call for meat promise him fair;</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118110" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118120">But give him none.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118130" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118140">If for light.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118150" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118160">He may fire the house, let him have none.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118170" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118180">If he chafe, laugh.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118190" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118200">If he rail, sing.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118210" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118220">If he speak fair, flout him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118230" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118240">Do any thing to vex him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118250" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118260">But nothing to content him, you hear my charge, as you respect your office regard it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118270" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118280">I warn you my lord, let me alone, and we knew not how to abuse a prisoner, we were not worthy to be a jailor.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e118290">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e118300">They renew blindman's buff on the lower stage,</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118310" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118320">Are you in breath my lord?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118330" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118340">As a brewer's horse, and as long-winded; look to yourself madam, I come upon you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118350" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118360">I am ready for you sir; oh for a bulrush to run a tilt at's nose.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118370" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118380">A fair miss i'faith.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118390" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118400">I'll mend it next course you shall see.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118410" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118420">In the corner of the left hand; udsfoot beware shins my lord,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118430" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118440">Madam.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118450" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118460">Here.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118470" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118480">Where?</p>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e118490">The boy throws him down,</stage>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118500">Help me up madam,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118510" who="A19975-boy">
            <pb facs="25"/>
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118520">O strange, cannot you get up without help? there's my glove, but come no nearer, as you love me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118530" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118540">I do love you madam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118550" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118560">O blind love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118570" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118580">True madam; your beauty has made me blind. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118590" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118600">Indeed loves sons like spaniels are all born blind,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118610" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118620">But they will see. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118630" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118640">Not till they be nine days old my lord,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118650" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118660">But will you give me the fingers that hold this glove madam?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118670" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118680">And the whole body to pleasure you my lord, but let me go a little.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118690" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118700">I will not lose you yet lady. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118710" who="A19975-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118720">But you shall my lord; hist, then keep me still. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118730">He fastens the glove to a post. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118740" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118750">Faith let go my lord, for she grows sullen, and you had as good talk to a post, and as good answer 'twould make you.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e118760">Exeunt.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118770" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118780">Nay but dear madam, do but answer me, may I presume, upon my knees I beg it; but to take a favour from your sweet lips? shall I? 'las I am not the first man, that love has blinded, may I presume't I would be loath to offend your mild patience so much, as with an unreverend touch: speak; if I shall reap the harvest of my honest desires, make me blessed in proposing the time when; what? not a word? are you displeased? or shall I take your silence for a consent? shall I? speak; or if modesty lock in your syllables, seal my assurance with a kiss: not? neither? shall I have neither your word nor your bond? nay then I must make bold with modesty; by this kiss madam, oh my hard fortune? have I made suit to a post all this while? what block but I, would have been so senseless? my excuse is, 'twas but to make my lady sport: and: madam? how? Lady? madam? boy; madam, Aspero ▪ but whist, I have the conceit, 'twas excellent in my lady, and i applaud it, suppose my lady and her prisoner had an intent of private business in the next room; was it not better in her to blind me, than I should as gentlemen ushers (Cases so standing) have<pb facs="25"/> blinded myself? again, i applaud her, and adore my stars that made me rather a blind then a seeing doorkeeper: shall I interrupt them? no: madam? they have not done yet, sure they have not: what have we here? A base viol! though i cannot tickle the minikin within, I'll (Though it be some what base) give them a song without, and the name of the ditty shall be;</p>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118790">The gentleman ushers voluntary.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e118800">He sings.</stage>
          <lg xml:id="A19975-e118810">
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118820">Peace, peace, peace, make no noise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118830">Pleasure and fear lie sleeping? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118840">End, end, end your idle toys,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118850">Jealous eyes will be peeping. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118860">Kiss, kiss and part, though not for hate for pity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118870">Ha done, ha' done, ha' done, for I ha' done my ditty. </l>
          </lg>
          <p xml:id="A19975-e118880">And if you have not done now too, let me be as base as my fiddle, if I rouse you not: madam for shame, what do you mean to make of me, how? sfoot what have you made of me already? all gone? Jailor?</p>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e118890">Enter assistance above.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118900" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118910">How now? who calls? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118920" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118930">Why saucy knave 'tis J. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118940" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118950">You, what you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118960" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e118970">A single v, I came in double, but I thank them, they are gone out, and left me here a single. —</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e118980" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e118990">Fool, and so I leave you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119000" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119010">Knave, I am Hortensio, I charge thee let me out. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119020" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119030">Fool, you lie, you are Aspero, and I have charge to keep you in.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119040" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119050">From whom? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119060" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119070">From my lord Hortensio. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119080" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119090">'Sfoot knave i tell thee I am he, and thou wilt not believe me, trust thine eyes, come in and see.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119100" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119110">'Twill not serve your turn, i like a whole skin better than a pinked one: content yourself tonight , and in the morning I'll tell you more.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119120" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119130">Where's my lady, send her hither,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119140" who="A19975-assistance">
            <pb facs="26"/>
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119150">She's busy with my lord Hortensio, but if you have any use for a woman, I'll send you one of the laundresses: fare you well sir, be content, you shall want nothing of any thing you have.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119160" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119170">Hortensio gone outland my lady busy with Hortensio ▪ I am gulled, palpably gulled: whilst I like a block stood courting the post, Aspero is in my apparel escapded: villains, traitors, open the door, the duke's abused, his daughter's fled: I proclaim ye all traitors that hinder me in the pursuit.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119180" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119190">O for a reasonable audience to applaud this scene of merriment: I'll go call my lady and my lord Hortensio. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e119200">Exit</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119210" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119220">Blindman's buff? I have buffed it fairly, and mine own gullery grieves me not half so much as the Duke's displeasure, jailer, not a word? jailer, there's no way to please a knave but fair words, and gold: honest kind jailer, here's gold for thee: do but take pity upon me, a miserable coney-catched courtier: not? neither fair nor foul? thou art a degree worse than a woman; what shall I do? I can compare my fortune and my unfortunate self to nothing so fitly as my base here, we suffer every fool to play upon us for their pleasure: and indeed 'twas the intent of our creator that made fiddles and servitors to nothing but to be played upon, and played upon we shall be, till our heart strings crack, and then they either cast us aside or hang us up, as worthy no other employment; well, if I can work my means, of escape, so: if not, I must lie by it.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e119230">Exit.</stage>
          <trailer xml:id="A19975-e119240">Finis actus quarti.</trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A19975-e119250">
          <head>Actus Qvintus.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e119260">Enter Octavio, Francisco, Hippolito Flaminco ▪ etc.</stage>
          <lg xml:id="A19975-e119270">
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119280">My daughter fled? and with Hortensio,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119290">It bears no formal shape of likelihood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119300"><pb facs="26"/> her eagle spirit soared too proud a pitch,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119310">To seize so base a prey; let privy search</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119320">Look through the city's bosom till they find her:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119330">For gone she is not. </l>
          </lg>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119340" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119350">Has not Anthony's son</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119360">Sent them by some base practice to their death? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119370" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119380">His breasts too full of honour; trusty Julio? </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e119390">Enter Julio.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119400">What weighty business draws thee from thy charge? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119410" who="A19975-jul">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119420">Came not the cause afore me? the proud Mantuans</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119430">Basely revolt, deposed me from the seat</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119440">And chair of regentship, sending in quest</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119450">Of proud Anthonio their late-banished Duke,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119460">Him if they find or Aspero his son<stage xml:id="A19975-e119470">Enter assist.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119480">They'll reinstall him in the regiment ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119490" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119500">Him let them seek in the vast shades of death, as for his son.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119510" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119520">He's sure enough my lord, he was a mad knave when he came in, but i think, I have made a tame fool of him by this time: for 'a has neither had bread nor water these four and forty hours.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119530" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119540">More villain thou. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119550" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119560">My lord, Hortensio was the villain, he left such command with me, he's the wheel that turns about, and I a country Jack must strike when I am commanded.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119570" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119580">Although my foe, he's honourably tempered,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119590">Yet armed against my life go ▪ call him forth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119600">Guard in my safety with a ring of steel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119610">And mark how proudly he'll demean revenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e119620">Enter assistance and Hortensio bareheaded with his crowd,</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119630" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119640">Goblins, spirits, furies, fairies, the prison is haunted. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119650" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119660">With a knave is't not? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119670" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119680">Yes, and an old fool my lord, in the likeness of Hortensio. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119690" who="A19975-octavio">
            <pb facs="27"/>
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119700">Villain where's Aspero. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119710" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119720">I know not my lord: I let him in and my lady to laugh at him, and it seems, he consented to treason, and let him out in his apparel.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119730" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119740">They consented together to cozen me, for taking delight (As my betters may do) in a foolish pastime called blindman's buff, they stole away my gown, escaped the prison, and left me in fool's paradise, where, what song I have played, my viol can witness, they made me a little better than a bawd my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119750" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119760">In act:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119770" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119780">Not merely in act: sed cogitation, et id satis est ut inquit Suetonius.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119790" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119800">Is he escaped ▪ and Florimell with him? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119810">Hortensio thy head shall answer it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119820" who="A19975-hortensio">
            <speaker>Hort.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119830">I pray let my tongue be my heads attorney, and plead my excuse.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119840" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119850">Urge no excuse, away with him to prison. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119860" who="A19975-assistance">
            <speaker>Assistance</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119870">It shall be done my lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119880" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e119890">Nay you sir too, shall taste of the same sauce, away with both,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119900" who="A19975-flamineo">
            <speaker>Flamineo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119910">Come my sons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119920">Let's levy present arms 'gainst Mantua. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119930">Being scarce come home we must abroad again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119940">The common good's a careful prince's pain. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A19975-e119950">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e119960">Enter Anthonio, Lucida, Hermia and lords.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e119970" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119980">You that in all my banished pilgrimage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e119990">Would never alienate your natural loves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120000">But in desire to see me reinstalled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120010">Have thrust out proud Octavio's substitute,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120020">And seated me in ancient dignity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120030">I am yours, and ready at your best dispose. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120040" who="A19975-lord">
            <speaker>Lord</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120050">Your own, my liege, we like inferior lights</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120060">Take life from your reflection, for like stars</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120070">Unto the sun, are counsellors to Kings ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120080"><pb facs="27"/> he feeds their orbs with fire, and their shine</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120090">Contend to make his glory more divine. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120100">And such are we to great Anthonio. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120110" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120120">The veins and arteries of Anthonio</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120130">Through which the blood of greatness flows in us.</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120140">Our life, and cause efficient of our state,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120150">And these our pretty partners in exile. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120160" who="A19975-lord">
            <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120170">We ha' yet performed but the least part of duty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120180">Your reinstalment: it rests, that with our blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120190">We keep out innovative violence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120200" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120210">You new-create me, and breath second life</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120220">Into my dying bosom, knew my son</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120230">Of this unlooked-for fortune, but ill fate</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120240">Has played the traitor, and given up his life</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120250">To coward treason. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e120260">A shout within.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e120270">Enter Aspero and Florimell with their pages.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120280" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e120290">Udsfoot what offence have I committed against the state, that these iron-handed plebeians so applaud me for?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120300" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120310">'Tis a sign they love you ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120320" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e120330">I had rather thy should hate me, it makes me suspect my bosom, for they love none, but the masters of factions, treasons, and innovations.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120340" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120350">Then you do not love the commons. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120360" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e120370">Yes, as wise men do their flattering wives, only for show: the popular voice is like a cry of bawling hounds, and they get the foot of a fantastic and popular-affecting statesman, they never leave him, till they have chased him into disgrace, and then, like hounds, are at a loss, and with their loss, see, I have found my father, safety attend you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120380" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120390">Welcome thou hope of Mantua and of us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120400">We now are honours new beginners boy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120410">And may we better thrive then heretofore. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120420" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e120430">Never doubt it father, I have attractive stuff that will draw customers.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120440" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120450">What lady's that. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120460" who="A19975-florimell">
            <pb facs="28"/>
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e120470">One that has played the part of a constable, brought you home a runaway.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120480" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e120490">A friend of mine father, but daughter to your arch-enemy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120500" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120510">Octauio's daughter? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120520" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e120530">Yes faith, you are out with the father, and I'll see if I can fall in with the daughter.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120540" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e120550">And am I not a good child to leave my father's love at six and seven, and hazard my honour upon your son's naked promise, and your hopeful acceptance.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120560" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120570">She has followed me through much danger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120580" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120590">The better welcome, I love her for't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120600" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e120610">Like her and you please, I'd have nobody love her but myself.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120620" who="A19975-antonio">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120630">And lady, though your father be our foe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120640">The virtuous love betwixt our son and you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120650">May ne'ertheless retain his sympathy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120660" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120670">Shall ne'ertheless retain his sympathy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120680">Anthonio know I am love's resolute,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120690">Confirmed and grounded in affection:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120700">I loved your son, not for he was a prince,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120710">But one no better than his present fortunes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120720">I'll love him still, since first I loved him so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120730">Let father, friends, and all the world say no. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120740" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e120750">There's mettle father, how can we choose but get cocking children, when father and mother too are both of the game.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e120760">Enter messenger.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120770" who="A19975-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120780">To arms my lord, Octavio comes in arms</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120790">To give a proud assault unto the city. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120800" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120810">Proud his assault, as proud be our resist,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120820">Vie shot for shot, and stake down life for life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120830">Our breast's as bold as theirs, our blood as deep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120840">All that we'll lose, or this our gettings keep. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120850" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120860">Come brother, talk not of devouring war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120870">Say messenger, comes not Octauio's sons? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120880" who="A19975-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120890">They do, as proudly as the morning sun</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120900"><pb facs="28"/> beating the azured pavement of the heaven. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120910" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120920">Then fear not father, my sister and myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120930">Will be your champions and defend the city. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120940" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120950">Why ladies, have you such large interest in our brothers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e120960" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120970">Princess, we have, within there: reach our shields,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e120980">When beauty fights, the god of battle yields. <stage xml:id="A19975-e120990">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e121000">Enter Francisco, Hippolito, Flamineo, Julio.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e121010">Enter Anthonio, Aspero, Florimell, two pages lords and messenger above.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121020" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121030">They offer parley, let me answer them. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121040">Brothers, how now? who made you soldiers? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121050">Faith e'en my father as he made you lovers ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121060">What? hath he changed your shepherd's hooks to swords? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121070">Of amoradoes made you armed knights? </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121080">O seld-seen metamorphosis! I have known</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121090">Soldiers turn lovers, but for amorous lovers</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121100">To reassume their valour, 'tis a change,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121110">Like winter-thunder, and a thing as strange. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121120" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121130">Our sister prisoner? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121140" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121150">Tell me Florimell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121160">Dost thou live there enforced, or of freewill? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121170" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e121180">Free will, brothers, mine own free will, all free in Mantua, here's free will i'faith, speak am I not a freewoman?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121190" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e121200">As if you had served for't, any man may set up under her copy without a protection.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121210" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121220">I wag? are you there too? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121230" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e121240">Yes faith my lord, my lady has had my attendance to a hair.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121250" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121260">You lie boy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121270" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121280">If not mine, somebody's else: there's one has done —</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121290" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121300">What have I done sirrah? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121310" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e121320">Nay nothing, but what my lady was very well content with.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121330" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121340">Why sister, shame you not to set your love</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121350">On one, that is our father's enemy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121360" who="A19975-florimell">
            <pb facs="29"/>
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121370">Shame? not a whit: but come, your wench's brothers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121380">I make no question, I have won my wager:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121390">Are they as fair as I? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121400" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121410">Leave that to trial. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121420">Aspero make surrender of our sister. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121430" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121440">And have her in quiet possession? what do you think me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121450" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121460">We think thee a proud villain and our foe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121470" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121480">By heaven, they're villains all that think him so,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121490" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121500">Why do you love him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121510" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121520">I should curse myself</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121530">If I should hate him:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121540" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121550">Bring the ladders forth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121560">Bravely assault to separate their lives,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121570">As they are sealing the walls, the ladies come forth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121580" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121590">Stand proud Francisco. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121600" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121610">Sand! O excellent word in a woman! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121620" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121630">Hold Hippolito. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121640" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121650">Hold! up with that word, and 'tis as good as the other. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121660" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121670">What nymph or goddess in my Hermia's shape,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121680">Stands to debar my entrance to the town:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121690" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121700">Madam, I wonder they enter not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121710" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121720">Why boy it seems they dare not,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121730" who="A19975-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121740">O cowards and have two such fair breaches already,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121750" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121760">Immortal Pallas that art more divine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121770">In my love's beauty that thou clothest thee in,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121780">With draw thyself, and give our fury limits. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121790" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121800">I will, but first Francisco take my shield. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121810" who="A19975-lucida">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121820">And mine as challenge to a single combat,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121830" who="A19975-hermia">
            <speaker>Her.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121840">Read the conditions and return your answers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121850" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e121860">Well done i'faith wenches, oh that the old graybeard my father were here, I'd have about with him as I am honourable.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121870" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121880">What's here! </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121890">A shepherd wooing of a country maid,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121900">As she sits angling by a river's side,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121910">By them an aged man making a net! </l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121920"><pb facs="29"/>The motto ▪ sic! this emblems moral is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121930">The former love I had with Lucida,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121940">And this hope tells me that's fair ▪ Lucida. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e121950" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121960">Brother, my shield the like presents to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121970">But holds far more familiar reference,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121980">Here doth the amorous shepherd kiss the nymph;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e121990">Which she with a chaste blush consents unto:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122000">And see, a gloomy man, clad like a pilgrim</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122010">Comes in, and separates their sweet delights:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122020">The motto, sic! I so my father came,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122030">And banished me from beauteous Hermia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122040">And this hope tells me is fair Hermia. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122050" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122060">The more I look, the more methinks 'tis she. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122070" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122080">The more I think the more I find 'tis she. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122090" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122100">What should I think to prove it is not she? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122110" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122120">Look, think, find, prove, do what you can,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122130">These are the wenches that you courted then:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122140">Then honey bees lay by your smarting stings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122150">And buzz sweet love into your lady's ears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122160">Tell them of kisses, and such pretty things,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122170">These drumming dubadubs love's pleasure fears. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122180" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122190">O heaven, o fortune, and most happy stars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122200">Do I find love, where I expected wars? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122210" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122220">I that but now was all for war and death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122230">Am made all love, war's humour's out of breath. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e122240">Enter Octavio, Julio, and others.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122250" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e122260">How, my son's love the daughters of my foe! it cannot be,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122270" who="A19975-jul">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122280">Then question them yourself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122290" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122300">Why how now sons, is this your worth in arms. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122310" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122320">Why are we not in arms father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122330" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122340">Yes, and in such arms as no coward, but would venture life to march in. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122350" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122360">Then boys, you love the daughters of Anthonio. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122370" who="A19975-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122380">We liked them first. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122390" who="A19975-hippolito">
            <pb facs="30"/>
            <speaker>Hip.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122400">Wel●ep● the liking still. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122410" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122420">And you will love them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122430" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122440">Father in faith they will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122450" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e122460">Ay, run away are you there? whom has your ladyship got to your husband?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122470" who="A19975-florimell">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A19975-e122480">One that I stumbled on at blindman buff, a proper man, a man every inch of him: and you would say so, and you knew but as much as I — mean to know ere I have done with him ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122490" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122500">Is he not son unto Anthonio? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122510" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122520">Great Duke I am, and prostrate on my knee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122530">I beg a peace, which if your spleen deny,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122540">I proudly stand where erst I mildly kneeled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122550">And East down bold defiance from these walls. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122560" who="A19975-octavio">
            <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122570">No more your loves make my proud heart ashamed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122580">Your consort's sweet, and I'll not be a mean</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122590">To make it jar: what my sons like shall stand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122600">By my consent, allowed and perfected;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122610">All hate is banished, and revenge lies dead. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19975-e122620" who="A19975-aspero">
            <speaker>Asp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122630">Then stead of spears, let Hymen's torches flame</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122640">With hallowed incense, and the god of spright,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122650">Swell up your veins with amorous delight:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122660">And so that up our single comedy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19975-e122670">〈◊〉 Plautus phrase: si places, plaudite. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19975-e122680">Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
          <trailer xml:id="A19975-e122690">Finis.</trailer>
          <pb facs="30"/>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A19975"><item xml:id="A19975-florimell" n="154">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-florimell</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">154</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A19975-aspero" n="131">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-aspero</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">131</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-octavio" n="102">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-octavio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">102</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-page" n="85">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-page</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">85</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-francisco" n="80">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-francisco</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">80</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-hortensio" n="67">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-hortensio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">67</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-hippolito" n="55">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-hippolito</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">55</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-boy" n="46">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-boy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">46</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-antonio" n="35">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-antonio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">35</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-hermia" n="28">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-hermia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">28</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-assistance" n="21">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-assistance</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">21</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-lucida" n="18">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-lucida</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">18</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-unassigned" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-lord" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-lord</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-flamineo" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-flamineo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-messenger" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-jul" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-jul</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-ambo" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-ambo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-florimel" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-florimel</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19975-brothers" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19975-brothers</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

