<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>2 Youth's Glory and Death's Banquet<date type="creation_date">1662</date></title>
        <author>Cavendish, Margaret</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nayoon Ahn</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A53060_05.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>356 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">11861873</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing N868.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">50022</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53060</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
            <author>Newcastle, William Cavendish, 1592-1676.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[24], 679 [i.e. 675], [4] p. : ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by A. Warren, for John Martyn, James Allestry, and Tho. Dicas ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1662.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>First edition.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Errata: p. [4] at end.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A53060_05-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A53060_05-e100020">
      <div n="2" type="play" xml:id="A53060_05-e100030">
        <pb facs="88" n="153"/>
        <head>The second part of youth's glory, and death's banquet.</head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A53060_05-e100040">
          <head>Act i.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e100050">
            <head>Scene 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100060">Enter the lord de l'amour, and the lady innocence; the lord de l'amour seems to appear angry. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100070" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100080">My lord, what makes you frown on me, surely I never willingly offended you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100090" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100100">But the report I hear of you offends me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100110" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100120">I hope my behaviour is not liable to any aspersion or evil censure; for, as you have used me civilly, so I have behaved myself modestly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100130" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100140">I perceive you are a subtle insinuating young lady.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100150" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100160">Think me not subtle, for being so broad as not to slight your love; not so uncivil, as to scorn your noble favours; but strive to merit your worthy affections; but if I have erred in my endeavours, pray pardon me, and if you please to tell me my error, I shall rectify it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100170" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100180">I hear you will speak more lies, than tell truths.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100190" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100200">Truly I am too strict a votary to truth to tell a lie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100210" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100220">I should be glad you were vowed one of her order.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100230" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100240">I am so, and have taken the habit of sincerity upon me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100250" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100260">Tell me truly, do you never use to lie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100270" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100280">If you have opinion that I never, or seldom, speak truth, let me say what I will, you will still believe it is a lie; but truly, I did never tell a lie as I do know of, but did always speak truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100290" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100300">I hear to my great grief you have many faults, pray mend them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100310" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100320">I am sorry there are so many ill reports, or rather aspersions laid on me as to grieve you; but surely, youth cannot commit many faults; but age, that hath had time to commit faults in; but if you can believe my faults surmounts not all accounts: I shall desire to know them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100330" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100340">Examine yourself, and you will find them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100350" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100360">I shall call a particular council, and make a general search, and what thoughts, words, or actions, I can find guilty, or prove criminal, I shall condemn, and sacrifice them on the altar of repentance, and crave mercy and forgiveness.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100370" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100380">Pray do so.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100390">Ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100400"><pb facs="89" n="154"/>Lady innocence alone. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100410">'Tis strange his humour should be so suddenly changed, from loving professions, kind expressions, and pleasing smiles, to sharp words, and angry frowns; and that he should seem to love me as much as he did, and now, to believe me so little, as it seems he doth, I hope it is only the superfluities of his affections, that runs into the indiscretion of jealousy.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100420">Ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100430">Enter Sanspareile and her audience. As soon as she hath taken her standing place,</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100440">A messenger enters.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100450" who="A53060_05-messenger">
              <speaker>Messenger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100460">The Queen of attention is come to be one of your audience.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100470">The company makes a bustle.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100480">Enter the Queen of attention, and her train. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100490">Sir Thomas father love kneels down, and kisses her hand.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100500" who="A53060_05-queen">
              <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100510">I am come to hear, and see your daughter, whom fame reports to be the wonder of this age.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100520" who="A53060_05-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100530">It had been more proper, and fit, for my daughter to have waited at your court-gates, until your majesty had commanded her into your presence, than for your majesty to come hither, to hear, and see her; but she being a plain bred girl, durst not be so bold.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100540" who="A53060_05-queen">
              <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100550">If your daughter's wit be answerable to her beauty, she is a wonder indeed.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100560">Sanspareile comes off from the place where she stands, and makes 3. Obeisances, and coming near kneels down, and kisses the Queen's hand. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100570" who="A53060_05-sanspareile">
              <speaker>Lady Sanspareile.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100580">Madam, this gracious honour, and honourable grace, is beyond the management of my young years; the evil of my weak confidence, and the compass of my little wit, and my obscure breeding, hath made me so ignorant, that I know not in what manner I should behave, or address myself towards your majesty; but if I commit faults in misbehaviour, pray impute it to my ignorant youth, and not to disobedience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100590" who="A53060_05-queen">
              <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100600">I see nothing yet in your behaviour, but that you may be not only a pattern for young, but also for grave age, to take example from.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100610" who="A53060_05-sanspareile">
              <speaker>Sanspareile.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100620">Madam, the generosity of your majesty's nature, the magnificence of your majesty's mind, and the charity of your majesty's disposition, gives an overflowing commendation, like to the goodness of the gods, that gives more to the creature, than the creature can deserve.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100630" who="A53060_05-queen">
              <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100640">Let me tell you young lady, your speeches are as pleasing to the ear, as your beauty is delightful to the eye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100650" who="A53060_05-sanspareile">
              <speaker>Sanspareile.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100660">Your majesty is like a deity, can turn or translate words, like poor mortals, into a glorified sense, like as into a glorified body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100670" who="A53060_05-queen">
              <pb facs="89" n="155"/>
              <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100680">Sir Thomas father love, if your daughter speak at all times, and always so eloquently, I should not wonder you let her speak in public.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100690" who="A53060_05-father">
              <speaker>Father,</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100700">I beseech your majesty, that you will rather judge me an over fond father, which is natural, than a vain opinionator, in that I give her liberty to speak in public.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100710" who="A53060_05-queen">
              <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100720">If it were a vanity, it might be well forgiven; but pray let me hear her speak.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100730">Sanspareile makes three obeisances as she steps back from the Queen to her standing-place, and then ascends. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100740" who="A53060_05-sanspareile">
              <speaker>Sanspareile.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100750">Great Queen! Ay, nor no other, should offer, or dare to speak before, or to such supreme persons as your majesty, without a sore premeditation; for the words and behaviours of speakers should be fitted to the degrees and qualities, powers, offices, and authorities of the auditory; but your majesty's commands makes that an obedient duty, that would otherways be a presumption; wherefore, on the ground of duty I speak at this time before your majesty; but the royalty of your person, the brightness of your beauty, the fame of your virtues, and the glorious splendour of your majestical grandeur hath so amazed me, that my understanding is as it were blind, which will cause my tongue to stagger, and my words to run stumbling out of my mouth; but I hope your justice will pardon them; for, as divine justice belongs to the gods, moral justice to nature; so humane justice to monarchial princes, which justice is weighed and measured out according to merit, or desert, be they good or bad: for which justice gods and princes are both feared and loved; and justice is the chief pillar or upholder of monarchical states and commonwealths; for without justice there can be no government, and without government there can be no rule, and without rule there can be no peace, and where peace is not, there will be wars and, wars causeth ruin and destruction; but for the most part, those kingdoms that have arrived to the height of glory, declines or falls to ruin: the reason is, that a low condition is necessitated, and weak; wherefore they seek for help to strengthen themselves, which makes or rather forces every particular person to associate, and unite either by laws of covenants, to which they submit and obey: but when a kingdom is in a glorious condition, and is full of prosperity, every particular citizen or man thinks he can stand upon his own foundation, flinging off their supporters, which is duty, and obedience, which makes them fall to ruin; for when men comes to that height of pride, caused by prosperity, that they all strive to be superiors, and commanders; they become factious and mutinous against the magistrates, rulers, or governors; which factions begets wars, either by calling in foreigners, or by making, or siding into parties amongst themselves; for it is to be observed, that states, or monarchies do oftener fall by the pride and factions of the commons, or subjects, than by the tyranny of the rulers or governors; but it is the nature of the vulgar sort of mankind, to be the most basest, fearfullest and dejected creatures in adversity, that nature hath made, and in prosperity to be the proudest, insultingest and imperious and cruelest of all creatures. But Kings and royal princes should do as gods, which is to keep their subjects in awe, with the superstitious fear of ceremonies; wherefore princes should do no actions, no, not the meanest, without ceremony to astonish the vulgar; for ceremonies begets<pb facs="90" n="156"/> fear, fear begets superstition, superstition reverence, reverence Obedience, Obedience brings peace, peace brings tranquillity; but where ceremony is not used, the gods are neglected, and princes despised; for ceremony is the throne which gods and princes sits on, which being pulled away, they fall from their glory; for ceremony is the royal crown which makes them majestical, it is the sceptre by which they rule, it is the altar at which all the subjects kneel, do bow, and they offer up there their natural free liberty.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100760">But most glorious Princess, you and your subjects are like the sun, and the rest of the planets, moving perpetually, keeping their proper sphere, they moving in civiler loyalty about you, to receive the light of your authority, and you move in them as the just centre, spreading your glorious beams round about the circumference of your dominions, and in the light of your commands they see their duty: and your laws are like the fixed stars, which twinkling move in the night of great offences, and doth assist the innocent with sparkling light. And your majesty governs like the gods, your wisdom by your works is known, and by your wisdom is your power immense.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100770">So doing her respects, comes off from her standing, and with three reverences comes to the Queen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100780" who="A53060_05-queen">
              <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100790">Young lady let me tell you, that you are fit to be a governess, (Although you be very young) that can speak so well of government.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100800" who="A53060_05-sanspareile">
              <speaker>Sanspareile.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100810">'Tis happier for me to be a subject to so gracious a sovereign, than if I were govern a people myself.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100820">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e100830">
            <head>Scene 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e100840">Enter the lady innocence, and her maid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100850" who="A53060_05-passive">
              <speaker>Passive.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100860">Madam, you retire yourself more to solitary than you were used to do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100870" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100880">Because I find the world not only more foolish, but more wicked than I thought it was, but who would endure the world, or the world's folly, since solitariness is sweet and melancholy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100890" who="A53060_05-passive">
              <speaker>Passive.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100900">The truth is, that words pleaseth the world more than reason; and vice is exercised more than virtue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100910" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100920">You say right, for words takes the world of mankind by the ears, drawing them about even where they please; when reason is not heard, also vice will be embraced, and virtue kicked away; thus words and vice will get a room, both in the head and heart, when reason and virtue are barred out, but if perchance they are crowded in, they are straight thrown out as unfit guests, or troublesome intruders.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100930" who="A53060_05-passive">
              <speaker>Passive.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100940">But madam, let me advise you from so much solitude, for obscurity shadows virtue, and buries beauty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100950" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100960">And solitude doth hide defects, as well as excellencies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100970" who="A53060_05-passive">
              <pb facs="90" n="157"/>
              <speaker>Passive.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e100980">But you have no defects to hide.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e100990" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101000">Nor excellencies to divulge.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101010">Enter the lady innocence, the lord de l'amour</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101020">Ex. passive.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101030" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101040">'Tis strange you can be so crafty in dissembling, and yet so young; for you appear to me to be innocently modest, and of a bashful nature, and yet it is told me you are so impudently bold, speaking so wantonly, as it is a shame to nature, which makes me fear you will prove dishonest.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101050" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101060">Perchance I might learn modest words, but not the signification; yet surely I never spoke such words I understood not, nor have I many speaking faults to accuse me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101070" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101080">I am told you speak so knowingly of marriage, as if you were a mother of many children.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101090" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101100">The mystery of marriage I neither know, nor guess at, neither do I know how children are bred or born.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101110" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour,</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101120">If you be so ignorant, you may lose your virginity for want of knowledge and wit to keep it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101130" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101140">I have been taught, none can be devirginated that suffers not immodest action, if so, I am a pure virgin, and my thoughts are so innocent, and my life so honest, as I wish the chambers of my mind or soul, (Which is the brain and the heart) were set open to your view; there should you see the pictures in the one, and read the letters in the other, for truth records all in the heart, and memory pencils all that the imaginations or senses brings into the brain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101150" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101160">I cannot but believe what is so confidently reported; but your words are such charms, as they inchant my angry passions, and makes my will a prisoner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101170" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101180">Let reason, as a knight of chivalry, and truth as his esquire, set him free, and open the gates of understanding, than you might see virtue clothed with white innocency, and truth free from the bonds of falsehood.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101190" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101200">So you were as wife as witty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101210" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101220">Wisdom is built upon the foundation of experience; wherefore none can be wise but those that are old; but though I am too young to be wise, yet not to be virtuously honest.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101230" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101240">Pray heaven you prove so.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101250">Ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101260">Lady innocency alone. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101270">Heaven bless my innocency from thieves of slander, that strives to steal away my honest fame.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101280">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e101290">
            <pb facs="91" n="158"/>
            <head>Scene 3.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101300">Enter two men, or scholars.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101310" who="A53060_05-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101320">This lady Sanspareile hath a strange spreading wit, for she can plead causes at the bar, decide causes in the court of judicature, make orations on public theatres; act parts, and speak speeches on the stage, argue in the schools, preach in the pulpits, either in theology, philosophy, moral and natural, and also physic and metaphysic.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101330" who="A53060_05-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2. Gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101340">The truth is, she is ushered by the Muses, led by the sciences, and attended by the arts.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101350">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e101360">
            <head>Scene 4.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101370">Enter the lady innocence, alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101380" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101390">I do perceive my shiftless youth is round beset with enemies.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e101400">Suspicions round about me placed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e101410">With slandering words my same disgraced:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e101420">My innocency, as craft is thought,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e101430">My harmless life to ruin brought;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e101440">Who will adore the gods, if they</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e101450">Vice, virtue, in one balance lay? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101460">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A53060_05-e101470">
          <head>Act ii.</head>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e101480">
            <head>Scene 5.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101490">Enter the lady Sanspareile, all in white satin, like as a bride, and her father and her audience, which are all lovers; these stand gazing upon her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101500" who="A53060_05-sanspareile">
              <speaker>Sanspareile.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101510">This noble assembly may chance to think it a vanity in me, never to receive any particular visit or address from any particular or single person, but I do so, by reason life is lost in particular acquaintance, as small rivers are in running through the earth. But in the public, life swims as in a full sea, having a fair gale of observation, and sails of opportune time to swim withal, marking the card of actions, and the needle of dispositions<pb facs="91" n="159"/> drawn or turned by the loadstone of affection, to the north-pole of experience, to guide me safe from the rocks of slander, and quicksands of scandal, till I come to the port of death, there to unload my life's merchandise; and I hope my voyage may be so prosperous, as I may be enriched with the praises of after-ages.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101520">Likewise, the reason why I choose to speak in public, is, that I would not speak idly, for in public I shall take care of what I speak, and to whom I speak, when in private visitations to single persons, my speech may be careless with negligence, in which I may throw away my time with my words; for, to speak to no purpose, is to make words useless, and words is the marks to distinguish things, and figures to number merits with, and notes to record the noble acts of men.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101530">But at this time I am to speak by my father's command, upon a subject which my contemplation hath no acquaintance with, which is marriage, and I hear by my father, that you have all treated with him, or rather entreated him to bestow me in marriage, which is to make me unhappy, not but that I believe what I hear, which is, that you are all persons of quality, birth, breeding, and merit, far beyond my desert, yet with the best, if any best there be, being all worthy; yet were I a wife to any one, I might be unhappy, by reason marriage is an encumbered life, although the husband and the wife were fitly matched for years, births, fortunes, dispositions, humours, capacities, wits, conversations, constancies, virtues, and affections; and first, by your leave, I will discourse of men's marriage, by reason man being accounted the supremer creature, and always bearing rule, he shall be first placed. As for marriage, to men it is a great hindrance to a speculative life, it cuts off fancies wings, and quenches out the poetical fire, it breaks the engine of invention, disturbs sweet contemplation, corrupts honest counsels, obstructs all heroic actions, obscures fame, and often times causes infamy by the wife's inconstancies, and many times by her indiscretion; for a man is dishonoured if his wife is but thought wanton, or but inclining to be amorous, and though she be as sober in her nature, and as constant as any woman can be, yet the very suspicion is a disgrace, and if the suspicion is a disgrace, what is a visible truth? His very neighbours makes horns as he passeth by their doors, whilst he sadly and shamefully hangs down his head with a dejected countenance, which makes him seem a coward and a fool, although it be unjust that the faults of the wife should be a blemish to the husband's honour; yet so it is, this being the greatest cause why husbands are jealous, which jealousy is more for their honour's sake, than for their wives affections; thus you see how dangerous a thing it is for man to marry, who must trust his honour to the management of a foolish woman, and women naturally like children, inconstant, unless education doth rectify their frail natures, peevish humours, various appetites, and inconstant affection: likewise marriage is not only apt to corrupt the mind with jealousy, but with covetousness; for the extreme fondness and natural love of parents to their children, makes them strive by all their endeavours to enrich them; this makes them gripe their tenants, pinch and half starve their servants, quarrel and dispute with their neighbours, corrupt judges take bribes, besides it makes men apt to rebel, and turn traitorous, murmuring at their taxes and impositions, it also makes them timorous and fearful in wars, by reason their wife and children may be ruined by their death. Also it makes them dull in their conversations,<pb facs="92" n="160"/> by reason they are always plodding for their worldly affairs; and for the Muses, had a husband time to entertain them, yet the wife would right them, or drive them from him, with their quarrelling disputes, or senseless prizes; besides most women are as jealous of the Muses, as of their maids; but to treat or discourse of married women, is to discourse of a most unhappy life, for all the time of their lives is ensnared with troubles, what in breeding and bearing children, what in taking and turning away servants, directing and ordering their family, counting their expenses, and disbursing their revenues, besides the vexations with their servants, for their quarrelling and combining, for their sloth and sluttery, for their spoils and carelessness, for their treachery and cozenage, and if they have children, what troubles and griefs do ensue? Troubled with their frowardness and untowardness, the care for their well being, the fear for their ill doing, their grief for their sickness, and their unsufferable sorrow for their death; yet this is the best part, and not to be avoided: but if these troubles be joined with an ill husband, it heightens their torments; for if he be a drunkard, she had better be married to a beast, her nostrils is staunched with the lees of wine, her eyes are offended with his rude behaviour, and her ears are struck with a cursed noise of cursing and oaths; and if he be a gamester, she lives in an unsettled condition, she knows not how soon she may want; for if she have plenty one day, she may be in a condition to beg the next. And if her husband be inconstant, and loves variety of women: oh how jealousy torments her, besides the wrongs she suffers from him! what affronts she receives from his mistress! How is she despised amongst her neighbours? slighted by her servant, suspected by the world for having some defect? as either to be incontinent, sluttish, foolish, froward, cross, unkind, ill natured, sickly, or diseased, when perchance the woman may be worthy to be marched with a temperate, wise, valiant, honest, rich and honourable man; and if women go fine, and take pleasure in themselves, and garments, their husbands are jealous; and if they regard not themselves or garments, their husbands dislikes them; for though men will swear to their wives they like them better in their old clothes, than other women in their glorious apparel; because they would not have them expensive, yet if their wives neglect themselves, regarding not their dressing, but sleights all outward adornments, and change of garments as prodigal spendthrifts, they starve their husbands esteem in their thrifty plainness, consumes their affections in their peiced petticoats, and buries their husbands love in their dirty rags; and from the dunghill of dirty rags, and grave of soul linen, is their husbands transformed to beastly adulteries, stealing by degrees out of one form into another, as from a doting husband, to a fond husband, form a fond to a discreet husband, from a discreet, to a careful husband, from a careful, to a careless, from a careless, to a disliking, from a disliking, to a hating, and then they begin to wander; as first, an eye glances, from an eye glance, to an admirer; from an admirer, to a professor, from a professor, to a dissembler; from a dissembler, to an adulterer; then for the dresses and garments of his mistress, first, from clean, to new; from new, to fine; from fine, to brave; from brave, to glorious; from glorious to fantastical; from fantastical to profusely various from profusely, various to any dirty slut. But his wife (On the other side, if his wife desires) appears handsome, and practises civil behaviour, and endeavours to be fine, takes care to be cleanly, observes to be fashionable, her<pb facs="92" n="161"/> husband straight becomes jealous, although she doth this for his sake, and to keep his affection, yet he thinks it is for the affection and sake of some other man, which causeth private discontents, from private discontents to quarrelling disputes; from quarrelling disputes, to public exclamations, from public exclamations, to open defiance; from open defiance, to divorcement; and though I cannot say this by, or from experience, having it only from relation, yet I do as faithfully believe it, as if I were experienced therein: on which faith, I made a vow never to marry, since I hear men are so hard to please, and apt to change; wherefore if I were married, instead of discoursing of several arguments, I should be groaning and sighing, and weeping, with several pains and vexations; and instead of a silent solitary contemplation, a clamorous quarrelsome conversation; instead of a peaceable life, I should be always in civil wars; and instead of being happy, I should be miserable; for marriage is like a ship, which always lies on the roughest billows of the sea, rolling from side to side with discontents, sailing uncertainly, with inconstancy, and various winds, but noble, civil, kind and affectionate gentlemen, as I have told you, I have made a vow never to marry, and surely marriage is not so happy an estate, or so pleasing a condition of life, as to persuade me to break my vow, neither can flattering rhetoric, nor enticing beauty, nor adoring, admiring, deploring, praying, weeping suitors persuade me, no, not a bleeding suitor, were I sure he would die, did he not enjoy me; for I will never be so dishonourable, perjurious, and impious, to break the holy laws, and pull the virgin altars down, built in the conscience, on which are vows offered to gods on high: should I blow out that with faint inconstancy, that pure bright vestal fire of innocency, from whence the essence of chaste thoughts ascends to heaven high; but rather than I would break my vow, I wish my ears as deaf as death, that hears no flattering sounds, nor sad complaints, nor terrifying threats, my eyes as dark as night, lest light should bring some false deluding object in, for to deceive me; my heart like adamant, so hard love cannot enter, nor pity nor compassion wound; but howsoever, I cannot be wife to you all; wherefore since I cannot be every man's wife, I will die every man's maid. But I must tell this noble assembly, their meeting hath occasioned a quarrel here; for bashfulness, and confidence hath fought a duel in my cheeks, and left the stains of blood there.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101540">After her respects.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101550">Ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101560">All her audience, her lovers goeth out silently, some lifting up their eyes, others their hands, some striking their hands on their breast, and the like.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101570">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e101580">
            <pb facs="93" n="162"/>
            <head>Scene. 6.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101590">Enter the lady innocence alone. </stage>
            <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101600">While I was in his favour, my mind was like a pleasant garden, where several fancies like several birds, did make sweet melody; and in this garden a large, high tree of noble ambition grew; whereon hung fruits of hopes, but low misfortunes now hath cut it down, and therewithal have built a house, where melancholy dwells, darkened with clouds of discontents, and winds of sighs, and showers of tears, doth blow and pour thereon. </p>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101610">She weeping and sighing.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101620">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e101630">
            <head>Scene. 7.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101640">Enter the lady incontinent, and the lord de l'amour.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101650" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101660">Faith you will be well wived, for your affianced is known to be a liar, and feared she will be a whore, and proved a thief.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101670" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101680">How, a thief?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101690" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101700">Why, she hath stolen my pearl chain worth a thousand pounds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101710" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101720">'Tis impossible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101730" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101740">It is not impossible to prove a thief.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101750" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101760">No, for there is too many to miss; but sure it is impossible she should prove one, she is so honourably born, and I never heard but she was virtuously bred.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101770" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101780">By your favour, covetousness or necessity, may tempt honourable births, and corrupt minds, that with plenty would be honest enough.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101790" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101800">I grant, misery may prove some noble souls sprung from honourable stocks, yet not to be so wickedly base as to steal, although so unworthy as to shark.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101810" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101820">Why, sharking is next neighbour to stealing, or as near kindred as an equivocation is to a lie. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101830" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101840">But she was never so necessitated, as to make her either a shark, or a thief, having always plenty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101850" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101860">But she is covetous, and youth that is fond of all things they see, desires to enjoy all things they have not, and will endeavour by any means or ways to compass their desires.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101870" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101880">I never found my youth prompt to any such acts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101890" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101900">Without more discourse, she hath stole my chain, and I can prove it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101910">She goeth out alone.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101920"><pb facs="93" n="163"/>Lord de l'amour alone</stage>
            <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101930">'Tis strange, I know not what to think, or how to judge, which of the two ladies is a devil; for surely one of them is. </p>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101940">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A53060_05-e101950">
          <head>Act iii.</head>
          <div n="8" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e101960">
            <head>Scene 8.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e101970">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e101980" who="A53060_05-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e101990">The lady Sanspareile is the miracle of this age, the world doth not parallel her with the like; for her behaviour is graceful and becoming, her countenance modest and wife, her speech majestical and witty, yet grave and learned, and her oratory is after a new way.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102000" who="A53060_05-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102010">It is reported, that there are many men come from all parts of the world to hear her, and those that cannot understand this language, comes only to see her, so famous is she to all the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102020" who="A53060_05-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102030">She is a great honour to our nation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102040" who="A53060_05-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102050">I hear she doth intend to plead in the behalf of poor suitors, and hath asked leave of the Queen to be a pleader at the bar, for all such as suffered wrong as injustices, and for such clients as hath just causes, but hath not means to follow the law, as to see the lawyers, and she will plead for them gratis. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102060" who="A53060_05-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102070">It is a pious and noble act.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102080" who="A53060_05-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102090">Also her father hath challenged all the eloquent orators of our nation, to make orations extemporately; likewise he hath challenged the most famous scholars and learned men to dispute with her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102100" who="A53060_05-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102110">Her father is most dotingly fond of her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102120" who="A53060_05-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102130">He hath reason, and out of love to her he is building a very fine library, to lay in all her works; for they say she writes much, and hath writ many excellent works.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102140" who="A53060_05-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102150">She deserves a statue for herself, as well as a library for her works.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e102160">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="9" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e102170">
            <pb facs="94" n="164"/>
            <head>Scene 9.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e102180">Enter the lady innocence, and adviser. the lord de l'amours man.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102190" who="A53060_05-adviser">
              <speaker>Adviser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102200">Madam, my lord and the lady incontinent hath sent me to tell you, you must come to be examined about the chain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102210" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102220">I am so shrunk up with fear, that methinks I could thrust myself into a nutshell to hide myself.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102230" who="A53060_05-adviser">
              <speaker>Adviser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102240">Faith if you could, it would not conceal you; for they would crack the nutshell and find you out.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e102250">Adviser goes out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e102260">Lady innocence alone. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e102270">O that innocency should tremble as much as guilt, with fear; but if they did b know how little I value the riches of the world, they would not believe I should se so frivolous a thing. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e102280">Enter as to the lady innocence, the lord de l'amour, the lady incontinent, and a justice; and the lady's two maids, informer and falsehood.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102290" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102300">The lady incontinent hath brought a justice, who hath power to make you confess.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e102310">She falls a shaking.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102320" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102330">You may perceive her guilty, she trembles and shakes and looks so pale.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102340" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102350">Pray judge me not guilty by my countenance, bring it not as a witness against me, for the childish fears in my heart, causeth a trembling, which like an earthquake, shakes my body, and makes my breath as pent up air, that pants for passage, striving to get forth, and my innocent bashfulness, or my bashful innocency, makes my eyes like perturbed lights, that see nothing clearly; my words to flow like rough and broken streams; for my mind is so troubled, and my passions in such a storm, as my words can neither flow easy, nor free.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102360" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102370">Here be two that will witness that she stole the chain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102380" who="A53060_05-falshood">
              <speaker>Falshood.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102390">I will swear she took the chain of pearl, and put it in her pocket, and so went out of the room with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102400" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102410">Why did not you follow her, and take it from her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102420" who="A53060_05-falshood">
              <speaker>Falshood</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102430">I thought she would bring it again, for I never suspected she would deny it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102440" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102450">And will you witness the same informer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102460" who="A53060_05-informer">
              <speaker>Informer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102470">I will witness I saw it in her hand, looking on it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102480" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102490">What say you for yourself lady innocence? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102500" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <pb facs="94" n="165"/>
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102510">I say my accusements doth not make me guilty of a crime; but I confess I took the chain in my hand, out of a curiosity, and trial of my judgement or skill, to see whether I could find any defect, in somuch valued, esteemed, and high-prized a thing as pearl; but not any ways out of a covetous appetite, as to steal it, nor had I any tempting thoughts thereto, nor wished I that or the like should be lawfully given me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102520" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102530">What did you with it, when you had done viewing it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102540" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102550">I laid it on the table from whence I took it off.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102560" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102570">But here are those that will swear you carried it away with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102580" who="A53060_05-maids">
              <speaker>Maids.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102590">Yes that we will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102600" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102610">I cannot always avoid a false accusation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102620" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102630">Will you swear you did not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102640" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102650">Yes, if my oath will be taken.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102660" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102670">Well, you did take it that is certain, wherefore you were best confess it, or you shall be wracked to make you confess it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102680" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102690">I will never bear false-witness against myself; I will die first.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102700" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102710">My lord, pray let her be carried away, and be whipped, until the be forced to confess it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102720" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102730">Let me killed first: for to be whipped is base, and is only fit for galley-slaves, or those that are born from slaves; but to be killed is noble, and gives an honourable triumph.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102740" who="A53060_05-justice">
              <speaker>Justice.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102750">Young lady, you are here accused by two witnesses, and unless you can bring evidence to clear you, you are liable to punishment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102760" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102770">Truly sir, I have but two invisible witnesses, conscience and innocency, to plead for me, and truth my judge, who cannot be bribed, although it may be overpowered, by false and slanderous reports.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102780" who="A53060_05-justice">
              <speaker>Justice.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102790">But it is imagined by your best friends, you are guilty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102800" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102810">Neither my friends, nor enemies, can create me a criminal, with their imaginations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102820" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102830">But speak, are you guilty?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102840" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102850">To what purpose should I speak? for what can I say to those that make it their delight to accuse, condemn, and execute? or what justice can I expect to have, where there is no equity? wherefore, to plead were a folly, when all hopes are cut off; to desire life, a double misery, if I must endure torments; but silence, and patience, shall be my two companions, the one to help me in my suffering, the other to cut of impertinencies.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e102860">She goes out from them.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102870" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102880">What think you justice, is she guilty?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102890" who="A53060_05-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102900">Why should you make a question, when it hath been proved by witnesses? Come justice, come, and drink a cup of sack, and give your opinion then.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e102910">The lady innocence comes, as passing by, alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102920" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102930">I am so confidently accused of this theft, as I am half persuaded I did take the chain, but that honour and honesty says I did not.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e102940">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="10" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e102950">
            <pb facs="95" n="166"/>
            <head>Scene 10.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e102960">Enter sir Thomas father love at one door, and a servant-maid at the other door. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e102970" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Sir Thomas father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e102980">Where is your mistress? the people do flock about the house to see her, as I think they will pull it upon my head if she shows not herself to them, wherefore call her.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e102990">The maid goes out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103000">Enter the lady Sanspareile.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103010" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Sir Thomas father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103020">Come, come child, there are such expectations without for thee; but what makes thee to look so heavy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103030" who="A53060_05-sanspareile">
              <speaker>Lady Sanspareile.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103040">Truly sir, I am not well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103050" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Sir Thomas father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103060">Not well? Heaven bless thee; where art thou sick?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103070" who="A53060_05-sanspareile">
              <speaker>Lady Sanspareile.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103080">I cannot say I am very sick, or in any great pain; but I find a general alteration in me, as it were a fainting of spirits.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103090" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Sir Thomas father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103100">Prithee say not so, thou dost so affright me; but thou art not very sick, art thou?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103110" who="A53060_05-sanspareile">
              <speaker>Lady Sanspareile.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103120">I hope I shall be better sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103130" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Sir Thomas father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103140">My dear child go to bed, whilst I send for some doctors to thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103150">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="11" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e103160">
            <head>Scene 11.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103170">Enter the lady innocence, alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103180" who="A53060_05-missing">
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103190">To whom shall I pour out my sad complaint? for all do them a melancholy mind. O gods! how willingly would I be buried in the grave with dust, and feast the worms, rather than live amongst mankind! Oh! oh! that these melancholy damps arising from my afflicted soul could extinguish the lamp of life, or that my sad and grieved thoughts that feed upon my troubled spirits, could bite with sorrows teeth, the thread of life asunder.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103200">She sits down on the ground, leaning her cheek on her hand, and weeps.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103210">Enter to her, her maid passive.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103220" who="A53060_05-passive">
              <speaker>Passive.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103230">My sweet mistress, why do you weep?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103240" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103250">The spring of grief doth send forth streams of tears to wash off my disgrace, and the foul spots which slandering tongues have stained, or rather stained my reputation; for which my eyes, did they not weep, would seem unnaturally unkind; but my dead reputation is embalmed with salt tears, bitter groans, shrouded in sorrows, and entombed in misery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103260" who="A53060_05-passive">
              <speaker>Passive.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103270">My dear lady, you are embalmed with the precious gums of<pb facs="95" n="167"/> virtue, and sweet spices of wit wrapped up in youth and beauty, and are entombed, or rather enthroned in honest hearts; wherefore waste not yourself with grief; for certainly the world will condemn your accusers, and not you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103280" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103290">Those feeble hopes cannot my spirits uphold, they give no light of comfort to my mind; for black despair, like melancholy night, muzzles my thoughts, and makes my soul as blind. O but why do I thus mourn in sad complaints, and do not curse fortune, fates, and destiny, their wheels, there spindle, threads, and chains?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103300">She heaves up her hands, and lifts up her eyes.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A53060_05-e103310">May nature great, turn all again to naught,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_05-e103320">That nothing may with joy receive a thought. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103330">She goes out in a very melancholy posture.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103340">Passive alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103350" who="A53060_05-missing">
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103360">She is deeply melancholy, heaven's ease her mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103370">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="12" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e103380">
            <head>Scene 12.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103390">Enter 2. or 3. Doctors. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103400" who="A53060_05-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Doctor. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103410">The lady Sanspareile cannot live, for the hath no pulse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103420" who="A53060_05-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Doctor. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103430">No, she is descending to the grave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103440" who="A53060_05-yyyy_3">
              <speaker>3. Doctor. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103450">But had we best tell her father so?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103460" who="A53060_05-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Doctor. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103470">No, by no means as yet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103480" who="A53060_05-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Doctor. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103490">Why not? he will know when she is dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103500">Enter the lady mother love, as to the doctors. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103510" who="A53060_05-mother_love">
              <speaker>Lady mother love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103520">Mr. doctors, what, do you mean to let my daughter die? will you not prescribe something to give her?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103530" who="A53060_05-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Doctor. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103540">Madam, we shall do our best, you may be confident.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103550" who="A53060_05-mother">
              <speaker>Lady mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103560">What if you prescribed a glister, or a purge?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103570" who="A53060_05-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Doctor. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103580">I shall not need madam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103590" who="A53060_05-mother">
              <speaker>Lady mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103600">Why, if any one be sick, they ought to have some remedies applied to them:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103610" who="A53060_05-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Doctor. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103620">We shall consider what course is best to be taken.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103630" who="A53060_05-mother_love">
              <speaker>Lady mother love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103640">For god's sake do not neglect her.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103650">Ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103660">Enter sir Thomas father love, to the doctors. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103670" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Sir Thomas father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103680">Mr. doctors, what is your opinion of my daughter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103690" who="A53060_05-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Doctor. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103700">Truly sir, she is very dangerous sick.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103710" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Sir Thomas father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103720">I can find no pulse she hath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103730" who="A53060_05-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Doctor. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103740">Nor we sir, that makes us doubt her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103750" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103760">Pray consult about her what is best to be done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103770" who="A53060_05-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Doctor. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103780">We shall sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103790">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="13" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e103800">
            <pb facs="96" n="168"/>
            <head>Scene 13.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103810">Enter the lord de l'amour, and the lady innocence.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103820" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103830">What makes you look so ghastly pale?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103840" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103850">I am so ashamed of my accusation, as my bashfulness is beyond all blushing, as greatest griefs are beyond all tears, it causes my limbs to tremble, face look pale, like death's assault, making my courage fail.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103860" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103870">Perchance you are ashamed to confess so base a crime; you may confess to me, for I shall strive to hide your faults, and cover them with some excuse; wherefore confess; for though it be a fault to steal, yet it is a double fault to hide it with a lie, and by these crimes you do offend the gods; nor will their anger be removed, unless you confess and ask pardon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103880" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103890">Your doctrine is very good, and application well applied, had I been guilty; but being innocent, they are vainly uttered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103900" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103910">I hope you will agree to resign the interest you have to me, if I should desire you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103920" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103930">Saints never offered up their souls to God more willingly, than I all interest to you; not but that I love you, yet I should be loath to be bound to one that hath so ill an opinion of me, as you have.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103940" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103950">The world would condemn me, if I should marry you, to stain my posterity with your crimes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103960" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e103970">O heavens, is my scandal of so deep a dye, as to stain predecessors and posterity! yours may avoid it, but my predecessors are spotted all over.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e103980">She goes out weeping.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e103990" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104000">I cannot choose but love her, although I fear she is guilty; but I perceive she is resolved not to confess, as being ashamed of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104010">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="14" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e104020">
            <head>Scene 14.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104030">Enter the lady Sanspareile in a bed, as being sick, the bed drawn on the stage, and her father kneels by the bedside whilst she speaks as dying. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104040" who="A53060_05-sanspareile">
              <speaker>Sanspareile.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104050">Let spotless virgins bear me to my grave, and holy anthems sing before my hearse, and soft-touched instruments to play the while, and keep just time with tears, that trickling fall from the sad eyes of my most sorrowful friends; and one my coffin spread upon a covering of smooth satin, white, to signify here how I lived a virgin, pure I lived and died; and let my works which I have wrought, and spun out of my brain, be given to time's library, to keep alive my name.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104060">And set a lilly-garland on my hearse,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104070">On every leaf therein, stick on a verse;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104080"><pb facs="96" n="169"/> and when my coffin to the grave you bring,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104090">Let poets on my hearse some verses fling. </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104100">For whilst I lived I worshipped nature great,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104110">And poets are by nature favoured. </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104120">I in the muse's arms desire to die,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104130">For I was bred up in their company:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104140">And my request's to them, when I am dead,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104150">I may amongst them be remembered. </l>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104160">But death draws near, my destiny is come; father farewell: may time take up my years, which death cuts off, and add them to your life: peace keep your mind, and comfort give you rest.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104170">He weeps.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104180" who="A53060_05-missing">
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104190">But why do you weep dear father? my life's not worth your tears; yet heavens do weep, and mingle with dull earth their crystal streams, and earth's refreshed thereby; so is not death, for death is ever dry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104200" who="A53060_05-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104210">O child! O child! my heart will break.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104220" who="A53060_05-sanspareile">
              <speaker>Sanspareile.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104230">Sir, why do you sigh and groan, and grieve, that I must die? life is perpetual, and death is but a change of shape.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104240">Only I wish that death may order it so,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104250">That from your roots I may your flower grow. </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104260">I fear not death, nor am I loath to die:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104270">Yet I am loath to leave your company. </l>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104280">But oh the muses stay my dying lips to close. farewell</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104290">Dyes.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104300">Her father starts up from her bedside, and stares about the bed; and the dead lady is drawn off the stage.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104310" who="A53060_05-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104320">What art thou stead? dear soul where dost thou go? stay and I will bear thee company.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104330">Stares about.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104340">Where art thou soul? why mak'st thou such great haste? I pray thee stay, and take thy aged father's soul along with thee, left it should wander in the dark and gloomy shades to find thee out. O! oh death! quick dispatch, let me unprisoned be, my body is old, decayed and worn, times ruins shows it. Oh! oh! let life fall, for pity pull it down. <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104350">[stops a time]</stage>am I not dead? you cruel powers above, to lengthen out an old man's life in misery and pain; why did not time put out the sight of both my eyes, and also deaf my ears, that I might neither hear, nor see, the death of my life's joy? O luxurious death, how greedily thou feedest on youth and beauty, and leist old age hang withering on life's tree? O shake me off, let me no longer grow, if not, grief shall by force snip off my tender stalk, and pity lay me in the silent grave. Hark, hark, I hear her call me? I come, I come child.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104360">He fetches a great sigh.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104370">O no, she is gone, she is gone, I saw her dead; her head hung down, like as a lily, whose stalk was broke by some rude blusterous wind.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104380">He stares about.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104390">There, there I see her on her duteous knee; her humble eyes cast to the ground; her spotless hands held up for blessings crave, asking forgiveness for faults not done. O no, she is dead! She is dead! I saw her eyelids close<pb facs="97" n="170"/> like watery clouds, which join to shut out the bright sun; and felt her hands which death made cold and numb, like as to crystal balls; she is gone, she is gone, and restless grows my mind; thoughts strive with thoughts, and struggle in my brain, passions with passions in my heart make war.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104400">My spirits run like furies all about;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104410">Help help for heaven's sake, and let life out. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104420">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="15" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e104430">
            <head>Scene 15.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104440">Enter the lady mother love alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104450" who="A53060_05-mother_love">
              <speaker>Lady mother love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104460">O my daughter! my daughter is dead, she is dead. O that ever I was born to bear a child to die before me. O she was the comfort of my heart, the pleasure of my eyes, the delight of my life. O she was good, she was sweet, she was fair. O what shall I do, what shall I do?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104470">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="16" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e104480">
            <head>Scene 16.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104490">Enter sir Thomas father love, half distracted. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104500" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Sir Thomas father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104510">Mercury lend me thy winged feet, that I may fly to heaven, there to observe, how all the gods and goddesses do gaze upon my beautiful child; for she is fairer than the light that great Apollo gives; and her discourse more ravishing than the music of the spheres; but as soon as she sees me, she will leave them all, and run unto me, as she used to do, kneeling will kiss my hands, which she must not do, being a goddess, and I a mortal, wherefore, I must kneel to her, and carry her an offering; but what shall the offering be? Let me think. Why I will kneel and offer up my aged life unto her memory; but now I think of it better, I cannot die in heaven; wherefore, let me study, let me study, what she did love best when she lived upon the earth; oh I now remember, when I did ask her what she loved best, she would answer, her father and her fame; but I believe, if she were here it would be a hard question for her to resolve, which she preferred; and being not to be separated in affection, we will not part in our resurrection; wherefore Mercury farewell: for I will fly up with the wings of her good fame.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104520">And carry up her wit, and there will strew</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104530">It on heaven's floor, as bright as stars will show;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104540">Her innocency shall make new milky ways,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104550">Her virtue shall create new worlds to praise</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104560">Her never-dying name. </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104570">Ha, ho! it shall be so, it shall be so. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104580">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A53060_05-e104590">
          <pb facs="97" n="171"/>
          <head>Act iv.</head>
          <div n="17" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e104600">
            <head>Scene 17.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104610">Enter the lady innocence alone, studious, with her eyes to the ground, thou casting them up speaks. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104620" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104630">I am not so much in love with the world, as to desire to live, nor have I offended heaven so much, as to be afraid to die; then way should I prolong my life, when honour bids me die? for what noble soul had not rather part with the body, than live in infamy? Then 'tis not death that affrights me, and yet I find my soul is loath to leave its bodily mansion; but oh to be buried in oblivion's grave is all I fear; no monumental fame, nor famous monument, my soul displeases, that makes it loath to leave the body in forgotten dust, whilst it doth sadly wander in the air.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104640">She walks a turn or two as in a musing thought, then speaks.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104650" who="A53060_05-missing">
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104660">Soul be at ease, for the memory of the dead is but like a dying beauty, vades by degrees, or like a flower withered, hath neither sent, colour, nor taste, but moulders into dust: so hath the mind no form of what is passed.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104670">But like as formless heaps those objects lie,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104680">And are entombed in the dark memory. </l>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104690">O foolish vanity, to be so much a slave to fame, since those that fame doth love the best, and favoureth most, are not eternal. wherefore</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104700">Nature persuades me to release my woe,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104710">Though foolish superstition nature's foe</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104720">Forbids it, yet reason aloud says die;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104730">Since ease, peace, rest, doth in the grave still lie. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104740">Walks about as in a silent musing, then speaks.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104750" who="A53060_05-missing">
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104760">I am resolved, then come sweet death, thou friend that never fails, give me my liberty. But stay my hasty resolution; for I would not willingly go to the grave as beasts do, without ceremony; for I being friendless, those humane funeral rites will be neglected, none will take the pains, nor be at the charge to see them performed; but some base vulgar person will throw me into the earth without respect or regard; wherefore I will living perform the ceremonies, and as a guess or friend be at my own funeral; it shall be so, and I will prepare it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104770">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="18" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e104780">
            <pb facs="98" n="172"/>
            <head>Scene 18.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104790">Enter sir Thomas father love alone, and for a time walks as in a musing or thinking, with his eyes cast on the ground, then speaks. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104800" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104810">Multitudes of melancholy thoughts crowd in my brain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104820">And run to pull down reason from his throne;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104830">Fury as captain leads the way,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104840">Patience and hope is trod upon:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104850">Oh these distracted thoughts bury my soul about,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104860">Seeking a place to get a passage out. </l>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104870">But all the ports are stopped. O cursed death, for to prolong a life that is so weary of its mansion.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e104880">Enter Mr. Comfort sir Thomas father loves friend. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104890" who="A53060_05-friend">
              <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104900">Sir, will you give order for your daughter's funeral, and direct how you will have her interred?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104910" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104920">How say you? why I will have you rip my body open, and make it as a coffin to lay her in, then heave us gently on sighs fetched deep, and lay us on a hearse of sorrowful groans, then cover us with a dark, black, pitchy, spongy cloud, made of thick vapour, drawn from bleeding hearts; from whence may tears of showers run pouring down, making a sea to drown remembrance in.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104930">But oh remembrance, is a fury grown,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e104940">Torments my soul, now she is gone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104950" who="A53060_05-friend">
              <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104960">Sir, where there is no remedy, you must have patience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104970" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e104980">Patience, out upon her, she is an idle lazy gossip, and keep; none company but cowards and fools, and slothful conscientious persons; neither is she useful but for indifferent employments: for what is of extraordinary worth, patience doth but disgrace it, not set it forth; for that which is transcendent and supreme, patience cannot reach. Wherefore give me fury, for what it cannot raise to heaven, it throws it straight to hell; were you never there?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e104990" who="A53060_05-friend">
              <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105000">No, nor I hope shall never come there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105010" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105020">Why sir, I was there all the last night, and there I was tortured for chiding my daughter two or three times whilst she lived; once because she went in the sun without her mask; another time because her gloves were in her pocket, when they should have been on her hands; and another time, because she slept when she should have studied, and then I remember she wept. O! o! those precious tears! Devil that I was to grieve her sweet nature, harmless thoughts, and innocent soul. O how I hate myself, for being so unnaturally kind. O kill me, and rid be of my painful life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105030" who="A53060_05-friend">
              <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105040">He is much distracted, heaven cure him.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105050">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="18" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e105060">
            <pb facs="98" n="173"/>
            <head>Scene 18.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105070">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105080" who="A53060_05-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Geentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105090">The miracle is deceased, the lady Sanspareile I hear is dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105100" who="A53060_05-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2. Gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105110">Yes, and it's reported her statue shall be set up in every college, and in the most public places in the city, at the public charge; and the Queen will build a sumptuous and glorious tomb on her sleeping ashes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105120" who="A53060_05-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1. Gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105130">She deserves more than can be given her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105140" who="A53060_05-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2. Gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105150">I hear her death hath made her father mad.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105160" who="A53060_05-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1. Gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105170">Though her death hath not made every one mad like her father, yet it hath made every one melancholy; for I never saw so general a sadness in my life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105180" who="A53060_05-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2. Gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105190">There is nothing moves the mind to sadness, more than when death devours youth, beauty, wit, and virtue all at once.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105200">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="19" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e105210">
            <head>Scene 19.</head>
            <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105220">There is a hearse placed upon the stage, covered with black, a garland of Cyprus at the head of the hearse, and a garland of myrtle at one side, and a basket of flowers on the other.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105230">Enter the lady innocence alone, dressed in white, and her hair hound up in several coloured ribbons; when she first comes in speaks thus. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105240" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105250">O nature, thou hast created bodies and minds subject to pains and torments, yet thou hast made death to release them! for though death hath power over life, yet life can command death when it will; for death dares not stay, when life would pass away; death is the ferryman, and life the waftage.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105260">She kneels down and prayeth</stage>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105270">But here great nature, I do pray to thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105280">Though I call death, let him not cruel be:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105290">Great Jove I pray, when in cold earth I lie,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105300">Let it be known how innocent I die. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105310">[then she rises and directs herself to her hearse.]</stage>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105320">Here in the midst my sadder hearse I see;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105330"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A53060_05-e105340">these verses the lord marquess writ.</note> covered with black, though my chief mourners be,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105350">Yet I am white, as innocent as day,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105360">As pure as spotless lilies born in may;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105370">My loose and flowing hair with ribbons tied,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105380">To make death amorous of me, now his bride;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105390"><pb facs="99" n="174"/> watchet for truth, hair-colour for despair,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105400">And white as innocent as purest air;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105410">Scarlet for cruelty to stop my breath,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105420">Darkening of nature, black, a type of death. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105430">[then she takes up the basket of flowers, and as she strews them speaks.]</stage>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105440">Roses and lilies about my coffin strew,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105450">Primroses, pinks, violets fresh and new:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105460">And though in deaths cold arms anon I lie<stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105470">[weeps]</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105480">I'll weep a shower of tears these may not die,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105490">A Cyprus' garland here is for my head,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105500">To crown me Queen of innocence, when dead;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105510">A myrtle garland on the left side placed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105520">To show I was a lover; pure and chaste;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105530">Now all my saddest rites being thus about me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105540">And I have not one wish that is without me. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105550">[she placeth herself on her hearse, with a dagger or pointed knife in her hand.]</stage>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105560">Here on this hearse I mount the throne of death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105570">Peace crown my soul, my body rest on earth:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105580">Yet before I die,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105590">Like to a swan I will sing my elegy. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105600">[she sings as she is sitting on the hearse, thus.]</stage>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105610">Life is a trouble at the best,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105620"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A53060_05-e105630">this song the lord marquess writ.</note> and in it we can find no rest;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105640">Joys still with sorrows they are crowned,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105650">No quietness till in the ground. </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105660">Man vexes man, still we do find,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105670">He is the torture of his kind:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105680">False man I scorn thee in my grave</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105690">Death come, I call thee as my slave. </l>
            </sp>
            <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105700">Here ends my lords writing.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105710">And just then stabs herself.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105720">In the mean time the lord de l'amour comes and peeps through the curtain; or hanging, and speaks as to himself, whilst she is a dying. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105730" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105740">I will observe how she passes away her time, when she is alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105750" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105760">Great Jove grant that the light of truth may not be put out, with the extinguisher of malice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105770" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105780">How she feeds her melancholy!</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105790">He enters and goeth to her.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105800">What are you acting a melancholy play by yourself alone? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105810" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105820">My part is almost done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105830" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <pb facs="99" n="175"/>
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105840">By heaven she hath stabbed herself.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105850">[calls help, help]</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105860" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105870">Call not for help, life is gone so far 'tis past recovery; wherefore stay and hear my last words; I die, as judging it unworthy to outlive my honest name, and honourable reputation. As for my accusers, I can easily forgive them, because they are below my hate or anger, neither are worthy my revenge; but you, for whom I had not only a devout, but an idolatrous affection, which offered with a zealous piety and pure flame the sincerity of my heart; but you, instead of rewarding my love, was cruel to my life and honour, for which my soul did mourn under a veil of sadness, and my thoughts covered with discontent sat weeping by: but those mourning thoughts I have cast off, clothing myself with death's pale garments; as for my pure reputation, and white simplicity, that is spotted with black infamy by hellish slander, I have laid them at heaven's gates, just gods to scour them clean, that all the world may know how innocent I have been: but oh! farewell, my fleeting spirits pure angels bear away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105880" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105890">O speak at the last! Are you guilty or not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105900" who="A53060_05-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105910">I am no more guilty of those crimes laid to my charge, than heaven is of sin.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e105920">O gods receive me. Oh! oh!</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105930">Dies.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e105940" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105950">Great patience assist me; heart hold life in,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e105960">Till I can find who is guilty of this sin. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105970">Ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e105980">The hearse drawn off the stage.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="20" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e105990">
            <head>Scene 20.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106000">Enter sir Thomas father love, brought in a chair as sick, his friend by him. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106010" who="A53060_05-mr_comfort_friend">
              <speaker>Mr. comfort friend.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106020">How are you now?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106030" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106040">O friend! I shall now be well, heaven hath pity on me, and will release me soon; and if my daughter be not buried, I would have her kept as long out of the grave as she can be kept, that I might bear her company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106050" who="A53060_05-friend">
              <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106060">She cannot be kept longer, because she was not unboweled.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106070" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106080">Who speaks her funeral oration?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106090" who="A53060_05-friend">
              <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106100">Why sir, your distemper hath so disordered all your family, as it was not thought of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106110" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106120">She shall not go to the grave without due praises, if I have life to speak them: wherefore raise me up, and carry me to the holy place before her hearse, thus in my chair, sick as I am; for I will speak her funeral oration, although with my last words, thus will I be carried living to my grave.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106130">He is carried out in a chair by servants.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106140">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="21" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e106150">
            <pb facs="100" n="176"/>
            <head>Scene 21.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106160">Enter the lord de l' Amour alone, as in a melancholy humour. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106170" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106180">When I do think of her, my mind is like a tempestuous sea, which foams and roars, and rolls in billows high; my brain like to a ship is wracked, and in it's ravenous waves my heart is drowned; and as several winds do blow, so several thoughts do move; some like the North with cold and chilly fears, others as from the South of hot revenge do blow;</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106190">As from the East despairing storms do rise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106200">A western grief blows tears into mine eyes. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106210">Walks about, and weeps.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106220">Enter master charity his friend. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106230" who="A53060_05-charity">
              <speaker>Mr. charity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106240">My lord, why are you so melancholy for that which is past, and cannot be helped?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106250" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106260">Oh! the remembrance of her death, her cruel death, is like the infernal furies, torments my soul, gives it no case nor rest; for sometimes my soul is flung into a fire of rage,</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106270">That burns with furious pain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106280">And then with frozen despair it rips it up again. </l>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106290">But I unjust and credulous, I was the cause of her untimely death.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106300">Enter the maid that accused her.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106310" who="A53060_05-falshood">
              <speaker>Falshood.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106320">O my lord, forgive me, for I have murdered the innocent lady you grieve for; for my false accusation was the hand that guided the dagger to her heart; but my ladies command was the thief that stole the chain, for she commanded me to take the chain, and accuse the lady of the theft, for which she gave me the chain for a reward; this I will witness by oath unto you and all the world; for it is heavier than a world upon my conscience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106330" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106340">Why did your lady so wicked an act?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106350" who="A53060_05-falshood">
              <speaker>Falshood.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106360">Through jealousy, which bred envy, envy malice, malice slander, and this slander hath produce murder.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106370">Enter informer, the other maid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106380" who="A53060_05-informer">
              <speaker>Informer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106390">O my lady! My lady hath hanged herself; for when she heard falsehood was gone to tell your lordship the truth of the chain, she went into a base place and hung herself; and upon her breast I found this written paper.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106400">She gives it de l'amour to read. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106410" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106420">It is the lady Incontinents handwriting.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106430">He reads it.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106440">I have been false to my marriage-bed, lived impudently in the sin of adultery,<pb facs="100" n="177"/> in the public face of the world; I have betrayed the trust imposed to my charge, slandered the innocent, poisoned the instrument I employed, falsehood. All which being summed up, was worthy of hanging. </p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106450">[falsehood falls down dead.]</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106460" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106470">She hath saved me a labour, and kept my heroic honour free from the stains of having laid violent hands on the effeminate sex.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106480" who="A53060_05-friend">
              <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106490">What shall be done with this dead body?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106500" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106510">Let her lady's body, with hers, be thrown into the fields, to be devoured of beasts.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106520">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A53060_05-e106530">
          <head>Act v.</head>
          <div n="22" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e106540">
            <head>Scene 22.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106550">Enter the funeral hearse of the lady Sanspareile, covered with white satin; a silver crown is placed in the midst; her hearse is born by six virgins all in white, other virgins go before the hearse, and strew flowers, white lilies, and white roses: the whilst this song is sung. </stage>
            <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106560"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A53060_05-e106570">this song was writ by the lord marquess.</note>spotless virgins as you go,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106580">Wash each step as white as snow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106590">With pure crystal streams, that rise</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106600">From the fountain of your eyes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106610">Fresher lilies like the day</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106620">Strew, and roses as white as they;</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106630">As an emblem to disclose</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106640">This flower sweet; short lived as those. </l>
            <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106650">The whilst her father is carried as sick in a chair, the chair covered with black, and born black by mourners, he himself also in close mourning; when they have gone about the stage.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106660">The hearse is set near to the grave, there being one made.</stage>
            <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106670">Then the father is placed in his chair, upon a raised place for that purpose, the raised place also covered with black; he being placed, speaks her funeral sermon.</p>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106680" who="A53060_05-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106690">Most charitable and noble friends, that accompany the dead corpse to the grave, I must tell you, I am come here, although I am as a dead man to the world, yet my desire is to make a living speech, before I go out of the world, not only to divulge the affections I had for my daughter, but to divulge her virtue, worth, and good graces; and as it is the custom for the nearest kindred, or best and constantest friends, or longest acquaintance, to speak their funeral oration, wherein I take myself to be all,<pb facs="101" n="179"/> wherefore most fit to speak her funeral oration; for I being her father, am her longest acquaintance, and constantest friend, and nearest in relation, wherefore the, fittest to declare unto the world my natural and fatherly love, death will be a sufficient witness; for though I am old, yet I was healthful when she lived, but now I cannot live many hours, neither would I, for heaven knows, my affections struggle with death, to hold life so long as to pay the last rites due to her dead corpse, struck by death's cruel dart: but most noble and charitable friends, I come not here with eye filled with salt tears; for sorrows thirsty jaws hath drunk them up, sucked out my blood, and left my veins quite dry, and luxuriously hath eat my marrow out; my sighs are spent in blowing out life's fire, only some little heat there doth remain, which my affections strive to keep alive to pay the last rites due to my dead child, which is, to set her praises forth, for living virtuously; but had I Nestor's years, 'twould prove too few, to tell the living storeys of her youth, for nature in her had packed up many piles of experience, of aged times, besides, nature had made her youth sweet, fresh and temperate, as the spring; and in her brain, flowers of fancies grew, wits garden set by nature's hand, wherein the Muses took delight, and entertained themselves therein, singing like nightingales, late at night; or like the larks ere the day begin; her thoughts were as the celestial orbs, still moving circular without back ends, surrounding the centre of her noble mind, which as the sun gave light to all about it; her virtues twinkled like the fixed stars, whose motion stirs them not from their fixed place; and all her passions were as other stars, which seemed as only made to beautify her form; but death hath turned a chaos of her form, which life with art and care had made, and gods had given to me: oh cursed death, to rob and make me poor! Her life to me was like a delightful mask, presenting several interchanging scenes, describing nature in her several dresses, and every dress put in a several way; also her life was like a monarchy, where reason as sole King, did govern all her actions; which actions, like as loyal subjects did obey those laws which reason decreed; also her life was like Jove's mansions high, as being placed above this worldly globe; from whence her soul looked down on duller earth, mixed not, but viewed poor mortals here below; thus was her life above the world, because her life prized not the trifles here; perchance this noble company will think I have said too much, and vainly, thus to speak.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106700">That fathers should not praise their children so,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106710">Because that from their root and stock did grow;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106720">Why may not roots boast if their fruits be good? </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106730">As hindering worth in their own flesh and blood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106740">Shall they dissemble, to say they are naught,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106750">Because they are their own? sure that's a fault</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106760">Unpardonable, as being a lie that's told,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106770">Detracting lies, the baser lies I hold. </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106780">Neither can strangers tell their life and worth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106790">Nor such affections have to set them forth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106800">As parents have, or those that's near of kin,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106810">Virtuous partiality, sure that's no sin,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106820">And virtue, though she be lovliest when undressed</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106830"><pb facs="101" n="178"/> yet she is pleased, when well she is expressed. </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106840">But oh! my words have spent my stock of breath,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106850">And life's commanded forth by powerful death;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106860">When I am dead, this company I pray,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106870">The last rites done, me by my daughter lay;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106880">And as her soul did with the muses fly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106890">To imitate her in her a verse, I die. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106900">He falls back in his chair and is dead.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e106910" who="A53060_05-comfort">
              <speaker>Mr. comfort.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106920">Noble friends, you heard his request, which was; to be buried in his daughter's grave; and whilst you show your charity, in laying the corpse of his daughter in the grave, I will carry out his body, and put it into a coffin, and then lay him in the same grave.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e106930">[the company said, do so.] Goes out with the body. </stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e106940">The whilst the virgins take up the lady Sanspareiles hearse, and whilst they are putting it into the grave, this song following was sung.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106950"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A53060_05-e106960">this song was writ by the lord marquess of Newcastle. </note>tender virgins, as your birth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106970">Put her gently in the earth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106980">What of moral, or divine,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e106990">Here is leapt up in this shrine;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107000">Rhetoric dumb philosophy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107010">Both those arts with her did die. </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107020">And grieved poets cannot choose,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107030">But lament for her their muse. </l>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e107040">When she was putting into the grave, this song following was sung.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107050">Her tomb, her monument, her name,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107060">Beyond an epitaph her fame;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107070">Death be not proud, embracing more</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107080">Now, than in all thy reign before;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107090">Boasting thy triumphs, since thou must</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107100">But justly glory in her dust,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107110">Let thy dart rust, and lay it by,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107120">For after her none's sit to die. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e107130">[after this her peal is rung on lutes, by musicians.] And the company goes out. </stage>
          </div>
          <div n="23" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_05-e107140">
            <head>Scene. 23.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e107150">A tomb is thrust on the stage, then the lord de l'amour enters. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e107160" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e107170">Now I am free, no hindrance to my own tragedy.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e107180">[he goeth to the tomb.]</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e107190">This tomb her sacred body doth contain.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e107200">[he draws his sword, then he kneels down by the tomb, and then prays.]</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e107210"><pb facs="102" n="180"/>Dear soul, pardon my crimes to thee; they were crimes of ignorance, not malice.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107220">Sweet gentle spirits, fly me not, but stay,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107230">And let my spirits walk thy spirit's way;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107240">You loved me once, your love in death renew,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107250">And may our souls be as two lovers true;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107260">Our blood's the bonds, our wounds the seals to print</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107270">Our new contract, and death a witness in't. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e107280">[he takes his sword.]</stage>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107290">Had I as many lives as poors in skin,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107300">He sacrifice them for my ignorant sin. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e107310">[as he speaks he falls upon his sword.]</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e107320">Enter his friend, master charity.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e107330">[he seeing him lie all in blood, almost dead, runs to him, and heaves him up.]</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e107340" who="A53060_05-friend">
              <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e107350">I did fear this, which made me follow him, but I am come too late to save his life. O my lord speak if you can!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_05-e107360" who="A53060_05-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_05-e107370">Friend, lay me in this tomb, by my affianced wife; for though I did not usher her to the grave, I will wait after her.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_05-e107380">[Dyes.]</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="epilogue" xml:id="A53060_05-e107390">
          <head>Epilogue.</head>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107400">Noble spectators, now you have seen this play,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107410">And heard it speak, let's hear what now you say;</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107420">But various judgements, various sentences give,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107430">Yet we do hope you'll sentence it may live. </l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107440">But not in prison be condemned to lie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107450">Nor whipped with censure, rather let it die</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107460">Here on this stage, and see the funeral rites,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107470">Which is, to put out all the candle lights. </l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107480">And in the grave of darkness let it rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107490">In peace and quiet, and not molest</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107500">The harmless soul, which hopes Mercury may</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107510">Unto the Elysium fields it safe convey. </l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107520">But if you sentence life, the muses will</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107530">Attend it up unto Parnassus hill. </l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107540">If so, pray let your hands, here in this place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_05-e107550">Clap it, as an applause, the triumph grace. </l>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A53060_05-e107560">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A53060_05"><item xml:id="A53060_05-delamour" n="46">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-delamour</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">46</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-innocence" n="42">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-innocence</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">42</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-father_love" n="17">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-father_love</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">17</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-incontinent" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-incontinent</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-sanspareile" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-sanspareile</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-yyyy_1" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-friend" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-friend</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-gentleman_2" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-gentleman_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-queen" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-queen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-gentleman_1" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-gentleman_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-passive" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-passive</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-missing" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-missing</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A53060_05-falshood" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-falshood</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-father" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-father</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-yyyy_2" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-yyyy_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-mother_love" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-mother_love</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-adviser" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-adviser</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-mother" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-mother</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-justice" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-justice</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-informer" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-informer</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-messenger" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-comfort" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-comfort</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-yyyy_3" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-yyyy_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-mr_comfort_friend" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-mr_comfort_friend</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-charity" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-charity</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_05-maids" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_05-maids</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

