<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A07518">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Triumphs of Truth; The Entertainment on Michaelmas Day 1613 <date type="creation_date">1613</date></title>
        <author>Middleton, Thomas</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nayoon Ahn</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A07518.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The triumphs of truth. A solemnity vnparalleled for cost, art, and magnificence, at the confirmation and establishment of that worthy and true nobly-minded gentleman, Sir Thomas Middleton, knight, in the honorable office of his Maiesties lieuetenant, the lord maior of the thrice famous citty of London. Taking beginning at his Lord-ships going, and proceeding after his returne from receiuing the oath of maioralty at Westminster, on the morrow next after Simon and Iudes day, October 29. 1613. All the showes, pageants, chariots; morning, noone, and night-triumphes. Directed, written, and redeem'd into forme, from the ignorance of some former times, and their common writer, by Thomas Middleton.</title>
            <author>Middleton, Thomas, d. 1627.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>16 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2005 December (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99855091</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 17903.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, 311.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">20563</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07518</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The triumphs of truth. A solemnity vnparalleled for cost, art, and magnificence, at the confirmation and establishment of that worthy and true nobly-minded gentleman, Sir Thomas Middleton, knight, in the honorable office of his Maiesties lieuetenant, the lord maior of the thrice famous citty of London. Taking beginning at his Lord-ships going, and proceeding after his returne from receiuing the oath of maioralty at Westminster, on the morrow next after Simon and Iudes day, October 29. 1613. All the showes, pageants, chariots; morning, noone, and night-triumphes. Directed, written, and redeem'd into forme, from the ignorance of some former times, and their common writer, by Thomas Middleton.</title>
            <title type="alt">Triumphes of truth.</title>
            <title type="alt">Song with the note.</title>
            <author>Middleton, Thomas, d. 1627.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[32] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes dwelling at the signe of the Hand, neere Holbourne-Bridge,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1613.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: The triumphes of truth.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Appended, with caption title: The song with the note.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-D4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Middleton, Thomas, -- Sir, -- 1550-1631 -- Early works to 1800.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A07518-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A07518-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A07518-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e100040">The triumphs of truth.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e100050">A solemnity unparallel for cost, art, and magnificence, at the confirmation and establishment of that worthy and true nobly. Minded gentleman, sir Thomas Middleton, knight, in the honourable office of his majesty's lieutenant, the lord mayor of the thrice famous city of London.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e100060">Taking beginning 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 lordships going and proceeding 〈…〉 e from receiving the oath of ma 〈…〉 Westminster, on the morrow of 〈…〉 and Jude's day, 〈◊〉 19 1613.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e100070">All the shows, pa 〈…〉, chariots; morning, noon, and night-triumphes.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e100080">Directed, written, underdeemed into form from the ignorance of some former times and their common writer.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e100090">By Thomas Middleton.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e100100">London. Printed by N 〈…〉 dwelling at the sign of the hand, oh 〈…〉 ●●●●●rne-bridge. 1613.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A07518-e100110">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To the great expectation of virtue and goodness, and most worthy of all those costs and honours, which the noble fellowship and society and grocers, and general love of the whole city, in full heaped bounties bestow upon him, the truly. Generous and judicious, sir Thomas Middleton, knight, lord mayor of the honourable city of London.</head>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e100120">As often as we shall fix our thoughts upon the almighty providence, soften they return to our capacities laden with admiration, either from the divine works of his mercy, or those incomprehensible of his justice: but here to instance only his omnipotent mercy, it being the health and preservation of all his works: and first not only in raising, but also in preserving your l. from many great and incident dangers, especially<pb facs="3"/> in foreign countries in the time of your youth and travels: and now with safety, love and triumph, to establish you in this years honour: crowning the perfection of your days, and the gravity of your life, with power, respect and reverence. Next, in that myself (Though unworthy) being of one name with your lordship, notwithstanding all oppositions of malice, ignorance and envy, should thus happily live, protected by part of that mercy (As if one fate did prosperously cleave to one name) now to do service to your fame and worthiness, and my pen, only to be employed in these bounteous and honourable triumphs, being but shadows to those eternal glories that stand ready for deservers, to which I commend the deserts of your justice, remaining ever</p>
        <closer xml:id="A07518-e100130">
          <signed xml:id="A07518-e100140">To your lordship, in the best of my observance, Thomas Middleton.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A07518-e100150">
      <div type="triumph" xml:id="A07518-e100160">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>The triumphs of truth.</head>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e100170">Search all chronicles, histories, records, in what language or letter soever; let the inquisitive man waste the dear treasures of his time and eyesight, he shall conclude his life only in this certainty, that there is no subject upon earth received into the place of his government with the like state and magnificence as is the lord mayor of the city of London. This being then infallible (Like the mistress of our triumphs) and not to be denied of any, how careful ought those gentlemen to be, to whose discretion and judgement the weight and charge of such a business is entirely referred and committed by the whole society, to have all things correspondent to that generous and noble freeness of cost and liberality, the streams of art, to equal those of bounty; a knowledge that may take the true height of such an honourable solemnity; the miserable want of both which in the impudent common writer, hath often forced from me much pity and sorrow; and it would heartily grieve any understanding spirit to behold many times so glorious a fire in<pb facs="4"/> bounty and goodness offering to match in self with freezing art, sitting in darkness, with the candle out, looking like the picture of black Monday. </p>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e100180">But to speak truth, which many beside myself can affirm upon knowledge, a care that hath been seldom equalled, and not easily imitated, hath been faithfully shown in the whole course of this business, both by the wardens and committees, men of much understanding, industry, and carefulness, little weighing the greatness of expense, so the cost might purchase perfection, so fervent hath been their desire to excel in that (Which is a learned and virtuous ambition) and so unfeignedly pure the loves and affections of the whole company to his lordship; if any shall imagine that I set fairer colours upon their deserts, than they upon themselves, let them but read and conceive, and their own understandings will light them to the acknowledgement of their errors. First, they may here behold love and bounty opening with the morning, earlier than some of former years, ready at the first appearing of his lordship, to give his ear a taste of the days succeeding glory, and thus the form of it presents itself.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e100190">At Soper-lane end a senate-house erected, upon which musicians sit playing; and more a quicken time, a sweet voice married to these words:</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e100200" who="A07518-missing">
          <lg type="song" xml:id="A07518-e100210">
            <head>The song.</head>
            <l xml:id="A07518-e100220">Mother of many honourable 'zounds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07518-e100230">Think not the glass too slowly runs</l>
            <l xml:id="A07518-e100240">That in time's hand is set,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07518-e100250">Because thy worthy son appears not yet:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07518-e100260">Lady be pleased, the hour grows on,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07518-e100270">Thy joy will be complete anon;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07518-e100280"><pb facs="4"/> thou shalt behold</l>
            <l xml:id="A07518-e100290">The man enrolled</l>
            <l xml:id="A07518-e100300">In honour's books, whom virtue raises,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07518-e100310">Love-circled round,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07518-e100320">His triumphs crowned</l>
            <l xml:id="A07518-e100330">With all good wishes, prayers, and praises. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e100340">After this sweet air hath liberally spent itself, at the first appearing of the lord mayor from Guildhall in the morning, a trumpet placed upon that scaffold, sounds forth his welcome; then after a strain or two of music, a grave feminine shape presents itself, from behind a silk curtain, representing London, attired like a reverend mother, a long white hair naturally flowing on either side of her: on her head a model of steeples and turrets, her habit crimson silk, near to the honourable garment of the city: her left hand holding a key of gold, who after a comely grace, equally mixed with comfort and reverence, sends from her lips this motherly salutation.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e100350" who="A07518-london">
          <speaker>The speech of London.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100360">Honour and joy salute thee, I am raised</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100370">In comfort and in love to see thee, glad</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100380">And happy in thy blessings, nor esteem</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100390">My words the less, cause I a woman speak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100400">A woman's counsel is not always weak. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100410">I am thy mother, at that name I know</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100420">Thy heart does reverence to me, as becomes</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100430">A son of honour, in whose soul burns clear</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100440">The sacred lights of divine fear and knowledge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100450">I know, that at this instant, all the works</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100460">Of motherly love in me, shown to thy youth</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100470">When it was soft and helpless, are summed up</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100480"><pb facs="5"/> in thy most grateful mind, thou well remember'st</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100490">All my dear pains and care, with what affection</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100500">I cherish thee in my bosom, watchful still</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100510">Over thy ways,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100520">Set wholesome and religious laws before</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100530">The footsteps of thy youth, showed thee the way</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100540">That lead thee to the glory of this day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100550">To which (With tears of the most fruitful joy</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100560">That ever mother shed) I welcome thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100570">O I could be content to take my part</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100580">Out of Felicity only in weeping,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100590">Thy presence and this day is so dear to me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100600">Look on my age (My honourable son)</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100610">And then begin to think upon thy office:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100620">See how on each side of me hang the cares</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100630">Which I bestowed on thee, in silver hairs. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100640">And now the faith, the love, the zealous fires</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100650">With which I cheered thy youth, my age requires,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100660">The duty of a mother I have shown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100670">Through all the rites of pure affection,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100680">In care, in government, in wealth, in honour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100690">Brought thee to what thou art, throw'st all from me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100700">Then what thou shouldst be I expect from thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100710">Now to thy charge, thy government, thy cares,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100720">Thy mother in her age submits her years. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100730">And though (To my abundant grief I speak it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100740">Which now o'erflows my joy) some sons I have</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100750">Thankless, unkind, and disobedient,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100760">Rewarding all my bounties with neglect,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100770">And will of purpose wilfully retire</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100780">Themselves, from doing grace and service to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100790">When they have got all they can, or hope for, from me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100800">The thankfulness in which thy life doth move,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100810"><pb facs="5"/> did ever promise fairer fruits of love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100820">And now they show themselves, yet they have all</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100830">My blessing with them, so the world shall see</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100840">'Tis their unkindness, no defect in me;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100850">But go thou forward (My thrice honoured son)</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100860">In ways of goodness, glory is best won</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100870">When merit brings it home, disdain all titles</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100880">Purchased with coin, of honour take thou hold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100890">By thy desert let others buy't with gold;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100900">Fix thy most serious thought upon the weight</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100910">Thou goest to undergo, 'tis the just government</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100920">Of this famed city, (Me) whom nations call</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100930">Their brightest eye, then with great care and fear</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100940">Ought I to be o'erseen to be kept clear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100950">Spots in deformed faces are scarce noted,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100960">Fair cheeks are stained if ne'er so little blotted. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100970">Seest thou this key of gold? it shows thy charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100980">This place is the King's chamber, all pollution,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e100990">Sin and uncleanness must be locked out here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101000">And be kept sweet, with sanctity, faith and fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101010">I see grace take effect, heaven's joy upon her,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101020">'Tis rare, when virtue opens the gate to honour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101030">My blessing be upon thee, son, and lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101040">And on my sons all, that obey my word. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e101050">Then making her honour, as before, the waits of the city there in service, his lordship and the worthy company, are led forward towards the water side, where you shall find the river decked in the richest glory to receive him; upon whose crystal bosom stands five islands artfully garnished with all manner of Indian fruit-trees, drugs, spiceries; and the like, the middle island with a fair castle especially beautified.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e101060"><pb facs="6"/>But making haste to return to the city again, where triumph waits in more splendour and magnificence, the first then that attends to receive his lordship off the water at Bainard's castle, is truth's angel on horseback, his raiment of white silk powdered with stars of gold: on his head a crown of gold, a trumpeter before him on horseback, and zeal the champion of truth, in a garment of flame-coloured silk, with a bright hair on his head, from which shoot fire-beams, following close after him, mounted alike, his right hand holding a flaming scourge, intimating thereby that as he is the manifester of truth, he is likewise the chastiser of ignorance and error. </p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e101070" who="A07518-angel">
          <speaker>The salutation of the angel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101080">I have within mine eye my blessed charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101090">Hail friend of truth, safety and jay attends thee;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101100">I am truth's angel, by my mistress sent</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101110">To guard and guide thee, when thou tookest thy oath</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101120">I stood on thy right hand, though to thy eye</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101130">In visible form I did not then appear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101140">Ask but thy soul 'twill tell thee I stood near;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101150">And 'twas a time to take care of thee then</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101160">At such a marriage before heaven and men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101170">(Thy faith being wed to honour) close behind thee</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101180">Stood errors minister, that still sought to blind thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101190">And wrap his subtle mists about thy oath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101200">To hide it from the nakedness of troth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101210">Which is truth's purest glory, but my light</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101220">Still as it shone, expelled her blackest spite;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101230">His mists fled by, yet all I could devise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101240">Could hardly keep them from some people's eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101250">But thine they flew from, thy care's but begun</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101260"><pb facs="6"/> wake on, the victory is not half yet won,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101270">Thou wilt be still assaulted, thou shalt meet</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101280">With many dangers, that in voice seem sweet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101290">And ways most pleasant to a worldling's eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101300">My mistress has but one, but that leads high</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101310">To yon triumphant city follow me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101320">Keep thou to truth, eternity keeps to thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e101330" who="A07518-zeal">
          <speaker>Zeale.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101340">On boldly man of honour, thou shalt win,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101350">I am truth's champion, zeal, the scourge of sin. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e101360">The trumpet then sounding, the angel and zeal rank themselves just before his lordship, and conduct him to paul's-chain, where in the south-yard error in a chariot with his infernal ministers attends to assault him, his garment of ash-colour silk, his head rolled in a cloud, over which stands, an owl, a mole on one shoulder, a bat on the other, all symbols of blind ignorance and darkness, mists hanging at his eyes: close before him rides envy his champion, eating of a humane heart, mounted on a rhinoceros, attired in red silk, suitable to the bloodiness of her manners her left pap bore, where a snake fastens, her arms half naked, holding in her right hand a dart tincted in blood.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e101370" who="A07518-error">
          <speaker>The greeting of error.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101380">Art come? O welcome my triumphant lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101390">My glories sweetheart! how many millions</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101400">Of happy wishes hath my love told out</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101410">For this desired minute, I was dead</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101420">Till I enjoyed the presence, I saw nothing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101430">A blindness thicker than idolatry,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101440">Cleave to my eyeballs, now I am all of light,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101450">Of fire, of joy, Pleasure runs nimbly through me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101460"><pb facs="7"/> let's join together both in state and triumph,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101470">And down with beggarly and friendless virtue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101480">That hath so long impoverished this fair city,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101490">My beasts shall trample on her naked breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101500">Under my chariot-wheels her bones lie pressed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101510">She ne'er shall rise again, great power this day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101520">Is given into thy hand, make use on't lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101530">And let thy will and appetite sway the sword,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101540">Down with them all now, whom thy heart envies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101550">Let not thy conscience come into thine eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101560">This twelvemonth, if thou lovest revenge or gain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101570">I'll teach thee to cast mists, to blind the plain</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101580">And simple eye of man, he shall not know't,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101590">Nor see thy wrath when 'tis upon his throat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101600">All shall be carried with such art and wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101610">That what thy lust acts, shall be counted fit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101620">Then for attendants that may best observe thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101630">I'll pick out sergeants of my band to serve thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101640">Here's gluttony and sloth, two precious slaves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101650">Will tell thee more than a whole heard of knaves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101660">The worth of every office to a hair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101670">And who bids most, and bow the markets are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101680">Let them alone to smell, and for a need,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101690">They'll bring thee in bribes for measure and light bread,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101700">Keep thy eye winking, and thy hand wide ope,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101710">Than thou shalt know what wealth is, and the scope</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101720">Of rich authority, ho 'tis sweet and dear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101730">Make use of time then, thou'st but one poor year,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101740">And that will quickly slide, then be not nice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101750">Both power and profit cleaves to my advice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101760">And what's he locks his ear from those sweet charms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101770">Or runs not to meet gain with wide-stretched arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101780">There is a poor thin threadbare thing, called truth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101790"><pb facs="7"/> I give thee warning of her, if she speak</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101800">Stop both thine ears close, most professions break</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101810">That ever dealt with her, an unlucky thing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101820">She's almost sworn to nothing, I can bring</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101830">A thousand of our parish, besides queans,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101840">That ne'er knew what truth meant, nor ever means. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101850">Some I could cull out here, e'en in this throng,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101860">If I would show my children, and how strong</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101870">I were in faction; alas poor simple stray,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101880">She's all her life time finding out one way:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101890">She 'as but one foolish way, straight on, right forward,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101900">And yet she makes a toil on't, and goes on</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101910">With care and fear forsooth, when I can run</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101920">Over a hundred with delight and pleasure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101930">Backways, and byways, and fetch in my treasure</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101940">After the wishes of my heart, by shifts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101950">Deceits, and slights, and I'll give thee those gifts;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101960">I'll show thee all my corners yet untold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101970">The very nooks where beldames hide their gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101980">In hollow walls and chimneys, where the sun</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e101990">Never yet shone, nor truth came ever near,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102000">This of thy life I'll make the golden year: follow me then. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102010">Envy. Learn now to scorn thy inferiors, those must love thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102020">And wish to eat their hearts, that sit above thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e102030">Zeal stirred up with divine indignation, at the impudence of these hellhounds, both forces their retirement, and makes way for the chariot wherein truth his mistress sits, in a close garment of white satin, which makes her appear thin and naked, figuring thereby her simplicity and nearness of heart to those that embrace her; a robe of white silk cast over it, filled with the eyes of eagles, showing her deep<pb facs="8"/> insight, and height of wisdom, over her thrice sanctified head a milk-white dove, and on each shoulder one, the sacred emblems of purity, meekness, and innocency, under her feet, serpents, in that she treads down all subtlety and fraud, her forehead impaled with a diadem of stars, the witness of her eternal descent; on her breast a pure round crystal, showing the brightness of her thoughts and actions; a sun in her right-hand, than which, nothing is truer, a fan filled all with stars in her left, with which she parts darkness, and strikes away the vapours of ignorance; if you harken to zeal her champion after his holy anger is passed against error, and his crew, he will give it you in better terms, or at least more smoothly and pleasingly.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e102040" who="A07518-zeal">
          <speaker>The speech of zeal.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102050">Bold furies, back, or with this scourge of fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102060">Whence sparkles out religious chaste-desire</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102070">I'll whip you down to darkness; this a place</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102080">Worthy my mistress, her eternal grace</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102090">Be the full object to feast all these eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102100">But thine the first, he that feeds here is wise;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102110">Nor by the naked plainness of her weeds</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102120">Judge thou her worth, no burnished gloss truth needs;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102130">That crown of stars shows her descent from heaven;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102140">That robe of white filled all with eagles eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102150">Her piercing sight through hidden mysteries;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102160">Those milk-white doves her spotless innocence;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102170">Those serpents at her feet her victory shows</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102180">Over deceit and guile, her rankest foes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102190">And by that crystal mirror at her breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102200">The clearness of her conscience is expressed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102210"><pb facs="8"/> and showing that her deeds all darkness shun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102220">Her right-hand holds truth's symbol, the bright sun;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102230">A fan of stars she in the other twists,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102240">With which she chaseth away errors mists:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102250">And now she makes to thee, her so even grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102260">For to her rich and poor look with one face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e102270" who="A07518-truth">
          <speaker>The words of truth.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102280">Man raised by faith and love, upon whose head</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102290">Honour sits fresh, let not thy heart be led</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102300">In ignorant ways of insolence and pride</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102310">From her, that to this day hath been thy guide;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102320">I never showed thee yet more paths than one,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102330">And thou hast found sufficient that alone</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102340">To bring thee hither, then go forward still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102350">And having most power, first subject thy will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102360">Give the first fruits of justice to thyself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102370">Then dost thou wisely govern, though that elf</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102380">Of sin and darkness still opposing me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102390">Counsels thy appetite to master thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102400">But call to mind what brought thee to this day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102410">Was falsehood, cruelty, or revenge the way? </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102420">Thy lust or pleasures? people's curse or hate? </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102430">These were no ways could raise thee to this state</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102440">The ignorant must acknowledge, if then from me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102450">Which no ill dare deny, or sin control,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102460">Forsake me not, that can advance thy soul:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102470">I see a blessed yielding in thy eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102480">Thou'rt mine, lead on, thy name shall never die. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e102490">These words ended, they all set forward, this chariot of truth and her celestial handmaids the graces and virtues, taking place next before his lord ship, zeal and the angel before that, the chariot of error following<pb facs="9"/> as near as it can get, all passing on, till they come into Paul's churchyard, where stand ready the five lands, those dumb glories that I spoke of before upon the water, upon the height of these five lands sit five persons representing the five senses, Visus, Auditus, Tactus, Gustus, Olfactus, (Or) seeing, hearing, touching, tasting, smelling; at their feet their proper emblems, Aquila, ceruus, araneus, simia, canis, an eagle, a heart, a spider, an ape, a dog. </p>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e102500">No sooner can your eyes take leave of these, but they may suddenly espy a strange ship making towards, and that which may raise greater astonishment, it having neither sailor nor pilot, only upon a white silk streamer these two words set in letters of gold, veritate governor, I am steered by truth; the persons that are contained within this little vessel are only four; a King of the Moors, his Queen, and two attendants of their own colour, the rest of their followers, people the castle that stands in the middle island, of which company two or three on the top appears to sight, this King seeming much astonished at the many eyes of such a multitude, utters his thoughts in these words.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e102510" who="A07518-king">
          <speaker>The speech of that King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102520">I see amazement set upon the faces</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102530">Of these white people, wondrings, and strange gazes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102540">Is it at me? does my complexion draw</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102550">So many Christian eyes, that never saw</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102560">A King so black before? no, now I see</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102570">Their entire object, they're all meant to thee</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102580">(Grave city governor) my Queen and I</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102590"><pb facs="9"/> well honoured with the glances that by,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102600">I must confess many wild thoughts may rise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102610">Opinions, common murmurs, and fixed eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102620">At my so strange arrival, in a land</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102630">Where true religion and her temple stand:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102640">I being a Moor, ethen in opinions lightness</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102650">As far from sanctity as my face from whiteness;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102660">But I forgive the judgins of th'unwise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102670">Whose censures ever quicken in their eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102680">Only begotten of outward form and show,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102690">And I think meet to let such censurers know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102700">However darkness dwells upon my face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102710">Truth in my soul sets up the light of grace;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102720">And though in days of error I did run</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102730">To give all adoration to the sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102740">The moon and stars; nay creatures base and poor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102750">Now only their creator I adore:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102760">My Queen and people all, at one time won,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102770">By the religious conversation</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102780">Of English merchants, factors, travellers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102790">Whose truth did with our spirits hold commerce</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102800">As their affairs with us, following their path</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102810">We all were brought to the true Christian faith:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102820">Such benefit in good example dwells,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102830">It oft hath power to convert infidels;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102840">Nor could our desire's rest, till we were led</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102850">Unto this place, where those good spirits were bred;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102860">And see how we arrived, in blessed time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102870">To do that mistress service, in the prime</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102880">Of these her spotless triumphs, and t'attend</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102890">That honourable man, her late sworn friend. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102900">If any wonder at the safe arrive</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102910">Of this small vessel, which all weathers drive</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102920"><pb facs="10"/> according to their rages, where appears</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102930">Nor mariner nor pilot (Armed 'gainst fears)</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102940">Know this came hither from man's guidance free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102950">Only by truth steered; as our souls must be;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102960">And see where one of her fair temples stands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102970">Do reverence, Moors, bow low, and kiss your hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e102980">Behold our Queen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e102990" who="A07518-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103000">Her goodnesses are such</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103010">We cannot honour her, and her house too much. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e103020">All in the ship and those in the castle bowing their bodies to the temple of saint Paul, but error smiling betwixt scorn and anger to see such a devout humility take hold of that complexion, breaks into these,</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e103030" who="A07518-error">
          <speaker>Error.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103040">What, have my sweet-facest devils forsook me too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103050">Nay, than my charms will have enough to do? </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e103060">But time, sitting by the frame of truth his daughter's chariot, attired agreeable to his condition, with his hourglass, wings, and scythe, knowing best himself when it is fittest to speak, goes forward in this manner:</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e103070" who="A07518-missing">
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103080">This time hath brought t'effect, for on thy day</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103090">Nothing but truth and virtue shall display:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103100">Their virgin ensigns, infidelity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103110">Barbarism and guile shall in deep darkness lie. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103120">O I could ever stand still thus, and gaze,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103130">Never turn glass again; wish no more days</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103140">So this might ever last, pity the light</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103150">Of this rich glory must be cased in night;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103160">But time must on, I go, 'tis so decreed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103170">To bless my daughter truth, and all her seed</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103180">With joys immortal, triumphs never ending:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103190">And as her hand lifts me, to thy ascending</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103200"><pb facs="10"/> may it be always ready (Worthy son)</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103210">To hasten which, my hours shall quickly run,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103220">Seest thou you place,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A07518-e103230">saint Paul's cross.</note> thither I'll weekly bring thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103240">Where truths celestial harmony thou shalt hear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103250">To which I charge thee bend a serious ear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103260">Lead on, times swift attendants. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e103270">Then the five lands pass along into Cheapside, the ship next after them; the chariot of truth still before his lordship, and that of prror still chased before it, where their eyes meet with another more subtle object, planting itself close by the little conduit, which may bear this character, the true form and fashion of a mount triumphant, but the beauty and glory thereof overspread with a thick sulphurous darkness, it being a fog or mist raised from error, enviously to blemish that place which bears the title of London's triumphant mount (The chief grace and luster of the whole triumph) at the four corners sit four monsters errors disciples, on whom hangs part of the mist for their clothing, holding in their hands little thick clubs, coloured like their garments; the names of these four monsters, barbarism, ignorance, impudence, falsehood, who at the near approaching of truth's chariot, are seen a little to tremble, whilst her deity gives life to these words.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e103280" who="A07518-truth">
          <speaker>Truth.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103290">What's here? the mist of error? dare his spite</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103300">Stain this triumphant mount? where our delight</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103310">Hath been divinely fixed so many ages,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103320">Dare darkness now breathe forth her insolent rages,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103330">And hang in poisonous vapours o'er the place</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103340"><pb facs="11"/> from whence we received love and returned grace? </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103350">I see if truth a while but turn her eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103360">Thick are the mists that o'er fair cities rise:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103370">We did expect to receive welcome here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103380">From no deformed shapes but divine and clear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103390">In steed of monsters that this place attends;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103400">To meet with goodness and her glorious friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103410">Nor can they so forget me to be far,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103420">I know there stands no other envious bar:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103430">But that foul cloud to darken this bright day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103440">Which with this fan of stars I'll chase away. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103450">Vanish infectious fog that I may see</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103460">This city's grace, that takes her light from me. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e103470">At this her powerful command, the vanish, give way, cloud suddenly rises, and changes into a bright spreading canopy, stuck thick with stars, and beams of gold, shooting forth round about it, the mount appearing then most rich in beauty and glory, the four monsters falling flat at the foot of the hill; that grave feminine shape, figuring London, sitting in greatest honour; next above her in the most eminent place, sits religion, the model of a fair temple on her head, and a burning lamp in her hand, the proper emblems of her sanctity, watchfulness, and zeal; on her right hand sits liberality, her head circled with a wreathe of gold, in her hand a cornucopia, or horn of abundance, out of which rusheth a seeming flood of gold, but no way flowing to prodigality; for as the sea is governed by the moon, so is that wealthy river by her eye, (For bounty must be led by judgement) and hence is artfully derived the only difference between prodigality and bounty, the one deals her gifts with open eyes, the<pb facs="11"/> other blindfold; on her left side sits perfect love, his proper seat being nearest the heart, wearing upon his head a wreath of white and red roses mingled together, the ancient witness of peace, love and union, wherein consists the happiness of this land, his right hand holding a sphere, where in a circle of gold, is contained all the 12 companies arms; and therefore called the spear of true brotherhood, or annulus amoris, the ring of love: upon his left hand stand two billing turtles, expressing thereby the happy condition of mutual love and society: on either side of this mount are displayed the charitable and religious works of London (Especially the worthy company of grocers) in giving maintenance to scholars, soldiers, widows, orphans, and the like, where are placed one of each number: and on the two heights sit knowledge and modesty; knowledge wearing a crown of stars, in her hand a perspective glass, betokening both her high judgement, and deep insight, the brow of modesty circled with a wreath all of red roses, expressing her bashfulness and blushings, in her hand a crimson banner, filled with silver stars, figuring the white purity of her shamefastness, her cheeks not red with shame or guilt, but with virgin-fear, and honour. At the back of this triumphant mount, chastity, fame, simplicity, meekness, have their seats, chastity wearing on her head a garland of white roses, in her hand a white silk banner, filled with stars of gold, expressing the eternity of her unspotted pureness: fame next under her, on her a head a crown of silver, and a silver trumpet in her hand, showing both her brightness and shrillness: simplicity with a milk-white dove upon her head, and<pb facs="12"/> meekness with a garland of mingled flowers, in her hand a white silk banner with a red cross, a lamb at her feet, by which both their conditions are sufficiently expressed; the mount thus made glorious by the power of truth, and the mist expelled, London thus speaks.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e103480" who="A07518-london">
          <speaker>London.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103490">Thick scales of darkness in a moment's space</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103500">Are fell from both mine eyes, I see the face</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103510">Of all my friends about me (Now) most clearly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103520">Religions sisters, whom I honour dear;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103530">O I behold the work, it comes from thee</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103540">Illustrious patroness, thou that madest me see</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103550">In days of blindest ignorance, when this light</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103560">Was e'en extinguished, thou redeemest my sight;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103570">Then to thy charge (With reverence) I commend</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103580">That worthy son of mine, thy virtuous friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103590">Whom on my love and blessing I require,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103600">To observe thee faithfully, and his desire</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103610">To imitate thy will, and there lie bounded,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103620">For power's a dangerous sea, which must be sounded</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103630">With truth and justice, or man soon runs on</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103640">'Gainst rocks and shelves to dissolution;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103650">Then that thou mayst the difference ever know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103660">Twixt truth and error, a few words shall show;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103670">The many ways that to blind error slide</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103680">Are in the entrance broad, hell-mouth is wide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103690">But when man enters far, he finds it then</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103700">Close, dark and straight, for hell returns no men;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103710">But the one sacred way which truth directs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103720">Only at entrance man's affection cheques,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103730">And is there strict alone, to which place throngs</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103740">All world's afflictions, calumnies and wrongs. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103750"><pb facs="12"/>But having passed those, than thou findest a way</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103760">In breadth, whole heaven, in length, eternal day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103770">Then following truth, she brings thee to that way;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103780">But first observe what works she here requires,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103790">Religion, knowledge, sanctity, chaste desires,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103800">Then charity, which bounty must express,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103810">To scholars, soldiers, widows, fatherless;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103820">These have been still my works, they must be thine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103830">Honour and action must together shine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103840">Or the best part's eclipsed, behold but this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103850">Thy very crest shows bounty, here 'tis put,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103860">Thou givest the open hand, keep it not shut;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103870">But to the needy, or deserving spirit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103880">Let it spread wide, and heaven enrolls that merit;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103890">Do these, and prove my hopeful worthy son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103900">Yet nothing's spoken, but needfully must be done. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103910">And so lead forward. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e103920">At which words the whole triumph moves in his richest glory towards the cross in cheap, at which place error full of wrath and malice to see his mist so chased away, falls into this fury.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e103930" who="A07518-error">
          <speaker>Error.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103940">Heart of all the fiends in hell! </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103950">Could her beggarly power expel</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103960">Such a thick and poisonous mist</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103970">Which set envy's snakes to twist;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103980">Up monsters, was her feeble frown</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e103990">Of force to strike my officers down? </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104000">Barbarism, impudence, lies, ignorance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104010">All your hellbred heads advance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104020">And once again with rotten darkness shroud</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104030">This mount triumphant, drop down sulphurous cloud. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e104040"><pb facs="13"/>At which the mist falls again, and hangs over all the beauty of the mount, not a person of glory seen, only the four monsters gather courage again, and take their seats, advancing their clubs above their heads, which no sooner perceived, but truth in her chariot making near to the place, willing still to rescue her friends and servants, from the powers of ignorance and darkness, makes use of these words,</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e104050" who="A07518-truth">
          <speaker>Truth.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104060">Dare yet the works of ugliness appear</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104070">'Gainst this day's brightness, and see us so near? </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104080">How bold is sin and hell, that yet it dare</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104090">Rise against us? but know (Perditions heir)</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104100">'Tis idle to contend against our power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104110">Vanish again foul mist from honour's bower. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e104120">Then the cloud dispersing itself again, and all the mount appearing glorious, it passeth so on to the standard, about which place, by elaborate action from error it falls again, and goes so darkened, till it comes to s. Laurence lane end, where by the former words by truth uttered, being again chased away, London thus gratefully requites her goodness.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e104130" who="A07518-london">
          <speaker>London.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104140">Eternity's bright sister, by whose light,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104150">Errors infectious works still fly my sight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104160">Receive thy servants thanks; now perfect love</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104170">Whose right hand holds a sphere, wherein do move</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104180">Twelve blessed societies, whose beloved increase,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104190">Styles it the ring of brotherhood, faith and peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104200">From thy harmonious lips let them all taste,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104210">The golden counsel that makes health long last. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e104220">Perfect love then standing up, holding in his right<pb facs="13"/> hand a sphere, on the other, two billing turtles, gives these words.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e104230" who="A07518-perfect_love">
          <speaker>Perfect love.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104240">First then I banish from this feast of joy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104250">All excess, epicurism, both which destroy</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104260">The healths of soul and body, no such guest</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104270">Ought to be welcome to this reverend feast</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104280">Where truth is mistress, who's admitted here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104290">Must come for virtue's love more than for cheer,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104300">These two white turtles may example give</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104310">How perfect joy and brotherhood should live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104320">And they from whom grave order is expected,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104330">Of rude excess must never be detected;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104340">This is the council which that lady calls</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104350">Golden advice, for by it no man falls</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104360">He that desires days healthful, sound and blessed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104370">Let moderate judgement serve him at his feast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104380">And so lead on, may perfect brotherhood shine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104390">Still in sphere, and honour still in thine. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e104400">This speech so ended, his lordship and the companies pass on to Guildhall; and at their returning back, these triumphs attend to bring his lordship towards saint Paul's church, there to perform those yearly ceremonial rites, which ancient and grave order hath determined, error by the way still busy and in action to draw darkness often upon that mount of triumph, which by truth is as often dispersed: than all returning homewards full of beauty and brightness, this mount and the chariot of truth, both placed near to the entrance of his lordship's gate, near leaden-hall; London, the lady of that mount; first gives utterance to these words,</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e104410" who="A07518-london">
          <pb facs="14"/>
          <speaker>London.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104420">Before the day sprang from the morning's womb</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104430">I rose, my care was earlier than the light,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104440">Nor would it rest till I now brought thee home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104450">Marrying to one joy both thy day and night;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104460">Nor can we call this night, if our eyes count</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104470">The glorious beams that dance about this mount,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104480">Sure did not custom guide 'em, men would say</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104490">Two noon were seen together in one day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104500">The splendour is so piercing, triumph seems</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104510">As if it sparkled, and to men's esteems</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104520">Threw forth his thanks, wrapped up in golden flames,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104530">As if he would give light to read their names</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104540">That were at cost this day to make him shine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104550">And be as free in thanks, as they in coin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104560">But see time checks me, and his scythe stands ready</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104570">To cut all off, no state on earth is steady,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104580">Therefore grave son the time that is to come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104590">Bestow on truth, and so thour't welcome home. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e104600">Time standing up in truth's chariot, seeming to make an offer with his scythe to cut off the glories of the day, growing near now to the season of rest and sleep, his daughter truth thus meekly stays his hand.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e104610" who="A07518-truth">
          <speaker>Truth.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104620">Father desist a while till I send forth</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104630">A few words to our friend, that man of worth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104640">The power that heaven, love, and the city's choice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104650">Have all conferred on thee with mutual voice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104660">As it is great, reverend, and honourable,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104670">Meet it with equal goodness, strive t'excel</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104680">Thy former self, as thy command exceeds</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104690">Thy last-years state, so let new acts, old deeds;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104700"><pb facs="14"/> and as great men in riches and in birth</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104710">(Heightening their bloods, and joining earth to earth,)</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104720">Bestow their best hours and most serious cares</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104730">In choosing out fit matches for their heirs:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104740">So never give thou over day or hour</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104750">Till with a virtue thou hast matched this power:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104760">For what is greatness if not joined with grace? </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104770">Like one of high-blood that hath married base. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104780">Who seeks authority with an ignorant eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104790">Is like a man seeks out his enemy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104800">For where before his follies were not spread</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104810">Or his corruptions, than their clearly read</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104820">E'en by the eyes of all men; 'tis so pure</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104830">A crystal of itself, it will endure</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104840">No poison of oppression, bribes, hired law,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104850">But 'twill appear soon in some crack or flaw,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104860">Howe'er men soothe their hopes with popular breath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104870">If not in life, she'll find that crack in death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104880">I was not made to fawn or stroke fin smooth</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104890">Be wise and hear me then that cannot soothe:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104900">I have set thee high now, be so in example,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104910">Made thee a pinnacle in honour's temple,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104920">Fixing ten thousand eyes upon thy brow</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104930">There is no hiding of thy actions now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104940">They must abide the light, and imitate me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104950">Or be thrown down to fire where errors be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104960">Nor only with these words thy ear I feed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104970">But give those part that shall in time succeed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104980">To thee in present, and to them to come</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e104990">That truth may bring you all with honour home</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105000">To these your gates, and to those, after these</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105010">Of which your own good actions keep the keys;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105020">Then as the loves of thy society</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105030"><pb facs="15"/> hath flowed in bounties on this day and thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105040">Counting all cost too little for true art,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105050">Doubling rewards there where they found desert,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105060">In thankfulness, justice, and virtuous care</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105070">Perfect their hopes, those thy requitals are;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105080">With fatherly respect embrace 'em all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105090">Faith in thy heart, and plenty in thy hall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105100">Love in thy walks, but justice in thy state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105110">Zeal in thy chamber, bounty at thy gate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105120">And so to thee and these a blessed night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105130">To thee fair city, peace, my grace and light. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A07518-e105140">Trumpets sounding triumphantly,</stage>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e105150">Zeal, the champion of truth on horseback, his head circled with strange fires, appears to his mistress, and thus speaks:</p>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e105160" who="A07518-missing">
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105170">See yonder, lady, errors chariot stands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105180">Braving the power of your incenst commands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105190">Emboldened by the privilege of night</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105200">And her black faction, yet to crown his spite</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105210">Which I'll confound, I burn in divine wrath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e105220" who="A07518-truth">
          <speaker>Truth.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105230">Strike then, I give thee leave to shoot it forth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A07518-e105240" who="A07518-zeal">
          <speaker>Zeal.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105250">Then here's to the destruction of that seat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07518-e105260">There's nothing seen of thee but fire shall eat. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e105270">At which, a flame shoots from the head of zeal, which fastening upon that Chariot of error sets it on fire, and all the beasts that are joined to it.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e105280">The firework being made by master Humphrey Nichols, a man excellent in his art: and the<pb facs="15"/> whole work and body of the triumph, with all the proper beauties of the workmanship most artfully and faithfully performed by John Grinkin: and those furnished with apparel and porters by Anthony Monday, gentleman.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e105290">This proud seat of error lying now only glowing in embers, (Being a figure or type of his lordship's justice on all wicked offenders in the time of his government,) I now conclude, holding it a more learned discretion to cease of myself, than to have time cut me off rudely, and now let him strike at his pleasure.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A07518-e105300">
      <div type="illustration" xml:id="A07518-e105310">
        <p xml:id="A07518-e105320">
          <figure xml:id="A07518-e105330">
            <head>Tam Robur · tam robor. In-colis arbor jovis. 1610. ❀</head>
            <p xml:id="A07518-e105340">No</p>
            <p xml:id="A07518-e105350">♃</p>
            <figDesc xml:id="A07518-e105360">printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="song" xml:id="A07518-e105370">
        <pb facs="16"/>
        <head>The song with the note.</head>
        <p xml:id="A07518-e105380"><gap reason="music" xml:id="A07518-e105390" n="16-a-0070"/>mother of many honourable sons, think not<gap reason="music" xml:id="A07518-e105400" n="16-a-0160"/> thy glass too slowly runs, that in time's hand is<gap reason="music" xml:id="A07518-e105410" n="16-a-0280"/> set, because thy worthy son appears not yet,<gap reason="music" xml:id="A07518-e105420" n="16-a-0390"/> lady be pleased the hour grows on, thy joys will be<gap reason="music" xml:id="A07518-e105430" n="16-a-0520"/> complete anon, thou shalt behold, the man enroll,<gap reason="music" xml:id="A07518-e105440" n="16-a-0640"/> in honors-book whom virtue raises, love circled,<pb facs="16"/><gap reason="music" xml:id="A07518-e105450" n="16-b-0010"/> round, his triumphs crowned, withal good wishes,<gap reason="music" xml:id="A07518-e105460" n="16-b-0120"/> prayers and praises.</p>
        <l xml:id="A07518-e105470">What greater comfort to a mother's heart,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07518-e105480">Then to behold her son's desert:</l>
        <l xml:id="A07518-e105490">Go hand in hand with love,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07518-e105500">Respect and honour (Blessings from above)</l>
        <l xml:id="A07518-e105510">It is of power all griefs to kill,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07518-e105520">And with a flood of joy to fill. </l>
        <l xml:id="A07518-e105530">Thy aged eyes,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07518-e105540">To see him rise,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07518-e105550">With glory decked, where expectation. </l>
        <l xml:id="A07518-e105560">Grace, truth, and fame,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07518-e105570">Met in his name,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07518-e105580">Attends his honour's confirmation. </l>
        <div n="bassus" type="part" xml:id="A07518-e105590">
          <head>Bassus.</head>
          <p xml:id="A07518-e105600">
            <gap reason="music" xml:id="A07518-e105610" n="16-b-1000"/>
          </p>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A07518-e105620">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A07518"><item xml:id="A07518-truth" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A07518-truth</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07518-london" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A07518-london</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07518-zeal" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A07518-zeal</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07518-error" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A07518-error</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07518-missing" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A07518-missing</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A07518-perfect_love" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07518-perfect_love</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07518-queen" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07518-queen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07518-angel" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07518-angel</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07518-king" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07518-king</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

