<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The  Tragedy of Charles Duke of Byron <date type="creation_date">1608</date></title>
        <author>Chapman, George</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nayoon Ahn</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A18404_02.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The conspiracie, and tragedie of Charles Duke of Byron, Marshall of France. Acted lately in two playes, at the Black-Friers. Writted by George Chapman.</title>
            <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>67 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99843385</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 4968.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 274-5(a).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">8115</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18404</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The conspiracie, and tragedie of Charles Duke of Byron, Marshall of France. Acted lately in two playes, at the Black-Friers. Writted by George Chapman.</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedie of Charles Duke of Byron.</title>
            <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[132] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by G. Eld for Thomas Thorppe, and are to be sold [by Laurence Lisle] at the Tygers head in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
            <date>1608.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The first word of the title is xylographic.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Bookseller's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: [A]2 B-R4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>"The tragedie of Charles Duke of Byron" has separate divisional title; register is continuous.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Biron, Charles de Gontaut, -- duc de, -- 1562-1602 -- Drama.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A18404_02-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A18404_02-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A18404_02-e100030">
        <pb facs="33"/>
        <p xml:id="A18404_02-e100040">The tragedy of Charles Duke of Byron.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18404_02-e100050">By George Chapman.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A18404_02-e100060">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A18404_02-e100070">
        <pb facs="34"/>
        <pb facs="34"/>
        <head>The tragedy of Charles Duke of Byron. </head>
        <div n="1" type="act_and_scene" xml:id="A18404_02-e100080">
          <head>Actus, i. Scaena, i.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e100090">Henry, Vidame, D'escures, Espernon, Janin.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e100100" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100110">Byron fallen in so traitorous a relapse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100120">Alleged for our ingratitude: what offices,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100130">Titles of honour, and what admiration,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100140">Could France afford him that it poured not on? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100150">When he was scarce arrived at forty years,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100160">He ran through all chief dignities of France. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100170">At fourteen years of age he was made colonel</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100180">To all the Suisses serving then in Flanders;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100190">Soon after he was marshal of the camp. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100200">And shortly after, marshal general:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100210">He was received high admiral of France</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100220">In that our parliament we held at Tours;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100230">Marshal of France in that we held at Paris. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100240">And at the siege of Amiens he acknowledged,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100250">None his superior but ourself, the King;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100260">Though I had there, the princes of the blood</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100270">I made him my lieutenant general,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100280">Declared him jointly the prime peer of France,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100290">And raised his barony into a duchy,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e100300" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Iani.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100310">And yet (My lord) all this could not allay</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100320">The fatal thirst of his ambition. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100330">For some have heard him say he would not die,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100340">Till on the wings of valour he had reached</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100350">One degree higher; and had seen his head ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100360">Set on the royal quarter of a crown;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100370">Yea at so unbelieved a pitch he aimed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100380">That he hath said his heart would still complain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100390">Till he aspired the style of sovereign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100400"><pb facs="35"/> and from what ground my lord rise all the levies</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100410">Now made in Italy? from whence should spring</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100420">The warlike humour of the count Fuentes? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100430">The restless stirrings of the Duke of Savoy? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100440">The discontent the Spaniard entertained,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100450">With such a threatening fury, when he heard</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100460">The prejudicial conditions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100470">Proposed him, in the treaty held at Vervins? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100480">And many other beaveries, this way aiming,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100490">But from some hope of inward aid from hence? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100500">And that, all this directly aims at you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100510">Your highness hath by one intelligence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100520">Good cause to think; which is your late advice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100530">That the sea army, now prepared at Naples,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100540">Hath an intended enterprise on Provence? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100550">Although the cunning Spaniard gives it out,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100560">That all is for Algier. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e100570" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100580">I must believe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100590">That without treason bred in our own breasts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100600">Spain's, affairs are not in so good estate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100610">To aim at any action against France:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100620">And if Byron should be their instrument,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100630">His altered disposition could not grow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100640">So far wide in an instant; nor resign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100650">His valour to these lawless resolutions</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100660">Upon the sudden; nor without some charms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100670">Of foreign hopes and flatteries sung to him:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100680">But far it flies my thoughts, that such a spirit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100690">So active, valiant, and vigilant;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100700">Can see itself transformed with such wild furies. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100710">And like a dream it shows to my conceits,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100720">That he who by himself hath won such honour:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100730">And he to whom his father left so much,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100740">He that still daily reaps so much from me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100750">And knows he may increase it to more proof</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100760">From me, than any other foreign King;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100770">Should quite against the stream of all religion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100780">Honour, and reason, take a course so foul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100790"><pb facs="35"/> and neither keep his oath, nor save his soul. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100800">Can the poor keeping of a citadel</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100810">Which I denied, to be at his disposure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100820">Make him forgo the whole strength of his honours? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100830">It is impossible, though the violence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100840">Of his hot spirit made him make attempt</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100850">Upon our person for denying him;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100860">Yet well I found his loyal judgement served,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100870">To keep it from effect: besides being offered,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100880">Two hundred thousand crowns in yearly pension,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100890">And to be general of all the forces</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100900">The Spaniards had in France; they found him still,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100910">As an unmatched Achilles in the wars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100920">So a most wise Ulysses to their words,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100930">Stopping his ears at their enchanted sounds;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100940">And plain he told them that although his blood</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100950">(Being moved) by nature, were a very fire</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100960">And boiled in apprehension of a wrong;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100970">Yet should his mind hold such a sceptre there,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100980">As would contain it from all act and thought</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e100990">Of treachery or ingratitude to his prince. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101000">Yet do I long, methinks , to see la fin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101010">Who hath his heart in keeping; since his state,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101020">(Grown to decay and he to discontent)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101030">Comes near the ambitious plight of Duke Byron,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101040">My lord Vidame, when does your lordship think,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101050">Your uncle of la fin will be arrived. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e101060" who="A18404_02-vidame">
            <speaker>Vid.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101070">I think (My lord) he now is near arriving</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101080">For his particular journey and devotion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101090">Vowed to the holy lady of Loretto,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101100">Was long since past and he upon return. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e101110" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101120">In him, as in a crystal that is charmed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101130">I shall discern by whom and what designs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101140">My rule is threatened and that sacred power</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101150">That hath enabled this defensive arm,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101160">(When I enjoyed but in an unequal nook,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101170">Of that I now possess) to front a King</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101180">Far my superior: and from twelve set battles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101190"><pb facs="36"/> march home a victor: ten of them obtained,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101200">Without my personal service; will not see</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101210">A traitorous subject foil me, and so end</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101220">What his hand hath with such success begun. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e101230">Enter a lady, and a nurse bringing the daulphine.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e101240" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101250">See the young dauphin brought to cheer your highness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e101260" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101270">My royal blessing, and the King of heaven,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101280">Make thee an aged, and a happy King:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101290">Help nurse to put my sword into his hand;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101300">Hold boy, by this; and with it may thy arm</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101310">Cut from thy tree of rule, all traitorous branches,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101320">That strive to shadow and eclipse thy glories;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101330">Have thy old father's angel for thy guide,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101340">Redoubled be his spirit in thy breast;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101350">Who when this state ran like a turbulent sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101360">In civil hates and bloody enmity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101370">Their wraths and envies, like so many winds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101380">Settled and burst: and like the halcyon's birth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101390">Be thine to bring a calm upon the shore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101400">In which the eyes of war may ever sleep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101410">As overmatched with former massacres,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101420">When guilty, made noblesse, feed on noblesse;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101430">All the sweet plenty of the realm exhausted;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101440">When the naked merchant, was pursued for spoil,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101450">When the poor peasants frighted neediest thieves</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101460">With their pale leanness; nothing left on them</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101470">But meager carcases sustained with air,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101480">Wand'ring like ghosts affrighted from their graves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101490">When with the often and incessant sounds</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101500">The very beasts knew the alarum bell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101510">And (Hearing it) ran bellowing to their home:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101520">From which unchristian broils and homicides,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101530">Let the religious sword of justice free</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101540">Thee and thy kingdoms governed after me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101550">O heaven! or if th'unsettled blood of France,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101560">With ease, and wealth, renew he civil furies:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101570"><pb facs="36"/> let all my powers be emptied in my son</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101580">To curb, and end them all, as I have done. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101590">Let him by virtue, quite out of from fortune,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101600">Her feathered shoulders, and her winged shoes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101610">And thrust from her light feet, her turning stone ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101620">That she may ever tarry by his throne. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101630">And of his worth, let after ages say,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101640">(He fighting for the land; and bringing home</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101650">Just conquests, laden with his enemies spoils)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101660">His father passed all France in martial deeds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101670">But he, his father twenty times exceeds. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e101680">Enter the Duke of Byron, D'avuergne and Laffin.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e101690" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101700">My dear friends D'auvergne ▪ and Laffin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101710">We need no conjurations to conceal:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101720">Our close intendments, to advance our states</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101730">Even with our merits; which are now neclected;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101740">Since Britain is reduced, and breathless war</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101750">Hath sheathed his sword, and wrapped his ensigns up;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101760">The King hath now no more use of my valour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101770">And therefore I shall now no more enjoy</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101780">The credit that my service held with him;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101790">My service that hath driven through all extremes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101800">Through tempests, droughts, and through the deepest floods;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101810">Winter's of shot: and over rocks so high</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101820">That birds could scarce aspire their ridgy tops;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101830">The world is quite inverted: virtue thrown</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101840">At vice's feet: and sensual peace confounds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101850">Valour, and cowardice: fame, and infamy;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101860">The rude and terrible age is turned again:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101870">When the thick air hid heaven, and all the stars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101880">Were drowned in humour, tough, and hard to pierce,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101890">When the red sun held not his fixed place;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101900">Kept not his certain course, his rise and set</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101910"><pb facs="37"/> nor yet distinguished with his definite bounds;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101920">Nor in his firm conversions, were discerned</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101930">The fruitful distances of time and place,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101940">In the well varied seasons of the year;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101950">When th'incomposed incursions of floods</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101960">Wasted and eat the earth; and all things showed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101970">Wild and disordered: naught was worse than now;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101980">We must reform and have a new creation</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e101990">Of state and government; and on our chaos</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102000">Will I sit brooding up another world. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102010">I who through all the dangers that can siege</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102020">The life of man, have forced my glorious way</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102030">To the repairing of my country's ruins,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102040">Will ruin it again, to readvance it;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102050">Roman Camillus, saved the state of Rome</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102060">With far less merit, than Byron hath France;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102070">And how short of this is my recompense. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102080">The King shall know, I will have better price</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102090">Set on my services; in spite of whom</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102100">I will proclaim and ring my discontents</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102110">Into the farthest ear of all the world. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102120" who="A18404_02-laffin">
            <speaker>Laff:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102130">How great a spirit he breathes? how learned? how wise? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102140">But (Worthy prince) you must give temperate air,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102150">To your unmatched, and more than human wind;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102160">Else will our plots be frost-bit, in the flower. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102170" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>D'au:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102180">Betwixt ourselves we may give liberal vent</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102190">To all our fiery and displeased impressions;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102200">Which nature could not entertain with life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102210">Without some exhalation; a wronged thought</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102220">Will break a rib of steel. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102230" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102240">My princely friend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102250">Enough of these eruptions; our grave councillor</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102260">Well knows that great affairs will not be forged</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102270">But upon anvils that are lined with wool;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102280">We must ascend to our intentions top</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102290">Like clouds that be not seen till they be up? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102300" who="A18404_02-laffin">
            <speaker>Laff:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102310">O, you do too much ravish; and my soul</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102320">Offer to music in your numerous breath;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102330"><pb facs="37"/> sententious, and so high, it wakens death;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102340">It is for these parts, that the Spanish King</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102350">Hath sworn to win them to his side</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102360">At any price or peril; that great Savoy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102370">Offers his princely daughter, and a dowry,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102380">Amounting to five hundred thousand crowns;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102390">With full transport of all the sovereign rights</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102400">Belonging to the state of Burgundy;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102410">Which marriage will be made, the only cement</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102420">T'effect and strengthen all our secret treaties;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102430">Instruct me therefore, (My assured prince)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102440">Now I am going to resolve the King</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102450">Of his suspicions, how I shall behave me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102460" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102470">Go my most trusted friend, with happy feet:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102480">Make me a sound man with him; go to court</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102490">But with a little train; and be prepared</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102500">To hear, at first, terms of contempt and choler,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102510">Which you may easily calm, and turn to grace. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102520">If you beseech his highness to believe</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102530">That your whole drift and course for Italy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102540">(Where he hath heard you were) was only made</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102550">Out of your long-well-known devotion</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102560">To our right holy lady of Lorretto,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102570">As you have told some of your friends in court:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102580">And that in passing Mylan and Thurin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102590">They charged you to propound my marriage</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102600">With the third daughter of the Duke of Savoy;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102610">Which you have done, and I rejected it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102620">Resolved to build upon his royal care</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102630">For my bestowing, which he lately vowed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102640" who="A18404_02-laffin">
            <speaker>Laff.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102650">O, you direct, as if the god of light</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102660">Sat in each nook of you; and pointed out</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102670">The path of empire; charming all the dangers</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102680">On both sides armed, with his harmonious finger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102690" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102700">Besides let me entreat you to dismiss,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102710">All that have made the voyage with your lordship,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102720">But specially the curate: and to lock</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102730">Your papers in some place of doubtless safety;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102740"><pb facs="38"/> or sacrifice them to the god of fire;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102750">Considering worthily that in your hands</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102760">I put my fortunes, honour, and my life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102770" who="A18404_02-laffin">
            <speaker>Laff:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102780">Therein the bounty that your grace hath shown me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102790">I prize passed life, and all things that are mine;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102800">And will undoubtedly preserve, and tender</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102810">The merit of it, as my hope of heaven. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102820" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>By●:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102830">I make no question; farewell worthy friend. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e102840">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e102850">Henry, chancellor, Laffin, D'escures, Janin, Henry having many papers in his hand.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102860" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102870">Are these proofs of that purely Catholic zeal</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102880">That made him wish no other glorious title,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102890">Then to be called the scourge of Huguenots? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102900" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102910">No question sir he was of no religion;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102920">But (Upon false grounds, by some courtiers laid)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102930">Hath oft been heard to mock and jest at all. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102940" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102950">Are not his treasons heinous? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102960" who="A18404_02-all">
            <speaker>All:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102970">— Most abhorred;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e102980" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e102990">All is confirmed that you have heard before,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103000">And amplified with many horrors more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e103010" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103020">Good De'laffin; you were our golden plummet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103030">To sound this gulf of all ingratitude;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103040">In which you have with excellent desert</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103050">Of loyalty and policy, expressed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103060">Your name in action; and with such appearance</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103070">Have proved the parts of his ingrateful treasons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103080">That I must credit, more than I desired,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e103090" who="A18404_02-laffin">
            <speaker>Laff:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103100">I must confess my lord, my voyages</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103110">Made to the Duke of Savoy and to Milan;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103120">Were with endeavour, that the wars returned,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103130">Might breed some trouble to your majesty;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103140">And profit those by whom they were procured;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103150">But since, in their designs, your sacred person</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103160">Was not excepted (Which I since have seen)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103170">It so abhorred me, that I was resolved</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103180">To give you full intelligence thereof;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103190"><pb facs="38"/> and rather choosed to fail in promises,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103200">Made to the servant; then infringe my fealty</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103210">Sworn to my royal sovereign and master;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e103220" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103230">I am extremely discontent to see,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103240">This most unnatural conspiracy;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103250">And would not have the marshal of Byron,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103260">The first example or my forced justice;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103270">Nor that his death should be the worthy cause,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103280">That my calm reign, (Which hitherto hath held</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103290">A clear and cheerful sky above the heads</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103300">Of my dear subjects) should so suddenly</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103310">Be overcast with clouds of fire, and thunder;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103320">Yet on submission, I vow still his pardon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e103330" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Ian:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103340">And still our humble counsels, (For his service)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103350">Would so resolve you, if he will employ</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103360">His honoured valour as effectually,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103370">To fortify the state, against your foes;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103380">As he hath practised bad intendments with them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e103390" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103400">That vow shall stand; and we will now address,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103410">Some messengers to call him home to court;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103420">Without the slenderest intimation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103430">Of any ill we know; we will restrain</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103440">(Withal forgiveness, if he will confess)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103450">His headlong course to ruin; and his taste,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103460">From the sweet poison of his friendlike foes:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103470">Treason hath blistered heels, dishonest things</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103480">Have bitter rivers, though delicious springs;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103490">Descures haste you unto him, and inform,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103500">That having heard by sure intelligence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103510">Of the great levies made in Italy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103520">Of arms and soldiers; I am resolute,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103530">Upon my frontiers to maintain an army;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103540">The charge whereof I will impose on him;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103550">And to that end, expressly have commanded,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103560">De Vic, our lord ambassador in Suisse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103570">To demand levy of six thousand men:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103580">Appointing them to march where Duke Byron</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103590">Shall have directions; wherein I have followed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103600"><pb facs="39"/>The counsel of my constable his gossip;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103610">Whose lik't advice, I made him him know by letters,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103620">Wishing to hear his own; from his own mouth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103630">And by all means conjure, his speediest presence;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103640">Do this with utmost haste. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e103650" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>Desc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103660">I will my lord. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e103670">Exit Desc.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e103680" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103690">My good lord chancellor, of many pieces,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103700">More than is here, of his conspiracies</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103710">Presented to us, by our friend, Laffin;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103720">You, only, shall reserve these seven and twenty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103730">Which are not those that must conclude against him;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103740">But mention only him: since I am loath,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103750">To have the rest of the conspirators, known. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e103760" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103770">My lord, my purpose is to guard all these,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103780">So safely from the sight of any other:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103790">That in my doublet I will have them sowed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103800">Without discovering them to mine own eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103810">Till need, or opportunity requires. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e103820" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103830">You shall do well my lord, they are of weight;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103840">But I am doubtful; that his conscience</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103850">Will make him so suspicious of the worst,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103860">That he will hardly be induced to come. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e103870" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Jan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103880">I much should doubt that to, but that I hope</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103890">The strength of his conspiracy, as yet</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103900">Is not so ready, that he dare presume,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103910">By his refusal to make known so much</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103920">Of his disloyalty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e103930" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103940">I yet conceive;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103950">His practises are turned to no bad end,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103960">And good Laffin, I pray you wright to him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103970">To hasten his repair: and make him sure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103980">That you have satisfied me to the full. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e103990">For all his actions, and have uttered naught,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104000">But what might serve to banish bad impressions. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e104010" who="A18404_02-labrun">
            <speaker>Laf.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104020">I will not fail my lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e104030" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104040">Convey your letters;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104050">By some choice friend of his: or by his brother:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104060">And for a third excitement to his presence;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104070"><pb facs="39"/> Janin, yourself shall go, and with the power</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104080">That both the rest employ to make him come,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104090">Use you the strength of your persuasions. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e104100" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Jan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104110">I will my lord, and hope I shall present him. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e104120">Exit Jan.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e104130">Enter Esper. Soisson, Vitry, Pralin, etc.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e104140" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Espa.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104150">Will't please your majesty to take your place,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104160">The mask is coming. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e104170" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104180">Room my lords, stand close. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e104190">Music and a song, above, and Cupid enters with a table written, hung about his neck; after him two torch-bearers; after them Mary, d'entragues, and 4. Ladies more with their torch-bearers, etc. Cupid speaks. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e104200" who="A18404_02-cupid">
            <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104210">My lord, these nymphs, part of the scattered train,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104220">Of friendless virtue (Living in the woods</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104230">Of shady Arden: and of late not hearing</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104240">The dreadful sounds of war; but that sweet peace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104250">Was by your valour lifted from her grave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104260">Set on your royal right hand: and all virtues</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104270">Summoned with honour, and with rich rewards,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104280">To be her handmaidens): these I say, the virtues,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104290">Have put their heads out of their caves and coverts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104300">To be her true attendants in your court:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104310">In which desire, I must relate a tale,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104320">Of kind and worthy emulation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104330">Twixt these two virtues, leaders of the train. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104340">This on the right hand is Sophrosyne,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104350">Or chastity: this other dapsyle</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104360">Or liberality: their emulation</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104370">Begat a jar, which thus was reconciled. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104380">Ay, (Having left my goddess mother's lap,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104390">To hawk, and shoot at birds in Arden groves,)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104400">Beheld this princely nymph ▪ with much affection,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104410">Left killing birds, and turned into a bird,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104420"><pb facs="40"/> like which I flew betwixt her ivory breasts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104430">As if I had been driven by some hawk,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104440">To sue to her for safety of my life;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104450">She smiled at first, and sweetly shadowed me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104460">With soft protection of her silver hand;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104470">Sometimes she tied my legs in her rich hair,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104480">And made me (Passed my nature, liberty)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104490">Proud of my fetters: as I pertly sat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104500">On the white pillows of her naked breasts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104510">I sung for joy; she answered note for note,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104520">Relish for relish, with such ease and art,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104530">In her divine division, that my tunes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104540">Showed like the god of shepherds to the suns,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104550">Compared with hers: ashamed of which disgrace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104560">I took my true shape, bow, and all my shafts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104570">And lighted all my torches at her eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104580">Which (Set about her, in a golden ring)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104590">I followed birds again, from tree to tree,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104600">Killed, and presented, and she kindly took. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104610">But when she handled my triumphant bow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104620">And saw the beauty of my golden shafts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104630">She begged them of me; ay, poor boy replied,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104640">I had no other riches; yet was pleased</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104650">To hazard all, and stake them 'gainst a kiss,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104660">At an old game I used, called penny-prick. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104670">She privy to her own skill in the play,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104680">Answered my challenge, so, I lost my arms:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104690">And now my shafts are headed with her looks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104700">One of which shafts she put into my bow ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104710">And shot at this fair nymph, with whom before</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104720">I told your majesty, she had some jar. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104730">The nymph did instantly repent all parts</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104740">She played in urging that effeminate war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104750">Loved and submitted; which submission</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104760">This took so well, that now they both are one:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104770">And as for your dear love, their discords grew,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104780">So for your love, they did their loues renew. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104790">And now to prove them capable of your court ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104800"><pb facs="40"/> in skill of such conceits, and qualities</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104810">As here are practised; they will first submit</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104820">Their grace in dancing to your highness doom,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104830">And pray the press to give their measures room,</l>
            <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e104840">Music, dance, etc. which done Cupid speaks. </stage>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104850">If this suffice, for one court compliment,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104860">To make them gracious, and entertained;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104870">Behold another parcel of their courtship,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104880">Which is a rare dexterity in riddles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104890">Shown in one instance, which is here inscribed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104900">Here is a riddle, which if any knight</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104910">At first fight can resolve; he shall enjoy</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104920">This jewel here annexed; which though it show</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104930">To vulgar eyes, no richer than a pebble;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104940">And that no lapidary, nor great man</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104950">Will give a sou for it; 'tis worth a kingdom:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104960">For 'tis an artificial stone composed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104970">By their great mistress, virtue: and will make</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104980">Him that shall wear it, live with any little,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e104990">Sufficed, and more content than any King. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105000">If he that undertakes cannot resolve it;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105010">And that these nymphs can have no harbour here;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105020">(It being considered, that so many virtues</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105030">Can never live in court) he shall resolve</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105040">To leave the court, and live with them in Arden,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105050" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105060">Pronounce the riddle: I will undertake it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105070" who="A18404_02-cupid">
            <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105080">'Tis this sir. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105090">What's that a fair lady, most of all likes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105100">Yet ever makes show she least of all seeks? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105110">That's ever embraced and affected by her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105120">Yet never is seen to please or come nigh her:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105130">Most served in her nightweeds: does her good in a corner,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105140">But a poor man's thing ▪ yet doth richly adorn her:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105150">Most cheap, and most dear, above all worldly pelf,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105160">That is hard to get in, but comes out of itself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105170" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105180">Let me peruse it, Cupid. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105190" who="A18404_02-cupid">
            <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105200">Here it is. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105210" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105220">Your riddle is good fame. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105230" who="A18404_02-cupid">
            <pb facs="41"/>
            <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105240">Good fame? how make you that good? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105250" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105260">Good fame is that a good lady most likes I am sure;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105270" who="A18404_02-cupid">
            <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105280">That's granted;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105290" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105300">Yet ever makes show she least of all seeks: for she likes it only for the virtue, which is not glorious. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105310" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105320">That holds well</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105330" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105340">'Tis ever embraced and affected by her: for she must, persever in virtue or fame vanishes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105350">Yet never is seen to please or come nigh her for fame is invisible,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105360" who="A18404_02-cupid">
            <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105370">Exceeding right. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105380" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18404_02-e105390">Most served in her night weeds: for ladies that most wear their nightweeds come left abroad, and they that come least abroad serve fame most; according to this; non forma sed fama in publicum exire de bet. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105400" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18404_02-e105410">'Tis very substantial,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105420" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18404_02-e105430">Does her good in a corner: that is in her most retreat from the world, comforts her; but a poor man's thing: for every poor man may purchase it, yet doth richly adorn a lady.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105440" who="A18404_02-cupid">
            <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18404_02-e105450">That all must grant.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105460" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18404_02-e105470">Most cheap for it costs nothing, and most dear, for gold can not buy it; above all worldly pelf; for that's transitory, and fame eternal. It is hard to get in; that is hard to get: but comes out of itself; for when it is virtuously deserved with the most inward retreat from the world, it comes out in spite of it, and so Cupid your jewel is mine.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105480" who="A18404_02-cupid">
            <speaker>Cup.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105490">It is: and be the virtue of it, yours. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105500">We'll now turn to our dance, and then attend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105510">Your highness will, as touching our resort,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105520">If virtue may be entertained in court,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105530" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105540">This show hath pleased me well, for that it figures. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105550">The reconcilement of my Queen and mistress:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105560">Come let us in and thank them and prepare,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105570">To entertain our trusty friend Byron. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e105580">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <trailer xml:id="A18404_02-e105590">Finis actus secundi.</trailer>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act_and_scene" xml:id="A18404_02-e105600">
          <pb facs="41"/>
          <head>Actus 3. Scaena i.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e105610">Enter Byron. D'auer.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e105620" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105630">Dear friend, we must not be more true to Kings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105640">Than Kings are to their subjects, there are schools,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105650">Now broken ope in all parts of the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105660">First founded in ingenious Italy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105670">Where some conclusions of estate are held,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105680">That for a day preserve a prince, and ever,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105690">Destroy him after: from thence men are taught,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105700">To glide into degrees of height by craft,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105710">And then lock in themselves by villainy:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105720">But God, who knows Kings are not made by art,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105730">But right of nature, nor by treachery propped,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105740">But simple virtue, once let fall from heaven,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105750">A branch of that green tree, whose root is yet ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105760">Fast fixed above the stars: which sacred branch,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105770">We well may liken to that laurel spray,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105780">That from the heavenly eagles golden seres,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105790">Fell in the lap of great Augustus' wife:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105800">Which spray once set, grew up into a tree,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105810">Whereof were garlands made, and emperors,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105820">Had their estates and foreheads crowned with them:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105830">And as the arms of that tree did decay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105840">The race of great Augustus wore away,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105850">Nero being last of that imperial line,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105860">The tree and emperor together died. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105870">Religion is a branch, first set and blessed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105880">By heaven's high finger in the hearts of Kings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105890">Which whilom grew into a goodly tree,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105900">Bright angels sat and sung upon the twigs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105910">And royal branches for the heads of Kings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105920">Were twisted of them but since squint-eyed envy:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105930">And pale suspicion, dashed the heads of kingdoms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105940">One 'gainst another: two abhorred twins,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105950">With two foul tails: stern war and liberty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105960">Entered the world. The tree that grew from heaven. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105970"><pb facs="42"/>Is overrun with moss; the cheerful music,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105980">That heretofore hath sounded out of it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e105990">Begins to cease; and as she casts her leaves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106000">(By small degrees) the kingdoms of the earth</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106010">Decline and wither: and look whensoever</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106020">That the pure sap in her, is dried up quite;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106030">The lamp of all authority goes out,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106040">And all the blaze of princes is extinct;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106050">Thus as the poet sends a messenger</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106060">Out to the stage, to show the sum of all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106070">That follows after: so are Kings revolts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106080">And playing both ways with religion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106090">Forerunners of afflictions imminent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106100">Which (Like a chorus) subjects must lament. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106110" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>D' Au.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106120">My lord I stand not on these deep discourses,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106130">To settle my course to your fortunes; mine</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106140">Are freely and inseparably linked:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106150">And to your love my life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106160" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106170">Thanks princely friend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106180">And whatsoever good shall come of me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106190">Pursued by all the Catholic prince's aids</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106200">With whom I join, and whose whole states proposed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106210">To win my valour, promise me a throne:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106220">All shall be equal with myself; thine own. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106230" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>La Brun.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106240">My lord here is D'escuris sent from the King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106250">Desires access to you. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e106260">Enter D'escuris.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106270" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106280">Attend him in. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106290" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>Desc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106300">Health to my lord the Duke:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106310" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106320">Welcome D'escuris,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106330">In what health rests our royal sovereign. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106340" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>Desc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106350">In good health of his body, but his mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106360">Is something troubled with the gathering storms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106370">Of foreign powers; that as he is informed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106380">Address themselves into his frontier towns;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106390">And therefore his intent, is to maintain:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106400"><pb facs="42"/> the body of an army on those parts;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106410">And yield their worthy conduct to your valour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106420" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106430">From whence hears he that any storms are rising? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106440" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>D'esc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106450">From Italy; and his intelligence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106460">No doubt is certain, that in all those parts</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106470">Levies are hotly made; for which respect,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106480">He sent to his ambassador de Vic,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106490">To make demand in Switzerland, for the raising</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106500">With utmost diligence of six thousand men;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106510">All which shall be commanded to attend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106520">On your direction; as the constable</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106530">Your honoured gossip gave him in advice;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106540">And he sent you by wrighting: of which letters,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106550">He would have answer, and advice from you</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106560">By your most speedy presence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106570" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106580">This is strange,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106590">That when the enemy is t'attempt his frontiers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106600">He calls me from the frontiers; does he think,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106610">It is an action worthy of my valour</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106620">To turn my back, to an approaching foe? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106630" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>Desc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106640">The foe is not so near, but you may come,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106650">And take more strict directions from his highness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106660">Than he thinks fit his letters should contain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106670">Without the least attainture of your valour;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106680">And therefore good my lord, forbear excuse</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106690">And bear yourself on his direction;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106700">Who well you know hath never made design</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106710">For your most worthy service, where he saw</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106720">That any thing but honour could succeed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106730" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106740">I will not come I swear:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106750" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>Des.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106760">I know your grace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106770">Will send no such unsavoury reply. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106780" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106790">Tell him that I beseech his majesty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106800">To pardon my repair till th'end be known</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106810">Of all these levies now in Italy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106820" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>Des.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106830">My lord I know that tale will never please him;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106840">And wish you as you love his love and pleasure ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106850">To satisfy his summons speedily:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106860"><pb facs="43"/> and speedily I know he will return you;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106870" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106880">By heaven it is not fit: if all my service</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106890">Makes me know any thing: beseech him therefore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106900">To trust my judgement in these doubtful charges,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106910">Since in assured assaults it hath not failed him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106920" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>Des.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106930">I would your lordship now, would trust his judgement. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e106940" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106950">God's precious, you're importunate passed measure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106960">And (I know) further, than your charge extends,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106970">I'll satisfy his highness, let that serve;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106980">For by this flesh and blood, you shall not bear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e106990">Any reply to him, but this from me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107000" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>Des.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107010">'Tis naught to me my lord, I wish your good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107020">And for that cause have been importunate. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e107030">Exit Desc:</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107040" who="A18404_02-brunel">
            <speaker>Brunel.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107050">By no means go my lord; but with distrust,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107060">Of all that hath been said or can be sent;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107070">Collect your friends, and stand upon your guard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107080">The Kings fair letters, and his messages</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107090">Are only golden pills, and comprehend</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107100">Horrible purgatives. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107110" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107120">I will not go,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107130">For now I see th'instructions lately sent me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107140">That something is discovered, are too true,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107150">And my head rules none of those neighbour nobles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107160">That every pursuant brings beneath the axe:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107170">If they bring me out, they shall see I'll hatch</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107180">Like to the blackthorn, that puts forth his leaf,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107190">Not with the golden fawnings of the sun,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107200">But sharpest showers of hail, and blackest frosts:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107210">Blows, batteries, breaches, showers of steel and blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107220">Must be his downright messengers for me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107230">And not the misling breath of policy:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107240">He, he himself, made passage to his crown</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107250">Through no more armies, battles, massacres,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107260">Than I will ask him to arrive at me;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107270">He takes on him, my executions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107280">And on the demolitions, that this arm,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107290">Hath shaken out of forts and citadels,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107300">Hath he advanced the trophies of his valour;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107310">Where I, in those assumptions may scorn,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107320"><pb facs="43"/> and speak contemptuously of all the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107330">For any equal yet, I ever found;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107340">And in my rising, not the Syrian star</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107350">That in the lion's mouth, undaunted shines,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107360">And makes his brave ascension with the sun,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107370">Was of th' Egyptians, with more zeal beheld,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107380">And made a rule to know the circuit ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107390">And compass of the year; then I was held</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107400">When I appeared from battle; the whole sphere,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107410">And full sustainer of the state we bear;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107420">I have alcides-like gone under th' earth</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107430">And on these shoulders born the weight of France:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107440">And (For the fortunes of the thankless King)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107450">My father (All know) set him in his throne,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107460">And if he urge me, I may pluck him out. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e107470">Enter mess:</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107480" who="A18404_02-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107490">Here is the precedent Janin, my lord;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107500">Sent from the King, and urgeth quick access. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107510" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107520">Another pursuivant? and one so quick? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107530">He takes next course with me, to make him stay:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107540">But, let him in, let's here what he importunes. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e107550">Enter Janin.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107560" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Janin.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107570">Honour, and loyal hopes to Duke Byron. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107580" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107590">No other touch me: say how fares the King? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107600" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Jan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107610">Farely my lord; the cloud is yet far off</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107620">That aims at his obscuring, and his will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107630">Would gladly give the motion to your powers</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107640">That should disperse it; but the means, himself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107650">Would personally relate in your direction ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107660" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107670">Still on that haunt? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107680" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Jan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107690">Upon my life, my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107700">He much desires to see you, and your sight</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107710">Is now grown necessary to suppress</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107720">(As with the glorious splendour of the sun)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107730">The rude winds that report breathes in his ears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107740">Endeavouring to blast your loyalty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107750" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107760">Sir, if my loyalty, stick in him no faster</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107770">But that the light breath of report may lose it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107780">(So I rest still unmoved) let him be shaken. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107790" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Jan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107800">But these aloof abodes, my lord bewray,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107810"><pb facs="44"/> that there is rather firmness in your breath. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107820">Then in your heart; truth is not made of glass,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107830">That with a small touch, it should fear to break,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107840">And therefore should not shun it; believe me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107850">His arm is long, and strong; and it can fetch</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107860">Any within his will, that will not come:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107870">Not he that surfeits in his mines of gold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107880">And for the pride thereof, compares with God,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107890">Calling (With almost nothing different)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107900">His powers invincible, for omnipotent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107910">Can back your boldest fort 'gainst his assaults;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107920">It is his pride, and vain ambition,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107930">That hath but two stairs in his high designs;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107940">(The lowest envy, and the highest blood)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107950">That doth abuse you; and gives minds too high,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107960">Rather a will by giddiness to fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107970">Than to descend by judgement. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e107980" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e107990">I rely</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108000">On no man's back nor belly; but the King</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108010">Must think that merit, by ingratitude cracked,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108020">Requires a firmer sementing than words. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108030">And he shall find it a much harder work</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108040">To solder broken hearts ▪ than shivered glasses. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108050" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Jan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108060">My lord, 'tis better hold a sovereign's love</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108070">By bearing injuries; then by laying out</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108080">Stir his displeasure; prince's discontents</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108090">(Being once incensed) are like the flames of Aetna,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108100">Not to be quenched, nor lessened: and be sure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108110">A subjects' confidence in any merit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108120">Against his sovereign, that makes him presume</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108130">To fly too high; approves him like a cloud,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108140">That makes a show as it did hawk at kingdoms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108150">And could command, all raised beneath his vapour:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108160">When suddenly, the fowl that hawlkt so fair,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108170">Stoops in a puddle, or consumes in air. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108180" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108190">I fly with no such aim, nor am opposed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108200">Against my sovereign; but the worthy height</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108210">I have wrought by my service, I will hold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108220"><pb facs="44"/> which if I come away, I cannot do;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108230">For if the enemy should invade the frontier,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108240">Whose charge to guard, is mine, with any spoil,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108250">(Although the King in placing of another</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108260">Might well excuse me) yet all foreign Kings</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108270">That can take note of no such secret quittance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108280">Will lay the weakness here, upon my wants;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108290">And therefore my abode is resolute. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108300" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Ian:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108310">I sorrow for your resolution,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108320">And fear your dissolution, will succeed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108330" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108340">I must endure it;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108350" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Ian:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108360">Fare you well my lord;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108370" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108380">Farewell to you;<stage xml:id="A18404_02-e108390">Enter Brun.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108400">Captain what other news? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108410" who="A18404_02-brulart">
            <speaker>Bru:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108420">La fin salutes you;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108430" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108440">Welcome good friend; I hope your wished arrival ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108450">Will give some certain end to our designs;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108460" who="A18404_02-brulart">
            <speaker>Bru:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108470">I know not that, my lord; reports are raised so doubtful and so different, that the truth of any one can hardly be assured. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108480" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108490">Good news, D'auvergne; our trusty friend la fin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108500">Hath cleared all scruple with his majesty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108510">And uttered nothing but what served to clear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108520">All bad suggestions. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108530" who="A18404_02-brulart">
            <speaker>Bru:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108540">So he says, my lord</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108550">But others say, la Fin's assurances</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108560">Are mere deceits; and wish you to believe;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108570">That when the Vidame, nephew to la fin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108580">Met you at autumn, to assure your doubts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108590">His uncle had said nothing to the King</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108600">That might offend you; all the journey's charge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108610">The King defrayed; besides, your truest friends</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108620">Willed me to make you certain that your place</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108630">Of government is otherwise disposed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108640">And all advice you, for your latest hope,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108650">To make retreat into the French county. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108660" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108670">I thank them all, but they touch not the depth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108680">Of the affairs, betwixt la fin and me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108690"><pb facs="45"/>Who is returned contented to his house,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108700">Quite freed, of all displeasure or distrust;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108710">And therefore, worthy friends we'll now to court. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108720" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>D' au</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108730">My lord, I like your other friends advices,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108740">Much better than Laffin's; and on my life</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108750">You can not come to court with any safety. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108760" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108770">Who shall infringe it? I know, all the court,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108780">Have better apprehension of my valour;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108790">Then that they dare lay violent hands on me;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108800">If I have only means to draw this sword,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108810">I shall have power enough to set me free,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108820">From seizure, by my proudest enemy. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e108830">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e108840">Esper: Vyt: Pralin:</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108850" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108860">He will not come I dare engage my hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108870" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vyt.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108880">He will be fetched then, I'll engage my head. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108890" who="A18404_02-pralin">
            <speaker>Pra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108900">Come, or be fetched, he quite hath lost his honour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108910">In giving these suspicions of revolt</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108920">From his allegiance: that which he hath won,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108930">With sundry wounds, and peril of his life;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108940">With wonder of his wisdom, and his valour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108950">He loseth with a most enchanted glory:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108960">And admiration of his pride, and folly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e108970" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108980">Why did you never see a fortunate man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e108990">Suddenly raised to heaps of wealth and honour? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109000">Nor any rarely great in gifts of nature,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109010">As valour, wit, and smooth use of the tongue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109020">Set strangely to the pitch of popular likings? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109030">But with as sudden falls the rich and honoured,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109040">Were overwhelmed by poverty ▪ and shame</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109050">Or had no use of both above the wretched. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109060" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109070">Men never are satisfied with that they have;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109080">But as a man, matched with a lovely wife,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109090">When his most heavenly theory of her beauties,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109100">Is dulled and quite exhausted with his practice:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109110">He brings her forth to feasts, where he alas,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109120">Falls to his viands with no thought like others,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109130">That think him blessed in her, and they (Poor men)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109140"><pb facs="45"/> court, and make faces, offer service, sweat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109150">With their desires contention, break their brains</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109160">For jests, and tales: sit mute, and lose their looks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109170">(Far out of wit, and out of countenance)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109180">So all men else, do what they have transplant,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109190">And place their wealth in thirst of that they want. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e109200">Enter Henry, Chanc: vyd: Desc: Janin.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109210" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109220">He will not come; I must both grieve and wonder,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109230">That all my care to win my subjects' love</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109240">And in one cup of friendship to comix,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109250">Our lives and fortunes: should leave out so many</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109260">As give a man (Contemptuous of my love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109270">And of his own good, in the kingdom's peace)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109280">Hope, in a continuance so ungrateful,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109290">To bear out his designs in spite of me;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109300">How should I better please all, than I do? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109310">When they supposed, I would have given some,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109320">Insolent garrisons; others citadels,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109330">And to all sorts, increase of miseries;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109340">Province by province, I did visit all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109350">Whom those injurious rumours had diswaide;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109360">And showed them how, I never sought to build,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109370">More forts for me, then were within their hearts;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109380">Nor use more stern constraints then their good wills,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109390">To succour the necessities of my crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109400">That I desired to add to their contents</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109410">By all occasions, rather than subtract;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109420">Nor wished I, that my treasury should flow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109430">With gold that swum in, in my subjects tears;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109440">And than I found no man, that did not bless,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109450">My few years reign, and their triumphant peace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109460">And do they now so soon, complain of ease? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109470" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109480">He will not come? <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e109490">Enter Byron, d' Auuergne; brother, with others ▪</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109500" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109510">O madness? he is come. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109520" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109530">The Duke is come my lord:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109540" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109550">O sir, you're welcome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109560"><pb facs="46"/> and fitly, to conduct me to my house;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109570" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109580">I must beseech your majesty's excuse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109590">That (Jealous of mine honour) I have used,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109600">Some of mine own commandment in my stay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109610">And came not with your highness soonest summons. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109620" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109630">The faithful servant right in holy writ;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109640">That said he would not come and yet he came:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109650">But come you hither; I must tell you now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109660">Not the contempt you stood to in your stay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109670">But the bad ground that bore up your contempt,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109680">Makes you arrive at no port, but repentance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109690">Despair, and ruin;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109700" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109710">Be what port it will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109720">At which your will, will make me be arrived,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109730">I am not come to justify myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109740">To ask you pardon nor accuse my friends,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109750" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109760">If you conceal my enemies you are one,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109770">And then my pardon shall be worth your asking,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109780">Or else your head be worth my cutting of. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109790" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109800">Being friend and worthy fautor of myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109810">I am no foe of yours, nor no impairer,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109820">Since he can no way worthily maintain</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109830">His prince's honour that neglects his own:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109840">And if your will have been to my true reason,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109850">(Maintaining still the truth of loyalty)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109860">A check to my free nature and mine honour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109870">And that on your free justice I presumed </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109880">To cross your will a little, I conceive,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109890">You will not think this forfeit worth my head;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109900" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109910">Have you maintained your truth of loyalty? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109920">When since I pardoned foul intentions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109930">Resolving to forget eternally, what they appeared in,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109940">And had welcomed you as the kind father doth his riotous son. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109950">I can approve facts fouler than th' intents,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109960">Of deep disloyalty and highest treason;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e109970" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109980">May this right hand be thunder to my breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e109990">If I stand guilty of the slenderest fact,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110000">Wherein the left of those two can be proved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110010"><pb facs="46"/> for could my tender conscience but have touched,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110020">At any such unnatural relapse;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110030">I would not with this confidence have run,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110040">Thus headlong in the furnace of a wrath,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110050">Blown, and thrice kindled: having way enough,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110060">In my election both to shun and sleight it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110070" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110080">You're grossly and vain gloriously abused,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110090">There is no way in Savoy nor in Spain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110100">To give a fool that hope of your escape,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110110">And had you not (Even when you did) arrived. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110120">(With horror to the proudest hope you had)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110130">I would have fetched you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110140" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110150">You must then have used. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110160">A power beyond my knowledge, and a will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110170">Beyond your justice. For a little stay</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110180">More than I used would hardly have been worthy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110190">Of such an open expedition;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110200">In which to all the censures of the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110210">My faith and innocence had been foully foiled;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110220">Which (I protest) by heaven's bright witnesses</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110230">That shine far, far, from mixture with our fears. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110240">Retain as perfect roundness as their spheres;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110250" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110260">'Tis well my lord, I thought I could have frighted</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110270">Your firmest confidence: some other time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110280">We will (As now in private) sift your actions. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110290">And pour more than you think into the si●e,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110300">Always reserving clemency and pardon</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110310">Upon confession, be you ne'er so foul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110320">Come let's clear up our brows shall we to tennis. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110330" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110340">I my lord if I may make the match. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110350">The Duke Espernon and myself will play,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110360">With you and count Soissons;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110370" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110380">I know my lord. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110390">You play well but you make your matches ill. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110400" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110410">Come 'tis a match. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e110420">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110430" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110440">How like you my arrival? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110450" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110460">I'll tell you as your friend in your ear. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110470">You have given more preferment to your courage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110480"><pb facs="47"/> then to the provident counsels of your friends. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110490" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>Worser Au.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110500">I told him so my lord, and much was grieved</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110510">To see his bold approach, so full of will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110520" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110530">Well I must bear it now, though but with th'head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110540">The shoulders bearing nothing. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110550" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110560">By saint John,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110570">'Tis a good headless resolution. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e110580">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act_and_scene" xml:id="A18404_02-e110590">
          <head>Actus. 4. Scen. 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e110600">Byron, D'avuergne.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110610" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110620">O the most base fruits of a settled peace! </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110630">In men, I mean; worse than their dirty fields,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110640">Which they manure much better themselves:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110650">For them they plant, and sow, and ere they grow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110660">Weedy, and choked with thorns, they grub and prune,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110670">And make them better, than when cruel war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110680">Frighted from thence the sweaty labourer:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110690">But men themselves, instead of bearing fruits,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110700">Grow rude, and foggy, overgrown with weeds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110710">Their spirits, and freedoms smothered in their ease;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110720">And as their tyrants and their ministers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110730">Grow wild in prosecution of their lusts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110740">So they grow prostitute, and lie (Like whores)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110750">Down and take up, to their abhorred dishonours:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110760">The friendless may be injured and oppressed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110770">The guiltless led to slaughter, the deserver</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110780">Given to the beggar; right be wholly wronged,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110790">And wrong be only honoured; till the strings</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110800">Of every man's heart, crack; and who will stir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110810">To tell authority, that it doth err. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110820">All men cling to it, though they see their bloods</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110830">In their most dear associates and allies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110840">Poured into kennels by it: and who dares</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110850">But look well in the breast, whom that impairs? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110860">How all the court now looks askew on me? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110870">Go by without saluting, shun my sight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110880">Which (Like a march sun) agues breeds in them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110890">From whence of late, 'twas health to have a beam. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e110900" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <pb facs="47"/>
            <speaker>D'au.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110910">Now none will speak to us, we thrust ourselves</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110920">Into men's companies, and offer speech,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110930">As if not made, for their diverted ears ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110940">Their backs turned to us, and their words to others,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110950">And we must like obsequious parasites,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110960">Follow their faces, wind about their persons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110970">For looks and answers: or be cast behind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e110980">No more viewed than the wallet of their faults. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e110990">Enter Soisson.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111000" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111010">Yet here's one views me, and I think will speak ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111020" who="A18404_02-soissons">
            <speaker>Soiss.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111030">My lord, if you respect your name and race,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111040">The preservation of your former honours,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111050">Merits and virtues; humbly cast them all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111060">At the King's mercy; for beyond all doubt,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111070">Your acts have thither driven them: he hath proofs</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111080">So pregnant, and so horrid, that to hear them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111090">Would make your valour in your very looks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111100">Give up your forces, miserably guilty:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111110">But he is most loath (For his ancient love</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111120">To your rare virtues:) and in their impair,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111130">The full discouragement of all that live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111140">To trust or favour any gifts in nature)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111150">T'expose them to the light; when darkness may</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111160">Cover her own brood, and keep still in day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111170">Nothing of you but that may brook her brightness:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111180">You know what horrors these high strokes do bring,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111190">Raised in the arm of an incensed King. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111200" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111210">My lord, be sure the King cannot complain</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111220">Of any thing in me, but my true service,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111230">Which in so many dangers of my death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111240">May so approve my spotless loyalty;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111250">That those quite opposite horrors you assure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111260">Must look out of his own ingratitude;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111270">Or the malignant envies of my foes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111280">Who pour me out in such a Stygian flood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111290">To drown me in myself, since their deserts</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111300">Are far from such a deluge; and in me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111310">Hid like so many rivers in the sea. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111320" who="A18404_02-soissons">
            <pb facs="48"/>
            <speaker>Soiss:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111330">You think I come to found you; fare you well,<stage xml:id="A18404_02-e111340">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e111350">Enter chancellor, Espernon, Janin, Vidame, Vytry, Pralin, whispering by couples, etc. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111360" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>D' au:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111370">See see, not one of them will cast a glance</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111380">At our eclipsed faces;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111390" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111400">They keep all to cast in admiration on the King:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111410">For from his face are all their faces moulded. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111420" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>D' au:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111430">But when a change comes; we shall see them all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111440">Changed into water, that will instantly</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111450">Give look for look, as if it watched to greet us;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111460">Or else for one, they'll give us twenty faces,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111470">Like to the little specks on sides of glasses;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111480" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111490">Is't not an easy loss to lose their looks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111500">Whose hearts so soon are melted? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111510" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>D'au:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111520">But methinks ,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111530">(Being courtiers) they should cast best looks on men,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111540">When they thought worst of them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111550" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111560">O no my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111570">They ne'er dissemble but for some advantage;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111580">They sell their looks, and shadows; which they rate</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111590">After their markets, kept beneath the state;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111600">Lord what foul weather their aspects do threaten? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111610">See in how grave a brake he sets his vizard:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111620">Passion of nothing; see, an excellent gesture:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111630">Now courtship goes a ditching in their foreheads;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111640">And we are fallen into those dismal ditches;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111650">Why even thus dreadfully would they be rapt,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111660">If the Kings buttered eggs, were only spilt. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e111670">Enter Henry.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111680" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111690">Lord chancellor;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111700" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Cha ▪</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111710">I my lord;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111720" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111730">And lord Vidame:<stage xml:id="A18404_02-e111740">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111750" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111760">And not Byron? here's a prodigious change;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111770" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>D'au:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111780">He cast no beam on you;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111790" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111800">Why now you see</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111810">From whence their countenances were copied. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e111820"><pb facs="48"/>Enter the captain of Byron's guard with a letter. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111830" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>D'au.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111840">See, here comes some news, I believe my lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111850" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111860">What says the honest captain of my guard? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111870" who="A18404_02-captain">
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111880">I bring a letter from a friend of yours. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111890" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111900">'Tis welcome then:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111910" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>D'au.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111920">Have we yet any friends? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111930" who="A18404_02-captain">
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111940">More than ye would I think: I never saw,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111950">Men in their right minds so unrighteous</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111960">In their own causes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e111970" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111980">See what thou hast brought,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e111990">He wills us to retire ourselves my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112000">And makes as if it were almost too late,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112010">What says my captain; shall we go or no? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e112020" who="A18404_02-captain">
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112030">I would your dagger's point had kissed my heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112040">When you resolved to come. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e112050" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112060">I pray the why? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e112070" who="A18404_02-captain">
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112080">Yet, doth that senseless apoplexy dull you? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112090">The devil or your wicked angel blinds you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112100">Bereaving all your reason of a man</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112110">And leaves you but the spirit of a horse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112120">In your brute nostrils: only power to dare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e112130" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112140">Why, dost thou think, my coming here hath brought me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112150">To such an unrecoverable danger? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e112160" who="A18404_02-captain">
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112170">Judge by the strange ostents that have succeeded,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112180">Since your arrival: the kind fowl, the wild duck,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112190">That came into your cabinet, so beyond</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112200">The sight of all your servants, or yourself:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112210">That flew about, and on your shoulder sat</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112220">And which you had so fed, and so attended;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112230">For that dumb love she showed you; just as soon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112240">As you were parted, on the sudden died. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112250">And to make this no less than an ostent;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112260">Another that hath fortuned since, confirms it:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112270">Your goodly horse Pastrana, which the archduke,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112280">Gave you at Brussels; in the very hour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112290">You left your strength, fel-mad, and killed himself;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112300">●●e like chanced to the horse the great Duke sent you:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112310">And, with both these, the horse the Duke of Lorraine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112320"><pb facs="49"/> sent you at, Vinsie made a third presage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112330">Of some inevitable fate that touched you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112340">Who like the other pined away and died,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e112350" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112360">All these together are indeed oftentful,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112370">Which by another like, I can confirm:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112380">The matchless Earl of Essex who some make,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112390">(In their most sure divinings of my death)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112400">A parallel with me in life and fortune,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112410">Had one horse likewise that the very hour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112420">He suffered death, (Being well the night before)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112430">Died in his pasture. Noble happy beasts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112440">That die, not having to their wills to live:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112450">They use no deprecations, nor complaints. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112460">Nor suit for mercy: amongst them the lion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112470">Serves not the lion; nor the horse the horse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112480">As man serves man: when men show most their spirits,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112490">In valour and their utmost dares to do;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112500">They are compared to lions, wolves, and boars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112510">But by conversion; none will say a lion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112520">Fights as he had the spirit of a man. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112530">Let me then in my danger now give cause,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112540">For all men to begin that simile. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112550">For all my huge engagement, I provide me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112560">This short sword only; which if I have time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112570">To show my apprehendor, he shall use,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112580">Power of ten lions if I get not lose. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e112590">Enter Henry, chancellor, Vidame, Janin, Vitry, Pralin.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e112600" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112610">What shall we do with this unthankful man? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112620">Would he (Of one thing) but reveal the truth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112630">Which I have proof of, underneath his hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112640">He should not taste my justice. I would give,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112650">Two hundred thousand crowns, that he would yield,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112660">But such means for my pardon, as he should;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112670">I never loved man like him: would have trusted,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112680">My son in his protection, and my realm:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112690">He hath deserved my love with worthy service,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112700"><pb facs="49"/> yet can he not deny, but I have thrice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112710">Saved him from death: I drew him of the foe. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112720">At fountain Francoise where he was engaged,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112730">So wounded and so much amazed with blows,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112740">That (As I played the soldier in his rescue,)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112750">I was enforced to play the marshal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112760">To order the retreat: because he said,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112770">He was not fit to do it nor to serve me,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e112780" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112790">Your majesty hath used your utmost means,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112800">Both by your own persuasions, and his friends</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112810">To bring him to submission, and confess</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112820">(With some sign of repentance) his foul fault:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112830">Yet still he stands prefract and insolent. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112840">You have in love and care of his recovery</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112850">Been half in labour to produce a course,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112860">And resolution, what were fit for him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112870">And since so amply it concerns your crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112880">You must by law cut of, what by your grace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112890">You cannot bring into the state of safety,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e112900" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Jan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112910">Begin at th' end my lord and execute,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112920">Like Alexander with Parmenio. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112930">Princes (You know) are masters of their laws,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112940">And may resolve them to what forms they please,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112950">So all conclude in justice; in whose stroke,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112960">There is one sort of manage for the great;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112970">Another for inferior: the great mother,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112980">Of all productions (Grave necessity)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e112990">Commands the variation: and the profit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113000">So certainly foreseen, commends the example. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113010" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113020">I like not executions so informal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113030">For which my predecessors have been blamed:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113040">My subjects and the world shall know; my power,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113050">And my authority by law's usual course</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113060">Dares punish; not the devilish heads of treason,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113070">But there confederates be they ne'er so dreadful ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113080">The decent ceremonies of my laws,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113090">And their solemnities shall be observed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113100">With all their sternness and severity. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113110" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <pb facs="50"/>
            <speaker>Vit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113120">Where will your highness have him apprehended? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113130" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113140">Not in the castle (As some have advised)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113150">But in his chamber;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113160" who="A18404_02-pralin">
            <speaker>Pral:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113170">Rather in your own,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113180">Or coming out of it; for 'tis assured</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113190">That any other place of apprehension,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113200">Will make the hard performance, end in blood. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113210" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113220">To shun this likelihood, my lord 'tis best</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113230">To make the apprehension near your chamber;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113240">For all respect and reverence given the place,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113250">More than is needful, to chastise the person,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113260">And save the opening of to many veins;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113270">Is vain and dangerous. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113280" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113290">Gather you your guard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113300">And I will find fit time to give the word,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113310">When you shall seize on him and on D'auvergne;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113320" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113330">We will be ready to the death; (My lord)<stage xml:id="A18404_02-e113340">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113350" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113360">O thou that governest the keen swords of Kings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113370">Direct my arm in this important stroke,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113380">Or hold it being advanced; the weight of blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113390">Even in the basest subject, doth exact</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113400">Deep consultation, in the highest King;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113410">For in one subject, deaths unjust affrights,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113420">Passions, and pains, (Though he be ne'er so poor)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113430">Ask more remorse, than the voluptuous spleens</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113440">Of all Kings in the world, deserve respect;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113450">He should be born grey-headed that will bear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113460">The sword of empire; judgement of the life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113470">Free state, and reputation of a man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113480">(If it be just and worthy) dwells so dark</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113490">That it denies access to sun and moon;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113500">The soul's eye sharpened with that sacred light,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113510">Of whom the sun itself is but a beam,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113520">Must only give that judgement; oh how much</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113530">Err those Kings then, that play with life and death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113540">And nothing put into their serious states,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113550">But humour and their lusts! For which alone</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113560">Men long for kingdoms; whose huge counterpoise</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113570"><pb facs="50"/> in cares and dangers, could a fool comprise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113580">He would not be a King but would be wise;</l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e113590">Enter Byron talking with the Queen: Esp: d' entragues, d' Av: with another lady, others attending.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113600" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113610">Here comes the man, with whose ambitious head</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113620">(Cast in the way of treason) we must stay</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113630">His full chase of our ruin and our realm;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113640">This hour shall take upon her shady wings</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113650">His latest liberty and life to hell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113660" who="A18404_02-d'auvergne">
            <speaker>D'av:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113670">We are undone? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113680" who="A18404_02-queen">
            <speaker>Queen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113690">What's that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113700" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113710">I heard him not;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113720" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113730">Madam you're honoured much, that Duke Byron</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113740">Is so observant; some, to cards with him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113750">You four, as now you come, sit to primero;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113760">And I will fight a battle at the chess;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113770" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113780">A good safe fight believe me; other war</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113790">Thirsts blood, and wounds, and his thirst quenched, is thankless;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113800" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113810">Lift, and then cut;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113820" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113830">'Tis right the end of lifting,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113840">When men are lifted to their highest pitch,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113850">They cut of those that lifted them so high. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113860" who="A18404_02-queen">
            <speaker>Queen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113870">Apply you all these sports so seriously? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113880" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113890">They first were from our serious acts devised,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113900">The best of which, are to the best but sports;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113910">(I mean by best, the greatest) for their ends,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113920">In men that serve them best, are their own pleasures. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113930" who="A18404_02-queen">
            <speaker>Queen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113940">So, in those best men's services, their ends</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113950">Are their own pleasures; pass. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113960" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113970">I vy't;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e113980" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e113990">I see't;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114000">And wonder at his frontless impudence;<stage xml:id="A18404_02-e114010">Exit Hen:</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114020" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114030">How speeds your majesty? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114040" who="A18404_02-queen">
            <speaker>Queen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114050">Well; the Duke instructs me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114060">With such grave lessons of mortality</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114070"><pb facs="51"/> forced out of our light sport; that if I lose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114080">I cannot but speed well. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114090" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114100">Some idle talk. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114110">For courtship's sake, you know does not amiss. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114120" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114130">Would we might hear some of it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114140" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114150">That you shall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114160">I cast away a card now, makes me think,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114170">Of the deceased worthy King of Spain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114180" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114190">What card was that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114200" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114210">The King of hearts (My lord)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114220">Whose name yields well the memory of that King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114230">Who was indeed the worthy King of hearts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114240">And had, both of his subjects' hearts, and strangers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114250">Much more than all the Kings of Christendom. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114260" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114270">He won them with his gold. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114280" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114290">He won them chiefly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114300">With his so general piety and justice:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114310">And as the little, yet great Macedon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114320">Was said with his humane philosophy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114330">To teach the rapeful Hyrcans, marriage;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114340">And bring the barbarous sogdians, to nourish,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114350">Not kill their aged parents; as before,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114360">Th' incestuous Persians to reverence</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114370">Their mothers, not to use them as their wives;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114380">The Indians to adore the Grecian gods,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114390">The Scythians to inter, not eat their parents;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114400">So he, with his divine philosophy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114410">(Which I may call his, since he chiefly used it)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114420">In Turkey, India, and through all the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114430">Expelled profane idolatry; and from earth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114440">Raised temples to the highest: whom with the word,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114450">He could not win, he justly put to sword,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114460" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114470">He sought for gold, and empire. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114480" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114490">'Twas religion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114500">And her full propagation that he sought;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114510"><pb facs="51"/> if gold had been his end, it had been hoarded,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114520">When he had fetched it in so many fleets:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114530">Which he spent not on Median luxury,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114540">Banquets, and women; Calidonian wine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114550">Nor dear Hyrcanian fishes ▪ but employed it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114560">To propagate his empire; and his empire</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114570">Desired t'extend so, that he might withal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114580">Extend religion through it, and all nations,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114590">Reduce to one firm constitution,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114600">Of piety, justice, and one public weal;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114610">To which end he made all his matchless subjects</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114620">Make tents their castles, and their garrisons;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114630">True Catholics countrymen; and their allies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114640">Heretics, strangers, and their enemies. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114650">There was in him the magnanimity. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114660" who="A18404_02-unassigned">
            <speaker>Montig.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114670">To temper your extreme applause (My lord)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114680">Shorten, and answer all things in a word,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114690">The greatest commendation we can give</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114700">To the remembrance of that King deceased;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114710">Is, that he spared not his own eldest son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114720">But put him justly to a violent death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114730">Because, he sought to trouble his estates. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114740" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114750">Is't so? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114760" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114770">That bit (My lord) upon my life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114780">'Twas bitterly replied, and doth amaze him. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e114790">The King suddenly enters having determined what to do.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e114800" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114810">It is resolved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114820">A work shall now be done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114830">Which, (While learned Atlas shall with stars be crowned,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114840">While th' ocean walks in storms his wavy round,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114850">While moons at full, repair their broken rings:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114860"><pb facs="52"/> while Lucifer foreshows Aurora's springs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114870">And Arctos sticks above the earth unmoved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114880">Shall make my realm be blessed, and me beloved;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114890">Call in the count d' Awergne. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e114900">Enter D'au.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114910">A word my lord. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114920">Will you become as wilful as your friend? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114930">And draw a mortal justice on your heads,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114940">That hangs so black and is so loath to strike? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114950">If you would utter what I know you know,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114960">Of his inhuman treason; on strong bar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114970">Betwixt his will, and duty were dissolved. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114980">For then I know he would submit himself;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e114990">Think you it not as strong a point of faith,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115000">To rectify your loyalties to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115010">As to be trusty in each others wrong? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115020">Trust that deceives ourselves in treachery,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115030">And truth that truth conceals an open lie;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115040" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>D'au.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115050">My lord if I could utter any thought,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115060">Instructed with disloyalty to you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115070">And might light any safety to my friend;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115080">Though mine own heart came after it should out;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115090" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115100">I know you may, and that your faith's affected</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115110">To one another, are so vain and false,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115120">That your own strengths will ruin you: ye contend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115130">To cast up rampiers to you in the sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115140">And strive to stop the waves that run before you,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115150" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>D'au.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115160">All this my lord to me is misery. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115170" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115180">It is; I'll make it plain enough. Believe me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115190">Come my lord chancellor let us end our mate. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e115200">Enter Varennes, whispering to Byron.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115210" who="A18404_02-varennes">
            <speaker>Var.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115220">You are undone my lord;<stage xml:id="A18404_02-e115230">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115240" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115250">Is it possible? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115260" who="A18404_02-queen">
            <speaker>Queen</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115270">Play good my lord: whom look you for? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115280" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115290">Your mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115300">Is not upon your game,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115310" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115320">Play, pray you play,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115330" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115340">Enough, 'tis late, and time to leave our play,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115350"><pb facs="52"/> on all hands; all forbear the room, my lord? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115360">Stay you with me; yet is your will resolved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115370">To duty, and the main bond of your life? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115380">I swear (Of all th' intrusions I have made,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115390">Upon your own good, and continued fortunes)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115400">This is the last; inform me yet the truth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115410">And here I vow to you, (By all my love;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115420">By all means shown you, even to this extreme,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115430">When all men else forsake you) you are safe. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115440">What passages have slipped twixt count Fuentes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115450">You, and the Duke of Savoy? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115460" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115470">Good my lord. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115480">This nail is driven already passed the head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115490">You much have overcharged, an honest man:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115500">And I beseech you yield my innocence justice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115510">(But with my single valour) 'gainst them all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115520">That thus have poisoned your opinion of me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115530">And let me take my vengeance by my sword:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115540">For I protest, I never thought an action,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115550">More than my tongue hath uttered. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115560" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115570">Would 'twere true. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115580">And that your thoughts and deeds, had fell no fouler. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115590">But you disdain submission, not remembering,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115600">That (In intentes urged for the common good)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115610">He that shall hold his peace being charged to speak:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115620">Doth all the peace and nerves of empire break</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115630">Which on your conscience lie, adieu, good night. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e115640">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115650" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115660">King's hate to hear what they command men speak,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115670">Ask life, and to desert of death ye yield. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115680">Where medicines loath, it irks men to be healed,</l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e115690">Enter Vitry, with two or three of the guard, Esper, Vidame, following. Vytry lays hand on Byron's sword.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115700" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vyt.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115710">Resign your sword (My lord) the King commands it ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115720" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115730">Me to resign my sword? what King is he,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115740">Hath used it better for the realm than I? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115750">My sword, that all the wars within the length,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115760">Breadth and the whole dimensions of great France,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115770">Hath sheathed betwixt his hilt and horrid point? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115780"><pb facs="53"/>And fixed ye all in such a florishing peace? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115790">My sword that never enemy could enforce,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115800">Bereft me by my friends? Now, good my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115810">Beseech the King, I may resign my sword,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115820">To his hand only. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e115830">Enter Janin.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115840" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Janin:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115850">You must do your office,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115860">The King commands you;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115870" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115880">'Tis in vain to strive,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115890">For I must force it;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e115900" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byron:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115910">Have I ne'er a friend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115920">That bears another for me? All the guard? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115930">What will you kill me? will you smother here</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115940">His life that can command, and save in field,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115950">A hundred thousand lives? For manhood's sake;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115960">Lend something to this poor forsaken hand;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115970">For all my service, let me have the honour</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115980">To die defending of my innocent self,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e115990">And have some little space to pray to God. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e116000">Enter Henry.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116010" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116020">Come, you are an atheist Byron, and a traitor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116030">Both foul and damnable; thy innocent self? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116040">No leper is so buried quick in ulcers</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116050">As thy corrupted soul: thou end the war? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116060">And settle peace in France? what war hath raged,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116070">Into whose fury I have not exposed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116080">My person ▪ which is as free a spirit as thine? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116090">Thy worthy father, and thyself, combined,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116100">And armed in all the merits of your valours;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116110">(Your bodies thrust amid the thickest fight ▪)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116120">Never were bristled with so many battles ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116130">Nor on the foe have broke such woods of lances</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116140">As grew upon my thigh; and I have marshalled;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116150">I am ashamed to brag thus; where envy</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116160">And arrogance, their opposite bulwark raise;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116170">Men are allowed to use their proper praise;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116180">Away with him;<stage xml:id="A18404_02-e116190">Exit Henry ▪</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116200" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116210">Away with him? live I? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116220"><pb facs="53"/>And here my life thus slighted? cursed man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116230">That ever the intelligensing lights</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116240">Betrayed me to men's whorish fellowships;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116250">To prince's moorish slaveries; to be made</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116260">The anvil, on which only blows, and wounds</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116270">Were made the seed, and wombs of others honours;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116280">A property for a tyrant, to set up,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116290">And puff down, with the vapour of his breath;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116300">Will you not kill me? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116310" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116320">No; we will not hurt you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116330">We are commanded only to conduct you</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116340">Into your lodging;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116350" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116360">To my lodging? where? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116370" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116380">Within the cabinet of arms my lord:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116390" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116400">What to a prison? Death; I will not go;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116410" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116420">We'll force you then;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116430" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116440">And take away my sword;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116450">A proper point of force; ye had as good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116460">Have robbed me of my soul; slaves of my stars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116470">Partial and bloody; oh that in mine eyes</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116480">Were all the sorcerous poison of my woes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116490">That I might witch ye headlong from your height,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116500">And trample of't, your execrable light. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116510" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116520">Come will you go my lord? this rage is vain;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116530" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116540">And so is all your grave authority;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116550">And that all France shall feel before I die;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116560">Ye see all how they use good Catholics;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116570" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116580">Farewell for ever; so have I deserved</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116590">An exhalation that would be a star</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116600">Fall when the sun forsook it, in a sink. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116610">Shoes ever overthrow that are too large,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116620">And hugest canons, burst with overcharge. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e116630">D'avuergne, Pralin, following with a guard.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116640" who="A18404_02-pralin">
            <speaker>Pra:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116650">My lord I have commandment from the King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116660">To charge you go with me, and ask your sword;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116670" who="A18404_02-d'aumale">
            <speaker>D' au:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116680">My sword, who fears it? it was ne'er the death</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116690">Of any but wild boars; I prithee take it;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116700"><pb facs="54"/> hadst thou advertised this when last we met,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116710">I had been in my bed, and fast asleep</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116720">Two hours ago ; lead; I'll go where thou wilt:<stage xml:id="A18404_02-e116730">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116740" who="A18404_02-vidame">
            <speaker>Vid:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116750">See how he bears his cross, with his small strength,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116760">On easier shoulders than the other Atlas. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116770" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116780">Strength to aspire, is still accompanied</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116790">With weakness to endure; all popular gifts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116800">Are colours, it will bear no vinegar;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116810">And rather to adverse affairs, betray;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116820">Thine arm against them; his state still his best</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116830">That hath most inward worth; and that's best tried,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116840">That neither glories, nor is glorified. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act_and_scene" xml:id="A18404_02-e116850">
          <head>Actus. 5. Scaena. 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e116860">Henry, Soissons, Janin, Descures, cum aliis.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116870" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116880">What shall we think (My lords) of these new forces</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116890">That (From the King of Spain) hath passed the Alps? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116900">For which (I think) his lord ambassador,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116910">Is come to court, to get their pass for Flanders? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e116920" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Ian:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116930">I think (My lord) they have no end for Flanders;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116940">Count Maurice being already entered Brabant</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116950">To pass to Flanders, to relieve Ostend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116960">And th'arch-duke full prepared to hinder him;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116970">And sure it is that they must measure forces,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116980">Which (Ere this new force could have passed the Alps)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e116990">Of force must be encountered. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e117000" who="A18404_02-soissons">
            <speaker>Soiss:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117010">'Tis unlikely,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117020">That their march hath so large an aim as Flanders;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e117030" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>Desc:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117040">As these times sort, they may have shorter reaches;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117050">That would pierce further;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e117060" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117070">I have been advertised,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117080">That count Fuentes (By whose means this army</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117090">Was lately levied; and whose hand was strong,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117100">In thrusting on Byron's conspiracy)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117110">Hath caused these cunning forces to advance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117120">With colour only to set down in Flanders;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117130">But hath intentional respect to favour</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117140"><pb facs="54"/> and countenance his false partisans in Bresse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117150">And friends in Burgundy; to give them heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117160">For the full taking of their hearts from me;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117170">Be as it will; we shall prevent their worst,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117180">And therefore call in Spain's ambassador,</l>
            <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e117190">Enter ambassador with others.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117200">What would the lord ambassador of Spain? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e117210" who="A18404_02-ambassador">
            <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117220">First (In my master's name) I would beseech</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117230">Your highness' hearty thought; that his true hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117240">(Held in your vowed amities) hath not touched,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117250">At any least point in Byron's offence;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117260">Nor once had notice of a crime so foul;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117270">Whereof, since he doubts not, you stand resolved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117280">He prays your leagues continuance in this favour;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117290">That the army he hath raised to march for Flanders,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117300">May have safe passage by your frontier towns,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117310">And find the river free, that runs by Rhone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e117320" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117330">My lord my frontiers shall not be disarmed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117340">Till, by arraignment of the Duke of Byron,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117350">My scruples are resolved; and I may know</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117360">In what account to hold your master's faith,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117370">For his observance of the league betwixt us;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117380">You wish me to believe that he is clear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117390">From all the projects caused by count Fuentes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117400">His special agent; but where, deeds, pull down,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117410">Words, may repair, no faith; I scarce can think</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117420">That his gold was so bounteously employed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117430">Without his special counsel, and command:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117440">These faint proceedings in our royal faiths,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117450">Make subjects prove so faithless: if because,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117460">We sit above the danger of the laws,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117470">We likewise lift our arms above their justice;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117480">And that our heavenly sovereign, bounds not us</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117490">In those religious confines; out of which</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117500">Our justice and our true laws are informed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117510">In vain have we expectance that our subjects,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117520">Should not as well presume to offend their earthly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117530">As we our heavenly sovereign? And this breach</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117540">Made in the forts of all society;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117550"><pb facs="55"/> of all celestial, and humane respects,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117560">Makes no strengths of our bounties, counsels arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117570">Hold out against their treasons; and the rapes</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117580">Made of humanity, and religion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117590">In all men's more than pagan liberties,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117600">Atheismes, and slaveries, will derive their springs</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117610">From their base presidents, copied out of Kings. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117620">But all this, shall not make me break the commerce,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117630">Authorised by our treaties; let your army</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117640">Take the directest pass, it shall go safe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e117650" who="A18404_02-ambassador">
            <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117660">So rest your highness ever; and assure</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117670">That my true sovereign, loathes all opposite thoughts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e117680" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117690">Are our dispatches made to all the Kings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117700">Princes, and potentates, of Christendom? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117710">Ambassadors and province governors,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117720">T'inform the truth of this conspiracy? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e117730" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Jan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117740">They all are made my lord, and some give out,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117750">That 'tis a blow given to religion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117760">To weaken it, in ruining of him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117770">That said, he never wished more glorious title,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117780">Then to be called the scourge of Hugenots. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e117790" who="A18404_02-soissons">
            <speaker>Soiss.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117800">Others that are like favourers of the fault,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117810">Said 'tis a politic advice from England,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117820">To break the feared javelins, both together ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e117830" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117840">Such shut their eyes to truth, we can but set</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117850">His lights before them, and his trumpet sound</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117860">Close to their ears; their partial wilfulness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117870">In resting blind, and deaf, or in perverting,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117880">What their most certain senses apprehend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117890">Shall naught discomfort our impartial justice. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117900">Nor clear the desperate fault that doth enforce it. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e117910">Enter Vyt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e117920" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vyt.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117930">The peers of France (My lord) refuse t'appear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117940">At the arraignment of the Duke Byron. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e117950" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117960">The court may yet proceed; and so command it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117970">'Tis not their slackness to appear shall serve,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117980">To let my will t'appear in any fact. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e117990">Wherein the boldest of them tempts my justice. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118000">I am resolved, and will no more endure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118010">To have my subjects make what I command,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118020"><pb facs="55"/> the subject of their oppositions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118030">Who evermore slack their allegiance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118040">As Kings forbear their penance; how sustain</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118050">Your prisoners their strange durance? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e118060" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118070">One of them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118080">(Which is the count D'auvergne) hath merry spirits,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118090">Eats well, and sleeps: and never can imagine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118100">That any place where he is, is a prison;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118110">Where on the other part, the Duke Byron,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118120">Entered his prison, as into his grave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118130">Rejects all food, sleeps not, nor once lies down:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118140">Fury hath armed his thoughts so thick with thorns,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118150">That rest can have no entry: he disdains</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118160">To grace the prison with the slenderest show,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118170">Of any patience, least men should conceive,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118180">He thought his sufferance in the best sort fit;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118190">And holds his bands so worthless of his worth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118200">That he impairs it, to vouchsafe to them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118210">The best part of the peace, that freedom owes it:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118220">That patience therein, is a willing slavery. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118230">And (Like the camel) stoops to take the load:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118240">So still he walks: or rather as a bird,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118250">Entered a closet, which unwares is made,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118260">His desperate prison (Being pursued) amazed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118270">And wrathful beats his breast from wall to wall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118280">Assaults the light strikes down himself, not our,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118290">And being taken, struggles, gasps, and bites,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118300">Takes all his takers strokings, to be strokes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118310">Abhorreth food, and with a savage will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118320">Frets, pines, and dies, for former liberty. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118330">So fares the wrathful Duke; and when the strength</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118340">Of these dumb rages, break out into sounds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118350">He breathes defiance ▪ to the world, and bids us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118360">Make ourselves drunk, with the remaining blood</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118370">Of five and thirty wounds received in fight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118380">For us and ours; for we shall never brag,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118390">That we have made his spirits check at death:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118400">This rage in walks and words; but in his looks</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118410"><pb facs="56"/> he cements all: and prints a world of books,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e118420" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118430">Let others learn by him to curb their spleens,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118440">Before they be curbed; and to cease their grudges:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118450">Now I am settled in my sun of height,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118460">The circular splendour, and full sphere of state. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118470">Take all place up from envy: as the sun,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118480">At height, and passive o'er the crowns of men,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118490">His beams diffused, and downright poured on them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118500">Cast but a little or no shade at all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118510">So he that is advanced above the heads,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118520">Of all his emulators, with high light,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118530">Prevents their envies, and deprives them quite,<stage xml:id="A18404_02-e118540">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e118550">Enter the chancellor, Harlay, potiers, Fleury, in scarlet gowns, Laffin, Descures, with other officers of state.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e118560" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118570">I wonder at the prisoners so long stay,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e118580" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Har:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118590">I think it may be made a question,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118600">If his impatience will let him come. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e118610" who="A18404_02-potiers">
            <speaker>Pot.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118620">Yes, he is now well stayed: time and his judgement,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118630">Have cast his passion and his fever of. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e118640" who="A18404_02-fleu">
            <speaker>Fleu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118650">His fever may be passed, but for his passions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118660">I fear me we shall find it spiced to hotly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118670">With his old powder. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e118680" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>Des.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118690">He is sure come forth;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118700">The carosse of the marquis of Rhosny</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118710">Conducted him along to th' arsenal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118720">Close to the riverside: and there I saw him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118730">Enter a barge covered with tapestry,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118740">In which the King's guards waited and received him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118750">Stand by there clear the place,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e118760" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118770">The prisoner comes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118780">My lord Laffin forbear your sight a while,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118790">It may incense the prisoner: who will know,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118800">By your attendance near us, that your hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118810">Was chief in his discovery; which as yet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118820">I think he doth not doubt,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e118830" who="A18404_02-labrun">
            <speaker>Laf.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118840">I will forbear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118850">Till your good pleasures call me,<stage xml:id="A18404_02-e118860">Exit Laf.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e118870" who="A18404_02-henry">
            <pb facs="56"/>
            <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118880">When he knows</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118890">And sees Laffin, accuse him to his face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118900">The court I think will shake with his distemper. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e118910">Enter Vitry, Byron, with others and a guard.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e118920" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118930">You see my lord, 'tis in the golden chamber. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e118940" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118950">The golden chamber? where the greatest Kings</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118960">Have thought them honoured to receive a place:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118970">And I have had it; am I come to stand</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118980">In rank and habit here of men arraigned,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e118990">Where I have sat assistant, and been honoured,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119000">With glorious title of the chiefest virtuous,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119010">Where the Kings chief solicitor hath said,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119020">There was in France, no man that ever lived,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119030">Whose parts were worth my imitation;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119040">That, but mine own worth; I could imitate none:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119050">And that I made myself inimitable,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119060">To all that could come after; whom this court</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119070">Hath seen to sit upon the flower de lice</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119080">In recompense of my renowned service. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119090">Must I be sat on now, by petty judges? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119100">These scarlet robes, that come to sit and fight</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119110">Against my life; dismay my valour more,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119120">Than all the bloody cassocks Spain hath brought</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119130">To field against it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119140" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119150">To the bar my lord. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e119160">He salutes, and stands to the bar.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119170" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Har.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119180">Read the indictment. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119190" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119200">Stay, I will invert</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119210">(For shortness' sake) the form of our proceedings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119220">And out of all the points, the process holds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119230">Collect five principal, with which we charge you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119240" who="A18404_02-xxxx_1">
            <speaker>1.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119250">First you conferred with one, called Picote,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119260">At Orleans born, and into Flanders fled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119270">To hold intelligence by him with the archduke,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119280">And for two voyages to that effect,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119290">Bestowed on him, five hundred, fifty crowns. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119300" who="A18404_02-xxxx_2">
            <speaker>2.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119310">Next you held treaty with the Duke of Savoy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119320">Without the King's permission; offering him</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119330">All service and assistance 'gainst all men,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119340"><pb facs="57"/> in hope to have in marriage, his third daughter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119350" who="A18404_02-xxxx_3">
            <speaker>3.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119360">Thirdly you held intelligence with the Duke,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119370">At taking in of Bourge, and other forts;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119380">Advising him, with all your prejudice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119390">'Gainst the King's army, and his royal person. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119400" who="A18404_02-xxxx_4">
            <speaker>4.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119410">The fourth is; that you would have brought the King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119420">Before saint Katherine's fort, to be there slain:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119430">And to that end writ to the governor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119440">In which you gave him notes to know his highness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119450" who="A18404_02-xxxx_5">
            <speaker>5.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119460">Fiftly, you sent Laffin to treat with Savoy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119470">And with the count Fuentes, of more plots,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119480">Touching the ruin of the King and realm. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119490" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119500">All this (My lord) I answer, and deny:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119510">And first for Picoté; he was my prisoner,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119520">And therefore I might well confer with him:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119530">But that our conference tended to the archduke,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119540">Is nothing so; I only did employ him</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119550">To captain la fortune, for the reduction</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119560">Of Seurre, to the service of the King. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119570">Who used such speedy diligence therein,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119580">That shortly 'twas assured his majesty,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119590" who="A18404_02-xxxx_2">
            <speaker>2.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119600">Next, for my treaties with the Duke of Savoy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119610">Roncas his secretary, having made</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119620">A motion to me, for the Duke's third daughter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119630">I told it to the King; who having since,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119640">Given me the understanding by la force</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119650">Of his dislike; I never dreamt of it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119660" who="A18404_02-xxxx_3">
            <speaker>3.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119670">Thirdly, for my intelligence with the Duke,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119680">Advising him against his highness' army:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119690">Had this been true, I had not undertaken</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119700">Th'assault of Bourg, against the King's opinion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119710">Having assistance but by them about me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119720">And (Having won it for him) had not been</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119730">Put out of such a government so easily. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119740" who="A18404_02-xxxx_4">
            <speaker>4.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119750">Fourthly, for my advice to kill the King;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119760">I would beseech his highness' memory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119770">Not to let slip, that I alone dissuaded</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119780">His viewing of that fort; informing him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119790"><pb facs="57"/> it had good marke-men; and he could not go,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119800">But in exceeding danger, which advice</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119810">Diverted him; the rather, since I said,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119820">That if he had desire to see the place</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119830">He should receive from me a plot of it;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119840">Offering to take it with five hundred men,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119850">And I myself would go to the assault. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119860" who="A18404_02-xxxx_5">
            <speaker>5.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119870">And lastly, for intelligences held,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119880">With Savoy and Fuentes: I confess,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119890">That being denied to keep the citadel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119900">Which with incredible peril I had got,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119910">And seeing another, honoured with my spoils,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119920">I 〈◊〉 so desperate that I found my spirit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119930">Enraged to any act, and wished myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119940">Covered with blood. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119950" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119960">With whose blood? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e119970" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119980">With mine own;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e119990">Wishing to live no longer, being denied,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120000">With such suspicion of me, and set will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120010">To rack my furious humour into blood. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120020">And for two months space, I did speak, and wright,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120030">More than I ought; but have done ever well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120040">And therefore your informers have been false. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120050">And (With intent to tyrannize) suborned. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120060" who="A18404_02-fleu">
            <speaker>Flen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120070">What if our witnesses come face to face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120080">And justify much more than we allege? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120090" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120100">They must be hirelings then, and men corrupted. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120110" who="A18404_02-potiers">
            <speaker>Pot.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120120">What think you of la fin? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120130" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120140">I hold la fin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120150">An honoured gentleman, my friend and kinsman. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120160" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Har.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120170">If he then aggravate, what we affirm,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120180">With greater accusations to your face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120190">What will you say? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120200" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120210">I know it cannot be. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120220" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120230">Call in my lord la fin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120240" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120250">Is he so near? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120260">And kept so close from me? can all the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120270">Make him a treacher. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e120280">Enter la fin.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120290" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <pb facs="58"/>
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120300">I suppose my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120310">You have not stood within; without the ear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120320">Of what hath here been urged against the Duke;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120330">If you have heard it, and upon your knowledge</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120340">Can witness all is true, upon your soul;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120350">Utter your knowledge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120360" who="A18404_02-laffin">
            <speaker>Laf●●. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120370">I have heard my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120380">All that hath passed here; and upon my soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120390">(Being charged so urgently in such a court)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120400">Upon my knowledge I affirm all true;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120410">And so much more: as had the prisoner lives</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120420">As many as his years, would make all forfeit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120430" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120440">O all ye virtuous powers, in earth and heaven,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120450">That have not put on hellish flesh and blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120460">From whence these monstrous issues are produced,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120470">That cannot bear in execrable concord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120480">And one prodigious subject; contraries;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120490">Nor (As the I'll that of the world admire)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120500">Is severed from the world) can cut yourselves</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120510">From the consent and sacred harmony</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120520">Of life, yet live; of honour, yet be honoured;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120530">As this extravagant, and errant rogue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120540">From all your fair decorums, and just laws,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120550">Finds power to do: and like a loathsome wen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120560">Sticks to the face of nature, and this court;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120570">Thicken this air, and turn your plaguy rage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120580">Into a shape as dismal as his sin. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120590">And with some equal horror tear him of</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120600">From sight and memory: let not such a court,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120610">To whose fame all the Kings of Christendom,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120620">Now laid their ears; so crack her royal trump,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120630">As to sound through it, that here vaunted justice</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120640">Was got in such an incest: is it justice</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120650">To tempt, and witch a man, to break the law,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120660">And by that witch condemn him? let me draw</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120670">Poison into me with this cursed air,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120680">If he bewitched me, and transformed me not;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120690">He bit me by the ear, and made me drink</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120700"><pb facs="58"/> enchanted waters; let me see an image</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120710">That uttered these distinct words; thou shalt die,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120720">Oh wicked King; and if the devil gave him</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120730">Such power upon an image; upon me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120740">How might he tyrannize? that by his vows</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120750">And oaths so Stygian, had my nerves and will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120760">In more awe than his own: what man is he</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120770">That is so high, but he would higher be? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120780">So roundly sighted, but he may be found,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120790">To have a blind side, which by craft, pursued,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120800">Confederacy, and simply trusted treason,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120810">May wrest him passed his angel, and his reason? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120820" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120830">Witchcraft can never taint an honest mind. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120840" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Harl.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120850">True gold, will any trial stand, untouched. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120860" who="A18404_02-potiers">
            <speaker>Pot.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120870">For colours that will stain when they are tried,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120880">The cloth itself is ever cast aside. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e120890" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120900">Sometimes, the very gloss in any thing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120910">Will seem a stain; the fault not in the light,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120920">Nor in the guilty object, but our sight. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120930">My gloss, raised from the richness of my stuff,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120940">Had too much splendour for the owly eye,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120950">Of politic and thankless royalty:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120960">I did deserve too much; a pleurisy</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120970">Of that blood in me is the cause I die. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120980">Virtue in great men must be small and sleight:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e120990">For poor stars rule, where she is exquisite,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121000">'Tis tyrannous, and impious policy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121010">To put to death by fraud and treachery;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121020">Sleight is then royal, when it makes men live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121030">And if it urge faults, urgeth to forgive. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121040">He must be guiltless, that condemns the guilty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121050">Like things, do nourish like, and not destroy them:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121060">Minds must be sound, that judge affairs of weight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121070">And seeing hands, cut corrosives from your sight. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121080">A lord intelligencer? hangman-like,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121090">Thrust him from human fellowship, to the deserts</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121100">Blow him with curses; shall your justice call</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121110">Treachery her father? would you wish her weigh</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121120"><pb facs="59"/> my valour with the hiss of such a viper? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121130">What I have done to shun the mortal shame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121140">Of so unjust an opposition;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121150">My envious stars cannot deny me this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121160">That I may make my judge's witnesses;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121170">And that my wretched fortunes have reserved</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121180">For my last comfort; ye all know (My lords)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121190">This body gashed with five and thirty wounds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121200">Whose life and death you have in your award,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121210">Holds not a vein that hath not opened been,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121220">And which I would not open yet again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121230">For you and yours; this hand that writ the lines</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121240">Alleged against me; hath enacted still,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121250">More good than there it only talked of ill. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121260">I must confess my choler hath transferred</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121270">My tender spleen to all intemperate speech:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121280">But reason ever did my deeds attend. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121290">In worth of praise, and imitation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121300">Had I born any will to let them lose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121310">I could have fleshed them with bad services,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121320">In England lately, and in Switzerland:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121330">There are a hundred gentlemen by name,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121340">Can witness my demeanour in the first;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121350">And in the last ambassage I adjure</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121360">No other testimonies than the seigneurs</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121370">De Vio, and Sillerie; who amply know,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121380">In what sort, and with what fidelity</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121390">I bore myself; to reconcile and knit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121400">In one desire so many wills disjoined,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121410">And from the King's allegiance quite withdrawn. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121420">My acts ask many men, though done by one. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121430">And I were but one, I stood for thousands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121440">And still I hold my worth, though not my place:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121450">Nor sleight me, judges, though I be but one,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121460">One man, in one sole expedition,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121470">Reduced into th'imperial power of Rome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121480">Armenia, Pontus, and Arabia, Syria, Albania, and Iberia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121490">Conquered th'hyrcanians; and to Caucasus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121500">His arm extended; the Numidians</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121510"><pb facs="59"/> and Afrique to the shores meridional,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121520">His power subjected; and that part of Spain</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121530">Which stood from those parts that Sertorius ruled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121540">Even to the Atlantic sea he conquered. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121550">Th'albanian Kings, he from the kingdoms chased,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121560">And at the Caspian sea, their dwellings placed:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121570">Of all the earth's globe, by power and his advice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121580">The round-eyed ocean saw him victor thrice:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121590">And what shall let me (But your cruel doom,)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121600">To add as much to France, as he to Rome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121610">And to leave justice neither sword nor word,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121620">To use against my life; this senate knows,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121630">That what with one victorious hand I took,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121640">I gave to all your uses, with another:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121650">With this I took, and propped the falling kingdom,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121660">And gave it to the King: I have kept</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121670">Your laws of state from fire; and you yourselves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121680">Fixed in this high tribunal; from whose height</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121690">The vengeful saturnals of the league</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121700">Had hurled ye headlong; do ye then return</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121710">This retribution? can the cruel King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121720">The kingdom, laws, and you, (All saved by me)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121730">Destroy their saver? what (Ay me) I did</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121740">Adverse to this; this damned enchanter did,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121750">That took into his will, my motion;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121760">And being bankrupt both of wealth and worth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121770">Pursued with quarrels, and with suits in law;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121780">Feared by the kingdom; threatened by the King;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121790">Would raise the loathed dunghill of his ruins,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121800">Upon the monumental heap of mine:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121810">Torn with possessed whirlwinds may he die,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121820">And dogs bark at his murderous memory,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e121830" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121840">My lord, our liberal sufferance of your speech,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121850">Hath made it late; and for this session,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121860">We will dismiss you; take him back my lord. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e121870">Exit Vit. and Byron.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e121880" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Har</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121890">You likewise may depart. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e121900">Exit Laffin.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e121910" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121920">What resteth now</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121930">To be decreed 'gainst this great prisoner? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121940">A mighty merit, and a monstrous cri●●,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121950"><pb facs="60"/> are here concurrent; what by witnesses;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121960">His letters and instructions, we have proved</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121970">Himself confesseth, and excuseth all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121980">With witchcraft, and the only act of thought. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e121990">For witchcraft I esteem it a mere strength</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122000">Of rage in him conceived 'gainst his accuser;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122010">Who being examined hath denied it all;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122020">Suppose it true, it made him false; but wills</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122030">And worthy minds, witchcraft can never force. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122040">And for his thoughts that broke not into deeds;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122050">Time was the cause, not will; the minds free act</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122060">In treason still is judged as th'outward fact. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122070">If his deserts have had a wealthy share,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122080">In saving of our land from civil furies:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122090">Manlius had so that fast the Capitol;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122100">Yet for his after traitorous factions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122110">They threw him headlong from the place he saved. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122120">My definite sentence then, doth this import:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122130">That we must quench the wildfire with his blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122140">In which it was so traitorously inflamed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122150">Unless with it, we seek to incense the land,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122160">The King can have no refuge for his life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122170">If his be quit: this was it that made</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122180">Lewis th'eleventh renounce his countrymen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122190">And call the valiant Scots out of their kingdom,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122200">To use their greater virtues, and their faiths,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122210">Than his own subjects, in his royal guard:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122220">What then conclude your censures? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e122230" who="A18404_02-omnes">
            <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122240">He must die. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e122250" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122260">Draw then his sentence, formally, and send him;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122270">And so all treasons in his death attend him. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e122280">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e122290">Enter Byron, Espernon, Soisson Janin, Vidame, Descures.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e122300" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122310">I joy you had so good a day my lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e122320" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122330">I won it from them all: the chancellor</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122340">I answered to his uttermost improvements:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122350">I moved my other judges to lament</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122360">My insolent misfortunes; and to loath</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122370"><pb facs="60"/> the pocky soul, and state-bawd, my accuser,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122380">I made reply to all that could be said,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122390">So eloquently, and with such a charm,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122400">Of grave enforcements, that methought I sat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122410">Like Orpheus casting reigns on savage beasts;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122420">At the arms end (As 'twere) I took my bar</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122430">And set it far above the high tribunal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122440">Where like a cedar on mount Lebanon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122450">I grew, and made my judges show like boxtrees ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122460">And boxtrees right, their wishes would have made them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122470">Whence boxes should have grown, till they had struck</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122480">My head into the budget: but alas,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122490">I held their bloody arms, with such strong reasons;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122500">And (By your leave) with such a ●yrck of wit:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122510">That I fetched blood upon the chancellor's cheeks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122520">Methinks I see his countenance as he sat;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122530">And the most lawyerly delivery</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122540">Of his set speeches: shall I play his part? <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e122550">Enter soiss: Espa</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e122560" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122570">For heaven's sake, good my lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e122580" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122590">I will i'faith,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122600">Behold a wicked man: a man debauched,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122610">A man, contesting with his King; a man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122620">On whom (My lords) we are not to connive,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122630">Though we may condole: a man:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122640">That laesa maiestate sought a lease,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122650">Of plus quam satis. A man that vi et armis</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122660">Assailed the King; and would per fas et nefas,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122670">Aspire the kingdom: here was lawyer's learning. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e122680" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122690">He said not this my lord, that I have heard. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e122700" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122710">This or the like, I swear ▪ I pen no speeches. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e122720" who="A18404_02-soissons">
            <speaker>Soiss.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122730">Then there is good hope of your wished acquittal. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e122740" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122750">Acquittal? they have reason; were I dead</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122760">I know they can not all supply my place;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122770">Is't possible the King should be so vain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122780">To think he can shake me with fear of death? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122790">Or make me apprehend that he intends it? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122800">Thinks he to make his firmest men, his clouds? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122810">The clouds (Observing their aerial natures)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122820">Are born aloft, and then to moisture hanged,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122830"><pb facs="61"/> fall to the earth; where being made thick, and cold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122840">They lose both all their heat, and levity;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122850">Yet then again recovering heat and lightness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122860">Again they are advanced: and by the sun</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122870">Made fresh and glorious; and since clouds are rapt</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122880">With these uncertainties: now up, now down,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122890">Am I to flit so with his smile, or frown? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e122900" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122910">I wish your comforts, and encouragements,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122920">May spring out of your safety; but I hear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122930">The King hath reasoned so against your life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122940">And made your most friends yield so to his reasons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122950">That your estate is fearful. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e122960" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122970">Yield to his reasons? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122980">O how friends reasons, and their freedoms stretch,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e122990">When power sets his wide tenters to their sides! </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123000">How, like a cure, by mere opinion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123010">It works upon our blood? like th' ancient gods</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123020">Are modern Kings, that lived passed bounds themselves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123030">Yet set a measure down, to wretched men ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123040">By many sophisms, they made good, deceit;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123050">And, since they passed in power, surpassed, in right:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123060">When Kings wills pass; the stars wink, and the sun,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123070">Suffers eclipse: rude thunder yields to them</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123080">His horrid wings: sits smooth as glass engazd,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123090">And lightning sticks twixt heaven and earth amazed:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123100">Men's faiths are shaken: and the pit of truth</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123110">O'erflows with darkness, in which justice sits,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123120">And keeps her vengeance tied to make it fierce;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123130">And when it comes, th' increased horrors show,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123140">Heaven's plague is sure, though full of state, and slow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123150" who="A18404_02-unassigned">
            <speaker>Sist.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123160">O my dear lord and brother,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123170">Oh the Duke? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123180" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123190">What sounds are these my lord? hark, hark, methinks </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123200">I hear the cries of people. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123210" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123220">'Tis for one,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123230">Wounded in fight here at saint Anthony's gate:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123240" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123250">Sfoot, one cried the Duke. I pray hearken,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123260">Again, or burst yourselves with silence, no:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123270">What countryman's the common headsman here? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123280" who="A18404_02-soissons">
            <pb facs="61"/>
            <speaker>Soiss.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123290">He's a Bourgonian. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123300" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123310">The great devil he is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123320">The bitter wizard told me, a Burgonian,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123330">Should be my headsman; strange concurrences:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123340">'Sdeath who's here? <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e123350">Enter 4. Ushers bare, Chanc: har: Pol: fleur: Vit: Pralin, with others. </stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123360">O then I am but dead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123370">Now, now ye come all to pronounce my sentence. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123380">I am condemned unjustly: tell my kinsfolks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123390">I die an innocent:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123400">If any friend pity the ruin of the state's sustainer</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123410">Proclaim my innocence; ah lord chancellor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123420">Is there no pardon? will there come no mercy? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123430">Ay, put your hat on, and let me stand bare,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123440">Show yourself right a lawyer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123450" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123460">I am bare,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123470">What would you have me do? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123480" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123490">You have not done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123500">Like a good justice; and one that knew</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123510">He sat upon the precious blood of virtue;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123520">You've pleased the cruel King, and have not born,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123530">As great regard to save as to condemn;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123540">You have condemned me, my lord chancellor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123550">But God acquits me; he will open lay</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123560">All your close treasons against him, to colour</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123570">Treasons laid to his truest images;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123580">And you my lord shall answer this injustice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123590">Before his judgement seat: to which I summon</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123600">In one year and a day your hot appearance;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123610">I go before, by men's corrupted domes;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123620">But they that caused my death, shall after come</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123630">By the immaculate justice of the highest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123640" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123650">Well, good my lord ▪ commend your soul to him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123660">And to his mercy, think of that, I pray. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123670" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123680">Sir, I have thought of it, and every hour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123690">Since my affliction, asked on naked knees</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123700">Patience to bear your unbelieved injustice:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123710">But you, nor none of you have thought of him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123720">In my eviction: you're come to your benches,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123730">With plotted judgements; your linked ears so loud,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123740"><pb facs="62"/> sing with prejudicate winds, that naught is heard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123750">Of all, poor prisoners urge 'gainst your award;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123760" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Har.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123770">Passion, my lord, transports your bitterness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123780">Beyond all colour; and your proper judgement:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123790">No man hath known your merits more than I;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123800">And would to God your great misdeeds had been,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123810">As much undone, as they have been concealed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123820">The cries of them for justice (In desert)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123830">Have been so loud and piercing; that they deafened</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123840">The ears of mercy; and have laboured more,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123850">Your judges to compress then to enforce them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123860" who="A18404_02-potiers">
            <speaker>Pot.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123870">We bring you here your sentence, will you read it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123880" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123890">For heaven's sake, shame to use me with such rigor;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123900">I know what it imports, and will not have,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123910">Mine ear blown into flames with hearing it;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123920">Have you been one of them that have condemned me? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123930" who="A18404_02-fleu">
            <speaker>Flen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123940">My lord I am your orator: God comfort you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e123950" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123960">Good sir, my father loved you so entirely,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123970">That if you have been one, my soul forgives you;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123980">It is the King (Most childish that he is</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e123990">That takes what he hath given) that injures me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124000">He gave grace in the first draught of my fault,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124010">And now restains it: grace again I ask;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124020">Let him again vouchsafe it: send to him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124030">A post will soon return: the Queen of England,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124040">Told me that if the wilful Earl of Essex,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124050">Had used submission, and but asked her mercy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124060">She would have given it, past resumption;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124070">She (Like a gracious Princess) did desire</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124080">To pardon him: even as she prayed to God,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124090">He would let down a pardon unto her;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124100">He yet was guilty, I am innocent:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124110">He still refused grace, I importune it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e124120" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124130">This asked in time (My lord) while he besought it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124140">And ere he had made his severity known,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124150">Had (With much joy to him) I know been granted;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e124160" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124170">No, no, his bounty, then was misery,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124180">To offer when he knew 'twould be refused;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124190"><pb facs="62"/> he treads the vulgar path of all advantage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124200">And loves men, for his vices, nor for their virtues;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124210">My service would have quickened gratitude,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124220">In his own death, had he been truly royal;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124230">It would have stirred the image of a King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124240">Into perpetual motion; to have stood</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124250">Near the conspiracy restrained at Nantes;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124260">And in a danger, that had then the wolf,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124270">To fly upon his bosom, had I only held</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124280">Intelligence with the conspirators;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124290">Who stuck at no check but my loyalty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124300">Nor kept life in their hopes, but in my death;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124310">The siege of Amiens, would have softened rocks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124320">Where covered all in showers of shot and fire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124330">I seemed to all men's eyes a fighting flame</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124340">With bullets cut, in fashion of a man;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124350">A sacrifice to valour (Impious King)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124360">Which he will needs extinguish, with my blood;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124370">Let him beware, justice will fall from heaven,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124380">In the same form I served in that siege,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124390">And by the light of that, he shall decern,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124400">What good, my ill hath brought him; it will nothing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124410">Assure his state: the same quench he hath cast</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124420">Upon my life, shall quite put out his fame;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124430">This day he loseth, what he shall not find,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124440">By all days he survives; so good a servant,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124450">Nor Spain so great a foe; with whom, alas,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124460">Because I treated am I put to death? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124470">'Tis put a politic gloze: my courage raised me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124480">For the dear price of five and thirty scars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124490">And that hath ruined me, I thank my stars ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124500">Come I'll go where ye will, ye shall not lead me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e124510" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124520">I fear his frenzy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124530">Never saw I man of such a spirit so amazed at death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e124540" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Har.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124550">He alters every minute: what a vapour? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124560">The strongest mind is to a storm of crosses. <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e124570">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e124580">Manent Esper: Soisson: Janin: Vidame, D'escures.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e124590" who="A18404_02-espernon">
            <speaker>Esp:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124600">O of what contraries consists a man! </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124610">Of what impossible mixtures? vice and virtue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124620"><pb facs="63"/> corruption, and eternness, at one time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124630">And in one subject, let together, lose? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124640">We have not any strength but weakens us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124650">No greatness but doth crush us into air. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124660">Our knowledges, do light us but to err,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124670">Our ornaments are burdens: our delights</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124680">Are our tormentors; fiends that (Raised in fears)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124690">At parting shake our roofs about our ears. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e124700" who="A18404_02-soissons">
            <speaker>Soi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124710">O virtue, thou art now far worse than fortune ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124720">Her gifts stuck by the Duke, when thine are vanished,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124730">Thou brav'st thy friend in need: necessity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124740">That used to keep thy wealth, contempt, thy love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124750">Have both abandoned thee in his extremes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124760">Thy powers are shadows, and thy comfort, dreams,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e124770" who="A18404_02-vidame">
            <speaker>Vid.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124780">O real goodness if thou be a power! </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124790">And not a word alone, in human uses,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124800">Appear out of this angry conflagration,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124810">Where this great captain (Thy late temple) burns,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124820">And turn his vicious fury to thy flame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124830">From all earth's hopes mere guilded with thy fame:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124840">Let piety enter with her willing cross,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124850">And take him on it; open his breast and arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124860">To all the storms, necessity can breathe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124870">And burst them all with his embraced death,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e124880" who="A18404_02-janin">
            <speaker>Ian,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124890">Yet are the civil tumults of his spirits,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124900">Hot and outrageous: not resolved, alas,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124910">(Being but one man) render the kingdom's dome;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124920">He doubts storms, threatens, rues, complains, implores,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124930">Grief hath brought all his forces to his looks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124940">And naught is left to strengthen him within,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124950">Nor lasts one habit of those grieved aspects:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124960">Blood expels paleness, paleness blood doth chase,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124970">And sorrow errs through all forms in his face,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e124980" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>Des.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e124990">So furious is he, that the politic law,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125000">Is much to seek, how to enact her sentence:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125010">Authority backed with arms, (Though he unarmed)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125020">Abhors his fury, and with doubtful eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125030">Views on what ground it should sustain his ruins,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125040"><pb facs="63"/> and as a savage boar that (Hunted long,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125050">Assailed and set up) with his only eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125060">Swimming in fire keeps of the baying hounds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125070">Though sunk himself, yet holds his anger up,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125080">And snows it forth in foam; holds firm his stand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125090">Of battalous bristles: feeds his hate to die,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125100">And whets his tusks with wrathful majesty. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125110">So fares the furious Duke, and with his looks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125120">Doth teach death horrors; makes the hangman learn</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125130">New habits for his bloody impudence;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125140">Which now habitual horror from him drives,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125150">Who for his life shuns death, by which he lives,</l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e125160">Enter chancellor, Harlay, Potier, Fleury, Vitry.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125170" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125180">Will not your lordship have the Duke distinguished</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125190">From other prisoners? where the order is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125200">To give up men condemned into the hands</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125210">Of th' executioner; he would be the death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125220">Of him that he should die by, ere he suffered,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125230">Such an abjection,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125240" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125250">But to bind his hands ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125260">I hold it passing needful,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125270" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Har.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125280">'Tis my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125290">And very dangerous to bring him lose. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125300" who="A18404_02-pralin">
            <speaker>Pra:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125310">You will in all despair and fury plunge him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125320">If you but offer it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125330" who="A18404_02-potiers">
            <speaker>Pot.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125340">My lord by this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125350">The prisoner's spirit is something pacified,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125360">And 'tis a fear that th'offer of those bands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125370">Would breed fresh furies in him, and disturb,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125380">The entry of his soul into her peace,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125390" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125400">I would not that, for any possible danger,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125410">That can be wrought, by his unarmed hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125420">And therefore in his own form bring him in,</l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18404_02-e125430">Enter Byron, a Bishop or two; with all the guards, soldiers with muskets.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125440" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125450">Where shall this weight fall? on what region,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125460">Must this declining prominent pour his load? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125470">I'll break my bloods high billows 'gainst my stars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125480">Before this will be shaken into a flat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125490"><pb facs="64"/> all France shall feel an earthquake; with what murmur,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125500">This world shrinks into chaos? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125510" who="A18404_02-bishop">
            <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125520">Good my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125530">Forgo it willingly; and now resign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125540">Your sensual powers entirely to your soul. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125550" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125560">Horror of death, let me alone in peace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125570">And leave my soul to me, whom it concerns;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125580">You have no charge of it; I feel her free,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125590">How she doth rouse, and like a falcon stretch</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125600">Her silver wings; as threatening death, with death;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125610">At whom I joyfully will cast her off:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125620">I know this body but a sink of folly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125630">The groundwork, and raised frame of woe and frailty ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125640">The bond, and bundle of corruption;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125650">A quick corpse, only sensible of grief,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125660">A walking sepulchre, or household thief:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125670">A glass of air, broken with less than breath,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125680">A slave bound face to face, to death, till death:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125690">And what said all you more? I know, besides</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125700">That life is but a dark and stormy night,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125710">Of senseless dreams, terrors, and broken sleeps;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125720">A tyranny, devising pains to plague</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125730">And make man long in dying, racks his death;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125740">And death is nothing, what can you say more? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125750">I bring a long globe, and a little earth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125760">Am seated like earth betwixt both the heavens:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125770">That if I rise; to heaven I rise; if fall</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125780">I likewise fall to heaven; what stronger faith,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125790">Hath any of your souls? what say you more? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125800">Why lose I time in these things? talk of knowledge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125810">It serves for inward use. I will not die</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125820">Like to a clergy man; but like the captain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125830">That prayed on horseback and with sword in hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125840">Threatened the sun, commanding it to stand;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125850">These are but ropes of sand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125860" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125870">Desire you then,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125880">To speak with any man? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125890" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125900">I would speak with la force, and saint Blancart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125910" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <pb facs="64"/>
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125920">Do they fly me? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125930">Where is provost, controller of my house? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125940" who="A18404_02-pralin">
            <speaker>Pra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125950">Gone to his house ith' country three days since. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e125960" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125970">He should have stayed here, he keeps all my blanks ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125980">Oh all the world forsakes me! wretched world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e125990">Consisting most of parts, that fly each other:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126000">A firmness, breeding all inconstancy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126010">A bond of all disjunction; like a man</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126020">Long buried, is a man that long hath lived;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126030">Touch him, he falls to ashes; for one fault,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126040">I forfeit all the fashion of a man;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126050">Why should I keep my soul in this dark light? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126060">Whose black beams lighted me to lose myself. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126070">When I have lost my arms, my fame, my wind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126080">Friends, brother, hopes, fortunes, and even my fury? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126090">O happy were the man, could live alone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126100">To know no man, nor be of any known! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126110" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Har.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126120">My lord, it is the manner once again</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126130">To read the sentence? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126140" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126150">Yet more sentences? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126160">How often will ye make me suffer death? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126170">As ye were proud to hear your powreful domes? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126180">I know and feel you were the men that gave it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126190">And die most cruelly to hear so often</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126200">My crimes and bitter condemnation urged:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126210">Suffice it, I am brought here; and obey,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126220">And that all here are privy to the crimes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126230" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126240">It must be read my lord, no remedy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126250" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126260">Read, if it must be, then, and I must talk. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126270" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Harl.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126280">The process being extraordinarily made and examined by the court, and chambers assembled —</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126290" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126300">Condemned for depositions of a witch? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126310">The common deposition, and her whore</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126320">To all whorish perjuries and treacheries. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126330">Sure he called up the devil in my spirits,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126340">And made him to usurp my faculties:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126350">Shall I be cast away now he's cast out? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126360">What justice is in this? dear countrymen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126370"><pb facs="65"/> take this true evidence, betwixt heaven and you ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126380">And quit me in your hearts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126390" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Ch●. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126400">Go on. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126410" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Har.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18404_02-e126420">Against Charles Gentalt of Byron: knight of both the orders; Duke of Byron, peer and marshal of France; governor of Burgundy, accused of treason in a sentence was given the 22. of this month, condemning the said Duke of Byron of heigh treason, for his direct conspiracies against the King's person; enterprises against his state. —</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126430" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126440">That is most false; let me for ever be,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126450">Deprived of heaven, as I shall be of earth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126460">If it be true: know worthy countrymen. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126470">These two and twenty months I have been clear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126480">Of all attempts against the King and state. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126490" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Har.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18404_02-e126500">Treaties and treacheries with his enemies, being marshal of the King's army, for reparation of which crimes they deprived him of all his estates, honours and dignities, and condemned him to lose his head upon a scaffold at the greave</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126510" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126520">The greave? had that place stood for my dispatch</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126530">I had not yielded; all your forces should not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126540">Stir me one foot; wild horses should have drawn,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126550">My body piecemeal, ere you all had brought me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126560" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Har.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18404_02-e126570">Declaring all his goods movable and immoveable whatsoever to be confiscate to the King: the signory of Byron to lose the title of duchy and peer for ever.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126580" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18404_02-e126590">Now is your form contented,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126600" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126610">I my lord</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126620">And I must now entreat you to deliver,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126630">Your order up, the King demands it of you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126640" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126650">And I restore it, with my vow of safety,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126660">In that world, where both he and I are one,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126670">I never broke the oath I took to take it,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126680" who="A18404_02-chancelor">
            <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126690">We'll now my lord we'll take our latest leaves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126700">Beseeching heaven to take as clear from you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126710">All sense of torment in your willing death:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126720">All love and thought of what you must leave here,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126730">As when you shall aspire heaven's highest sphere,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126740" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126750">Thanks to your lordship and let me pray to,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126760">That you will hold good censure of my life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126770"><pb facs="65"/> by the clear witness of my soul in death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126780">That I have never passed act 'gainst the King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126790">Which if my faith had let me undertake,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126800">They had been three years since, amongst the dead;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126810" who="A18404_02-harlay">
            <speaker>Harl:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126820">Your soul shall find his safety in her own,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126830">Call the executioner ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126840" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126850">Good sir I pray,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126860">Go after and beseech the chancellor</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126870">That he will let my body be interred,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126880">Amongst my predecessors at Byron:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126890" who="A18404_02-d'escures">
            <speaker>Desc:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126900">I go my lord:<stage xml:id="A18404_02-e126910">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e126920" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126930">Go, go? can all go thus? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126940">And no man come with comfort? farewell world:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126950">He is at no end of his actions blessed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126960">Whose ends will make him greatest, and not best;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126970">They tread no ground, but ride in air on storms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126980">That follow state, and hunt their empty forms;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e126990">Who see not that the valleys of the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127000">Make even right with the mountains? that they grow</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127010">Green, and lie warmer; and ever peaceful are,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127020">When clouds spit fire as hills, and burn them bare? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127030">Not valleys part, but we should imitate streams,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127040">That run below the valleys, and do yield</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127050">To every molehill; every bank embrace</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127060">That cheques their currants; and when torrents come,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127070">That swell and raise them passed their natural height,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127080">How mad they are, and troubled? like low strains</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127090">With torrents crowned, are men with diadems;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127100" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127110">My lord 'tis late; wilt please you to go up? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127120" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127130">Up? 'tis a fair preferment, ha ha ha,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127140">There should go shouts to up-shots; not a breath</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127150">Of any mercy, yet? come, since we must;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127160">Who's this? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127170" who="A18404_02-pralin">
            <speaker>Pral:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127180">The executioner, my lord;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127190" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127200">Death slave, down, or by the blood that moves me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127210">I'll pluck thy throat out; go, I'll call you straight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127220">Hold boy; and this,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127230" who="A18404_02-hangman">
            <speaker>Hang:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127240">Soft boy I'll bar you that</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127250" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127260">Take this then, yet I pray thee, that again</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127270"><pb facs="66"/> I do not joy in sight of such a pageant</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127280">As presents death; though this life have a curse;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127290">'Tis better than another, that is worse;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127300" who="A18404_02-bishop">
            <speaker>Arch:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127310">My lord, now you are blind to this world's sight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127320">Look upward to a world of endless light;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127330" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127340">Ay, ay, you talk of upward still to others,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127350">And downwards look, with headlong eyes yourselves. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127360">Now come you up sir; but not touch me yet;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127370">Where shall I be now? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127380" who="A18404_02-hangman">
            <speaker>Hang:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127390">Here my lord;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127400" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127410">Where's that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127420" who="A18404_02-hangman">
            <speaker>Hang:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127430">There, there, my lord;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127440" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127450">And where, slave, is that there? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127460">Thou seest I see not? yet I speak as I saw;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127470">Well, now is't fit? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127480" who="A18404_02-hangman">
            <speaker>Hang:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127490">Kneel, I beseech your grace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127500">That I may do mine office with most order;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127510" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127520">Do it, and if at one blow thou art short,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127530">Give one and thirty, I'll endure them all. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127540">Hold; stay a little; comes there yet no mercy? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127550">High heaven curse these exemplary proceedings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127560">When justice fails, they sacrifice our example;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127570" who="A18404_02-hangman">
            <speaker>Hang:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127580">Let me beseech you, I may cut your hair;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127590" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127600">Out ugly image of my cruel justice;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127610">Yet wilt thou be before me, stay my will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127620">Or by the will of heaven I'll strangle thee;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127630" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127640">My lord you make to much of this your body,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127650">Which is no more your own;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127660" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127670">Nor is it yours;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127680">I'll take my death, with all the horrid rites</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127690">And representments, of the dread it merits;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127700">Let tame nobility, and numbed fools</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127710">That apprehend not what they undergo,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127720">Be such exemplary, and formal sheep;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127730">I will not have him touch me, till I will;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127740">If you will needs rack me beyond my reason,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127750">Hell take me, but I'll strangle half that's here,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127760">And force the rest to kill me ▪ I'll leap down</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127770"><pb facs="66"/> if but once more they tempt me to despair;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127780">You wish my quiet, yet give cause of fury:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127790">Think you to set rude winds upon the sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127800">Yet keep it calm? or cast me in a sleep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127810">With shaking of my chains about mine ears? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127820">O honest soldiers, you have seen me free,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127830">From any care, of many thousand deaths! </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127840">Yet, of this one, the manner doth amaze me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127850">View, view, this wounded bosom, how much bound</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127860">Should that man make me, that would shoot it through;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127870">Is it not pity I should lose my life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127880">By such a bloody and infamous stroke? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127890" who="A18404_02-soldier">
            <speaker>Soldi:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127900">Now by thy spirit, and thy better angel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127910">If thou wert clear, the continent of France,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127920">Would shrink beneath the burden of thy death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127930">Ere it would b● are it;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127940" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127950">Who's that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e127960" who="A18404_02-soldier">
            <speaker>Soldi:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127970">I say well:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127980">And clear your justice, here is no ground shrinks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e127990">If he were clear it would: and I say more,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128000">Clear, or not clear, if he with all his foulness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128010">Stood here in one scale, and the Kings chief minion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128020">Stood in another, here: put here a pardon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128030">Here lay a royal gift, this, this, in merit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128040">Should hoist the other minion into air:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e128050" who="A18404_02-vitry">
            <speaker>Vit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128060">Hence with that frantic:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18404_02-e128070" who="A18404_02-byron">
            <speaker>Byr:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128080">This is some poor witness</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128090">That my desert, might have outweighed my forfeit:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128100">But danger, haunts desert, when he is greatest;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128110">His hearty ills, are proved out of his glances,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128120">And Kings suspicions, needs no balances;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128130">So here's a most decretal end of me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128140">Which I desire, in me, may end my wrongs;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128150">Commend my love, I charge you, to my brothers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128160">And by my love, and misery command them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128170">To keep their faiths that bind them to the King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128180">And prove no stomachers of my misfortunes;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128190">Nor come to court, till time hath eaten out,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128200"><pb facs="67"/> the blots, and scars of my opprobrious death;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128210">And tell the Earl, my dear friend of D'auvergne,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128220">That my death utterly were free from grief,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128230">But for the sad loss of his worthy friendship;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128240">And if I had been made for longer life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128250">I would have more deserved him in my service,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128260">Beseeching him to know I have not used</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128270">One word in my arraignment; that might touch him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128280">Had I no other want then so ill meaning:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128290">And so farewell for ever: never more</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128300">Shall any hope of my revival see me;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128310">Such is the endless exile of dead men. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128320">Summer succeeds the spring; autumn the summer,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128330">The frosts of winter, the fall'n leaves of autumn:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128340">All these, and all fruits in them yearly fade,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128350">And every year return: but cursed man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128360">Shall never more renew, his vanisht face;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128370">Fall on your knees, than statists ere ye fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128380">That you may rise again: knees bent too late,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128390">Stick you in earth like statues: see in me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128400">How you are poured down from your clearest heavens;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128410">Fall lower yet: mixed with th' unmoved centre,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128420">That your own shadows may no longer mock ye ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128430">Strick, strike, oh strike;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128440">Fly, fly commanding soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128450">And on thy wings for this thy body's breath,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18404_02-e128460">Bear the eternal victory of death. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A18404_02-e128470">Finis.</trailer>
        <pb facs="67"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A18404_02"><item xml:id="A18404_02-byron" n="119">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-byron</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">119</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-henry" n="50">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-henry</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">50</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-chancelor" n="33">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-chancelor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">33</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-espernon" n="26">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-espernon</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">26</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-vitry" n="21">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-vitry</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">21</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-janin" n="17">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-janin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">17</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-harlay" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-harlay</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-daumale" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-daumale</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-descures" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-descures</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-cupid" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-cupid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-soissons" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-soissons</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-pralin" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-pralin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-laffin" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-laffin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-queen" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-queen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-hangman" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-hangman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-potiers" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-potiers</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-captain" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-captain</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A18404_02-vidame" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-vidame</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-fleu" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-fleu</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-brulart" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-brulart</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-xxxx_4" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-xxxx_4</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-xxxx_5" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-xxxx_5</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-ambassador" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-ambassador</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-xxxx_2" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-xxxx_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-soldier" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-soldier</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-bishop" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-bishop</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-labrun" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-labrun</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-xxxx_3" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-xxxx_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-unassigned" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-omnes" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-omnes</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-xxxx_1" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-xxxx_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-brunel" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-brunel</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-messenger" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-dauvergne" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-dauvergne</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-all" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18404_02-varennes" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18404_02-varennes</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

