<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A20867">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Jack Drum's Entertainment<date type="creation_date">1600</date></title>
        <author>Marston, John</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A20867.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Iacke Drums entertainment: or The comedie of Pasquill and Katherine. As it hath bene sundry times plaide by the Children of Powles.</title>
            <author>Marston, John, 1575-1634.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>36 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2005 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99841094</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 7243.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 177(a).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">5653</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20867</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Iacke Drums entertainment: or The comedie of Pasquill and Katherine. As it hath bene sundry times plaide by the Children of Powles.</title>
            <title type="alt">Jacke Drums entertainment</title>
            <title type="alt">Jacke Drums entertainment: or The comedie of Pasquill and Katherine.</title>
            <title type="alt">Comedie of Pasquill and Katherine.</title>
            <title type="alt">Pleasant comedie of Pasquill and Katherine.</title>
            <author>Marston, John, 1575-1634.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[72] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed [By Thomas Creede] for Richard Oliue, dwelling in Long Lane,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1601.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Anonymous. Mainly by John Marston.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-I4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: A pleasant comedie of Pasquill and Katherine.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A20867-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A20867-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A20867-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A20867-e100040">Jack drums entertainment: or the comedy of Pasquill and Katherine. As it hath been sundry times played by the children of Paul's. </p>
        <p xml:id="A20867-e100050">At London printed for Richard olive, dwelling in long lane. 1601.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A20867-e100060">
      <head><pb facs="2"/><pb facs="2"/>❧ John Drum's entertainment, or the comedy of Pasquill and Katherine. </head>
      <div type="introduction" xml:id="A20867-e100070">
        <head>The introduction.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e100080">Enter the Tyer-man.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100090" who="A20867-missing">
          <p xml:id="A20867-e100100">In good faith gentlemen, I think we shall be forced to give you right John drums entertainment, for he that composed the book, we should present, hath done us very vehement wrong, he hath snatched it from us, upon the very instance of entrance, and with violence keeps the boys from coming on the stage. So God help me, if we wrong your delights, 'tis infinitely against our endeavours, unless we should make a tumult in the tiring-house. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e100110">Exit Tyer-man.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e100120">Enter one of the children.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100130" who="A20867-missing">
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100140">You much mistake his action Tire-man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100150">His violence proceeds not from a mind</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100160">That grudgeth pleasure to this generous presence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100170">But doth protest all due respect and love</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100180">Unto this choice selected influence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100190">He vows, if he could draw the music from the spheres</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100200"><pb facs="3"/> to entertain this presence with delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100210">Or could distil the quintessence of heaven</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100220">In rare composed scenes, and sprinkle them</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100230">Among your ears, his industry should sweat</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100240">To sweeten your delights: but he was loath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100250">Wanting a prologue, and ourselves not perfect,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100260">To rush upon your eyes without respect:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100270">Yet if you'll pardon his defects and ours,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100280">He'll give us passage, and you pleasing scenes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100290">And vows not to torment your listening ears</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100300">With mouldy fopperies of stale poetry,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100310">Unpossible dry musty fictions:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100320">And for our parts to gratify your favour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100330">We'll study till our cheeks look wan with care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100340">That you our pleasures, we your loves may share. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e100350">Exit.</stage>
      </div>
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A20867-e100360">
        <head>Actus primus.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e100370">Enter Jack drum, and Timothy Twedle, with a taber and a pipe.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100380" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e100390">Come Timothy Twedle, tickle thy pipe on the green, as I have tippled the pot in the seller, and the hoy for the honour of Highgate, you old Trojan.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100400" who="A20867-twedle">
          <speaker>Twedle.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e100410">And a heigh for the honour of Highgate, hem, by my halidom, though I say it, that should not say it, I think I am as perfect in my pipe, as officers in poling, courtiers in flattery, or wenches in falling: why look you Jack drum, 'tis even as natural to me, as bawdry to a sumner, knavery to a promoter, or damnation to an usurer. But is Holloway Morice prancing up the hill?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100420" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e100430">Ay, i; and sir Edward, and the yellow toothed, sunk-eyed, gouty shanked usurer Maman, my young<pb facs="3"/> mistresses and all are coming to the green, lay cushions, lay the cushions, ha the wenches!</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100440" who="A20867-twedle">
          <speaker>Twed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e100450">The wenches, ha, when I was a young man and could tickle the minikin, and made them cry thanks sweet Timothy, I had the best stroke, the sweetest touch, but now (I may sigh to say it) I am fallen from the fiddle and betook me to thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e100460">He plays on his pipe.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e100470">Enter sir Edward fortune, m. Mamon, Camelia, Katherine, and Winifride, Camelia's maid.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100480" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e100490">Sit m. Mammon, ha here's a goodly day nigh.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100500" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e100510">I thank you sir, and faith what news at court?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100520" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <stage xml:id="A20867-e100530"><l xml:id="A20867-e100540">What news at court? ha, ha, now Jesu God,</l><l xml:id="A20867-e100550">Fetch me some Bordeaux wine, what news at court? </l><l xml:id="A20867-e100560">Reprobate fashion, when each ragged clout,</l><l xml:id="A20867-e100570">Each cobbler's spawn, and yeasty bowzing bench,</l><l xml:id="A20867-e100580">Reeks in the face of sacred majesty</l><l xml:id="A20867-e100590">His stinking breath of censure, out-upont,</l> he drinks.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100600">Why by this Bordeaux juice, 'tis now become</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100610">The shewing-horn of bezelers discourse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100620">The common food of prate: what news at court? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100630">But in these stiff necked times when every jade</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100640">Huffs his upreared crest, the zealous bent</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100650">Of councillors solid cares is trampled on</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100660">By every hackneys heels: o I could burst</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100670">At the conjectures fears, preventions</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100680">And restless tumbling of our tossed brains:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100690">Ye shall have me an empty cask that's furred</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100700">With naught but barmy froth, that ne'er travelled</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100710">Beyond the confines of his mistress lips,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100720">Discourse as confident of peace with Spain ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100730">As if the genius of quick Machiavel</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100740"><pb facs="4"/> ushered his speech. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100750" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e100760">O forbear, you are too sharp with me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100770" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>S. Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100780">Nay m ▪ Mammon, misinterpret not,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100790">I only burn the bavin heath of youth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100800">That cannot court the presence of fair time</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100810">With ought but with, what news at court sweet sir? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100820">I had rather that Kemp's morris were their chat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100830">For of foolish actions, may be they'll talk wisely, but of</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100840">Wise intendments, most part talk like fools. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100850">The sum is this, bear only this good thought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100860">The counsel-chamber is the phoenix nest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100870">Who wastes itself, to give us peace and rest. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e100880">The taber and pipe strike up a morris. A shout within. A lord, a lord, a lord, who!</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100890" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100900">O a morris is come, observe our country sport,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100910">'Tis Whitsuntide, and we must frolic it. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e100920">Enter the morris.</stage>
        <lg xml:id="A20867-e100930">
          <head>The song.</head>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100940">Skip it, and trip it, nimbly, nimbly, tickle it, tickle it, lustily,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100950">Strike up the taber, for the wench's favour, tickle it, tickle it, lustily:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100960">Let us be seen, on Highgate green, to dance for the honour of Holloway. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100970">Since we are come hither, let's spare for no leather,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e100980">To dance for the honour of Holloway. </l>
        </lg>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e100990" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101000">Well said my boys, I must have my lords livery, what is't, a maypole? troth 'twere a good body for a courtier's imprezza, if it had but this life, frustra florescit. Hold cousin hold.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e101010">He gives the fool money.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101020" who="A20867-fool">
          <speaker><pb facs="4"/>Foole.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101030">Thanks cousin, when the lord my father's audit comes, we'll repay you again. Your benevolence too sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101040" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101050">What a lord's son become a beggar?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101060" who="A20867-fool">
          <speaker>Foole.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101070">Why not, when beggars are become lords sons, come 'tis but a small trifle.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101080" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101090">O sir, many a small make a great.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101100" who="A20867-fool">
          <speaker>Foole.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101110">No sir, a few great make a many small, come my lords, poor and need hath no law.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101120" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>S. Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101130">Nor necessity no right, drum down with them into the cellar, rest content, rest content, one bout more and then away.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101140" who="A20867-fool">
          <speaker>Foole.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101150">Speak like a true heart, I kiss thy foot sweet knight.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e101160">The morris sing and dance, and exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101170" who="A20867-mall">
          <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101180">Sir Edward fortune you keep too great a house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101190">I am your friend, in hope your son in law,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101200">And from my love I speak, you keep too great a house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101210">Go too you do, yond same dry throated husks</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101220">Will suck you up, and you are ignorant</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101230">What frosty fortunes may benumb your age,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101240">Poverty, the prince's frown, a civil war, or. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101250" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>S. Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101260">Or what? tush, tush, your life hath lost his taste,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101270">O madness still to sweat in hot pursuit</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101280">Of cold abhorred sluttish niggardise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101290">To exile ones fortunes from their native use,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101300">To entertain a present poverty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101310">A willing want, for infidel mistrust</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101320">Of gracious providence: o lunacy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101330">I have two thousand pound a year, and but two girls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101340">I owe nothing, live in all men's love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101350">Why should I now go make myself a slave</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101360">Unto the god of fools; put worst: then here's my rest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101370">I had rather live rich to die poor, then live poor to die rich. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101380" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker><pb facs="5"/>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101390">O but so great a mass of coin might mount from wholesome thrift, that after your decease your issue might swell out your name with pomp.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101400" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>S. Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101410">Ha, I was not born to be my cradle's drudge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101420">To choke and stifle up my pleasure's breath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101430">To poison with the venomed cares of thrift</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101440">My private sweet of life: only to scrape</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101450">A heap of muck, to fatten and manure</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101460">The barren virtues of my progeny,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101470">And make them sprout, spite of their want of worth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101480">No, I do love my girls should wish me live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101490">Which few do wish that have a greedy sire:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101500">But still expect and gape with hungry lip,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101510">When he'll give up his gouty stewardship. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101520" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101530">You touch the quick of sense, but then I wonder</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101540">You not aspire unto the eminence</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101550">And height of pleasing life: to court, to court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101560">There burnish, there spread, there stick in pomp</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101570">Like a bright diamond in a lady's brow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101580">There plant your fortunes in the flowering spring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101590">And get the sun before you of respect:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101600">There trench yourself within the people's love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101610">And glitter in the eye of glorious grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101620">What's wealth without respect and mounted place? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101630" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>S. Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101640">Worse and worse, I am not yet distraught,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101650">I long not to be squeezed with mine own weight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101660">Nor hoist up all my sails to catch the wind</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101670">Of the drunk reeling commons: I labour not</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101680">To have an awful presence, nor be feared</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101690">(Since who is feared, still fears to be so feared)</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101700">I care not to be like the Horeb calf,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101710">One day adored, and next pashed all in pieces:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101720">Nor do I envy poliphemiam puffs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101730"><pb facs="5"/> Swizars slopped greatness: I adore the sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101740">Yet love to live within a temperate zone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101750">Let who will climb ambitious glibery rounds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101760">And lean upon the vulgars' rotten love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101770">I'll not corrival him: the sun will give</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101780">As great a shadow to my trunk as his:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101790">And after death like chesmen having stood</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101800">In play for Bishops, some for knights, and pawns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101810">We all together shall be tumbled up, into one bag,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101820">Let hushed calm quiet, rock my life asleep :</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101830">And being dead, my own ground press my bones,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101840">Whilst some old beldame hobbling o'er my grave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101850">May mumble thus: here lies a knight whose money</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101860">Was his slave. Now Jack what news? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e101870">Enter Jack drum.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101880" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101890">And please your wor. the morris have ta'en their liquor.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101900" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101910">Hath not the liquor ta'en them?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101920" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101930">Tripped up their heels or so? one of them hath undertaken to dance the morris from Highgate to Holloway on his heels, with his hands onwards.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101940" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>S. Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101950">That's nothing hard.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101960" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e101970">Yes sir, 'tis easier for him to dance on his head than his heels, for indeed his heels are turned rank rebels, they will not obey, but they are tumbling down the hill a pace.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e101980" who="A20867-mall">
          <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e101990">And I must after then, farewell my soul's delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102000">Sweet Katherine adieu. Camelia goodnight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102010" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>S. Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102020">Nay not to London sir tonight , i'faith at least stay supper.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102030" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102040">Hark you sir, there's but two lambs, a dozen capons, half a score couple of rabbits, three tarts, and four tansies, for supper, and therefore I beseech you<pb facs="6"/> give him Jack drums entertainment: let the Jebusite depart in peace.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102050" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102060">Why Jack, is not that sufficient?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102070" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102080">I for any christian, but for a yawning usurer 'tis but a bit, a morsel, if you table him, he'll devour your whole lordship, he is a quicksand, a Goodwin, a gulf, as hungry as the jaws of a jail, he will waste more substance than Ireland soldiers: a die, a drab, and a paunch-swollen usurer, devour whole monarchies: let him pass sweet knight, let him pass.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102090" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102100">Peace knave peace. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102110">Daughter, lay your express commandment upon the stay of master Mammon, what 'tis women's year,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102120">Dian doth rule, and you must domineer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102130" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102140">No she'll not wish my stay, o I am cursed</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102150">With her inexorable swiftness, by her love</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102160">Which dotes me more than new coined glowing gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102170">The utmost bent of my affection</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102180">Shoots all my fortunes to obtain her love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102190">And yet I cannot praise, but still am loathed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102200">My presence hated, therefore Mammon down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102210">Farewell sir Edward, farewell beauty's crown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102220" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102230">Faith as it please you for going, and her for wooing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102240">I will enforce neither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102250" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Kath.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102260">With your pardon sir, I shall sooner hate myself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102270">Then love him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102280" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102290">Nay be free my daughters in election,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102300">O, how my soul abhors enforced yokes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102310">Chiefly in love, where the affections bent:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102320">Should wholly sway the father's kind consent. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102330">Fore-god when I was bachelor, had a friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102340">Nay had my father wished me to a wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102350">That might have liked me, yet their very wish</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102360"><pb facs="6"/> made me mistrust my love had not true course,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102370">But had some sway from duty which might hold</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102380">For some slight space: but o when time shall search</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102390">The strength of love, than virtue, and your eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102400">Must knit his sinews: I choosed myself a wife</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102410">Poor, but of good dissent, and we did live</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102420">Till death divorced us, as a man would wish:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102430">I made a woman, now wenches make a man:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102440">Choose one either of valour, wit, honesty, or wealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102450">So he be gentle, and you have my heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102460">I'faith you have: what, I have land for you both,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102470">You have love for yourselves. Here's m. Mammon now. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102480" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102490">A club-fisted usurer.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102500" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102510">A wealthy, careful, thriving citizen.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102520" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102530">Careful, ay, ay, let nothing without good black and white, I warrant you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102540" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102550">Yes sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102560" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102570">No sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102580" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102590">A little back wind, saving your wor. sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102600" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102610">I am scoffed at, where's my man there ho?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102620" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102630">Sir you need not take the pepper in the nose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102640">Your nose is fiery enough. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102650" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102660">What Flawne, what Christopher, heart where's the knave become? Hold sirrah carry my cloak.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e102670">Enter Flawne.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102680" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Kathe.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102690">It seems he can scarce carry himself.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102700" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102710">He's over the shoes, yet he'll hold out water, for I have liquored him soundly.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102720" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102730">Why cannot you come where heady liquore is, but you must needs bouze? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102740">What a man may lead a horse to the water, but he'll choose to drink. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102750" who="A20867-flawne">
          <speaker>Flawn.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102760">True, but I am no horse, for I cannot choose but drink.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102770" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker><pb facs="7"/>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102780">A pale weak stripling, yet contend with ale.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102790" who="A20867-flawne">
          <speaker>Flawne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102800">Why the weakest go to the pot still.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102810" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102820">That jest shall save him. Sir Edward now good day.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e102830">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102840" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e102850">Nay sir, we'll bring you a little of the way.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102860" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102870">Rely on me Christopher, I will be thy staff,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102880">And thy master's nose shall be thy lantern and candlelight</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e102890">Exeunt all. Manent Camelia and Winifride.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102900" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102910">Mistress Camelia, methinks your eye</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102920">Sparkles not spirit as 'twas wont to do. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102930" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102940">My mind is dull, and yet my thoughts are fixed</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102950">Upon a pleasing object, Brabant's love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e102960" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102970">Indeed young Brabant is a proper man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102980">And yet his legs are somewhat of the least:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e102990">And faith a chitty well complexioned face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103000">And yet it wants a beard: a good sweet youth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103010">And yet some say he hath a valiant breath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103020">Of a good hair, but o, his eyes, his eyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103030" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103040">Last day thy praise extolled him to the skies.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103050" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103060">Indeed he wears good clothes, and throws his cloak</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103070">With good discretion under his left arm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103080">He curles his boot with judgement, and takes a whiff</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103090">With graceful fashion, swears a valorous oath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103100">But o the devil, hath a hateful fault, he is a younger brother. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103110" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103120">A younger brother? O intolerable.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103130" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103140">No mistress, no: but there's m. John,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103150">M. John Ellis, there's a lad i'faith,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103160">Ha for a virtuous honest good youth! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103170" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103180">Tut he is good, because he knows not how to be bad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103190">Nor wherefore he is good. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103200" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103210">I know not, methinks not to be bad, is good enough in these days.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103220" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103230">Nay he is a fool, a perfect idiot.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103240" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Win.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103250">Why all the better. And I'll tell you this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103260"><pb facs="7"/> the greatest lady in the land affects him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103270">Nay dotes upon him, ay, and lies with him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103280" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103290">What lady, good sweet Winifrid, what lady say ▪ faith there be some good parts about the fool, which I perceive not, yet another may: what lady, good sweet Winifrid? say quick good wench.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103300" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Winif.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103310">The lady fortune. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103320" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Camel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103330">Why my name's fortune too.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103340" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Winif.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103350">Then you must needs favour him ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103360">For fortune favours fools. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103370" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Camel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103380">O but to hug a fool is odious.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103390" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Winif.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103400">Foul water quencheth fire well enough,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103410">And with more lively pallor, you shall taste</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103420">The juice of pleasure's fount at private times:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103430">Pish, by my maidenhead, were I to match,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103440">I would elect a wealthy fool fore all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103450">Then may one hurry in her chariot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103460">Shine in rich purpled tissue, have hundred loves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103470">Rule all, pay all, take all, without check or snib. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103480">When being married to a wise man (Oh the lord)</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103490">You are made a fool, a ward, curbed and controlled, and (Oh) out upon't. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103500" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103510">Believe me wench, thy words have fired me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103520">I'll lay me down upon a bank of pinks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103530">And dream upon't; sweet fool, I 'tis most clear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103540">A foolish bed-mate, why he hath no peer. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e103550">Exit Camelia.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103560" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Winif.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103570">Ha, ha, her love is as uncertain as an almanac, as unconstant as the fashion, just like a whiff of tobacco, no sooner in at the mouth, but out at the nose: I think in my heart I could make her enamoured on Timothy Twedle: well he that fees me best, speeds best. For as it pleased my bribed lips to blow,<pb facs="8"/> so turns her feathery fancy to and fro.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e103580">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e103590">Enter Brabant junior at one door, Ned planet at the other.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103600" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103610">Good speed thee my good sweet planet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103620">How dost thou chuck? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103630" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103640">How now Brabant, where have you lived these three or four days?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103650" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103660">Ho at the glittering court my Pytheas. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103670" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103680">Plague on ye Pytheas, what have you done there?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103690" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103700">Why lane in my lady's lap, eat, drink, and sleep.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103710" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103720">So hath thy lady's dog done, what art in love</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103730">With you Highgate mammer still? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103740" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103750">Still, I still, and still, I in eternity.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103760" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Plan.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103770">It shall be chronicled next after the death of banks his horse, I wonder why thou lovest her?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103780" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103790">Love hath no reason.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103800" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103810">Then is love a beast.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103820" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103830">O my Camelia is love itself.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103840" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103850">The devil she is: heart her lips look like a dried neats-tongue: her face as richly yellow, as the skin of a cold custard, and her mind as settled as the feet of bald pated time.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103860" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103870">Plague on your hateful humour, out upon't,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103880">Why should your stomach be so queasy now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103890">As to bespawl the pleasures of the world? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103900">Why should you run an idle counter-course</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103910">Thwart to the path of fashion? Come your reason? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103920">O you are buried in philosophy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103930">And there entombed in supernaturalls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103940">You are dead to native pleasures life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103950" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e103960">Let me buss thy cheek sweet Pug,<pb facs="8"/> now I am perfect hate, I loved but three things in the world, philosophy, thrift, and myself. Thou hast made me hate philosophy. A usurer's greasy codpiece made me loath thrift: but if all the brewer's jades in the town can drug me from love of myself, they shall do more than e'er the seven wise men of Greece could: come, come, now I'll be as sociable as Timon of Athens. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e103970" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103980">Along with me then, you droming sackbut,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e103990">I'll bring thee to a crew. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104000" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104010">Of fools wilt not?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104020" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104030">Faith if you have any weight of judgement, you may easily sound what depth of wits they draw, there's first my elder brother.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104040" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104050">O the prince of fools, unequalled idiot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104060">He that makes costly suppers to try wits:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104070">And will not stick to spend some 20. pound</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104080">To grope a gull: that same perpetual grin</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104090">That leads his corky jests to make them sink</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104100">Into the ears of his deryders with his own applause. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104110" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104120">Indeed his jests are like Indian beef, they will not last, and yet he powders them soundly with his own laughter.</p>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104130">Then there's the goatish Frenchman, monsieur John fo de King, know'st thou him?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104140" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104150">O, I to a hair, for I knew him when he had never a hair on his head.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104160" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104170">He is a faithful pure rogue.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104180" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104190">Ay, ay, as pure as the gold that hath been seven times tried in the fire.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104200" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104210">Then there's John Ellis, and profound tongued master puff, he that hath a perpetuity of compliment, he whose phrases are as neatly decked as my lord mayor's<pb facs="9"/> hensmen, he whose throat squeaks like a treble organ, and speaks as small and shrill, as the Irishman cry pip, fine pip.</p>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104220">And when his period comes not roundly off, takes toll of the tenth hair of his Bourbon lock: as thus. Sweet sir, repute me as a (Puff) selected spirit born to be the admirer, of your never enough admired (Puff). </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104230" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104240">O we shall be overwhelmed with an inundation of laughter. Come, where are they?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104250" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104260">Here at this tavern.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104270" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104280">In, in, in, in, I long to burst my sides and tire my spleen with laughter.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e104290">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e104300">Enter two pages, the one laughing, the other crying.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104310" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page. 1.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104320">Why dost thou cry?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104330" who="A20867-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104340">Why dost thou laugh?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104350" who="A20867-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104360">I laugh to see thee cry.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104370" who="A20867-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104380">And I cry to see thee laugh. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104390">Peace be to us. Here's our masters. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e104400">Enter Brabant signior, planet, Brabant junior, John Ellis, m. puff, and monsieur John fo de King.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104410" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104420">You shall see his humour, I pray you be familiar with this gentleman master puff, he is a man of a well grown spirit, richly worth your. I assure you, ha, ha, ha.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104430" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104440">Sir I enrol you in the legend of my (Puff) intimates, I shall be infinitely proud if you will deign to value me worthy the embracement of your (Puff) better affection.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104450" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker><pb facs="9"/>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104460">Speak you from your thought sir?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104470" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puffe.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104480">Ay, or would my silk stock should lose his gloss else, I shall triumph as much in the purchase of your (Puff) love, as if I had obtained the great elixir: let us incorporate our affections I pray you: let me be forward in your favour.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104490" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104500">Sir, I pray you let me beg you for a fool.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104510" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104520">I affect no rudeness gentlemen, the heavens stand</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104530">Propitious to your fair designs:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104540">As soon as next the sun shall 'gin to shine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104550">I will salute the eyes of Katherine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104560" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104570">Of Katherine, m. planet observe the next,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104580">M. John, what makes you so melancholy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104590" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>Ellis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104600">I do not use to answer questions.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104610" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104620">What are you thinking on now?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104630" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104640">I do not use to think.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104650" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104660">He looks as demurely as if he were asking his father blessing.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104670" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104680">I do not use to ask my father blessing.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104690" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104700">Heart, how chance he is out of his similes?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104710" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104720">I have followed ordinaries this twelvemonth , only to find a fool that had lands, or a fellow that would talk treason, that I might beg him. John, be my ward John, faith I'll give thee two coats a year and be my fool.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104730" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104740">He shall be your fool, and you shall be his</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104750">Coxcomb. Ha, ha, I have a simple wit, ha, ha. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104760" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104770">I shall crow o'er him then.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e104780">Enter Winifride.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104790" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104800">Is there not one m. John Ellis here?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104810" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104820">There sits the thing so called.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e104830">Winifride and Ellis talk.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104840" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Br. sig.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104850">Now to the last course: monsieur John fo de King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e104860"><pb facs="10"/> I will help you to a wench monsieur. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104870" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104880">No point, a burn child fear de fire.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104890" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>Ellis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104900">As a hungry dog waiteth for a mutton bone, or as a tattered footboy for a cast suit, even so will I attend on my mistress.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e104910">Enter Winifride.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104920" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104930">O my Vinifride, pray you awe, by gour, me ang de for her.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104940" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104950">Nay stay, stay, I will help you to a delicate plump-lipped wench.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104960" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104970">Toh, phi, phi, your proffer ware stink: stay Vinifride; or by gour die, me die, me die by gour, me ang so desirous adieu goot sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e104980" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e104990">O stay monsieur, how do you pronounce Demurra? Ha, ha, I'll plague him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105000" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105010">Grand sot, my vench is gone, and me brule, and me brule, like one mad bule, me go into de vaterto cool my reine, ang my back made de vater hize again, does so brule, me burst vor a vench, and yet grand pox on you all, pree you adieu.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105020" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>Ellis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105030">As the jig is called for when the play is done, even so let monsieur go.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105040" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105050">He, me teach you much French vor dis, I go to Highgate, adieu grand sors.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e105060">Exit monsieur.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105070" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>Ellis</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105080">As sore eyes cannot endure the sun, nor scabbed hands abide salt water, so must I leave all, and see my mistress, and as fair ladies do use soul foils, even so do I bid you farewell.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e105090">Exit Ellis.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105100" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105110">Why this is sport imperial, by my gentry, I would spend forty crowns, for such another feast of fools. Ha, ha.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105120" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105130">I wonder who would be the fool then?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105140" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker><pb facs="10"/>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105150">Why 'tis the recreation of my intellect, I think I speak as significant, ha, ha, these are my zanies, I fill their paunches, they seed my pleasures, I use them as my fool's faith, ha, ha.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105160" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105170">'Tis a generous honour.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105180" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105190">Troth I think you have a good wit, ha? pray you sup with me, I love good wits, because mine own is not unfortunate: pray you sup with me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105200" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105210">I'll give God thanks sir, that hath sent a fool to feed me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105220" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105230">Come along then, ye shall have a capon, a tansy, and some kickshaws of my wits, ha, ha, some toys of my spirit.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e105240">Exit Bra. sig. and Bra. junior.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105250" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105260">I will eat his meat, and spend's money, that's all the spite I can do him: but if I can get a patent for concealed sots, that Daw shall troop among my idiots.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e105270">Exit.</stage>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A20867-e105280">
        <head>Actus secundus.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e105290">Enter m. Puffe with his page.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105300" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puffe.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105310">Boy what's o'clock ?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105320" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105330">Past three, and a fair morning.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105340" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puffe.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105350">Burns not that light within the sacred shrine? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105360">I mean the chamber of bright Katherine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105370" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105380">Ay, should appear by these presence, that it doth.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105390" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puffe.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105400">I wonder that the light is up so soon.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105410" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105420">O mistress snuff was weary with sleeping in the socket, and therefore hath newly put on her stammel petticoat, and taken her pewter state to give light to things are in darkness.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105430" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker><pb facs="11"/>Puff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105440">And I know that women of gravity and sweetness are soon up.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105450" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105460">I see that women of levity and lightness, are soon down.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105470" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105480">Boy clear thy throat, and mount thy sweetest notes</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105490">Upon the bosom of this sleek cheeked air:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105500">That it may gently breathe them in the ear</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105510">Of my adored mistress: come begin. </l>
        </sp>
        <lg xml:id="A20867-e105520">
          <head>The song.</head>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105530">Delicious beauty that doth lie</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105540">Wrapped in a skin of ivory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105550">Lie still, lie still upon thy back,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105560">And fancy let no sweet dreams lack</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105570">To tickle her, to tickle her with pleasing thoughts. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105580">But if thy eyes are open full,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105590">Then deign to view an honest gull,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105600">That stands, that stands, expecting still</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105610">When that thy casement open will</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105620">And bless his eyes, and bless his eyes, with one kind glance. </l>
        </lg>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e105630">The casement opens, and Katherine appears.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105640" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puf.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105650">All happiness and unconceived delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105660">Wait on the love of sweet faced Katherine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105670" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Kathe.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105680">Good youth amen: I do return your wish</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105690">With ample interest of beatitude. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105700" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puf.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105710">I do protest, with ceremonious (Puff) lips</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105720">The purest blood of my affection,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105730">Is even fatally predestinate</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105740">To consecrate itself unto your (Puff) love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105750" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105760">Unto my love? O sir you bind me to you:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105770"><pb facs="11"/> fair gentleman I have a thankful heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105780">Though not a glorious speech to sweet my thanks. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105790" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puf.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105800">Reward my love then with your kinder love.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105810" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105820">With my love sir, I relish not your speech.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105830" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puf.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105840">I with your love, in pleasing marriage.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105850" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105860">Alas sir, cannot be my loves a man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105870">Who hardly can requite the dear protests</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105880">Of kind affection, which you seem to vow</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105890">Unto his fortunes: kind youth, you did wish</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105900">All happiness to wait upon my love:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105910">Well he shall know it when we next do meet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e105920">And thank you kindly: now good morrow sweet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105930" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puf.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105940">You take my, my, my meaning (Puff.)</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105950" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105960">Nay if he be puffing once, the fire of his wit is out.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105970" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puf.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e105980">Why she is gone. Heart did I rise for this?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e105990" who="A20867-unassigned">
          <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e106000">She cannot endure puffing. O you puffed her away</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106010" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puf.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e106020">Let's slink along unseen, 'tis yet scarce day.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e106030">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e106040">Enter Mamon with Flawne, bearing a light before Mamon.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106050" who="A20867-flawne">
          <speaker>Flawn.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e106060">Now methinks I hold the candle to the devil.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106070" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e106080">Put out the light, the day begins to break.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106090" who="A20867-flawne">
          <speaker>Flawn.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e106100">Would the day and thy neck were broke together.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106110" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e106120">O how the gout and love do tire me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106130" who="A20867-flawne">
          <speaker>Flawne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e106140">Why sir, love is nothing but the very gout.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106150" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e106160">As how Flawne? as how?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106170" who="A20867-flawne">
          <speaker>Flawne</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e106180">Thus sir: gout and love, both come with idleness, both incurable, both humorous, only this difference: the gout causeth a great tumour in a man's legs, and love a great swelling in a woman's belly.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106190" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e106200">Why then o love, o gout, o gouty love, how thou torments old Mammon: good morrow to the<pb facs="12"/> sweet lipped Katherine, eternal spring unto thy beauty's love.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106210" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106220">Alas good aged sir, what make you up? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106230">In faith I pity you, good soul to bed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106240">Troth soon you'll cry, o God my head, my head. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106250" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106260">No Katherine, the wrinkling print of time</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106270">Erred, when it sealed my forehead up with age:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106280">I have as warm an arm to entertain</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106290">And hug thy presence in a nuptial bed ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106300">As those that have a cheek more lively red:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106310">And though my voice be rude, yet Flawne can sing</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106320">Paeans of beauty, and of Katherine. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106330">List to the music that corrupts the gods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106340">Subverts even destiny, and thus it shogs. </l>
        </sp>
        <lg xml:id="A20867-e106350">
          <head>The song.</head>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106360">Chunk, chunk, chunk, chunk, his bags do ring</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106370">A merry note with chuncks to sing ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106380">Those that are far more young and witty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106390">Are wide from singing such a ditty</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106400">As chunk, chunk, chunk,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106410">There's chunk that makes the lawyer prate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106420">There's chunk that make a fool of fate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106430">There's chunk, that if you will be his,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106440">Shall make you live in all heart's bliss ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106450">With chunk, chunk, chunk. </l>
        </lg>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106460" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106470">'Tis well sung good old man, hence with your gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106480">Leave the green fields 'tis dewy; you'll take cold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106490" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106500">The casements shut, well here I'll lurk and stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106510">To see who bears the glory of the day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106520">Hence, hence, to London, Flawne let me alone. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e106530">Enter</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106540" who="A20867-flawne">
          <speaker><pb facs="12"/>Flawne</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e106550">I can hardly leave him alone, for the devil and double ducats, still associate him, but I am gone.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e106560">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e106570">Enter Pasquill.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106580" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pasquil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106590">The glooming morn with shining arms hath chaste</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106600">The silver ensign of the grim cheeked night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106610">And forced the sacred troops of sparkling stars</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106620">Into their private tents, yet calm husht sleep</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106630">Strikes dumb the snoring world: yet frolic youth</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106640">That's lately matched unto a well shaped lass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106650">Clips his sweet mistress, with a pleasing arm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106660">Whilst the great power of imperious love</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106670">Summons my duty to salute the shine</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106680">Of my love's beauties. Unequalled Katherine</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106690">I bring no music to prepare thy thoughts</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106700">To entertain an amorous discourse:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106710">More music's in thy name, and sweet dispose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106720">Then in Apollo's lyre, or Orpheus close. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106730">I'll chant thy name, and so inchant each ear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106740">That Katherine's happy name shall hear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106750">My Katherine, my life, my Katherine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106760" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Kathe.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106770">My Ned, my Pasquil, sweet I come, I come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106780">Even with like swiftness, though not with like heart:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106790">As the fierce falcon stoops to rising fowl</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106800">I hurry to thee: do not go away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106810">The place is private, and 'tis yet scarce day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106820" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e106830">O these kind words imparadise my thoughts.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106840" who="A20867-mall">
          <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106850">Ha, ha, young Pasquil have I found you out ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106860">Is't you must bore my nose, I'll bore your heart:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106870">Why this same boy's as bare as naked truth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106880">A low ebd gallant, yet she'll match with him:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106890">I'll match him, if his skin be poniard proof ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106900"><pb facs="13"/> he may scape the force of gold and murder, if not ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106910">As you return sir, I will pepper you. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A20867-e106920">Exit.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A20867-e106930">Enter Katherine to Pasquill.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106940">And art thou come dear heart, first fee be this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106950">This kind embrace, and next this modest kiss. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e106960" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106970">This is no kiss, but an ambrosian bowl,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106980">The nectar dew of thy delicious soul:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e106990">Let me suck one kiss more, and with a nimble lip,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107000">Nibble upon those rosy banks, more soft and clear</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107010">Then is the jewelled tip of Venus' ear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107020">O how a kiss inflames a lover's thought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107030">With such a fuel let me burn and die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107040">And like to Hercules so mount the sky. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107050" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107060">Come you grow wanton. O you bite my lip.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107070" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107080">In faith you jest, I did but softly sip</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107090">The roseal juice of your reviving breath:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107100">Let clumsy judgements, chillblained gouty wits</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107110">Bung up their chief content within the whoops</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107120">Of a stuffed dry fat: and repose their hopes</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107130">Of happiness, and heart's tranquillity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107140">Upon increase of dirt: but let me live</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107150">Clipped in the cincture of a faithful arm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107160">Lulled in contented joy, being made divine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107170">With the most precious love of Katherine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107180" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107190">Let the unsanctified spirit of ambition</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107200">Entice the choice of muddy minded dames</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107210">To yoke themselves to swine, and for vain hope</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107220">Of gay rich trappings, be still spurred and pricked</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107230">With pining discontent for nuptial sweets. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107240">But let me live loved in my husband's eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107250">Whose thoughts with mine, may sweetly sympathize. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107260" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107270">The heavens shall melt, the sun shall cease to shine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107280">Before I leave the love of Katherine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107290" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker><pb facs="13"/>Kathe.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107300">Nay when heavens melted, and the sun struck dead,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107310">Even then my love shall not be vanquished. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107320" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107330">When I turn fickle, virtue shall be vice.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107340" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107350">When I prove false, hell shall be paradise.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107360" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107370">My life shall be maintained by thy kind breath.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107380" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107390">Thy love shall be my life, thy hate my death.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107400" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107410">O when I die let me embrace thy waste.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107420" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107430">In death let me be counted thine and chaste.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107440" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107450">Heaven's grant, being dead my soul may live nigh thee</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107460" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107470">One kiss shall give thee mine eternally.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107480" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107490">In fair exchange vouchsafe my heart to take.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107500" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107510">With all my mind, wear this Ned for my sake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107520">But now no more, bright day malings our love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107530">Farewell, yet stay, but 'tis no matter too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107540">My father knows I think, what must ensue. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107550">Adieu, yet hark, nay faith, adieu, adieu. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107560" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107570">Peace to thy passions, till next interview.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e107580">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e107590">Enter Mamon, and monsieur John fo de King.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107600" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107610">Now monsieur be but confident, and hold</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107620">There is the price of blood, this way he comes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107630">Strike home bold arm, and thou shalt want no crowns. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107640" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107650">Fear you noting, when he is die, me bring you word. <stage xml:id="A20867-e107660">Exit Mamon.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107670">He, by gour brave crown, brave money,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107680">Me have here a patent to take up, one, two, threescore</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107690">Vench: fine crown, fine vench, unreasonably fine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107700">Dis money is my bawd. Me send a French crown</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107710">To fetch a fine vench, de French crown fetch de</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107720">Fine vench, de fine vench take de French crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107730">And give me de French pox. He excellent, you see</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107740">Me kill a man, you see me hang like de burgullian,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107750">He no poine: he by gour, me have much vitt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107760"><pb facs="14"/> ang me much bald, and me ang much bald wit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107770">Here come de gentleman metre Pasquill. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e107780">Enter Pasquill.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107790" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pasquill.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107800">Is't possible that sisters should so thwart</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107810">In native humours? one's as kind and fair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107820">As constant, virtuous, and as debonaire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107830">As is the heart of goodness: the other, proud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107840">Inconstant, fantastic, and as vain in loves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107850">As travellers in lies: blessed Katherine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107860">Camelia's not thy sister, if she be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107870">She's bastard to the sweets that shine in thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107880" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107890">Boniour metre Pasquill, sance jest, me am hired to kill you, monsieur Mammon, messier: jounck, jounck, give me money to stab you, but me know there is a god that hate blood, derfore, me no kill, me know dear is a vench, that love crown, derefore me keep de money.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107900" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107910">Unhallowed villain, that with gold and blood, thinks that almighty love can be withstood.</p>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107920">Hold monsieur, there are more crowns, only do this, return to Mammon, tell him the deed is done, and bring him hither, that he may vainly triumph in my blood, I have some painting which I found by chance in loose Camelia's chamber, with that I'll stain my breast, go and return with speed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107930" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e107940">He, by gour I smell a rat, me fly, me fly, by gour.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e107950">Exit monsieur.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e107960" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107970">Lewd miscreant, that through the throat of hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107980">Wouldst mount to heaven, and enjoy love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e107990">Invaluably precious: no rank churl,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108000">Thou wast not made to slaver her fair lips</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108010">With thy dead rheumy chops, nor clip her waste,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108020">With thy shrunk bloodless arm, I hear him come. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108030">Now Pasquill feign, o thou eternal light,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108040"><pb facs="14"/> mourn that thy creatures should in blood delight. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e108050">He lies down, and feigns himself dead.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e108060">Enter Mamon and monsieur.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108070" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108080">Now smug faced boy, now nibble on her lips,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108090">Now sip the dew of her delicious breath. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108100">Stink, rot, damn, bake in thy cluttered blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108110">Snakes, toads, and earwigs, make thy skull their nest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108120">Engendering deaw-wormes, cling o'erthrwart thy breast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108130" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108140">Hush, hush, leave praying for dead, 'tis no good</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108150">Calvianism, puritanism. Dissemble, here are company. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e108160">Exit Moun.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e108170">Enter Bra. sig. and planet.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108180" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e108190">Good morrow sir, who lies there murdered?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108200" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108210">O gentlemen, the kindest virtuous youth</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108220">That e'er adorned London. Damned thieves</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108230">To spoil such hopes: the last words that he spoke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108240">Sticks still within the hollow of mine ear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108250">Katherine quoth he, hold m. Mammon dear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108260">I know not what he meant, but so he said. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108270">If that you pass to Highgate, tell the knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108280">Pasquill is sunk into eternal night. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108290" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e108300">Faith 'twas a good youth, come Brabant, come away.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e108310">Exeunt Brabant and planet.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108320" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108330">Dead Kate, dead Kate, dead is the boy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108340">That kept rich Mammon from his joy. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e108350">Mamon sings. Lantara, etc. Pasquill riseth, and striketh him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108360" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e108370">O the devil, the ghost of Pasquill, I am dead, if you have any courtesy in you, believe it. I believed you when you feigned, believe me now, for I am almost dead, numbed up with fear, give faith sweet gentle youth.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108380" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108390">Old wretch, amend thy thoughts, purge, purge, repent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108400">I'll hide thy ulcer, be but penitent. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e108410">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108420" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker><pb facs="15"/>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e108430">Ha, I think 'twas but his ghost that swept along.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A20867-e108440">Enter monsieur singing.</stage>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e108450">Grand sot Mammon, pho, fie, fie, fie, a foutra pour vos chūck, chunk. John fo de King, teach you a ding, John fo de King grand sot, sot, sot. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e108460">Exit monsieur.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108470" who="A20867-mall">
          <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108480">Death, plague, and hell, how is cursed Mammon vexed? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108490">Scourged with the whip of sharp derision:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108500">I'll home, and starve, this cross, this peevish hap,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108510">Strikes dead my spirits like a thunderclap. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e108520">Exit Mamon.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e108530">Enter Brabant junior, and planet.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108540" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108550">God's precious, I forgotten to bring my page,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108560">To breathe some ditty in my mistress ear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108570" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e108580">Wouldst have a ballet to salute her with?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108590" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e108600">No, but a song. How wouldst thou court thy mistress?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108610" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e108620">Why with the world, the flesh and the devil.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108630" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108640">Right dog, well thou'lt swear, that I am blessed</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108650">Beyond infinity of happiness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108660">When thou beholdest admired Camelia. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108670" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108680">And God would bless me with 3. such mistresses,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108690">I would give two of them to the devil, that he would take the third. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108700" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108710">O when she clips, and clings about my neck,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108720">And sucks my soul forth with a melting kiss. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108730" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e108740">Doth she use thee so kindly then, ha?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108750" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108760">O ay, and calls me dear, dear Brabant, and (O Jesu God)</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108770">I cannot express her sweets of entertain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108780">She'll so insinuate with chaste amorous speech,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108790">And play the wanton with such pretty grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108800">And vows love to me: o I'll make thee mad</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108810">To see how gracious brabant's in her eye. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108820">Here is her window, mark but when I call,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108830">How swift she comes, and with what kind salutes</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108840"><pb facs="15"/> she welcomes me. What ho Camelia? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108850">Faith you'll be ta'en up, what in bed so late? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e108860">Winifride looks from above.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108870" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e108880">And you take her up Brabant, she'll take you down.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108890" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e108900">Heart they hear not: my Camelia wake?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108910" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e108920">What harsh uncivil tongue keeps such a coil?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108930" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108940">Winifrid 'tis I. Tell my sweet duck I am here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108950">Now mark Ned planet, now observe her well. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e108960" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108970">She wonders at your rudeness that intrudes</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108980">Upon the quiet of her morning's rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e108990">And she's amazed, that with such impudence</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109000">You dare presume to intimate some love to her,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109010">As if she knew you more than for a youth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109020">A younger brother, and a stipendiary. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e109030">Enter John Ellis.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109040" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109050">Now mark Ned planet, now observe her kindness. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109060">Good morrow m. John. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109070" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>Ellis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109080">As the country maid crieth to her cow to milk her, or as the traveller knocketh with his hosts for a reckoning, even so do I call to thee o mistress.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e109090">Camelia from her window.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109100" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109110">Sweet John my love, here's thy Camelia:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109120">Hold wear this favour, with this kiss upon't. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109130" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109140">Flesh and blood cannot bear such disgrace.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e109150">Brabant beats Ellis.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109160" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109170">Help, help, help, help, he boxes me that he doth. Help, help.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e109180">Enter sir Edward, Katherine, drum, and Twedle.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109190" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109200">What outrage have we here so early up? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109210">Sir you do wrong the quiet of my house. <stage xml:id="A20867-e109220">Enter Camelia.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109230">I'faith you do, and 'tis but rudely done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109240">Go too 'tis not. Is this a place to brawl? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109250" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker><pb facs="16"/>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109260">And please thee knight, I'll tell thee faith and troth.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109270" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109280">What did he strike thee sweet?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109290" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109300">I in good deed la, and a my conscience, I think he hath made my nose bleed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109310" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109320">And would not you draw your weapon out, and to it lustily, as long as you could stand?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109330" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109340">I do not use to draw.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109350" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109360">Did he give thee a box on the ear, and wouldst thou take it?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109370" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109380">And he be such a fool to give it me, why should not I be so wise as to take it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109390" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109400">Pure honesty, kind duck, kiss me sweet John. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109410" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109420">Heart sir Edward, will you suffer this? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109430">Now on my life she is enamoured on the fool's babble. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109440" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109450">Go too sir boy forbear, you wrong my love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109460">And you forget yourself to use such jests,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109470">Such nasty ribaldry upon my daughter:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109480">I tell you m. Brabant, doth she love</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109490">Any that meriteth the name of man? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109500" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109510">Why he's no man, but a very —</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109520" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>S. Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109530">Well, well, no more; my house, myself, my love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109540">Opens their hearts with liberal embrace</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109550">To entertain your presence: I or any man's</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109560">So they'll be civil, modest, not profane,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109570">Not like to those that make it their chief grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109580">To be quite graceless. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109590" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109600">Well said honest knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109610">We have had blood enough today already:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109620">Ned pasquil's slain by bloody murdering rogues. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109630" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109640">Speak softly, God forbid, my daughter hears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109650">Tell me the circumstance, I pray you sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109660" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109670">Eternal death unto my happiness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109680">My Pasquil slain? O God, o God, o God. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e109690">Exit Katherin, tearing her hair.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109700" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker><pb facs="16"/>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109710">Ay, and I think the usurer made a tent</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109720">Even of his nose it was so red and near:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109730" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109740">God for his mercy, what mischance is here? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109750">A good youth, a virtuous modest youth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109760">I'faith he was. And I can tell your sir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109770">My daughter Katherine, where is she now? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109780">Whither's she gone? Drum call her hither straight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109790" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109800">Your drum will sound a call sir presently.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e109810">Exit drum.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109820" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109830">And as I told you sir, my daughter Katherine</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109840">Affected him right dear: by my peace of soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109850">If he had lived, I could have heartily wished</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109860">He had been my son in law, i'faith I could:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109870">But see the will of God. How now drum,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109880">Where's my daughter? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109890" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e109900">Sir, she is either invisible, or deaf, for I can neither see her, nor she hear me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109910" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109920">Body of me, my heart misgives me now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109930">Look, call, search, run all about. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109940">My daughter gone? Go all and search her out. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109950">Here's Pasquil ha? Is this the man that's dead? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e109960">Enter Pasquil.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e109970" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109980">Let me entreat this favour, do not search</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e109990">Or be inquisitive why I feigned:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110000">Repute me worthy your better censure: and thus think</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110010">My cause was urgent, the rest lie buried. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110020" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110030">Well, I would you had not feigned.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110040" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110050">Why would you have had me dead indeed?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110060" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110070">O no, but I have lost my child I fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110080">By your strange feigning, she no sooner heard</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110090">The tidings of your death, but gone she was,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110100">And God knows whither. Ha what news now? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e110110">Enter drum.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110120" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker><pb facs="17"/>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110130">'Tis easier to find wit in ballading, honesty in brokers, virginity in Shoreditch, than to hear of my mistress.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110140" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110150">Broach me a fresh butt of canary sack,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110160">Let's sing, drink, sleep, for that's the best relief:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110170">To drown all care, and overwhelm all grief. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110180">Pour wine, sound music, let our bloods not freeze,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110190">Drink Dutch like gallants, let's drink upsey freeze. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e110200">Exeunt sir Edward, planet, Brabant, drum and Twedle.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110210" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110220">Servant you'll go in too, and stay dinner?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110230" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110240">I in truth, for as the itch is augmented</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110250">By scratching, so is my love by seeing my mistress. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e110260">Exeunt Camelia and Ellis.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110270" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110280">How's this, how's this, my Katherin gone hence? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110290">Senses awake, and thou amazed soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110300">Unwind thyself from out the labyrinth</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110310">Of gaping wonder, and astonishment. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110320">My Katherine departed? how? which way? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110330">Fool, fool, stand not debating, but pursue</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110340">Haste to her comfort, for from thee doth spring</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e110350">(Wretch that thou art) her cause of sorrowing. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e110360">Exit.</stage>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A20867-e110370">
        <head>Actus tertius.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e110380">Enter a page solus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110390" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110400">Ha, ha, ha, tipsy, tipsy, tipsy, all turned whirligig, John fo de King, drum, and Timothy Twedle, are rare fine, ha for the heavens, i'faith: drums lion drunk, and he dings the pots about, cracks the glasses, swaggers with his own shadow. Honest Timothy is maudlin drunk, and he weeps for kindness, and kisses the hilts of Jack drums dagger. Mounsieurs goat drunk, and he<pb facs="17"/> shrugs, and scrubs, and he's it for a wench. Here they come reeling, I must pack, or we shall swagger, for they having a crack in their heads, and I a fault in my hands, we shall ne'er agree.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e110410">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e110420">Enter drum, monsieur, and Twedle.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110430" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110440">A servingman quoth you? Heart, and if I serve any that's flesh and blood, would I might never taste my liquore more: stand bare whilst he makes water, out upon't, I'll to Ireland, and there I'll tan, ran, ty, ry, dan, sa, sa, sa, sa: nay 'tis the only life.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110450" who="A20867-twedle">
          <speaker>Twe.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110460">Nay good thewte heart, good kind Jack, stay, if you would love me, as I love you, we would live and die together: and please God, would I were dead, and you are gone. And here's m. John so de King, a very honest man too.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110470" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110480">Ay, ay, he's a very good honest man: for there's not a hair betwixt him and heaven.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110490" who="A20867-twedle">
          <speaker>Twe.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110500">He'll live with us now and teach us French.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110510" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110520">I by my trot, ang you help me to a vench now, me teach you French. 5. tousand, tousand year, o your secke is hot, and make me brule, and brule, and burn, for a (He) by gour your seck is hot.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e110530">Enter Winifride.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110540" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110550">Welcome Basilisco, thou wilt carry level, and knock ones brains out with thy pricking wit. Kiss me sweet wench, kiss me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110560" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110570">He my Vinifride, by gour you are come, in te very nick to pleasure me, prithee you kiss me, clip me, love me, or by gour me ang die certain.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110580" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110590">Out you French dog, touch my love, and I'll —</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110600" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110610">Touch her, by gour me touch her, and touch her, and touch her.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110620" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker><pb facs="18"/>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110630">I'll touch you, I'll slash you, I'll vench ye.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110640" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110650">Put up, put up, for the passion of God put up, or if you'll needs too it, sheath both your weapons in me first.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110660" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110670">Heart touch my love, touch my Winifrid? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110680" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110690">Hark you Jack, come to my chamber an hour hence, and you shall have what you will ask, and I can grant.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110700" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110710">Why then my choler's down. John fo de King. Foutra for you.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e110720">Exit drum.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110730" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110740">Foutra for me, futtra, futtra, futtra, five tousand futtras for you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110750" who="A20867-twedle">
          <speaker>Twe.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110760">Stay friend Jack, I'll reel along with you, if you'll not swagger.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e110770">Exit Twedle.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110780" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110790">Sweet, sweet monsieur, hang you slaves, I love you infinitely.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110800" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110810">By gour me teach you French four tousand year dan.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110820" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110830">Well monsieur, I'll give you pleasure.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110840" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110850">But will you presently? quickly, for by gour me am a hot shot.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110860" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110870">I so they say, I heard you were under the torrid zone last day.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110880" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110890">Pish 'tis no matter, me am like a tobacco pipe, de more me am burne, de cleaner me am.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110900" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110910">Well then, two hours hence come to my chamber, and Timothy Twedle shall give you me in a sack.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110920" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110930">In a sack? Ha very well.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110940" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110950">And you shall carry me to my master's house at Holloway, for in the house we cannot be private without suspect. Till then, farewell.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e110960">Exit Winifride.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e110970" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker><pb facs="18"/>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e110980">By my trot unreasonably good, I carry de vench on my back, and devench carry me on her (He) fine back, fine vench, fine monsieur, fine, fine, fine knight, all fine, unreasonably fine, me sing vor joy; by gour me sing la, liro, liro la, lilo.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e110990">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e111000">Enter Brabant signior, Brabant junior, and planet.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111010" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111020">Gentlemen, as e'er you loved wench, observe m. puff and me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111030" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111040">What shall we observe you for?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111050" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111060">O for our compliment.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111070" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111080">Compliment, what's that?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111090" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111100">Compliment, is as much as (What call you it) 'tis derived of the Greek word, a pox on't.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111110" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111120">Compliment, is as much as what call you it, 'tis derived of the Greek word, a pox on't.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e111130">Enter Puffe.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111140" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111150">You shall see m. puff and me toss it, i'faith mark with what grace I encounter him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111160" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111170">Heart thy brother's like the instrument the merchants sent over to the great Turk: you need not play upon him, he'll make music of himself, and he be once set going.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111180" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111190">M. puff, I long to do fair service to your love.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111200" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puffe.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111210">Most accomplished wit, exquisitely accoutred, (Puff) judgement, I could wish my ability worthy your service, and my service worthy your ability.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111220" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111230">By the lord fustian, now I understand it: compliment is as much as fustian.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111240" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111250">I protest your abilities are infinite, your perfections matchless, your matchless perfection infinite in ability, and your infinite ability, matchless in perfection.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111260" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker><pb facs="19"/>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111270">Good again, rejoice Brabant, thy brother will not live long, he talks idly already.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111280" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111290">Delicious spirit, disparage not your courtesy, stand not bare to him that was born to honour you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111300" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111310">Let us press our hairs then, with an uniform consent.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111320" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111330">The pressure of my hairs, or the puncture of my heart, stands at the service of your solid perfections: my life is bound to your love, your love being my life, though my life be not worthy your love, your perfection is the centre to which all the parallels of my affection are drawn: your love my life, your perfection, my affection, being —</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111340" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111350">Your ass, my fool.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111360" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111370">Being chained by the mighty coplet of inevitable destiny, who seeth the sun, but he must adore it: who seeth beauty, but he must honour it: who vieweth gold, but he must covet it: then, (O then) who can behold your sunlike beauteous golden beauties, but he must more than adore, much more than honour, and most infinitely love to be out, out, out.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111380" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111390">Out he is indeed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111400" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111410">He's at a stand, like a resty jade, or a fiddler, when he hath cracked his minikin.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111420" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111430">Outrageously addicted to the worthy pursuit of such matchless worth.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111440" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111450">Sir, I can rest but truly thankful, for your more than good conceit of my no less than little worth. And now fir for the consequent hours of the day; how stands your intention for employment?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111460" who="A20867-puff">
          <speaker>Puff:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111470">I ha' ta'en my leave of sir Edward, bid adieu to love, my mistress is gone, my humour is spent, my joys are at an end, and therefore gentlemen, I leave<pb facs="19"/> love, and fall to the (Puff) law, I will inter myself in Ployden's coffin, and take an eternal congee of the world. And so sweet gallants farewell.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e111480">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111490" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111500">Nay I'll follow you to your grave. Gentlemen you'll not accompany the corse?</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e111510">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111520" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111530">No, no, look Ned Brabant, yond's a pleasing object for thy eyes.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e111540">Enter Camelia, Ellis, and Winifride.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111550" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111560">My mistress is turned Bucephalus, nobody must ride her but Alexander: nobody kiss her but John Ellis. Now stand and list good planet. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111570" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111580">Come sweetest love, let's give time pleasing wing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111590">What shall we make some purposes or sing? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111600" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111610">I will sing, so you will bear my burden.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111620" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111630">Come lay thy head then in my virgin lap,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111640">And with a soft sleek hand I'll clap thy cheek,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111650">And wring thy fingers with an ardent gripe:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111660">I'll breathe amours, and even entrance thy spirit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111670">And sweetly in the shade lie dallying. </l>
        </sp>
        <lg xml:id="A20867-e111680">
          <head>The song.</head>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111690">Now dally sport and play, this merry month of May,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111700">This is the merry, merry month, sweet time for dallying:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111710">The birds sit chirping, chirping, the doves sit billing, billing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111720">Philip is treading, is treading, is treading, is treading, is treading,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111730">All are to pleasures willing. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111740">You that are fair and witty, observe this easy ditty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111750">And leave not nature's nature's bliss; do not refuse to kiss. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111760">The birds sit chirping, chirping, the doves sit billing, billing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111770">Philip is treading, is treading, etc. </l>
        </lg>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111780" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111790">Death I can holder: life of love</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111800"><pb facs="20"/> amazing beauty, let not me seem rude,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111810">Though thus I seem to square with modesty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111820" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e111830">Pray you let me go, for he'll begin to square, and even as some do wear muffs for warmth, some for wantonness, some for pride, some for neither, but to hide gouty fingers, so will I get your father's consent, and marry you. Fare you well.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e111840">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111850" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111860">Sir it were good you got a benefice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111870">Some evenuched vicarage, or some fellowship,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111880">To prop up your weak younger brothership. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111890">Match with your equals, dare not to aspire</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111900">My seat of love, I wis sir, I look higher. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e111910" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111920">Astonishment of nature, be not proud</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111930">Of fortune's bounties: Brabant is a man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111940">Though not so clogged with dirt as others are:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111950">I do confess my younger brothership;</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111960">Yet therein lay no such disparagement</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111970">As your high scorn imputes unto my worth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111980">Coach jades and dogs, are coupled still together,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e111990">Only for outward likeness, growth and strength,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112000">But the bright models of eternity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112010">Are joined together for affection,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112020">Which in the soul is formed. O let this move,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112030">Love should make marriage, and not marriage love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112040" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112050">Woo her no more Brabant, thou'lt make her proud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112060">You Dutch ancient why should you look higher? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112070">His births as good as yours, and so's his face:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112080">Put off your iengle, jangles, and be not as fair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112090">He shall renounce it, fore this audience,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112100">Put off your clothes, and you are like a Banbery cheese,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112110">Nothing but paring: why should you be proud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112120">And look on none but weathercocks forsooth? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112130">O you shall have a thousand pound a year! </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112140"><pb facs="20"/>Bar lady that's a bumming sound. But hark,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112150">Wilt therefore be a slave, unto a slave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112160">One that's a bound rogue unto ignorance? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112170">Well thou'lt serve to make him gelid broths,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112180">And scratch his head, and may be now and then</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112190">He'll slaver thee a kiss. Plague on such marriages. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112200" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e112210">Rude uncivil clown.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112220" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e112230">Tut rail not at me, turn your eye upon the leprosy of your own judgement, loathe it, hate it, scorn it, and love this young gentleman, who is a fool in nothing but in loving thee: mad in nothing but affecting thee: and cursed in eternity if he marry thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112240" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112250">Sir you ha' spoken exceeding pleasingly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112260">For which I love you, as I love a dull dead eye. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112270">Brabant I do conjure thee court not me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112280">Do not presume to love or fancy me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112290" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112300">How not presume to love or fancy you? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112310">Heart, I will love you, by this light I will</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112320">Whether you will or no, I'll love you still. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112330">Spite of your teeth I will your love pursue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112340">I will by heaven, and so sweet soul adieu. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e112350">Exit Bra. junior.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112360" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e112370">Farewell, and never view my face again.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e112380">Exit Camelia.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112390" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112400">Hark you fair Winifrid, sweet gentle maid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112410">I have but feigned with you all this while,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112420">I dote upon the sweet Camelia,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112430">And if your favour will but second me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112440">I vow when I shall wed Camelia,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112450">To endow you with a hundred pound a year,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112460">And what I have shall stand at your command. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112470" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Win.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112480">Sir I will undertake to forward your fair love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112490">So you'll remember what you here do vow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112500" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker><pb facs="21"/>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112510">If I forget it, heaven forget me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112520">Do you but praise me, let not her once know</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112530">I love, or do affect her for the world. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112540" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e112550">Well fear no rubs, farewell fair bounteous sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e112560">Exit Winifride.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112570" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112580">It works, it works, magnificent delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112590">Laughter, triumph, for ere the sun go down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112600">Thy forehead shall be wreathed, with pleasure's crown. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e112610">Exit planet.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e112620">Enter Pasquil at one door, and his page at the other.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112630" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112640">Now my kind page, canst thou nor hear, nor see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112650">Which way my Katherine hath bent her steps? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112660" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e112670">Sir I can.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112680" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112690">What canst thou my sweet page? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112700">What canst thou boy? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112710">O how my soul doth burn in longing hope,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112720">And hangs upon thy lips for pleasing news. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112730" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e112740">Sir I can tell ye.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112750" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e112760">What ▪ o how my heart doth quake and throb with fear.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112770" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e112780">Sir I can tell you nothing of her in good faith.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112790" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112800">O thou hast tortured me with lingering hope,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112810">Go haste away, fly from the pestilence</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112820">Of my contagious grief, it will infect thee boy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112830">Murder thy youth, and poison thy life's joy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112840">Run search out Katherine, in her eyes dwell</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112850">Heavens of joy; but in Pasquil hell. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112860">O thou omnipotent, infinity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112870">Crack not the sinews of my patience</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112880">With racking torment: insist not thus to scourge</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112890">My tender youth with sharp affliction,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112900">If I do love that glory of thy hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112910">That rich idea of perfection,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112920">With any lustful or profane intent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112930"><pb facs="21"/> crossed be my love, murdered be all my hopes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112940">But if with chaste and virtuous arm I clip</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112950">The rarest model of thy workmanship,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112960">Be then propitious: o eternal light,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e112970">And bless my fortunes, maugre hellish spite. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e112980">Enter Katherine in a petticoat.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e112990" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113000">Black sorrow, nurse of plaints, of tears, and groans,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113010">Evaporate my spirit with a sigh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113020">That it may hurry after his sweet breath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113030">Who made thee dote on life, now hunt for death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113040" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113050">What soul is that, that with her tearful eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113060">Seems to lament with me in miseries? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113070" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113080">Here seems to be the pressure of his trunk,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113090">Dear earth confirm my doubt, was this the place</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113100">Which the fair body of my Pasquil pressed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113110">When he lay murdered? See the drooping grass</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113120">Hangs down his mourning head, and seems to say</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113130">This was the fatal place, where Pasquil lay. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113140">O thou sweet print, stamped by the fairest limbs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113150">The richest coffin of the purest soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113160">That ever pressed the bosom of the earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113170">First drink my tears, and next suck up my blood. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113180">Now thou immortal spirit of my love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113190">Thou precious soul of Pasquil view this knife</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113200">Which once thou gavest me, and prepare thy arm</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113210">To clip the spirit of thy constant love. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113220">Dear Ned I come, by death I will be thine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113230">Since life denies it to poor Katherine. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e113240">She offers to stab herself.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113250" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113260">Hold, hold, thou miracle of constancy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113270">First let heaven perish, and the crazde world run</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113280">Into first chaos of confusion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113290">Before such cruel violence be done</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113300"><pb facs="22"/> to her fair breast, whose fame by virtue won,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113310">Shall honour women whilst there shines a sun. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113320" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Kathe.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113330">Thrice sacred spirit, why dost thou forsake</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113340">Elysium pleasures, to withhold the arm</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113350">Of wretched Katherine? O let me die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113360">Retire sweet ghost, do not pollute thy hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113370">With touch of mortals. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113380" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113390">Amazement of thy sex, Pasquill doth live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113400">And lives to love thee in eternity. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113410">Be not aghast, recover spirit, (Sweet)</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113420">'Tis Pasquill speaks, 'tis Pasquill clips thy waste,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113430">'Tis Pasquill prints a kiss on thy fair hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113440" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113450">What do I dream? or have I drawn the sluice</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113460">Of life up? and through streams of blood</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113470">Unfelt, have set my prisoned soul at large? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113480">Am I in heaven? or in Pasquil's arms? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113490">I am in heaven, for my Ned's embrace</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113500">Is Katherine's long wished celestial place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113510" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113520">Divinity of sweetness, I protest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113530">If these inferior orbs were rolled up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113540">And the imperial heaven barred to my view,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113550">'Twere not so gracious, nor so much desired,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113560">As my dear Katherine is to Pasquil's sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113570" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e113580">Heaven of content, Paphos of my delight.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113590" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e113600">Mirror of constancy, lifeblood of love.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113610" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e113620">Center to whom all my affections move.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113630" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e113640">Renown of virgins, whose fame shall never fleet.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113650" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113660">O I am mazed with joy, I pray thee sweet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113670">Unfold to me, what sad mischance it was,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113680">Forced thy death's rumour, and such woes dispersed? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113690">Sad sorrow passed, delights to be rehearsed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113700" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113710">It will be tedious, but in brief think thus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113720">Old Mammon's malice was the venombd foam,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113730"><pb facs="22"/> that poisoned all the sweets of our content. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113740" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Kathe.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113750">Alas dear heart, that love should be so crossed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113760">Now good Ned fetch my gown, 'tis at yond house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113770">I would be loath to turn to Highgate thus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113780" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113790">I am obliged with infinite respect, to do you service. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113800">O power divine, was ever such a love as Katherine? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113810" who="A20867-unassigned">
          <speaker>Ent. Ma.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113820">Look Mammon, search Mammon, this way she went,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113830">Put on thy spectacles, this way she went:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113840">Blessed, blessed, blessed, be thy nativity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113850">Yonder she sits, I'll either have her now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113860">Or none shall e'er enjoy her with content. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113870" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e113880">How loves impatient, when will Ned return?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113890" who="A20867-mall">
          <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e113900">Tut, 'tis no matter when, look where thy Mammon is.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113910" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113920">Good devil, for god's sake do not vex my sight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113930">Didst not thou plot the death of my dear love? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e113940" who="A20867-mall">
          <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113950">Yes, yes, and would complot ten thousand deaths,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113960">Even damn my soul, for beauteous Katherine. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113970">My ship shall comb the ocean's curled back</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113980">To furnish thee with brave habiliments,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e113990">Rucks of rich pearl, and sparkling diamonds</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114000">Shall fringe thy garments with embroidery:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114010">Thy head shall blaze as bright with orient stone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114020">As did the world being burned by Phaeton. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114030" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114040">You make me death, for pities sake forbear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114050">O when will Pasquil come? Good sir depart. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114060">When wilt return? I pray you sir go hence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114070">And troth, I will not hate you: nay I'll speak</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114080">Against my heart, and say I loathe you not. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114090">You vex my patience, gentle sir forbear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114100">I beg it on my knee, and with a tear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114110" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114120">Tut will you love me, and detest yond boy?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114130" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114140">Heaven detest me first, and loathe my soul.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114150" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114160">Is it your final resolution?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114170" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker><pb facs="23"/>Ka.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114180">God knows it is. So good sir rest content.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114190" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114200">Ay, I will rest, and thou shalt rest thus blurred,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114210">Thus poisoned; venomed with this oil of toads:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114220">If Mammon cannot get thee, none shall joy</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114230">Which he could not enjoy. I fear no law,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114240">Gold in the firmest conscience makes a flaw. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114250">Rot like to Helen: spittle hence, adieu,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114260">Let Pasquil boast in your next interview. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114270" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114280">Be pitiful and kill me gentle sir. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114290">Heaven my heart is cracked with misery:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114300">Where shall I hide me? which way shall I cleanse</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114310">The eating poison of this venomed oil? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114320">Poor wretch (Alas) see where thy Pasquil comes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114330" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114340">Here love put on your gown. How now? good God,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114350">Heaven give me patience: who hath used thee thus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114360" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114370">The devil in the shape of Mammon. Sweet</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114380">Touch me not. Pasquil I conjure thee now</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114390">By all the power of affection,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114400">By that strict bond of love that links our hearts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114410">Leave and abandon me eternally. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114420">I merit now no love, yet prithee sweet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114430">Vouchsafe to give me leave to love thee still. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114440">But I do bind thee by thy sacred vow</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114450">Of our once happy, and thrice blessed love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114460">Follow not Katherine: good Ned, do not grieve,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114470">In time just heaven may our woes relieve. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e114480">Exit Katherine.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114490" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas. fureus.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114500">O dira fata, saeva, miseranda, horida</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114510">Quis hic locus? quae regio? quae mundi plaga? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114520">Ubi sum? Katherina, Katherina, eheu Katherina. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e114530">Enter Mamon.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114540" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114550">My spectacles will betray me, look</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114560">Mammon, search Mammon, hereabouts they fell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114570" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker><pb facs="23"/>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114580">Welcome erra pater, you that make prognostications for ever. Where's you almanac?</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e114590">Pulles his indentures out of Mammon's bosom.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114600" who="A20867-mall">
          <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114610">Lord bless my obligations, lord bless my bonds, lord bless my obligations. Alas, alas, alas.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114620" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114630">Let me see sir now, when will true valour be at the full? O there's an opposition 'tis eclipsed, Venus, I Venus is mounted. Where's the goat now? Combed, fine combed. O here are dog days, out upon't dog days, dog days, dog days, out upon't.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e114640">He tears the papers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114650" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114660">Alas my obligations, my bonds, my obligations, my bonds. Alas, alas, alas.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114670" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114680">Katherina, Katherina, ehew Katherina.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e114690">Exit Pasquil.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114700" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114710">Obligations, obligations: alas my obligations, I am undone, undone, undone.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e114720">Enter Flawne.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114730" who="A20867-flawne">
          <speaker>Flawne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114740">Sir, sir, sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114750" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114760">What sir you for, you dog, you hound, you</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114770">Crust, what's best news with you now? Out-alas my</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e114780">Obligations, my bonds, I am undone, undone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114790" who="A20867-flawne">
          <speaker>Flawne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114800">Sir, the best news is, your ship (The Hopewell) hath happed ill, returning from Barbary. 'tis but sunk, or so, not a scrap of goods saved.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114810" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114820">Villains, rogues, Jews, Turks, infidels, my nose will rot off with grief. O the gout, the gout, the gout, I shall run mad, run mad, run mad.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114830" who="A20867-flawne">
          <speaker>Flawne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114840">Amen, amen, amen. But there's other news to comfort you withal sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114850" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114860">Let's hear them good Flawne. My ship, my bonds, my bonds, my ship, I shall run mad unless thy good news reclaim me. Let's hear thy news.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114870" who="A20867-flawne">
          <speaker><pb facs="24"/>Flawne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114880">Your house with all the furniture is burned, not a rag left, the people stand warming their hands at the fire, and laugh at your misery.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114890" who="A20867-mamon">
          <speaker>Mam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114900">I defy heaven, earth and hell, renounce my nose, plague, pestilence, confusion, famine, sword and fire, devour all, devour me, devour Flawne, devour all: bonds, house, and ship, ship, house, and bonds, despair, damnation, hell, I come, I come, so room for Mammon, room for usury, room for thirty in the hundred. I come, I come, I come.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e114910">Exit Mamon.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114920" who="A20867-flawne">
          <speaker>Flawne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114930">Why methinks this is right now, I'll even lay him up in bedlam, commit him to the mercy of the whip, the entertainment of bread and water, and the the sting of a usurer's conscience for ever.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e114940">Exit Flawne.</stage>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A20867-e114950">
        <head>Actus quartus.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e114960">Enter drum and Winifride.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114970" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e114980">Truly mistress Winifrid, as I would be willing to be thankful, and thankful to find you willing to prostrate your fair parts to my pleasure, so I hope you will remember your promise, and promise what you now remember, if you have forgotten, I would be glad to put you in mind of it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e114990" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115000">Truly friend John, as I would be loath to break my promise, so I would be unwilling to keep my word to the dishonesting of my virginity. Marry for a night's lodging or so, I will not be straight laced to my friend. Therefore thus it must be. Tonight I must lie at the farm at Holloway, thither shall you be conveyed in this sack, and laid in my chamber, from whence you shall have free access to the pleasures of my private bed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115010" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker><pb facs="24"/>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115020">Well then be constant Winifrid, and you shall find me faithful Jack drum: and so taking leave of your lips, I betake me to the tuition of the sack.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115030">Enter Twedle.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115040">Exit drum.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115050" who="A20867-twedle">
          <speaker>Twe.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115060">Winifrid my mistress Camelia stays for you to attend her to the green, I must go and clap my tabers cheeks there, for the heavens i'faith.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115070" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115080">Stay a little here, and if John fo de King come, give him that sack. O I could crack my whalebones, break my busk, to think what laughter may arise from this.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115090">Exit Winifride.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115100">Enter monsieur.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115110" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115120">By my trot, dis love is a most cleanly gentleman, he is very full of shift, de fine vench, can invent ten tousand, tousand trick to kiss a men (He) see by gour she ha' keep her word, she is in de seck already, he, brave by gour, my blood das sparkle in my vein for joy. Metre Timotty you must give me dat seck dear.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115130" who="A20867-timothy">
          <speaker>Timo.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115140">Owy da monsieur, that is well pronounced is it not?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115150" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115160">Ritt, ritt, ritt, excellan: excellan: adieu Timothy, me am almost burst for joy.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115170">Exit monsieur.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115180" who="A20867-twedle">
          <speaker>Twe.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115190">Well, I know what the wenches on the green are saying now, as well as if I were in their bellies, when will Timothy come, when will honest Timothy approach, when will good Timothy draw near? Well wenches now rejoice, for Timothy Twedle doth come.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115200">Exit Twedle.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115210">Enter Pla. Bra. sig. and Bra. junior.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115220" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115230">Brother how like you of our modern wits? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115240">How like you the new poet Mellidus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115250" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115260">A slight bubbling spirit, a cork, a husk.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115270" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker><pb facs="25"/>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115280">How like you musus fashion in his carriage?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115290" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115300">O filthily, he is as blunt as Pawles. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115310" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115320">What think you of the lines of Decius? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115330">Writes he not a good cordial sappy style? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115340" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115350">A surreinde jaded wit, but 'a rubs on.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115360" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115370">Brabant thou art like a pair of balance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115380">Thou weigh'st all saving thyself. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115390" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Br. sig.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115400">Good faith, troth is, they are all apes and gulls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115410">Vile imitating spirits, dry heathy turfs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115420" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115430">Nay brother, now I think your judgement errs.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115440" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115450">Err, he cannot err man, for children and fools speak truth always.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115460">Enter monsieur with a sack, and Jack drum in it.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115470" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115480">See who comes yonder sweating with a pack.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115490" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115500">Monsieur, what do you bear there ha?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115510" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115520">Prithee you away, you break my glasses der, Jesus, now me know not what to do, zot dat I was to come dis way widd dem.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115530" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115540">Glasses you salt rheum, come what ha' you there?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115550" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115560">Trick no more for Jesus sake, by gour me have brittle vare, if you knock it, it will break presant, pre you adieu.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115570" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Br. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115580">We must know what's in the bag i'faith.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115590" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115600">By my trot, me tell you true, will you no trick me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115610" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115620">No faith, but see you tell us true, or else.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115630" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115640">Or else, or else by gour, do what you please wid me: sweet Vinifride, my very art dus vurst, he by gour, me did not dink to wrong ye dus: come out sweet Vinifrid, me much discredit ye.</p>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115650">He Jack drum. Jesu vat made you dear?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115660" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115670">Gentlemen my m. desires you to come sup with him, I was sent to invite you, and this itching goat, would needs ease my legs and carry me: I hope you'll<pb facs="25"/> come, and so I take my leave. Ay, I am gulled, but if I quit her not, well.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115680">Exit drum.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115690" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115700">Come, there's some knot of knavery in this trick.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115710" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115720">His colour is not currant, well, let pass.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115730" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115740">Come monsieur, come, I'll help you to a</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115750">Go down the hill before, I'll follow you. Wench,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115760" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115770">Me dank you: mor deu, he mon a me, me am trooke dead wit grief, de cock of my humour is down, and me may hang myself vor a vench.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115780">Exit Moun.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115790" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115800">Gentlemen will you laugh heartily now?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115810" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115820">Ay, and if thou wilt play the fool kindly now.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115830" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115840">I will straight frame the strongest eternal jest</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115850">That e'er was builded by invention:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115860">My wife lies very private in the town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115870">I'll bring the French man to her presently,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115880">As to a loose lascivious courtesan:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115890">Nor he, nor you, nor she, shall know the rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115900">But it shall be immortal for a jest. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115910">Exit Bra. sig.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115920" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e115930">Farewell brother, we shall meet at Highgate soon.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115940" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115950">The wicked jest be turned on his own head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e115960">Pray God he may be kindly cuckoled. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115970">Exeunt both.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e115980">Enter Camelia and Winifride.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e115990" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116000">Carry this favour to my Ellis straight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116010">I long to see him, prithee bid him come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116020" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116030">I would be loath to nourish your defame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116040">And therefore mistress pray you pardon me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116050" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e116060">What is thy judgement of my Ellis change?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116070" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116080">No that is firm: but your estate is changed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116090">You know your sister's strangely vanished,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116100">And now the hope and revenue of all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116110"><pb facs="26"/> calls you his sole, and fair apparent heir:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116120">Now therefore would I have you change your love. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116130">Indeed I yield 'tis modern policy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116140">To kiss even dirt that plasters up our wants. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116150">I'll not deny, 'tis worthy wit's applause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116160">For women on whom lowering fortune squints,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116170">And casts but half an eye of due respect,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116180">To pin some amorous idiot to their eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116190">And use him as they use their looking-glass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116200">See how to adorn their beauties by his wealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116210">And then case up the fool and lay him by. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116220">But for such ladies as yourself is now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116230">Whose fortunes are sustained by all the props</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116240">That gracious fortune can advance you with,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116250">For such a one to yoke her free sweet youth</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116260">Unto a loon, a dane-like barbarous sot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116270">A guilden truncheon, fie, 'tis slavish vile. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116280">O what is richer than content in love? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116290">And will you now having so huge a ruck</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116300">Of heaped up fortunes, go and chain yourself</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116310">To a dull post, whose very eyes will blaze</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116320">His base bred spirit, where so e'er he comes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116330">And shame you with the very name of wife. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116340">No mistress, no, I have found out a man</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116350">That merits you, if man can merit you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116360" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116370">Lord what a tide of hate comes creeping on</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116380">Upon my former judgement? Come, the man? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116390" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116400">The man? (O God) the man is such a man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116410">That he is matchless: o, I shall profane</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116420">His name, with unrespected utterance. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116430" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e116440">O thou torment'st me, dear Winifrid the man?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116450" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116460">By the sweet pleasures of an amorous bed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116470">I think you will be deified by him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116480"><pb facs="26"/>O God the most accomplished man that breathes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116490">And planet is the man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116500" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e116510">Out on the devil, there's a man indeed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116520" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116530">Nay look you now, you'll straight o'ershoot yourself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116540">You'll say he's sour and unsociable:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116550">Tush you know him not, that humour's forced:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116560">But in his native spirit he's as kind</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116570">As is the life of love. And then the clearest skin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116580">The whitest hand, the cleanest well shaped leg:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116590">The quickest eye: fie, fie, I shall but blur</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116600">And sully his bright worth with my rude speech. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116610" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e116620">Well, if he court me, I'll not be much coy.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116630" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116640">Court you? nay you must court him for ought I know:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116650">You must not think forsooth, that I am feed</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116660">To urge you thus. I solemnly protest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116670">I motion this out of my pure vowed love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116680">Which wisheth all advancement and content</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116690">To attend the glory of your beauteous youth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116700" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116710">O I am planet stricken Winifrid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116720">How shall I intimate my love to him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116730" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wi.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116740">I saw him coming up the hill even now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116750">Send him a favour, and I'll bear it to him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116760">And tell him you desire to speak with him. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e116770">Exit Winifride.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116780" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e116790">Do, do, dear Winifrid, sweet wench make haste.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e116800">Enter sir Edward fortune, and John Ellis, with a paper in his hand.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116810" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>Ellis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e116820">Sir, I have her good will, and please you now to give me your consent, and look you sir, here I have itemed forth what I am worth.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116830" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e116840">Tush show me no items, and she love you, a god's name: I'll not be cursed by my daughter for<pb facs="27"/> forcing her to clip a loathed, abhorred match: and see how fortunate we are; look where she stands.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116850" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e116860">Sweet planet, thou only governest me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116870" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e116880">Daughter give me your hand, with your consent, I give you to this gentleman.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116890" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e116900">Marry phoh, will you match me to a fool?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116910" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116920">God pardon me, not I: why m. Ellis ha? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116930">Had you her consent, speak freely man? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116940" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116950">Indeed la now; I thought so: by my troth</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e116960">You said you loved me, that you did indeed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116970" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e116980">I as my fool, my idiot to make sport.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e116990" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117000">Fie daughter, you are too plain with him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117010">Alas my son simile is out of countenance. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117020" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117030">Truly as a mill-horse, is not a horse mill, and as a cart jade, is not a jade cart, even so will I go hang myself.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117040" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117050">Marry God forbid, what frolic, frolic man, we'll have a cup of sack and sugar soon, shall quite expel these musty humours of stale melancholy.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e117060">Enter Pasquil and a country wench, with a basket of eggs.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117070" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117080">Is this the egg where Castor and Pollux bred? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117090">I'll crack the bastard in the very shell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117100" who="A20867-multiple">
          <speaker>Coun. maid.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117110">Alas my markets, my markets are clean spoiled.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e117120">Exit wench.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117130" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117140">Ubi Helena, ubi Troia, is't not true my Ganymede,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117150">When shall old Saturn mount his throne again? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117160">See, see, alas how bleak religion stands. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117170">Katherina, Katherina, you damned titanoies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117180">Why prick you heavens ribs with blasphemy? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117190">Python yet breathes, old grey haired piety. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117200" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117210">Alas kind youth, how came he thus distraught?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117220" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker><pb facs="27"/>Page.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117230">I left him in pursuit of Katherine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117240">And found him in this strange distemperature. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117250" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117260">O sir, is't you that stamp on literature? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117270">You are inspired you with prophesy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117280" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117290">Not I, as I shall be saved, I am m. John Ellis I.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117300" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117310">Come, come, let's entice him by some good means,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117320">I'll labour to reclaim him to his wits. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117330">O now my daughter Katherine remembers me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117340">Where art thou girl? heaven give me patience. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117350" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117360">Poor, poor Astrea, who blurs thy orient shine? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117370">Come yond's the Capitol of Jupiter,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117380">Let's whip the senate, else they will not leave</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117390">To have their justice blasted with abuse</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117400">Of flattering sycophants. Come let's mount the stars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117410">Reverend antiquity go you in first —</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117420">Dotage will follow. Then comes pale faced lust —</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117430">Next Sodom, than Gomorha, next poor I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117440">By heaven my heart is burst with misery. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e117450">Exit Pas.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e117460">Enter Brabant signior, monsieur and the page.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117470" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117480">I ha tell ye de very troth of the lag jest, by gour your England damosels are so fear, so vittie, so kit, by my troth she toss me wish vey she please der: but pre ye were is de vench? Is dis de house? Ha is dis de house, pre ye tell me ha?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117490" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117500">It is, it is, and she is in the inner chamber:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117510">Boy call her forth. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e117520">Exit page.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117530" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <stage xml:id="A20867-e117540">Sings.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117550">By gour den me must needs now sing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117560">Ding, ding, a ding, ding a, ding a, ding,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117570">For me am now at pleasure's spring. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117580">Ding a, ding, ding, ding a, ding a, ding a, ding,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117590">And a he da vench, da vench, da vench,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117600">Which must my bruling humour quench. Coma, coma, come. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e117610"><pb facs="28"/>Enter mistress Brabant.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117620" who="A20867-mrs_brabant">
          <speaker>Mistress Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117630">Now sweet, you kept your promise well last night.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117640" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117650">By gorshe give him much kind word already.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117660" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117670">Well to make thee amends, boy fetch us a quart of canary sack. Pry thee Mall entertain this French gentleman.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117680" who="A20867-mrs_brabant">
          <speaker>Mistress Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117690">Sir you are very welcome to my lodging.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117700" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117710">Me danck you, and first me kiss your finger, next me buss your lip, and last me clip your vast, and now foutra for de Vinifride. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117720" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117730">Sir Edward's caterer passed by sir, you willed me to remember lemons.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117740" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117750">God's precious 'tis true: boy go with me to Billingsgate. Mall I'll return straight.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e117760">Exit Bra. sig. and his page.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117770" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117780">Will ye no vin sir, he, he is gone purposely, by my troth most kind gentleman. Fair madam prithee ye pity me, by gour me languish for your love, me am a povera French gentleman, prithee you show me your bedchamber.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117790" who="A20867-mrs_brabant">
          <speaker>Mistress Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117800">What mean you sir, by this strange passion?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117810" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117820">Nay noting, by gour damosel, you be so fair, so admirably fair, flesh and blood cannot endure your countenance, me brule, ang me brule, ang ye ha' no compassion, by gour me ang quite languish. Last night me go to bed, ang me put de candle behind me, and by my troth me see clean torough me. Me ang so dry, me put a cold plattre at my back, and my back melt de plattre quite, do so burn. Prithee you show me your bed Chambre, me will be secret constant: I love you unreasonably vell ▪ unreasonably vell by gour.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117830" who="A20867-mrs_brabant">
          <speaker>Mistress Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117840">In faith you make me blush, what should I say?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117850" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker><pb facs="28"/>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117860">Say no, ang take it: or ark you one ting, say neder yea nor no, but take it, ang say noting.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117870" who="A20867-mrs_brabant">
          <speaker>Mistress Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117880">You will be close and secret?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117890" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117900">Secred, by gour as secred as your soul, me will tell noting, possible.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117910" who="A20867-mrs_brabant">
          <speaker>Mistress Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117920">Well sir, if it please you to see my chamber, 'tis at your service.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e117930">Exit mist. Brabant.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117940" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e117950">He now me ang brave monsieur, by gour ang me had know dis, me wood have eat some potatoes, or Ringo: but vell: he. Me will tanck metre Brabant vor dis, by gour me am caught in heaven bliss.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e117960">Exit monsieur.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e117970">Enter Camelia and Winifride, hanging on planets arms.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e117980" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e117990">O too unkind, why dost thou scorn my love? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118000">She that with all the vehemence of speech</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118010">Hath been pursued, and kneeled too for love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118020">Prostrates herself, and all her choicest hopes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118030">As low as to thy feet, disdain me not,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118040">To scorn a virgin, is man's odious blot ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118050" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118060">To scorn a man, is virgin's odious blot. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118070">Wert thou as rich as is the ocean's womb,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118080">As beauteous as the glorious frame of heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118090">Yet would I loathe thee worse than varnished skulls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118100">Whose ryuels are daubed up with plastering paint. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118110" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e118120">O rocky spirit.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118130" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118140">Breathe not in vain, I hate thy flatterings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118150">Detest thy purest elegance of speech,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118160">Worse than I do the croaking of a toad. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118170" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e118180">Sweet gentleman.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118190" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118200">Peace you rebato pinner, poting-stick,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118210">You bribed corrupters of affection:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118220"><pb facs="29"/> I hate you both, by heaven I hate her more</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118230">Than I do love myself. Hence pack, away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118240">I'll sooner dote upon a blear-eyed witch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118250">A sapless beldame, then I'll flatter thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118260" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118270">Be not too cruel sweet planet, dear relent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118280">Compassionate my amorous languishment. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118290" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118300">Ha, ha, I pray thee kneel, beg, blubber, cry,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118310">Whilst I behold thee with a loathing eye:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118320">And laugh to see thee weep. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118330" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118340">Look, on my knees I creep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118350">Be not impenetrable beauteous youth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118360">But smile upon me, and I'll make the air</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118370">Court thy choice ear with soft delicious sounds. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118380">Bring forth the viols, each one play his part,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118390">Music's the quiver of young Cupid's dart. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e118400">The song with the viols.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118410" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118420">Out Siren, peace screech-owl, hence chattering pie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118430">The blacked beaked night crow, or the howling dog,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118440">Shall be more gracious than thy squeaking voice:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118450">Go sing to m. John. I shall be blunt</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118460">If thou depart not, hence, go mourn and die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118470">I am the scourge of light inconstancy. <stage xml:id="A20867-e118480">Exit Camelia and Winifride.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118490">Thus my dear Brabant, am I thy revenge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118500">And whip her for the peevish scorn she bore</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118510">To thy weak younger birth: o that the souls of men</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118520">Were temperate like mine, than nature's paint</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118530">Should not triumph o'er our infirmities. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118540">I do adore with infinite respect,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118550">Women whose merit issues from their worth</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118560">Of inward graces, but these rotten posts</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118570">That are but guilt with outward garnishment,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118580"><pb facs="29"/> oh how my soul abhors them. Yond's my friend,<stage xml:id="A20867-e118590">Enter Brabant junior.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118600">I will conceal what I for him have wrought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118610">Nice jealousy mistakes a friendly part:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118620">Now Brabant where's thy elder brother ha? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118630">What hath he built the jest with monsieur yet? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118640" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118650">Faith I know not, but I heard he left the</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118660">Frenchman with his wife. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118670" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e118680">Knew she thy brothers meaning?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118690" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e118700">Not a whit, she's a mere stranger to this merriment.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118710" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118720">Hit and be lucky, o that 'twere lawful now</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118730">To pray to God that he were cuckoled. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118740">Dear Brabant I do hate these bombast wits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118750">That are puffed up with arrogant conceit</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118760">Of their own worth, as if omnipotence</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118770">Had hoist them to such unequalled height,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118780">That they surveyed our spirits with an eye</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118790">Only create to censure from above,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118800">When good souls they do nothing but reprove. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118810">See where a shallop comes. How now, what news? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e118820">Enter Winifride, and whispers with planet.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118830" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118840">What might this mean, that Winifrid salutes</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118850">The blunt taongued planet, with such private speech? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118860">See with what vehemence she seems to urge</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118870">Some private matter. Planet is my friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118880">And yet the strongest link of friendship's strained,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118890">When female love puts to her mighty strength. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118900">Mark, mark, she offers him Camelia's scarf:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118910">Now on my life 'tis so: planet supplants my love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118920" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118930">Friend I must leave thee, prithee pardon me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118940">We'll meet at supper soon with the good knight. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e118950">Exeunt Pla. and Winifride.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e118960" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker><pb facs="30"/>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118970">Ay, ay, content: o hell to my delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118980">My friend will murder me, thin cobweb lawn</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e118990">Burst with each little breath of tempting sweets. <stage xml:id="A20867-e119000">Winifride speaks from within.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119010">She entreats you m. planet, to meet</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119020">Her at the cross stile. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e119030" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119040">Ha, at the cross stile, well I'll meet him there. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119050">He that's perfidious to me in my love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119060">Confusion take him, and his blood be spilt</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119070">Without confusion to the murderer. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e119080">Exit Brabant.</stage>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A20867-e119090">
        <head>Actus Qvintus.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e119100">Enter Bra. ju. and his page, charging a pistol.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e119110" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119120">So load it soundly, murders great with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119130">Go boy, discharge it, even in planet's breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119140">Shoot him quite through, and through, thou canst not sin</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119150">To murder him, that murdered his dear friend</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119160">With damned breach of friendship, when he is slain</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119170">Bring me his cloak and hat, here I will stay</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119180">To be embraced in steed of planet: go, away. <stage xml:id="A20867-e119190">Exit boy.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119200">I had rather die with blood upon my head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119210">Shame and reproach clogging my heavy hour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119220">Then t'have my friend still wounding of my soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119230">With reprobate apostasism in love. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119240">O this sophisticate friendship, that dissolves</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119250">With every heat of fancy, let it melt</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119260">Even in hell's forge ▪ hark, the pistol is discharged,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119270">The act of gory murder is performed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119280">Have mercy heaven: o my soul is rent</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119290"><pb facs="30"/><stage xml:id="A20867-e119300">Enter the page.</stage>with planet's wound. Come boy the hat and cloak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119310">Go post to Scotland, there are crowns for thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119320">Leave Brabant unto death, and obloquy. <stage xml:id="A20867-e119330">Exit page.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119340">Why now the ulcerous swelling of my hate</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119350">Is broken forth: o that these women's beauties,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119360">This nature's witchcraft, should inchant our souls</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119370">So infinitely unrecoverable,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119380">That hell, death, shame, eternal infamy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119390">Cannot reclaim our desperate resolves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119400">But we will on spite of damnation. <stage xml:id="A20867-e119410">Enter Camelia and Winifride.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119420">Come ye poor garments of my murdered friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119430">Mourn that you are compelled to hide his limbs</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119440">That slew you master. See Camelia comes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119450">I'll stand thus muffled and deceive her sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119460">When love makes head, friendship is put to flight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e119470" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119480">Persist not still, o thou relentless youth</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119490">To scorn my love: what though I scorned thy friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119500">Do not upbraid me still with hating him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119510">Do not still view me with a loathing eye. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119520">For Brabant's sake, do you but love me sweet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119530">And I'll not scorn him. Why shouldst be so nice</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119540">In keeping laws of friendship? didst thou e'er hear</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119550">Of any soul that held a friend more dear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119560">Than a fair woman? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e119570" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119580">O the sting of death, how hath Brabant erred? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119590">Hence thou vile womb of my damnation,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119600">O thou wronged spirit of my murdered friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119610">Thou guiltless, spotless, pure immaculate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119620"><pb facs="31"/> behold this arm thrusting swift vengeance</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119630">Into the trunk of a cursed damned wretch. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e119640">He draws his rapier.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e119650" who="A20867-winifrid">
          <speaker>Wini.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e119660">He'll spoil himself, let's run and call for help.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e119670">Exit camel. and Wini.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e119680" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119690">Now have I room for murder, this vast place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119700">Hushed silence, and dumb solitude, are fit</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119710">To be observers of my tragedy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119720">Planet accept the smoke of reeking blood</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119730">To expiate thy murder. Friend I come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119740">We'll troop together to Elysium. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e119750">Enter sir Edward, Camelia, Winifride, Ellis, Brabant sig. Twedle, drum, and others.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e119760" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e119770">Hold harebrained youth, what mischief mads thy thoughts?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e119780" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119790">Forbear good knight, you never sinned so deep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119800">As in detaining this just vengeance</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119810">To light upon me, but know I will die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119820">I have infringed the laws of God and man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119830">In shedding of my planets guiltless blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119840">Who I supposed corrivaled me in love</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119850">Of that Camelia, but injuriously:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119860">And therefore gentle knight, let mine own hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119870">Be mine own hangman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e119880" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e119890">Brother I'll get you pardon, fear it not.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e119900" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119910">You'll get my pardon, brother pardon me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119920">You shall not, for I'll die in spite of thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e119930" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e119940">I am turned wild in wonder of this act.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e119950"><pb facs="31"/>Enter planet and the page.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e119960" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119970">Come Brabant come, give me my cloak and hat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119980">The evening's raw and dank, I shall take cold. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e119990">How now? turned mad, why starest thou on me thus? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120000">Give me my cloak. Heart is the youth distraught? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120010" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e120020">Ha, dost thou breathe, let's see where is thy wound?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120030" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e120040">Dost breathe, my wound, what dost thou mean by this?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120050" who="A20867-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120060">Gentlemen I can direct you forth</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120070">This labyrinth of intricate misdoubts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120080">My m. willed me kill that gentleman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120090">Now I thought he was mad in putting me</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120100">To such an enterprise, and therefore soothed him up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120110">With I sir, yes sir, and so sir, at each word,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120120">Whilst he would show me how to hold the dag,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120130">To draw the cock, to charge, and set the flint,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120140">Mean time I had the wit to think him mad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120150">And therefore went, and as he willed me shot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120160">Which he God knows, thought pierced his dear friends heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120170">Then went and borrowed that same hat and cloak</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120180">Of m. planet, brought them to my master,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120190">And so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120200" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120210">No more, no more, knight I will make thee smile</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120220">When I discourse how much my friend hath erred. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120230" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120240">I will dissolve and melt my soul tonight ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120250">In influent laughter. Come 'My jocund spirit</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120260">Presageth some unhoped for happiness:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120270">We'll crown this evening with triumphant joy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120280">I'll sup upon this green, here's room enough</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120290">To draw a liberal breath, and laugh aloud:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120300"><pb facs="32"/> drum fetch the table: Twedle scour your pipe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120310">For my old bones will have a round tonight . </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120320">Now by my troth and I had thought on't too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120330">I would have had a play: i'faith I would. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120340">I saw the children of Paul's last night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120350">And troth they pleased me pretty, pretty well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120360">The apes in time will do it handsomely. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120370" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120380">I'faith I like the audience that frequenteth there</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120390">With much applause: a man shall not be choked</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120400">With the stench of garlic, nor be pasted</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120410">To the barmy jacket of a beer ▪ brewer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120420" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120430">'Tis a good gentle audience, and I hope the boys</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120440">Will come one day into the court of requests. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120450" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120460">I and they had good plays, but they produce</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120470">Such musty fopperies of antiquity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120480">And do not suit the humorous age's backs</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120490">With clothes in fashion. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120500" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120510">Well Brabant well, you will be censuring still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120520">There lies a jest in steep will whip you fort't. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120530" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120540">Gallants I have no judgement in these things,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120550">But will it please you sit? Camelia</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120560">Call these same gentlemen unto thee wench:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120570">Oh there with thee my Katherine was wont</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120580">To sit with graceful presence, well let't pass:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120590">Fetch me a cup of sack. Come gallants sit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120600">M. Brabant, m. planet, I pray you sit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120610">Young m. Brabant, and gods precious m. John,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120620">Sit all, and consecrate this night to mirth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120630">Here is old Ned's place: come, sound music there,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120640">What gallants have you never a page can entertain</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120650">This pleasing time with some French brawl or song? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120660">What shall we have a galliard? troth 'tis well. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120670"><pb facs="32"/><stage xml:id="A20867-e120680">A galliard.</stage>good boy i'faith, I would thou hadst more room. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e120690">Enter Katherine.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120700" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120710">Once more the gracious heavens have renewed</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120720">My wasted hopes, once more a blessed chance</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120730">Hath fetched again my spirit from the sound</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120740">And languishing despair of happiness. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120750">A skilful beldame with the juice of herbs</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120760">Hath cured my face, and killed the venom's power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120770">And now if Pasquil live and love me still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120780">Heaven is bounteous to poor Katherine. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120790">Yond sups my father, but my ned's not there</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120800">I fear, and yet I know not what I fear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120810" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e120820">Gallants I drink this to Ned Pasquil's health.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120830" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e120840"> i'faith I'll pledge him, would he had his wits.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120850" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120860">And I my daughter. Fill me one cup more:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120870">No grief so potent, but neat sparkling wine</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120880">Can conquer him: o this is juice divine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120890" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120900">Would he had his wits. O what a numbing fear</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120910">Strikes a cold palsy through my trembling blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e120920">Enter Pasquil mad.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e120930" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120940">Virtue shall burst open the iron gates of hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120950">I'll not be cooped up, room for Phaeton ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120960">Lame policy how canst thou go upright? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120970">O lust, stain not sweet love. Fie be not lost</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120980">Upon the surge of vulgar humours. You idiot</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e120990">Rivet my armour, and caparison,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121000">A mighty centaur, for I'll run at tilt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121010">And tumble down y on giant in the dust. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121020">Sit gentle judges of great Radamanth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121030">Let not Proserpine rule thee. O she's dead ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121040">Now thou art right Aeacus, I appeal to thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121050">Have pity on a wretch's misery. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121060" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker><pb facs="33"/>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121070">I am quite sunk with grief, what shall we do</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121080">To get recovery of his wits again? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121090" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121100">Let music sound, for I have often heard</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121110">It hath such sweet agreement with our souls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121120">That it corrects vain humours, and recalls</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121130">His straggling fancies to fair union. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121140" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121150">Why the soul of man is naught but simphonies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121160">A sound of disagreeing parts, yet fair unite</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121170">By heaven's hand, divine by reason's light. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121180" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e121190">Sound music, then pray God it take effect.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e121200">The musics sounds, and Pasquil's eye is fixed upon Catherine.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121210" who="A20867-brabant_jr">
          <speaker>Bra. junior</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121220">Mark with what passion he sucks up the sweets</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121230">Of this fame delicate harmonious breath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121240" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121250">Observe him well, methinks his eye is fixed</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121260">Upon some object that seems to attract</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121270">His very soul forth with astonishment</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121280">Mark with what vehemence his thoughts do speak</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121290">Even in his eyes, some creature stands far off,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121300">That hath entranced him with a pleasing sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121310" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121320">Amazement, wonder, stiff astonishment,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121330">Stare and stand gazing on this miracle,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121340">Perfection, of whate'er a humane thought</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121350">Can reach with his discursive faculties,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121360">Thou whose sweet presence purifies my sense,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121370">And dost create a second soul in me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121380">Dear Katherine, the life of Pasquil's hopes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121390" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Ka.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e121400">Dear Pasquil, the life of Katherine's hopes.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121410" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121420">Once more let me embrace the constant'st one</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121430">That e'er was termed her sex perfection. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121440" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker><pb facs="33"/>Kathe.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121450">Once more let me be valued worth his love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121460">In decking of whose soul, the graces strove. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121470" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121480">Spite hath outspent itself, and thus at last,</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e121490">Both speak.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121500" who="A20867-missing">
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121510">We clip with joyful arm each others waist. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121520" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121530">O pardon me thou dread omnipotence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121540">I thought thou couldst not thus have blessed me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121550">O thou hast dewed my grey hairs with thy love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121560">And made my old heart sprout with fertile joy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121570" who="A20867-katherine">
          <speaker>Kathe.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121580">Forget dear father, that my act hath wronged</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121590">The quiet of your age. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121600" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121610">No more, no more, I know what thou wouldst say</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121620">Daughter, there's nothing but salvation,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121630">Could come unto my heart more gracious</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121640">Than is the sight of my dear Katherine. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121650">Son Pasquill now, for thou shalt be my son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121660">What frolic gentle youth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121670" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e121680">Is Mammon here?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121690" who="A20867-drum">
          <speaker>Drum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e121700">O sir, m. Mammon is in a city of jury, called Bethlem, alias plain bedlam: the price of whips is mightily risen since his brain was pitifully overtumbled, they are so fast spent upon his shoulders.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121710" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e121720">O sacred heavens, how just is thy revenge?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121730" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121740">Why? did he cast you in the labyrinth</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121750">Of these strange crosses? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121760" who="A20867-pasquill">
          <speaker>Pas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121770">Yes honoured knight, which in more private place</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121780">And fitter time, I will disclose at large. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121790" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121800">Faith sister, as I am your elder born,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121810">So will I match before or with you sure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121820">Young m. Brabant? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121830" who="A20867-brabant">
          <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e121840">By this light not I. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121850" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e121860">Honest m. Ellis? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121870" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker><pb facs="34"/>Ellis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121880">No indeed la, not I, I do not use to marry ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121890">For even as black patches are worn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121900">Some for pride, some to stay the rheum, and</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121910">Some to hide the scab, even so John Ellis</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e121920">Scorn her, that hath scorned him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121930" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Came.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e121940">Virtuous master planet. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121950" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e121960">Errant wandering star we shall ne'er agree.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121970" who="A20867-camelia">
          <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e121980">M. Brabant, m. planet, m. Ellis, faith I'll have any.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e121990" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122000">But nobody will have thee, this is the plague of light inconstancy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122010">Go Twedle, bid the butler broach fresh wine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122020">Set up wax lights, and furnish new the boards,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122030">Knock down a score of beeves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122040">Invite my neighbours straight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122050">And make my dressers groan with weight of meat. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122060">M. Ellis, pray you let us hear your high Dutch song,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122070">You are admired for it: good let's hear it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122080" who="A20867-ellis">
          <speaker>El.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e122090">I do not use to sing, and yet even as when the sky falls we shall have larks, even so when my voice riseth, you shall have a song.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e122100">He singeth, holding a bowl of drink in his hand.</stage>
        <lg xml:id="A20867-e122110">
          <head>The song.</head>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122120">Give us once a drink, for an the black bowl,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122130">Sing gentle butler balley moy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122140">For an the black bowl. Sing gentle butler balley moy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122150">Give us once some drink, for an the pint pot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122160">Sing gentle butler balley moy, the pint pot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122170">For an the black bowl. Sing gentle butler balley moy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122180">Give us once a drink, for an the quart pot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122190">Sing gentle butler bally moy, the quart, the pint pot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122200">For an the black bowl. Sing gentle butler bally moy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122210">Give us once some drink, for an the pottle pot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122220">Sing gentle butler bally moy, the pottle, the quart, the pint pot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122230">For an the black bowl. Sing gentle butler bally moy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122240"><pb facs="34"/>Give us once a drink, for an the gallon pot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122250">Sing gentle butler bally moy, the gallon, the pottle, the quart, the pint pot, for an the black bowl. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122260">Sing gentle butler bally moy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122270">Give us once a drink for an the firkin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122280">Sing gentle butler bally moy, the firkin, the gallon, the pottle, the quart, the pint pot, for an the black bowl. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122290">Sing gentle butler bally moy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122300">Give us once a drink for an the kilderkin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122310">Sing gentle butler bally moy, the kilderkin, the firkin, the gallon, the pottle, the quart, the pint pot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122320">For and the black bowl. Sing gentle butler bally moy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122330">Give us once some drink for an the barrel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122340">Sing gentle butler bally moy, the barrel, the kilderkin, the</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122350">Firkin, the gallon, the pottle, the quart, the pint pot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122360">For an the black bowl. Sing gentle butler bally moy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122370">Give us once some drink for an the hogshead,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122380">Sing gentle butler bally moy, the hogshead, the barrel, the</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122390">Kilkerkin, the firkin, the gallon, the pottle, the quart, the pint pot, for an the black bowl. Sing gentle butler bally moy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122400">Give us once a drink for an the but,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122410">Sing gentle butler bally moy, the but, the hogshead, the barrel, the kilderkin, the firkin, the gallon, the pottle, the quart, the pint pot, for an the black bowl. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122420">Sing gentle butler bally moy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122430">Give us once some drink for an the pipe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122440">Sing gentle butler bally moy, the pipe, the but, the hogshead, the barrel, the kilderkin, the firkin, the gallon, the pottle, the quart, the pint pot, for an the black bowl. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122450">Sing gentle butler bally moy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122460">Give us once some drink for an the tun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122470">Sing gentle butler bally moy, the tun, the pipe, the but, the the hogshead, the barrel, the kilderkin, the firkin, the gallon, the pottle, the quart, the pint pot, for an the black bowl. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122480">Sing gentle butler bally moy. </l>
        </lg>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122490" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker><pb facs="35"/>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122500">Well done, i'faith 'twas chanted merrily:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122510">What my gallants, never a tickling jest</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122520">To make us swoon with mirth ere we go in? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122530" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122540">Faith gent. I ha' brewed such a strong headed jest</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122550">Will make you drunk, and reel with laughter:</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122560">You know monsieur John fo de King? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122570" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e122580">Very well, he read French to my daughters.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122590" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e122600">I to gull the fool, have brought him to my wife, as to a loose lascivious courtesan, she being a mere stranger to the jest, and there some three hours ago left him: but I am sure she hath so cudgeled him with quick sharp jests, and so battered him with a volley of her wit, as indeed she is exceeding witty, and admirable chaste, that in my conscience he'll never dare to court women more. Would to God he were returned.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e122610">Enter monsieur.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122620" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e122630">See even on your wish he's come.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122640" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e122650">Jesu preserve you sweet metre Brabant, by gour de most delicate plump vench dat ever me touch: me am your slave, your peasant; by gour a votre service whilst I live vor dis.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122660" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e122670">He would persuade you now that he touched her, with an immodest hand. Ha, ha, ha.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122680" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e122690">Touch her, by gour me tuch her, and touch her, and me touch her, me never tuch such a vench, de finea foot, de cleanest leg, de sleekest skin: and me tell e sure token, she hath de finest little varte you know veare: he by gour me never tuch such a vench.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122700" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e122710">Pray God he have not brewed a heady jest indeed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122720" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e122730">Why faith gentlemen I am cuckold, by this light I am.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122740" who="A20867-monsieur">
          <speaker><pb facs="35"/>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A20867-e122750">By gour me no know, you tell a me 'twas a courtesan, pray you pardon me, by my troth, me teach you French to th'end of de vorlde.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122760" who="A20867-planet">
          <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122770">Come here's thy cap of maintenance, the coronet</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122780">Of cuckolds. Nay you shall wear it, or wear</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122790">My rapier in your guts by heaven. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122800">Why dost thou not well deserve to be thus used? </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122810">Why shouldst thou take felicity to gull</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122820">Good honest souls, and in thy arrogance</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122830">And glorious ostentation of thy wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122840">Think God infused all perfection</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122850">Into thy soul alone, and made the rest</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122860">For thee to laugh at? Now you censurer</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122870">Be the ridiculous subject of our mirth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122880">Why fool, the power of creation</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122890">Is still omnipotent, and there's no man that breathes</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122900">So valiant, learned, witty, or so wise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122910">But it can equal him out of the same mould. </l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122920">Wherein the first was formed. Then leave proud scorn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122930">And honest self made cuckold, wear the horn. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122940" who="A20867-brabant_sr">
          <speaker>Bra. sig.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122950">Wear the horn? Ay, spite of all your teeth</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122960">I'll wear this crown, and triumph in this horn. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A20867-e122970" who="A20867-edward">
          <speaker>Sir Ed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122980">Why faith 'tis valorously spoke fair sir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e122990">We'll solemnise your coronation</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e123000">With royal pomp. Now gentlemen prepare</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e123010">A liberal spirit to entertain a jest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e123020">Where free light jocund mirth shall be enthroned</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e123030">With sumptuous state. Now music beat the air,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e123040">Entrance our thoughts with your harmonious sounds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A20867-e123050">Our fortune laughs, and all content abounds. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A20867-e123060">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
        <trailer xml:id="A20867-e123070">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A20867-e123080">
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A20867-e123090">
        <pb facs="36"/>
        <head>The names of all the men and women, that act this play.</head>
        <list xml:id="A20867-e123100">
          <head>The men.</head>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123110">1. Sir Edward fortune.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123120">2. Brabant signior, and his page.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123130">3. Brabant junior, and his page.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123140">4. Planet.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123150">5. Puff, and his page.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123160">6. John Ellis.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123170">7. Mammon the usurer, with a great nose.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123180">8. Flawne his page.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123190">9. Timothy Twedle.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123200">10. Jack drum.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123210">11. Pasquil.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123220">12. Monsieur.</item>
        </list>
        <list xml:id="A20867-e123230">
          <head>The women.</head>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123240">1. Katherine.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123250">2. Camelia.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123260">3. Winifrid.</item>
          <item xml:id="A20867-e123270">4. Market woman.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A20867"><item xml:id="A20867-planet" n="69">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-planet</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">69</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-edward" n="52">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-edward</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">52</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-pasquill" n="46">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-pasquill</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">46</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-camelia" n="42">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-camelia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">42</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A20867-brabant_sr" n="40">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-brabant_sr</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">40</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-katherine" n="38">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-katherine</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">38</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-monsieur" n="37">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-monsieur</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">37</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-mamon" n="36">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-mamon</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">36</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-winifrid" n="33">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-winifrid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">33</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-brabant_jr" n="31">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-brabant_jr</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">31</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-drum" n="26">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-drum</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">26</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-brabant" n="22">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-brabant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">22</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-puff" n="21">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-puff</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">21</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-ellis" n="20">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-ellis</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">20</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-page" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-page</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-flawne" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-flawne</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-twedle" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-twedle</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-mall" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-mall</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-mrs_brabant" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-mrs_brabant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-fool" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-fool</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-missing" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-missing</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-unassigned" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-xxxx_2" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-xxxx_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-multiple" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-multiple</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-timothy" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-timothy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A20867-xxxx_1" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A20867-xxxx_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

