<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A02732">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Arches of Triumph<date type="creation_date">1604</date></title>
        <author>Dekker, Thomas; Webster, John; Harrison, Stephen</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A02732.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The arch's of triumph erected in honor of the high and mighty prince. Iames. the first of that name. King, of England. and the sixt of Scotland. at his Maiesties entrance and passage through his honorable citty &amp; chamber of London. vpon the 15th. day of march 1603. Invented and published by Stephen Harrison ioyner and architect: and graven by William Kip.</title>
            <author>Harrison, Stephen, joiner and architect.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>17 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99857174</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 12863.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 208.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">22858</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02732</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The arch's of triumph erected in honor of the high and mighty prince. Iames. the first of that name. King, of England. and the sixt of Scotland. at his Maiesties entrance and passage through his honorable citty &amp; chamber of London. vpon the 15th. day of march 1603. Invented and published by Stephen Harrison ioyner and architect: and graven by William Kip.</title>
            <title type="alt">Arch's of triumph erected in honor of the high and mighty prince. James</title>
            <title type="alt">Arch's of triumph erected in honor of the high and mighty prince. James. the first of that name. King, of England. and the sixt of Scotland.</title>
            <title type="alt">Arches of triumph erected in honor of the high and mighty prince. James.</title>
            <title type="alt">Exercitationes virtutum in omni ætate minificos afferunt fructus.</title>
            <title type="add">The magnificent entertainment.</title>
            <title type="add">B. Jon: his part of King James his royall and magnificent entertainement through his honorable cittie of London, Thurseday the 15. of March. 1603.</title>
            <author>Harrison, Stephen, joiner and architect.</author>
            <author>Kip, William,</author>
            <author>Dekker, Thomas, ca. 1572-1632.</author>
            <author>Jonson, Ben, 1573-1637.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[20] p., [7] plates.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>By Iohn VVindet, printer to the honourable citie of London, and are to be sold at the authors house in Lime-street, at the signe of the Snayle,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1604]</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The texts are by Thomas Dekker (adapatations from his "The magnificent entertainment"), John Webster, Ben Jonson (speeches reprinted from his "B. Jon: his part of King James his royall and magnificent entertainement"), and others.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Kip may not have done all the engraving.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The title page is engraved; at head: Exercitationes virtutum in omni ætate minificos [sic] afferunt fructus.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Imprint from colophon.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: [A]1 B-K1, including title page.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>James, -- I, -- King of England, -- 1566-1625.</term>
          <term>Arches, Triumphal -- England -- London -- Early works to 1800.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A02732-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A02732-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A02732-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100040">The arches of triumph erected in honour of the high and mighty prince. James. the first of that name. King, of England. and the sixth of Scotland. at his majesty's entrance and passage through his honourable city and chamber of London. upon the 15th. day of march 1603</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100050">Invented and published by Stephen Harrison. Joiner and architect: and graven by William Kip.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A02732-e100060">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To the right honourable sir Thomas Bennet knight, lord mayor of this city, the right worsipfull the aldermen his brothers, and to those worshipful commoners, elected committees, for the managing of this business.</head>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100070">The love which I bear to your honour and worships: and the duty wherewith I am bound to this honourable city, makes me appear in this boldness to you; to whom I humbly consecrate these fruits of my invention, which time hath now at length brought forth, and ripened to this perfection. That magnificent royalty, and glorious entertainment, which you yourselves for your part, out of a free, a clear, and very bounteous disposition, and so many thousands of worthy citizens, out of a sincere affection and loyalty of his majesty, did with the sparing of no cost, bestow but upon one day, is here new wrought up again, and shall endure for ever. For albeit those monuments of your loves were erected up to the clouds, and were built never so strongly, yet now their lastingness should live but in the tongues and memories of men: but that the hand of art gives them here a second more perfect being, advanceth them higher than they were before, and warrants them that they shall do honour to this city, so long as the city shall bear a name. Sorry I am that they come into the world no sooner: but let the hardness of the labour; and the small number of hands, that were busied about them, make the fault (If it be a fault) excusable. I would not care if these unpainted pictures were more costly to me, so that they might appear curious enough to your lordship and worships; yet in regard, that this present age can lay before you no precedent that ever any in this land performed the like, I presume these my endeavours shall receive the more worthy liking of you. And thus dedicating my labours and love to your honourable and kind acceptations, I most humbly take my leave, this 16 of June 1604.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A02732-e100080">
          <signed xml:id="A02732-e100090">Most affectionately devoted to your lordship and worships, Stephen Harrision. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="ode" xml:id="A02732-e100100">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>Ode.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A02732-e100110">
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100120">Babel that strove to wear</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100130">A crown of clothes, and up did rear</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100140">Her forehead high,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100150">With an ambitious lust to kiss the sky,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100160">Is new or dust, or not at all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100170">Proud Nymrod's wall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100180">And all his antique monuments,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100190">Left to the world as presidents,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100200">Cannot now show (To tell where they did stand,)</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100210">So much in length as half the builders hand. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A02732-e100220">
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100230">The Mansolaean tomb;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100240">The sixteen curious gates in Rome,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100250">Which times prefer,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100260">Both past and present: Nero's theater,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100270">That in one day was all gilt o'er:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100280">Add to these more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100290">Those columns, and those pyramids, that won</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100300">Wonder by height: the coloss of the sun:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100310">Th' Egyptian obelisks: are all forgotten:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100320">Only their names grow great: themselves be rotten. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A02732-e100330">
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100340">Dear friend! what honour then</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100350">Bestowest thou on thy country men? </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100360">Crowning with praise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100370">By these thy labours, (As with wreathes of bays)</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100380">This royal city: where now stand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100390">(Built by thy hand)</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100400">Her arches in new state; so made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100410">That their fresh beauties ne'er shall fade:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100420">Tho● of our English triumphs rearest the fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100430">Bo●e those of old; but above all, thy name. </l>
          <closer xml:id="A02732-e100440">
            <signed xml:id="A02732-e100450">Tho. Dekker.</signed>
          </closer>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="ode" xml:id="A02732-e100460">
        <head>Ode.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A02732-e100470">
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100480">Triumphs were wont with sweat and blood be crowned:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100490">To every brow</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100500">They did allow. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100510">The living laurer which begirted round</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100520">Their rusty helmets, and had power to make</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100530">The soldier smile, while mortal wound did ache. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A02732-e100540">
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100550">But our more civil passages of state</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100560">(Like happy feast</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100570">Of enured rest</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100580">Which bells and woundless canons did relate,)</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100590">Stood high in joy: since warlike triumphs bring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100600">Remembrance of our former sorrowing. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A02732-e100610">
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100620">The memory of these should quickly fade,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100630">(For pleasures stream</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100640">Is like a dream. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100650">Passant and fleet as is a shade,)</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100660">Unless thyself which these fair models bred,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100670">Had given them a new life when they were dead. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A02732-e100680">
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100690">Take then (Good country man and friend) that merit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100700">Which folly lends. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100710">(Not judgment sends,)</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100720">To foreign shores for stranger to inherit:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100730">Perfection must be bold with front upright,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e100740">Though envy gnash her teeth whilst she would bite. </l>
          <closer xml:id="A02732-e100750">
            <signed xml:id="A02732-e100760">Joh. Webster.</signed>
          </closer>
        </lg>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A02732-e100770">
      <div type="section" xml:id="A02732-e100780">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>The device called Londinium.</head>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100790">These five triumphal arches were first taken in hand in the beginning of April 1603. presently after his majesty was proclaimed. It being expected that his passage would have been through his honourable city and chamber to his coronation upon saint James his day following: but by reason of the sickness, it pleased his majesty to be solemnly crowned at Westminster, without sight of these triumphs: notwithstanding the business being set on foot, went on with all expedition; till Bartholmew-tide and then ceased because of the great mortality, 40. days more was given for the preparing of this triumphal arch. In which time, the streets for that purpose were diligently surveyed, heights, breadths and distances taken, as it were to make fortifications for the solemnities: seven pieces of ground like so many fields for a battle) were plotted forth, upon which these triumphs should be erected: the gladsome and long desired morning at length is come, in which the streets seem to be paved with people, that in heaps flock together, to behold their proud heads that were advanced in this manner.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100800">The first Pegme was erected in Fanchurch-street, the back of it so learning on the East end of the church, that it overspread the whole street. And thus we describe it.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100810">It was a flat-square, built upright; the perpendicular-line of the whole frame, (That is to say, the distance from the bottom to the top,) as the ground-line, is (Also in this, so in all the rest) to be found out and tried by the scale, divided by 1. 2. 3. 4. and 5. and set at the lower end of the piece: by which figures feet are represented: so that in all the descriptions, where mention is to be made of heights, breadths, or any other commensurable proportions, you shall find them left thus — with a blank, because we wish you rather to apply them to the scale yourself, than by setting them down, to call either your skill or judgement in question.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100820">And note withal, that the ground-plot hath not the same scale which the upright hath, for of the two scales, which you see annexed, the lesser is of the ground, and standeth in the ground-plot, the greater, for the edisice or building itself.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100830">This gate of passage, then (Into which his majesty made his first entrance) was derived from the Tuscana (Being the principal pillar of those 5. upon which the noble frame of Architecture doth stand,) for the Tuscan column is the strongest and most worthy to support so famous a work, as this fabric was, considering that upon his rustic pillars, the goodliest houses, turrets, steeples, etc. within this city, were to be born: and those models, stood as a coronet on the forehead or battlements of this great and magnificent edisice. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100840">The cheeks or sides of the gate, were (As it were) doubly guarded with the portraitures of Atlas' King of Mauritania, who (According to his own shortness and thickness) from the symmetry of his foot, caused a pillar to be made, whose height with base and capital was 6. times the thickness in height. And so is this of ours, bearing the name of Tuscana, as we said before, and reaching to the very point of the arch, from whence we did derive Dorica which bore up the architrave, freeze, and coronixe, and was garnished with corbels or croxtels fitting such work, besides the beauty of pyramids, beasts, water, tables, and many other enrichments, which you may find expressed in the piece itself.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100850">From a gallery directly over the gate, the sound of loud music (Being the waits and oboes of the city) was sent forth.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100860">At the foot of the battlements was in capital letters inscribed this word Londinium, and beneath that, these words camera regia. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100870">In this pegme or arch triumphal, were placed 12. personages, of which she that had the pre-eminence to sit highest, was called monarchia britannica. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100880">At her feet sat divine wisdom. <list xml:id="A02732-e100890"><head>On her right hand sat three of the daughters of genius urbis, whose names were</head><item xml:id="A02732-e100900">Veneration,</item><item xml:id="A02732-e100910">Promptitude,</item><item xml:id="A02732-e100920">Vigilance:</item></list><list xml:id="A02732-e100930"><head>On her left, the other three, viz.</head><item xml:id="A02732-e100940">Gladness,</item><item xml:id="A02732-e100950">Loving affection,</item><item xml:id="A02732-e100960">Unanimity.</item></list></p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100970">Beneath all these stood the genius of the city, richly attired, being supported on the right hand by a person figuring the council of the city; and on the left by a person figuring the warlike force of the city. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100980">Directly under these, in an aback thrust out before the rest, lay Thamesis the river, leaning his arm upon a gourd, out of which, water with live fishes were seen to run forth, and play about him.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e100990">The speakers were only Thamesis and genius, who uttered these speeches following on the other side.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="section" xml:id="A02732-e101000">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <head>The speeches of gratulation.</head>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e101010" who="A02732-genius">
          <speaker>Genius.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101020">Time, fate, and fortune have at length conspired,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101030">To give our age the day so much desired. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101040">What all the minutes, hours, weeks, months, and years,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101050">That hang in file upon these silver hairs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101060">Could not produce, beneath the Britane stroke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101070">The Roman, saxon, Dane, and Norman yoke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101080">This point of time bath done ▪ now London rear</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101090">Thy forehead high, and on it strive to wear</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101100">Thy 〈◊〉 gems teach thy steep towers to rise</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101110">Higher with people: set with sparkling eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101120">Thy spacious windows: and in every street,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101130">Let thronging joy, love, and amazement meet. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101140">Cleave all the air with shouts, and let the cry</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101150">Strike through as long, and universally</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101160">As thunder; for, thou now art blessed to see</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101170">That sight, for which thou didst begin to be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101180">When Brutus' plough first gave thee infant bounds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101190">And I, thy genius walks auspicious rounds</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101200">In every furrow; then did I forelook,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101210">And saw this day marked white in Clotho's book. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101220">The several circles, both of change and sway,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101230">Within this isle, there also figured lay:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101240">Of which the greatest, perfectest, and last</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101250">Was this, whose present happiness we taste. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101260">Why keep you silence daughters? What dull peace</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101270">Is this inhabits you? Shall office cease</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101280">Upon th'aspect of him, to whom you owe</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101290">〈…〉 shall time know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101300">That article, wherein your flame stood still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101310">An 〈…〉 now heaven avert an I'd</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101320">Of that black look. Ere pause possess your breasts</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101330">I wish you more of plagues: "Zeal when it rests,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101340">Leaves to be zeal. Up thou tame river, wake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101350">And from thy liquid limbs this slumber shake:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101360">Thou drownest thyself in inofficious sleep;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101370">And these thy sluggish waters seem to creep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101380">Rather them flow. Uprise, and swell with pride</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101390">Above thy banks. " now is not every tide. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e101400" who="A02732-thamesis">
          <speaker>Thamesis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101410">To what vain end should I contend to show</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101420">〈…〉 powers, when seas of pomp o'erflow</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101430">The city's face: and cover all the shore</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101440">With sand is more rich than Tagus wealthy ore? </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101450">When in the stood of joy, that comes with him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101460">He drowns the world; yet makes it live and swim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101470">And spring with gladness: not my fishes here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101480">Though they be dumb, but do express the cheer</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101490">Of these bright streams. No less may these, and I</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101500">Boast our delights, albe't we silent lie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e101510" who="A02732-genius">
          <speaker>Genius.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101520">Indeed, true gladness doth not always speak:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101530">"Joy bred and born but in the tongue, is weak. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101540">Yet (Lest the fervour of so pure a flame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101550">As this my city bears, might lose the name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101560">Without the apt eventing of her heat)</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101570">Know greatest James (And no less good, than great.) </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101580">In the behalf of all my virtuous sons,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101590">Whereof my eldest there, thy pomp foreruns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101600">(A man without my flattering, or his pride,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101610">As worthy, as he's blessed to be thy guide)</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101620">In his grave name, and all his brothers' right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101630">(Who thirst to drink the nectar of thy sight)</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101640">The council, commoners, and multitude;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101650">(Glad, that this day so long denied, is viewed)</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101660">I tender thee the heartiest welcome, yet</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101670">That ever King had to his empire's seat:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101680">Never came man, more longed for, more desired</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101690">And being come, more reverenced, loved, admired:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101700">Hear, and record it:" in a prince it is</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101710">"No little virtue, to know who are his. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101720">With like devotions, do I stoop t'embrace</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101730">This springing glory of thy godlike race;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101740">His country's wonder, hope, love, Joy and pride:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101750">How well doth he become the royal side</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101760">Of this erected, and broad spreading tree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101770">Under whose shade may Britain ever be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101780">And from this branch, may thousand branches more</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101790">Shoot o'er the main, and knit with every shore</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101800">In bonds of marriage, kindred, and increase;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101810">And style this land, the navel of their peace. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101820">This is your servant's wish, your city's vow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101830">Which still shall propagate itself, with you;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101840">And free from spurs of hope, that slow minds 〈◊〉:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101850">" he seeks no hire, that owes his life to love. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101860">And here she comes that is no less a part</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101870">In this day's greatness, then in my glad heart. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101880">Glory of Queens, and glory of your name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101890">Whose graces do as far outspeak your fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101900">As fame doth silence, when her trumpet rings</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101910">You daughter, sister, wife of several Kings:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101920">Besides alliance, and the style of mother,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101930">In which one title you drown all your other. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101940">Instance, be that fair shoot, is gone before</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101950">Your eldest joy, and top of all your store,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101960">With those, whose sight to us is yet denied,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101970">But not our zeal to them, or ought beside</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101980">This city can to you: for whose estate</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e101990">She hopes you will be still good advocate</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102000">To her best lord. So, whilst you mortal are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102010">No taste of sour mortality once dare</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102020">Approach your house; nor fortune greet your grace</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102030">But coming on, and with a forward face. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102040">
          <pb facs="4"/>
          <figure xml:id="A02732-e102050"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section" xml:id="A02732-e102060">
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <head>The Italians pegme stood in Gracious-street.</head>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102070">The second triumphal arch was erected by the Italians: the cost theirs: the invention their own: it took up the whole breadth of Gracious-street (On which it stood) being — foot: the height of it was — foot. The lower part of this building, was a large square, garnished with four great Corinthia columns: in the midst of which square, was cut out a fair and a spacious high gate, arched, being — foot in the perpendicular-line, and — in the ground-line: directly over the gate were advanced the arms of the kingdom, the supporters whereof were fairly cut out to the life.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102080">On the top of this first square (Being flat) was erected another square which bore in the fore side four more lesser columns, on which were all the garnishments belonging to those pillars: as namely, the architrave freeze and Cornish, on which square was placed a great canted pedestal, which with his mouldings did diminish onwards to smaller cants, on which top was fixed a personage carved or moulded out to the life, her left hand leaning on a sword, with the point downward, and her right hand reaching forth a diadem, which, she seemed by bowing of her knee and head, to bestow upon his majesty. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102090">On the four corners of this upper part, stood four naked portraitures (In great) with artificial trumpets in their hands.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102100">All which shapes that were erected in most lively colours, together with pyramids, long streamers, galleries, and all other enrichments belonging to this arch triumphant: I refer you to the model or piece itself, for the front of it, as the next leaf will show you, so likewise proportional was the back side to the forefront. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102110">The Italians, were placed within two little galleries very richly and stately hung, under the arch of the passage: in whose behalf, thus much Latin was delivered.</p>
        <div type="subsection" xml:id="A02732-e102120">
          <head>The Italians speech.</head>
          <p xml:id="A02732-e102130">Salve, rex magne, salve. Salutem maiestati tuae itali, foelicissimum aduentum laeti, foelices sub te futuri, precamur. Eccè hic omnes, exigui munere, pauculi numero: sed magni erga maiestatem animi, multi obsequij. At nec Atlas, qui coelum sustinet, ne; ipsa coeli convexa, altitudinem attingant meritorum regis optimi, hoc est, eius quem de Teipso expressists doctissimo (Deus!) et admirabili, penicillo, beatissimos populos, ubi et philosophus regnat, et rex philosophatur. Salve; vive rex potentissime, foeliciter. Regna, rex sapientissime, foeliciter. Itali optamus omnes, itali clamamus omnes, omnes, omnes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="subsection" xml:id="A02732-e102140">
          <head>The same in English.</head>
          <p xml:id="A02732-e102150">All hail mighty monarch! we (The Italians) full of joy to behold thy most happy presence, and full of hopes to enjoy a felicity under thy royal wing, do wish and pray for the health of thy majesty. Behold, here we are all; mean in merit: few in number: but towards thy sovereign self, in our loves great, in our duties more. For neither Atlas, who bears up heaven, no nor the arched roof itself of heaven, can by many-many degrees reach to the top and glorious height of a good and virtuous King's deservings. And such a one is he, whom (Good God!) most lively, most wisely, and in wonderful colours, thou didst then pencil down in thine own person, when thou saidst those people were blessed, where a philosopher rules, and where the ruler plays the philosopher. All hail thou royalest of Kings; live thou mightiest of princes: reign thou wisest of monarchs in all prosperity: these are the wishes of us Italians: the hearty wishes of us all: all, even all.</p>
          <p xml:id="A02732-e102160">
            <pb facs="6"/>
            <pb facs="6"/>
            <figure xml:id="A02732-e102170"/>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="section" xml:id="A02732-e102180">
        <pb facs="7"/>
        <pb facs="7"/>
        <head>The pegme of the Dutchmen.</head>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102190">The third welcome that his majesty received, was from the Belgians, who had builded a stately triumphal arch, to entertain him in, and thus was it contrived.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102200">So wide did the body of it extend itself, that it swallowed up the breadth of the whole street, near the royal exchange in Cornhill. The passage of state was a gate, comely, and large, ascending — foot in height, and — foot in the breadth, neatly arched, and graced with two lesser posterns on the sides, whose dimensions you may behold in the model.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102210">Sundry inscriptions were in golden letters to be seen, both over the gate, and in the tables, filled with excellent pictures; as the King in his imperial robes: with other portraitures of princes, and poetical emblems of peace, etc. On the back part also were pieces, wherein were drawn the people of the seventeen provinces at their husbandry; their exchange: their mart: also seventeen children on the fore side, representing the seventeen provinces, sat in degrees, each of them having a scutcheon in his hand, figuring his province. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102220">On the shoulders of this Belgic body, stood rows of balusters with pedestals, that supported lions rampant, bearing up banners: and above them in the midst of another square about with balusters likewise, was advanced a woman (Figuring divine providence, her feet fastened to a great pedestal, whose top was curiously connexed and knit together with the tails of two dolphins. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102230">Other garnishments there were that gave illustration and beauty to this building, as columns, pyramids, etc. whose proportions your eye may measure on the other side. The speech, wherein the love of these strangers was testified, was delivered by a boy in Latin, and is thus much in English.</p>
        <div type="subsection" xml:id="A02732-e102240">
          <head>The speech of the Dutchmen.</head>
          <p xml:id="A02732-e102250">Great King, those so many sceptres, which even fill thy right hand, are all thine own, only by the providence of heaven. Behold, heaven itself laughs to see thy subjects smile, and thunder out loud plaudities, to hear their aves. This honour of sovereignty being at the beginning of the world bestowed but upon few; upon the heads of few were the cares of a crown set, for to sway only but one empire (Happily) as it is a labour hard: so none can undergo the weight but such as are mighty: but (With a beck as it were) to control many nations (And those of different dispositions too) o! the arm of man can never do that, but the finger of God. God therefore (That guides the chariot of the world) holds the reins of thy kingdom in his own hand: it is he whose beams lend a light to thine. It is he that teacheth thee the art of ruling, because none but he made thee a King. And therefore as thou growest in years, thou waxest old in virtues: of all thy virtues, religion sitting highest. And most worthy; for by religion, the hearts of barbarous nations are made soft: by religion, rebellion hath a yoke cast about her neck, and is brought to believe, that those laws to which thou submittest even thy royal self, are most easy. With religion justice keeps company, who once fled from this profane world, but hearing the name of King James she is again returned. By her side sits her sister fortitude, whose life is ready (In heroic actions) to be spent for the safety of thy people. Besides to make these virtues full, Apollo and the Muses, resign, the one his golden lyre, the other their laurel, to thy royal hands, whilst plenty (Daughter to industry) lays the blessings both of country and city in heaps at thy feet. These are the gifts of heaven: the fame then spreading itself so far, that (To wonder at them) both the poles seem to come together. We (The Belgians) likewise come, to that intent: a nation banished from our own cradles, yet nursed and brought up in the tender bosom of a princely mother, Eliza. The love which we once dedicated to her (As a mother) doubly do we vow it to thee, our sovereign, and father: entreating we may be sheltered under thy wings now, as under hers: our prayers being, that he who through the loins of so many kingdoms, may likewise multiply thy years, and lengthen them out to the age of a phoenix: and that thy Queen (Who is one part of thyself) with thy progeny (Who are the second hopes of thy people,) may both give too, and receive from, thy kingdom immortal glory.</p>
          <p xml:id="A02732-e102260">
            <pb facs="8"/>
            <pb facs="8"/>
            <figure xml:id="A02732-e102270"/>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="section" xml:id="A02732-e102280">
        <pb facs="9"/>
        <pb facs="9"/>
        <head>The device called, nova foelix Arabia, the new Arabia foelix.</head>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102290">This pegme presented itself above the great conduit in cheap: and carried the name of the new Arabia, under which title the whole island of Britannia was figured.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102300">This was beautified with a large gate in the midst: on each side was cut out a postern, either of which was — foot wide, and — foot high: before which posterns two portals were built from the same, having their sides open four several ways, and serving as pedestals (Of rustic) to support two great pyramids, whose bases were held up with four great balls, and four lions.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102310">This mechanic body had other dead limbs, (Which you may behold cut out on the other side.) The lively and stirring parts were these. viz. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102320">In the most eminent place was advanced a person, representing Arabia britannica, and within a nesete (Beneath her) stood fame. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102330">Directly under her, in a wide hollow square, were exalted five green mounts, the one swelling above the other; upon which the five senses, (Hearing, seeing, feeling, smelling and taste,) sat heavily drooping: before which mounts, an artificial laver was erected, called the fount of virtue; out of which (From sundry pipes) upon his majesty's approach, ran wine very plenteously.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102340">At the foot of this fount lay detraction and oblivion, sleeping till his majesty's approach; but being arrived at the place, and the trump of fame, starting up the senses, they two likewise awaked, doing their best, with clubs to beat down the fount, but were hindered by the senses, and a person representing circumspection. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102350">Upon several ascensions, (And close adjoining to the pyramids,) were seated at one side, the three graces, and on the other side the three hours. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102360">The speakers were fame, hours, Euphrosyne (One of the graces) and circumspection, who was mounted on a stage, railed round about with pilasters, being drawn forth some thirty foot in length from the other building. And thus sounded their voices.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e102370" who="A02732-fame">
          <speaker>Fame.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102380">Turn into ice mine eyeballs whilst the sound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102390">Flying through this brazen tromp, may back rebound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102400">To stop fame's hundred tongues, leaning them mute,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102410">As is an untouched bell, or stringless lute,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102420">For virtue's fount, which late ran deep and clear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102430">Dries: and melts all her body to a tear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102440">You graces: and you hours that each day run,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102450">On the quick errands of the golden sun,</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A02732-e102460">Hereupon fame sounding her trumpet, the senses start up, detraction and oblivion, awaken, and vanish, whilst circumspection appears, uttering thus much to the King.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e102470" who="A02732-circumspection">
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102480">Great monarch of the West, whose glorious stem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102490">Does new support a triple diadem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102500">Wearing more than that of thy grand grandsire, Brute.) </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102510">Thou that mayst make a King thy substitute,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102520">And dost besides the red-rose and the white,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102530">With the rich flower of France, thy garland dight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102540">Wearing about Kings now, or those of old,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102550">A double crown, of laurel and of gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102560">Oh let my voice pass through thy royal care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102570">And whisper thus much, that we figure here. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102580">A new Arabia, in whose spiced nest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102590">A phoenix lived, and died in the sun's breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102600">Her loss made sight, in tears to drown her eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102610">Oh say? to virtue's fount what has befallen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102620">That thus her veins shrink up. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e102630" who="A02732-graces">
          <speaker>Graces — howres.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102640">We cannot tell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e102650" who="A02732-euphrosyne">
          <speaker>Evphrosine.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102660">Behold the fivefold guard of sense, which keeps</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102670">The sacred stream, sits drooping: near them sleep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102680">Two horrid monsters: fame, summon each sense,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102690">To tell the cause of this strange accidence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102700">The ear grew deaf, taste like a sick-man lies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102710">Finding no relish: every other sense</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102720">Forgot his office, worth and excellence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102730">Whereby this fount of virtue 'gan to freeze,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102740">Threatened to be drunk up by two enemies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102750">Snaky detraction, and oblivion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102760">But at thy glorious presence both are gone. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102770">Thou being that sacred phoenix, that doth rise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102780">From th'ashes of the first; beams from thine eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102790">So virtually shining, that they bring</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102800">To England's new Arabia, a new spring:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102810">For joy whereof, nymphs, senses, hours and fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e102820">Echo-loud hymns to his imperial name. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102830">At the end of this speech, a song (To an excellent music) was delivered, which being finished, his majesty went on.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102840">
          <pb facs="10"/>
          <pb facs="10"/>
          <figure xml:id="A02732-e102850"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section" xml:id="A02732-e102860">
        <pb facs="11"/>
        <pb facs="11"/>
        <head>The device called, hortus euporiae, garden of plenty.</head>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102870">The fifth pegme was a summer Arbour, and seemed to grow close to the little conduit in cheap, which joining to the back of it, served (Or might be supposed to have been) as a fountain to water the fruits of this garden of plenty. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102880">This green bower spread itself likewise (As all the rest did) over the whole breadth of the street; having two gates arched and grated arbor-wise, to the height of — feet, and breadth of —: the sides of which gates were born up with four great French terms, standing upon pedestals, which contained in their full height — foot. Between these open passages were a pair of stairs mounted, at the bottom of which (On two pillars) were fixed two satires, carved out in wood. Both the roof and sides of these gates, were artificially hung with pompions, cucumbers, grapes, cherries, pears, apples, and all other fruits, which the land bringeth forth. The upper part also (Which was closed with three round tops, fortune standing on the midst of the three) was garnished with lesser fruits, and with all sorts of flowers, made by art.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102890">The whole frame of this summer house, stood (At the ground-line) upon — foot, the perpendicular, stretching itself to —.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102900">Peace and plenty had the highest places in this bower, and sat to gether: directly under them, sat two other persons, representing gold and silver, supporting the globe of the world between them: on each side of them sat two other persons, the one Pomona, goddess of fruits, the other Ceres, goddess of corn.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102910">Upon two large descents (A little below these) were placed at one end the nine muses, at the other end the seven liberal sciences. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102920">Sylvanvs, and his followers, (Who upon sight of his majesty, played upon cornets) gave entertainment to his majesty, in these speeches following.</p>
        <div type="subsection" xml:id="A02732-e102930">
          <head>The speech.</head>
          <p xml:id="A02732-e102940">Most happy prince, pardon me, that being mean in habit, and wild in appearance (For my richest livery is but leaves, and my stateliest dwelling but in the woods) thus rudely with piping Syluancs, I presume to intercept your royal passage. These are my walks, yet stand I not here to cut off your way, but to give it a full and a bounteous welcome, being a messenger sent from the lady Eirene my mistress; those that sleep under the warmth of her wings adore her by the sacred and celestial name of peace; her daughter Euporia (Well known by the name of plenty) is at this present with her, (Being indeed never from her side:) under yonder arbour they sit ▪ which after the daughter's name is called hortus euporiae (Plenties bower.) Chaste are they both, and both maidens, in memory of a virgin to whom they were nurse-children, for whose sake (Because they were bound to her for their life) me have they charged to lay at your imperial feet, (Being your hereditary due) the tribute of their love. And with it thus to say. That they have languished many heavy months for your presence, which to them would have been, (And proud they are that it shall be now so) of the same operation and influence, that the sun is to the spring, and the spring to the earth; hearing therefore what treble preferment you have bestowed upon this day, wherein besides the beams of a glorious sun, two other clear and gracious stars shine cheerfully on these her homely buildings; into which (Because no duty should be wanting) she hath given leave even to strangers, to be sharers in her happiness, by suffering them to bid you likewise welcome: by me (Once hers, now your vassal) she entreats, and with a knee sinking lower than the ground on which you tread, do I humbly execute her pleasure, that ere you pass further, you would deign to walk into yonder garden. The hesperides live not there, but the Muses, and the Muses no longer than under your protection. Thus far am I sent to conduct you thither, prostrately begging this grace (Since I dare not, as being unworthy, lackey by your royal side) that yet these my green followers and myself may be joyful forerunners of your expected approach. Away sylvans. </p>
          <p xml:id="A02732-e102950">
            <pb facs="12"/>
            <pb facs="12"/>
            <figure xml:id="A02732-e102960"/>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="section" xml:id="A02732-e102970">
        <pb facs="13"/>
        <pb facs="13"/>
        <head>The device called, cozmoz neoz, new world.</head>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102980">The sixth triumphal arch, was (In the shape which you see it caries on the other side) erected above the conduit in Fleetstreet; extending itself over the whole street, to the length of — foot, and in height — foot: the gate of it was — foot wide, and — foot hie. The two posterns were answerable to those of others set down before: and were cut out of the two round towers which ris up in proportionable measures, from the ground on the foreside with battlements and balisters round enclosing the tops, containing in all their heights — foot: over the gate, and just in the midst of the building, (Which was spacious and left open) a globe was seen to move being filled with all the estates that are in the land; and this engine was turned about by four persons, representing the four elements, (Earth, water, air, and fire) who were placed so quaintly, that the globe seemed to have his motion even on the crowns of their heads.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e102990">The lively garnishments to this building were 23 persons, of which the principal and worthiest was Astraea (Justice) who was advanced to the highest seat: beneath her in a cant by herself, Arete (Virtue) was placed: and at her feet fortune, who trod upon the globe.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e103000">In a dark and obscure place (Near virtue) sat envy: beneath whom, on several ascensions were placed the Cardinal virtues, justice, fortitude, temperance and prudence; and in an opposite seat, the four kingdoms, England, Scotland, France and Ireland. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e103010">Zeal was the presenter of this device, who spoke thus.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e103020" who="A02732-zeal">
          <speaker>Zeale.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103030">The populous globe of this our English I'll. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103040">Seemed to move backward at the funeral pile</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103050">Of her dead female majesty: all states</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103060">From nobles down to spirits of meaner fates,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103070">Moved opposite to nature and to peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103080">As if these men had been th'antipodes. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103090">But see, the virtue of a regal eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103100">Th'attractive wonder of man's majesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103110">Our globe as drawn in a right line again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103120">And now appear new faces and new men:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103130">The elements, earth, water, air and fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103140">(Which ever clipped a natural desire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103150">To combat each with other) being at first</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103160">Created enemies, to fight their worst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103170">See: as the peaceful presence of their King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103180">How quietly they move without their sting. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103190">Earth not devouring: fire not defacing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103200">Water not drowning: and the air not chasing:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103210">But propping the quaint fabric that here stands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103220">Without the violence of their wrathful hands. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103230">Mirror of times, lo, where they fortune sits</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103240">Above the world, and all our human wits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103250">But thy high virtue above that: what pen</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103260">Or art, or brain, can reach thy virtues then? </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103270">At whose immortal brightness and true light,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103280">Envy's infectious eyes have lost their sight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103290">Her snakes (Not daring to shoot forth their stings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103300">'Gainst such a glorious object) down she flings</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103310">Their forks of venom into her own maw,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103320">Whilst her rank teeth the glittering poisons chew,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103330">For 'tis the property of envy's blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103340">To dry away at every kingdoms good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103350">Especially when she had eyes to view</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103360">These four main virtues which here figure you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103370">Justice in causes: fortitude 'gainst foes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103380">Temperance in spleen; and prudence in all those:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103390">And then so rich an empire, whose fair breast</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103400">Contains four kingdoms by your entrance blessed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103410">By Brute divided, but by you alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103420">All are again united, and made one:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103430">Whose fruitful glories shine so far and even,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103440">They touch not only earth, but they kiss heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103450">From whence Astraea is descended hither,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103460">Who with our last Queen's spirit fled up thither,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103470">Foreknowing on the earth she could not rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103480">Till you had locked her in your rightful breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103490">And therefore all estates, whose proper arts</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103500">Live by the breath of majesty, had hearts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103510">Burning in holy zeals immaculate sires,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103520">With quenchless ardours and unstained desires. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103530">To see what they now see, your powerful grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103540">Reflecting joys on every subject's face. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103550">These painted flames and yellow-burning stripes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103560">Upon this robe being but as shows and types,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103570">Of that great zeal; and therefore in the name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103580">Of this glad city, whither no prince ever came,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103590">More loved, more longed for, lowly I entreat</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103600">You'd be to her as gracious as you're great:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103610">So with reverberate shouts our globe shall ring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103620">The musics close being thus, God save our King. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e103630">
          <pb facs="14"/>
          <pb facs="14"/>
          <figure xml:id="A02732-e103640"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section" xml:id="A02732-e103650">
        <pb facs="15"/>
        <pb facs="15"/>
        <head>The device called, templum jani, temple of Janus.</head>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e103660">The seventh and last pegme (Within the city) was erected at Temple-bar, being adjoined close to the gate: the building was in all points like a temple, and ● dedicated to Janus Quadrifrons. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e103670">Beneath that four-faced head of Janus was advanced the arms of the kingdom, with the supporters cut out to the life: from whence being removed they now are placed in the  Guild-hall . </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e103680">The walls and gates of this temple were brass; the pillars silver, their capitals and bases gold: all the frontispiece (Downward from those arms) was beautified and supported by twelve rich columns, of which the four lowermost, being great Corinthian pillars, stood upon two large pedestals, with a fair v●●x over them in stead of architrave, frieze and cornice: above them, eight columns more, were likewise set, two and two upon a large pedestal; for as our work began (For his majesty's entrance) with rustic, so did we think it fit, that this out temple, should end with the most famous column, whose beauty and goodliness is derived both from the Tuscan, Doric, Ionic and Corinthian, and received his full perfection from Titus Vespasian, who advanced it to the highest place of dignity in his arch triumphal, and (By reason that the beauties of it were a mixture taken from the rest) he gave it the name of composita or Italica: within the temple stood an altar, with burning incense upon it, before which a flamen appears, and to the flamen comes the genius of the city. The principal person in this temple, was peace. At her feet lay war grovelling. At her right hand stood wealth. On the same hand likewise, but somewhat remote, and in a cant by herself, quiet was seated, the first hand maid of peace, whose feet stood upon tumult. On the left hand (At the former distance) liberty the second handmaid of peace had her place, at whose feet servitude lay subjected. Beneath these (On distinct degrees) sat two other hand maids of peace, safety and Felicity, safety trampling upon danger and felicity upon unhappiness. Genius and flamen spoke thus much.</p>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e103690" who="A02732-genius">
          <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103700">Stay, what art thou, that in this strange attire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103710">Dar'st kindle stranger, and unhallowed fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103720">Upon this altar? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e103730" who="A02732-flamin">
          <speaker>Fl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103740">Rather what art thou</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103750">That dar'st so rudely interrupt my vow? </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103760">My habit speaks my name. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e103770" who="A02732-genius">
          <speaker>Ge.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103780">A flamen? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e103790" who="A02732-flamin">
          <speaker>Fl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103800">Yes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103810">And Martialis called. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e103820" who="A02732-genius">
          <speaker>G●.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103830">I so did guess</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103840">By my short view, but whence didst thou ascend</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103850">Hither? or how? or to what mystic end? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e103860" who="A02732-flamin">
          <speaker>Fl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103870">The noise, and present tumult of this day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103880">Roused me from sleep, and silence, where I lay</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103890">Obscured from light; which when I wake to see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103900">I wondering thought what this great pomp might be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103910">When (Looking in my calendar) I found</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103920">The ides of Marche were entered, and I bound</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103930">With these, to celebrate the genial feast</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103940">Of Anna styled Perenna, Mars his guest;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103950">Who, in this month of his, is yearly called</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103960">To banquet at his altars; and installed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103970">A goddess with him, since she files the year,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103980">And knits the oblique scarce that girds the sphere. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e103990">Whilst four faced Ianus turns his vernal look</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104000">Upon their meeting hours, as if he took</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104010">High pride and pleasure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A02732-e104020" who="A02732-genius">
          <speaker>Ge.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104030">Sure thou still dost dream. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104040">And both thy tongue, and thought rides on the stream</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104050">Of fantasy: behold here he nor she,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104060">Have any altar ▪ fane, or deity. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104070">Stoop; read but this inscription: and then view</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104080">To whom the place is consecrate. 'tis true</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104090">That this is Janus' temple, and that now</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104100">He turns upon the year his freshest brow;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104110">That this is Mars his month; and these the ides,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104120">Wherein his Anne was honoured; both the tides,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104130">Titles, and place, we know: but these dead rites</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104140">Are long since buried, and new power excites</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104150">More high and hearty flames. Lo, there is he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104160">Who brings with him a greater Anne than she:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104170">Whose strong and potent virtues have defaced</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104180">Stern Mars his statues, and upon them placed</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104190">His, and the world's blessed blessings: this hath brought</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104200">Sweet peace to sit in that bright state she ought</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104210">Unbloody, or untroubled; hath forced hence</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104220">All tumults, fears, or other dark portents,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104230">That might invade weak minds; hath made men see</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104240">Once more the face of welcome liberty:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104250">And doth (In all his present acts) restore</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104260">That first pure world, made of the better ore. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104270">Now innocence shall cease to be the spoil</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104280">Of ravenous greatness, or to sleep the soil</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104290">Of raised peasantry with tears, and blood;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104300">No more shall rich men (For their little good)</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104310">Suspect to be made guilty; or vile spies</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104320">Enjoy the lust of their so murdering eyes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104330">Men shall put off their iron minds, and hearts;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104340">The time forget his old malicious artes</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104350">With this new minute; and no print remain</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104360">Of what was thought the former age's stain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104370">Back flamen, with thy superstitious fumes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104380">And sense not here; thy ignorance presumes</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104390">Too much, in acting any ethnic rite</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104400">In this translated temple: here no wight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104410">To sacrifice save my devotion comes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104420">That brings instead of those thy masculine gums. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104430">My city's heart, which shall for ever burn</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104440">Upon this altar, and no time shall turn</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104450">The same to ashes: here I fix it fast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104460">Flame bright, flame high, and may it ever last. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104470">Whilst I, before the figure of thy peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104480">Still tend the fire; and give it quick increase</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104490">With prayers, wishes, vows; whereof be these</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104500">The least, and weakest: that no age may lose</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104510">The memory of this so rich a day;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104520">But rather, that it henceforth yearly may</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104530">Begin our spring, and with our spring the prime,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104540">And first account of years, of months, of time:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104550">And may these ides as fortunate appear</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104560">To thee, as they to Caesar fatal were. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104570">Be all thy thoughts born perfect, and thy hopes</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104580">In their events still crowned beyond their scopes. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104590">Let not wide heaven that secret blessing know</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104600">To give, which she on thee will not bestow:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104610">Blind fortune be thy slave; and may her store</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104620">(The less thou seest it) follow thee the more. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104630">Much more I would: but see, these brazen gates</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104640">Make haste to close, as urged by thy fates;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104650">Here ends my city's office, here it breaks:</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104660">Yet with my tongue, and this pure heart, she speaks</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104670">A short farewell; and lower than thy feet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104680">With fervent thanks, thy royal pains doth greet. </l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104690">Pardon, if my abruptness breed disease;</l>
          <l xml:id="A02732-e104700">He merits not t'offend, that hasts to please. </l>
        </sp>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104710">
          <pb facs="16"/>
          <pb facs="16"/>
          <figure xml:id="A02732-e104720"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section" xml:id="A02732-e104730">
        <pb facs="17"/>
        <pb facs="17"/>
        <head>Lectori Candido.</head>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104740">Reader, the limbs of these great triumphal bodies (Lately disjointed and taken in sunder) I have thou seest (For thy sake) set in their apt and right places again: so that now they are to stand as perpetual monuments, not to be shaken in pieces, or to be broken down, by the malice of that envious destroyer of all things, time. Which labours of mine, if they yield thee either profit or pleasure, thou art (In requital thereof) to pay many thanks to this honourable city, whose bounty towards me, not only in making choice of me, to give directions for the entire workmanship of the five triumphal Arch's builded by the same, but also (In publishing these pieces,) I do here gladly acknowledge to have been exceeding liberal.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104750">Nor shall it be amiss in this place to give thee intelligence of some matters (By way of notes) which were not fully observed, nor freely enough set down in the printed book of these triumphs: amongst which these that follow are chiefest.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104760">His majesty departed from the tower between the hours of 11. and 12 and before 5. had made his royal passage through the city, having a canopy born over him by 8. Knights.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104770">The first object that his majesty's eye encountered (After his entrance into London) was partly of the children of Christ's church hospital, to the number of 300. who were placed on a scaffold, erected for that purpose in barking churchyard by the tower. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104780">The way from the tower to Temple-bar was not only sufficiently gravelled, but all the streets (Lying between those two places) were on both sides (Where the breadth would permit) railed in at the charges of the city, Paul's churchyard excepted.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104790">The liveries of the companies (Having their streamers, ensigns, and banerets spread on the tops of their rails before them) reached from the middle of mark lane, to the pegme at temple bar. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104800">Two marshals were chosen for the day, to clear the passage both of them being well mounted, and attended on by six men (Suitably attired) to each marshal. </p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104810">The conduits of Cornhill, of cheap, and of Fleetstreet, that day ran claret wine very plenteously: which (By reason of so much excellent music, that sounded forth not only from each several pegme, but also from divers other places) ran the faster and more merrily down into somebody's bellies.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104820">As touching the oration uttered by sir Henry Montague (Recorder of the city) with the gifts bestowed on the King, the Queen, and the prince (Being three cups of gold) as also, all such songs, as were that day sung in the several arches, I refer you to the book in print, where they are set down at large.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104830">And thus much you shall understand, that no manner of person whatsoever, did disburse any part towards the charge of these five triumphs, but only the mere citizens being all freemen; heretofore the charge being born by fifteens and the chamber of London (As may appear by ancient presidents) but now it was levied amongst the companies. The other two arches erected by merchant-strangers (Viz the Italians and Dutchmen) were only their own particular charge.</p>
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104840">The city elected 16. Committees to whom the managing of the whole business was absolutely referred: of which number 4. were aldermen, the other 12. Commoners, viz. one out of each of the 12. Companies. Other committees were also appointed as overseers and surveyors of the work. Farewell. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A02732-e104850">
      <div type="colophon" xml:id="A02732-e104860">
        <p xml:id="A02732-e104870">Imprinted at London by John Windet, printer to the honourable city of London, and are to be sold at the author's house in Lime-street, at the sign of the snail. 1604.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A02732"><item xml:id="A02732-genius" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A02732-genius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A02732-flamin" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A02732-flamin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A02732-euphrosyne" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A02732-euphrosyne</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A02732-circumspection" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A02732-circumspection</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A02732-graces" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A02732-graces</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A02732-fame" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A02732-fame</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A02732-zeal" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A02732-zeal</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A02732-thamesis" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A02732-thamesis</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

