<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1 &amp; 2 The Troublesome Reign of King John <date type="creation_date">1589</date></title>
        <author>anon.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nayoon Ahn</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A04520_01.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The first and second part of the troublesome raigne of Iohn King of England. With the discouerie of King Richard Cordelions base sonne (vulgarly named, the bastard Fawconbridge:) Also, the death of King Iohn at Swinstead Abbey. As they were (sundry times) lately acted by the Queenes Maiesties Players. Written by W. Sh.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>46 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006 June (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99842112</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 14646.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 101(b).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">6741</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04520</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The first and second part of the troublesome raigne of Iohn King of England. With the discouerie of King Richard Cordelions base sonne (vulgarly named, the bastard Fawconbridge:) Also, the death of King Iohn at Swinstead Abbey. As they were (sundry times) lately acted by the Queenes Maiesties Players. Written by W. Sh.</title>
            <title type="alt">Troublesome raigne of King Iohn.</title>
            <title type="alt">Troublesome raigne of King John.</title>
            <author>Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616,</author>
            <author>Marlowe, Christopher, 1564-1593,</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[92] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>By Valentine Simmes for Iohn Helme, and are to be sold at his shop in Saint Dunstons Churchyard in Fleetestreet,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1611.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The troublesome raigne of John King of England.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The attribution to Shakespeare is probably spurious; sometimes also attributed to Christopher Marlowe.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-L4 M2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: The troublesome raigne of King Iohn.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>John, -- King of England, -- 1167-1216 -- Drama.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A04520_01-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A04520_01-e100020">
      <div n="1" type="part" xml:id="A04520_01-e100030">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>The troublesome reign of King John.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e100040">Enter K. John, Queen Elinor his mother, William Marshall Earl of Pembroke, the Earls of Essex, and of Salisbury. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100050" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Queen Elianor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100060">Barons of England, and my noble lords;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100070">Though God and fortune have bereft from us</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100080">Victorious Richard scourge of infidels,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100090">And clad this land in stole of dismal hue:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100100">Yet give me leave to joy, and joy you all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100110">That from this womb hath sprung a second hope,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100120">A King that may in rule and virtue both</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100130">Succeed his brother in his empery. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100140" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>K. John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100150">My gracious mother Queen, and barons all;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100160">Though far unworthy of so high a place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100170">As is the throne of mighty England's King;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100180">Yet John your lord, contented uncontent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100190">Will (As he may) sustain the heavy yoke</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100200">Of pressing cares, that hang upon a crown. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100210">My lord of Pembroke and lord Salisbury,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100220">Admit the lord Chattilion to our presence;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100230">That we may know what Philip King of France</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100240">(By his ambassadors) requires of us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100250" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elinor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100260">Dare lay my hand that Elinor can guess</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100270">Whereto this weighty embassade doth tend:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100280">If of my nephew Arthur and his claim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100290">Then say, my son, I have not missed my aim. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e100300">Enter Chattilion and the two Earls.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100310" who="A04520_01-john">
          <pb facs="3"/>
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100320">My lord Chattilion, welcome into England:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100330">How fares our brother Philip King of France? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100340" who="A04520_01-chattilion">
          <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100350">His highness at my coming was in health,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100360">And willed me to salute your majesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100370">And say the message he hath given in charge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100380" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e100390">And spare not man, we are prepared to hear.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100400" who="A04520_01-chattilion">
          <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e100410">Philip, by the grace of God most Christian King of France, having taken into his guard and protection Arthur D. of Britain son and heir to Jeffrey thine elder brother, requireth in the behalf of the said Arthur, the kingdom of England, with the lordship of Ireland, Poiters, Anjou, Touraine, main: and I attend thine answer.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100420" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100430">A small request: belike he makes account,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100440">That England, Ireland, Poiters, Anjou, Touraine, main,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100450">Are nothing for a King to give at once:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100460">I wonder what he means to leave for me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100470">Tell Philip, he may keep his lords at home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100480">With greater honour than to send them thus</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100490">On embassades that not concern himself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100500">Or if they did, would yield but small return. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100510" who="A04520_01-chattilion">
          <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e100520">Is this thine answer?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100530" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e100540">It is, and too good an answer for so proud a message.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100550" who="A04520_01-chattilion">
          <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100560">Then King of England, in my master's name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100570">And in prince Arthur Duke of Britain's name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100580">I do defy thee as an enemy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100590">And wish thee to prepare for bloody wars. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100600" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elinor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100610">My lord (That stands upon defiance thus)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100620">Commend me to my nephew, tell the boy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100630">That I Queen Elianor (His grandmother)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100640">Upon my blessing charge him leave his arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100650">Whereto his headstrong mother pricks him so:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100660">Her pride we know, and know her for a dame</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100670">That will not stick to bring him to his end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100680">So she may bring herself to rule a realm. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100690">Next, wish him to forsake the King of France,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100700">And come to me and to his uncle here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100710">And he shall want for nothing at our hands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100720" who="A04520_01-chattilion">
          <pb facs="3"/>
          <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e100730">This shall I do, and thus I take my leave.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100740" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100750">Pembroke, convey him safely to the sea,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100760">But not in haste: for as we are advised,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100770">We mean to be in France as soon as he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100780">To fortify such towns as we possess</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100790">In Anjou, Touraine, and in Normandy. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e100800">Exit Chatt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e100810">Enter the shreeve and whispers the Earl of Salis. in the care.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100820" who="A04520_01-sals">
          <speaker>Sals.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e100830">Please it your majesty, here is the shrieve of Northhamptonshire, with certain persons that of late committed a riot, and have appealed to your majesty, beseeching your highness for special cause to hear them.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100840" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100850">Will them come near, and while we hear the cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100860">Go Salisbury and make provision,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100870">We mean with speed to pass the sea to France. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100880">Say shrive, what are these men, what have they done? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100890">Or whereto tends the course of this appeal? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100900" who="A04520_01-shrive">
          <speaker>Shrive</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e100910">Please it your majesty, these two brothers unnaturally falling at odds about their fathers living, have broken your highness' peace, in seeking to right their own wrongs without course of law, or order of justice, and unlawfully assembled themselves in mutinous manner, having committed a riot, appealing from trial in their country to your highness: and here I Thomas Nidigate shrine of Northamptonshire do deliver them over to their trial.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100920" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e100930">My lord of Essex, will th'offenders to stand forth, and tell the cause of their quarrel.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100940" who="A04520_01-essex">
          <speaker>Essex</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e100950">Gentlemen, it is the King's pleasure that you discover your griefs, and doubt not but you shall have justice.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100960" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e100970">Please it your m. the wrong is mine: yet will I abide all wrongs, before I once open my mouth t'unrip the shameful slander of my parents, the dishonour of myself, and the bad dealing of my brother in this princely assembly.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e100980" who="A04520_01-robert">
          <speaker>Robert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e100990">Then, by my prince his leave, shall Robert speak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101000">And tell your majesty what right I have</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101010">To offer wrong, as he accounteth wrong. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101020">My father (Not unknown unto your grace)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101030">Received his spurs of knighthood in the field,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101040"><pb facs="4"/> at kingly Richard's hands in Palestine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101050">Whenas the walls of Acon gave him way:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101060">His name sir Robert Fauconbridge of Mountbery. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101070">What by succession from his ancestors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101080">And warlike service under England's arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101090">His living did amount to at his death</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101100">Two thousand marks revenue every year:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101110">And this (My lord) I challenge for my right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101120">As lawful heir to Robert-fauconbridge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101130" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101140">If firstborn son be heir indubitate</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101150">By certain right of England's ancient law,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101160">How should myself make any other doubt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101170">But I am heir to Robert Fauconbridge? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101180" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101190">Fond youth, to trouble these our princely cares,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101200">Or make a question in so plain a case:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101210">Speak, is this man thine elder brother born? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101220" who="A04520_01-robert">
          <speaker>Robert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101230">Please it your grace with patience for to hear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101240">I not deny but he mine elder is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101250">Mine elder brother too: yet in such sort,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101260">As he can make no title to the land. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101270" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101280">A doubtful tale as ever I did hear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101290">Thy brother, and thine elder, and no heir:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101300">Explain this dark aenigma. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101310" who="A04520_01-robert">
          <speaker>Robert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101320">I grant (My lord) he is my mother's son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101330">Base born, and base begotten, no Fauconbridge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101340">Indeed the world reputes him lawful heir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101350">My father in his life did count him so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101360">And here my mother stands to prove him so:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101370">But I (My lord) can prove, and do aver</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101380">Both to my mother's shame, and his reproach,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101390">He is no heir, nor yet legitimate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101400">Then (Gracious lord) let Fauconbridge enjoy</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101410">The living that belongs to Fauconbridge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101420">And let not him possess another's right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101430" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e101440">Prove this, the land is thine by England's law.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101450" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elin.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101460">Ungracious youth, to rip thy mother's shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101470">The womb from whence thou didst thy being take,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101480"><pb facs="4"/> all honest ears abhor thy wickedness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101490">But gold I see doth beat down nature's law. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101500" who="A04520_01-mother">
          <speaker>Mother</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101510">My gracious lord, and you thrice reverend dame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101520">That see the tears distilling from mine eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101530">And scalding sighs blown from a rented heart:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101540">For honour and regard of womanhood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101550">Let me entreat to be commanded hence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101560">Let not these ears here receive the hissing sound</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101570">Of such a viper, who with poisoned words</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101580">Doth macerate the bowels of my soul. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101590" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101600">Lady, stand up, be patient for a while:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101610">And fellow, say, whose bastard is thy brother? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101620" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101630">Not for myself, nor for my mother now;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101640">But for the honour of so brave a man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101650">Whom he accuseth with adultery:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101660">Here I beseech your grace upon my knees,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101670">To count him mad, and so dismiss us hence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101680" who="A04520_01-robert">
          <speaker>Robert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101690">Nor mad, nor mazde, but well advised, I</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101700">Charge thee before this royal presence here</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101710">To be a bastard to King Richard's self,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101720">Son to your grace, and brother to your majesty. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101730">Thus bluntly, and</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101740" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Elian.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101750">Young man, thou needst not be ashamed of thy kin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101760">Nor of thy sire. But forward with thy proof. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101770" who="A04520_01-robert">
          <speaker>Robert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101780">The proof so plain, the argument so strong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101790">As that your highness and these noble lords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101800">And all (Save those that have no eyes to see)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101810">Shall swear him to be bastard to the King. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101820">First, when my father was ambassador</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101830">In Germany unto the emperor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101840">The King lay often at my father's house;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101850">And all the realm suspected what befell:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101860">And at my father's back-return again</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101870">My mother was delivered, as 'tis said,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101880">Six weeks before the account my father made. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101890">But more than this: look but on Philip's face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101900">His features, actions, and his lineaments,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101910"><pb facs="5"/> and all this princely presence shall confess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101920">He is no other but King Richard's son. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101930">Then gracious lord, rest he King Richard's son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101940">And let me rest safe in my father's right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e101950">That am his rightful son and only heir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101960" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e101970">Is this thy proof, and all thou hast to say?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e101980" who="A04520_01-robert">
          <speaker>Robert</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e101990">I have no more, nor need I greater proof.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102000" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102010">First, where thou saidst in absence of thy sire</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102020">My brother often lodged in his house:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102030">And what of that? base groom to slander him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102040">That honoured his ambassador so much,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102050">In absence of the man to cheer the wife? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102060">This will not hold, proceed unto the next. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102070" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elin.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102080">Thou sayest she teemed six weeks before her time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102090">Why good sir squire, are you so cunning grown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102100">To make account of women's reckonings? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102110">Spit in your hand and to your other proofs:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102120">Many mischances happen in such affairs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102130">To make a woman come before her time. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102140" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102150">And where thou sayest, he looketh like the King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102160">In action, feature and proportion:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102170">Therein I hold with thee, for in my life</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102180">I never saw so lively counterfeit</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102190">Of Richard Cordelion, as in him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102200" who="A04520_01-robert">
          <speaker>Robert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102210">Then good my lord, be you indifferent judge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102220">And let me have my living and my right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102230" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elinor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102240">Nay, hear you sir, you run away too fast:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102250">Know you not, omne simile non est idem? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102260">Or have read in. Hark ye good sir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102270">'Twas thus I warrant, and no otherwise,</l>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e102280">She lay with sir Robert your father, and thought upon King Richard my son, and so your brother was formed in this fashion.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102290" who="A04520_01-robert">
          <speaker>Robert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102300">Madam, you wrong me thus to jest it out,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102310">I crave my right: King John, as thou art King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102320">So be thou just, and let me have my right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102330" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102340">Why (Foolish boy) thy proofs are frivolous,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102350"><pb facs="5"/> nor canst thou challenge any thing thereby. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102360">But thou shalt see how I will help thy claim:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102370">This is my doom, and this my doom shall stand</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102380">Irrevocable, as I am King of England. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102390">For thou knowest not, we'll ask of them that know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102400">His mother and himself shall end this strife:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102410">And as they say, so shall thy living paste. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102420" who="A04520_01-robert">
          <speaker>Robert.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102430">My lord, herein I challenge you of wrong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102440">To give away my right, and put the doom</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102450">Unto themselves. Can there be likelihood</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102460">That she will lose? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102470">Or he will give the living from himself? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102480">It may not be my lord. Why should it be? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102490" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102500">Lords, keep him back, and let him hear the doom. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102510">Essex, first ask the mother thrice who was his sire? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102520" who="A04520_01-essex">
          <speaker>Essex.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102530">Lady Margaret, widow of Fauconbridge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102540">Who was father to thy son Philip? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102550" who="A04520_01-mother">
          <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e102560">Please it your majesty, sir Rob. Fauconbridge. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102570" who="A04520_01-robert">
          <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e102580">This is right, ask my fellow there if I be a thief.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102590" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e102600">Ask Philip whose son he is.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102610" who="A04520_01-essex">
          <speaker>Essex.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e102620">Philip, who was thy father?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102630" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e102640">Mas my lord, and that's a question: and you had not taken some pains with her before, I should have desired you to ask my mother.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102650" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e102660">Say, who was thy father?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102670" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e102680">Faith (My lord) to answer you, sure he is my father that was nearest my mother when I was begotten, and him I think to be sir Robert Fauconbridge. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102690" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102700">Essex, for fashion's sake demand again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102710">And so an end to this contention. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102720" who="A04520_01-robert">
          <speaker>Robert.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e102730">Was ever man thus wronged as Robert is?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102740" who="A04520_01-essex">
          <speaker>Essex.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e102750">Philip speak I say, who was thy father?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102760" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e102770">Young man how now, what art thou in a trance?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102780" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Elianor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e102790">Philip awake, the man is in a dream.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e102800" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102810">Philippus atavis aedite regibus. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102820">What sayest thou Philip, sprung of ancient Kings? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102830">Quo me rapit tempestas? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102840"><pb facs="6"/>What wind of honour blows this fury forth? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102850">Or whence proceed these fumes of majesty? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102860">Methinks I hear a hollow echo sound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102870">That Philip is the son unto a King:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102880">The whistling leaves upon the trembling trees,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102890">Whistle in consort I am Richard's son:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102900">The bubbling murmur of the waters fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102910">Records Philippus Regius filius:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102920">Birds in their flight make music with their wings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102930">Filling the air with glory of my birth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102940">Birds, bubbles, leaves, and mountains, echo, all</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102950">Ring in mine ears, that I am Richard's son. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102960">Fond man! ah whither art thou carried? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102970">How are thy thoughts ywrapt in honour's heaven? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102980">Forgetful what thou art, and whence thou camest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e102990">Thy father's land cannot maintain these thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103000">These thoughts are far unfitting Fauconbridge:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103010">And well they may; for why this mounting mind</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103020">Doth soar too high to stoop to Fauconbridge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103030">Why how now? knowest thou where thou art? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103040">And knowest thou who expects thine answer here? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103050">Wilt thou upon a frantic madding vain</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103060">Go lose thy land, and say thyself base born? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103070">No, keep thy land, though Richard were thy sire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103080">Whate'er thou thinkst, say thou art Fauconbridge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103090" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e103100">Speak man, be sudden, who thy father was.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103110" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103120">Please it your majesty, sir Robert</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103130">Philip, that Fauconbridge cleaves to thy jaws:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103140">It will not out, I cannot for my life</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103150">Say I am son unto a Fauconbridge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103160">Let land and living go, 'tis honour's fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103170">That makes me swear King Richard was my sire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103180">Base to a King adds title of more state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103190">Than knights begotten, though legitimate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103200">Please it your grace, I am King Richard's son. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103210" who="A04520_01-robert">
          <speaker>Robert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103220">Robert revive thy heart, let sorrow die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103230">His faltring tongue not suffers him to lie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103240" who="A04520_01-mother">
          <pb facs="6"/>
          <speaker>Mother</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e103250">What headstrong fury doth enchant my son?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103260" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e103270">Philip cannot repent, for he hath done.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103280" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103290">Then Philip blame not me, thyself hast lost</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103300">By wilfulness, thy living and thy land. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103310">Robert, thou art the heir of Fauconbridge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103320">God give thee joy, greater than thy desert. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103330" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. elia.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e103340">Why how now Philip, give away thine own?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103350" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103360">Madam, I am bold to make myself your nephew,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103370">The poorest kinsman that your highness hath:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103380">And with this proverb 'gin the world anew,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103390">Help hands, I have no lands, honour is my desire;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103400">Let Philip live to show himself worthy so great a sire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103410" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Eli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103420">Philip, I think thou knewest thy grandams mind:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103430">But cheer thee boy, I will not see thee want</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103440">As long as Elinor hath foot of land;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103450">Henceforth thou shalt be taken for my son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103460">And wait on me and on thine uncle here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103470">Who shall give honour to thy noble mind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103480" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103490">Philip kneel down, that thou mayst thoroughly know</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103500">How much thy resolution pleaseth us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103510">Rise up sir Richard Plantagenet King Richard's son. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103520" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103530">Grant heavens that Philip once may show himself</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103540">Worthy the honour of Plantagenet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103550">Or basest glory of a bastard's name. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103560" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103570">Now gentlemen, we will away to France,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103580">To check the pride of Arthur and his mates:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103590">Essex, thou shalt be ruler of my realm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103600">And towards the main charges of my wars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103610">I'll cease the lazy abbey lubbers lands</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103620">Into my hands to pay my men of war. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103630">The Pope and popelings shall not grease themselves</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103640">With gold and groats, that are the soldiers due. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103650">Thus forward lords, let our command be done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103660">And march we forward mightily to France. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e103670">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e103680">Manet Philip and his mother.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103690" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e103700">Madam, I beseech you deign me so much leisure as the hearing of a matter that I long to impart to you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103710" who="A04520_01-mother">
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e103720">What's the matter Philip? I think your suit in secret, tends to some money matter, which you suppose burns in the bottom of my chest.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103730" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103740">No madam, it is no such suit as to beg or borrow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103750">But such a suit, as might some other grant,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103760">I would not now have troubled you withal. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103770" who="A04520_01-mother">
          <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e103780">A god's name let us hear it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103790" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103800">Then madam thus, your ladyship sees well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103810">How that my scandal grows by means of you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103820">In that report hath rumoured up and down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103830">I am a bastard, and no Fauconbridge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103840">This gross attaint so tilteth in my thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103850">Maintaining combat to abridge mine ease,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103860">That field and town, and company alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103870">What so I do, or wheresoever I am,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103880">I cannot chase the slander from my thoughts. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103890">If it be true, resolve me of my fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103900">For pardon madam, if I think amiss. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103910">Be Philip Philip, and no Fauconbridge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103920">His father doubtless was as brave a man. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103930">To you on knees, as sometime Phaeton,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103940">Mistrusting sielly Merop for his sire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103950">Straining a little bashful modesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103960">I beg some instance whence I am extraught. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e103970" who="A04520_01-mother">
          <speaker>Mother</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103980">Yet more ado to haste me to my grave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e103990">And wilt thou too become a mother's cross? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104000">Must I accuse myself to close with you? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104010">Slander myself, to quiet your affects? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104020">Thou movest me Philip with this idle talk,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104030">Which I remit, in hope this mood will die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e104040" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104050">Nay lady mother, hear me further yet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104060">For strong conceit drives duty hence awhile:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104070">Your husband Fauconbridge was father to that son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104080">That carries marks of nature like the fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104090">The son that blotteth you with wedlock's breach,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104100">And holds my right, as lineal in descent</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104110">From him whose form was figured in his face ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104120"><pb facs="7"/> can nature so dissemble in her frame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104130">To make the one so like as like may be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104140">And in the other print no character</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104150">To challenge any mark of true descent? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104160">My brother's mind is base, and too too dull,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104170">To mount where Philip lodgeth his affects,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104180">And his external graces that you view,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104190">(Though I report it) counterpoise not mine:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104200">His constitution plain debility,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104210">Requires the chair, and mine the seat of steel. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104220">Nay, what is he, or what am I to him? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104230">When any one that knoweth how to carp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104240">Will scarcely judge us both one country born. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104250">This madam, this, hath driven me from myself:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104260">And here by heaven's eternal lamps I swear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104270">As cursed Nero with his mother did,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104280">So I with you, if you resolve me not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e104290" who="A04520_01-mother">
          <speaker>Mother</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104300">Let mother's tears quench out thy anger's fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104310">And urge no further what thou dost require. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e104320" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104330">Let son's entreaty sway the mother now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104340">Or else she dies: I'll not infringe my vow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e104350" who="A04520_01-mother">
          <speaker>Mother</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104360">Unhappy task: must I recount my shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104370">Blab my misdeeds, or by concealing die? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104380">Some power strike me speechless for a time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104390">Or take from him a while his hearings use. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104400">Why wish I so, unhappy as I am? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104410">The fault is mine, and he the faulty fruit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104420">I blush, I faint, o would I might be mute. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e104430" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e104440">Mother be brief, I long to know my name.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e104450" who="A04520_01-mother">
          <speaker>Mother</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e104460">And longing die, to shroud thy mother's shame.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e104470" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104480">Come madam come, you need not be so loath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104490">The shame is shared equal twixt us both. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104500">Is't not a slackness in me, worthy blame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104510">To be so old, and cannot write my name. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104520">Good mother resolve me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e104530" who="A04520_01-mother">
          <speaker>Mother</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104540">Then Philip hear thy fortune, and my grief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104550">My honour's loss by purchase of thyself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104560"><pb facs="8"/> my shame, thy name, and husbands secret wrong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104570">All maimed and stained by youths unruly sway. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104580">And when thou knowest from whence thou art extraught,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104590">Or if thou knew'st what suits, what threats, what fears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104600">To move by love, or massacre by death. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104610">To yield with love, or end by love's contempt. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104620">The mightiness of him that courted me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104630">Who tempered terror with his wanton talk,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104640">That something may extenuate the guilt. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104650">But let it not advantage me so much:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104660">Upbraid me rather with the Roman dame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104670">That shed her blood to wash away her shame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104680">Why stand I to expostulate the crime</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104690">With pro et contra, now the deed is done? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104700">When to conclude two words may tell the tale,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104710">That Philip's father was a prince's son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104720">Rich England's rule, world's only terror he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104730">For honour's loss left me with child of thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104740">Whose son thou art, then pardon me the rather,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104750">For fair King Richard was thy noble father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e104760" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104770">Then Robin Fauconbridge I wish thee joy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104780">My sire a King, and I a landless boy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104790">God's lady mother, the world is in my debt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104800">There's something owing to Plantagenet. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104810">I marry sir, let me alone for game,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104820">I'll act some wonders now I know my name. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104830">By blessed Mary. I'll not sell that pride</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104840">For England's wealth, and all the world beside. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104850">Sit fast the proudest of my father's foes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104860">Away good mother, there the comfort goes. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e104870">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e104880">Enter Philip the French King, and Lewis, Limoges, Constance, and her son Arthur. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e104890" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104900">Now 'gin we broach the title of thy claim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104910">Young Arthur in the Albion territories,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104920">Scaring proud Angiers with a puissant siege:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104930"><pb facs="8"/> brave Austria, cause of Cordelion's death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104940">Is also come to aid thee in thy wars;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104950">And all our forces join for Arthur's right. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104960">And, but for causes of great consequence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104970">Pleading delay till news from England come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104980">Twice should not Titan hide him in the West,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e104990">To cool the fetlocks of his weary team,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105000">Till I had with an unresisted shock</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105010">Controlled the manage of proud Angiers walls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105020">Or made a forfeit of my fame to chance. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e105030" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Const.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105040">May be that John in conscience or in fear</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105050">To offer wrong where you impugn the ill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105060">Will send such calm conditions back to France,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105070">As shall rebate the edge of fearful wars:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105080">If so, forbearance is a deed, well done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e105090" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105100">Ah mother, possession of a crown is much,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105110">And John as I have heard reported of,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105120">For present vantage would adventure far. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105130">The world can witness, in his brother's time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105140">He took upon him rule, and almost reign;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105150">Then must it follow as a doubtful point,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105160">That he'll resign the rule unto his nephew. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105170">I rather think the menace of the world</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105180">Sounds in his ears, as threats of no esteem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105190">And sooner would he scorn Europa's power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105200">Than lose the smallest title he enjoys;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105210">For questionless he is an Englishman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e105220" who="A04520_01-lewis">
          <speaker>Lewis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105230">Why are the English peerless in compare? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105240">Brave cavaliers as ere that island bred,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105250">Have lived and died, and dared, and done enough,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105260">Yet never graced their country for the cause:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105270">England is England, yielding good and bad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105280">And John of England is as other Johns. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105290">Trust me young Arthur, if thou like my reed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105300">Praise thou the French that help thee in this need. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e105310" who="A04520_01-limoges">
          <speaker>Lymog.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105320">The Englishman hath little cause I trow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105330">To spend good speeches on so proud a foe. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105340"><pb facs="9"/>Why Arthur here's his spoil that now is gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105350">Who when he lived outroved his brother John:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105360">But hasty curs that lie so long to catch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105370">Come halting home, and meet their overmatch. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105380">But news comes now, here's the ambassador. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e105390">Enter Chattilion.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e105400" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>K. Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105410">And in good time, welcome my lord Chattillion:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105420">What news? will John accord to our command? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e105430" who="A04520_01-chattilion">
          <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105440">Be I not brief to tell your highness all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105450">He will approach to interrupt my tale:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105460">For one self bottom brought us both to France. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105470">He on his part will try the chance of war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105480">And if his words infer assured truth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105490">Will lose himself, and all his followers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105500">Ere yield unto the least of your demands. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105510">The mother Queen she taketh on amain</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105520">'Gainst lady Constance, counting her the cause</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105530">That doth effect this claim to Albion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105540">Conjuring Arthur with a grandame's care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105550">To leave his mother; willing him submit</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105560">His state to John, and her protection,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105570">Who (As she saith) are studious for his good. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105580">More circumstance the season intercepts:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105590">This is the sum, which briefly I have shown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e105600" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>K. Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105610">This bitter wind must nip somebody's spring:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105620">Sudden and brief, why so, 'tis harvest weather. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105630">But say Chattilion, what persons of account are with him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e105640" who="A04520_01-chattilion">
          <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105650">Of England, Earl Pembroke and Salisbury,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105660">The only noted men of any name. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105670">Next them, a bastard of the Kings deceased,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105680">A hardy wild-head, tough and venturous,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105690">With many other men of high resolve. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105700">Then is there with them Elinor mother Queen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105710">And blanch her niece, daughter to the King of Spain:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105720">These are the prime birds of this hot adventure. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e105730">Enter John and his followers, Queen, bastard, Earles, etc.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e105740" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>K. Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105750">Me seemeth John, an overdaring spirit</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105760"><pb facs="9"/> effects some frenzy in thy rash approach,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105770">Treading my confines with thy armed troops. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105780">I rather looked for some submiss reply</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105790">Touching the claim thy nephew Arthur makes</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105800">To that which thou unjustly dost usurp. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e105810" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>K. John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105820">For that Chattilion can discharge you all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105830">I list not plead my title with my tongue. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105840">Nor came I hither with intent of wrong</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105850">To France or thee, or any right of thine;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105860">But in defence and purchase of my right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105870">The town of Angiers: which thou dost begird</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105880">In the behalf of lady Constance son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105890">Whereto nor he nor she can lay just claim. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e105900" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Constance</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105910">Yes (False intruder) if that just be just,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105920">And headstrong usurpation put apart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105930">Arthur my son, heir to thy elder brother,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105940">Without ambiguous shadow of descent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105950">Is sovereign to the substance thou withholdst. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e105960" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elinor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105970">Misgoverned gossip, stain to this resort,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105980">Occasion of these undecided jars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e105990">I say (That know) to check thy vain suppose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106000">Thy son hath naught to do with that he claims. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106010">For proof whereof, I can infer a will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106020">That bars the way he urgeth by descent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106030" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Con.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106040">A will indeed, a crabbed woman's will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106050">Wherein the devil is an overseer,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106060">And proud dame Elinor sole executress:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106070">More wills than so, on peril of my soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106080">Were never made to hinder Arthur's right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106090" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106100">But say there was, as sure there can be none,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106110">The law intends such testaments as void,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106120">Where right descent can no way be impeached. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106130" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elinor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106140">Peace Arthur peace, thy mother makes thee wings</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106150">To soar with peril after Icarus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106160">And trust me youngling for the father's sake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106170">I pity much the hazard of thy youth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106180" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Constance</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106190">Beshrew you else how pitiful you are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106200"><pb facs="10"/> ready to weep to hear him ask his own;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106210">Sorrow betide such grandames and such grief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106220">That minister a poison for pure love. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106230">But who so blind, as cannot see this beam,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106240">That you forsooth would keep your cousin down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106250">For fear his mother should be used too well? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106260">I there's the grief, confusion catch the brain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106270">That hammers shifts to stop a prince's reign. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106280" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. elia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106290">Impatient, frantic, common slanderer,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106300">Immodest dame, unnurtured quarrel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106310">I tell thee I, not envy to thy son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106320">But justice makes me speak as I have done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106330" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>K. Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e106340">But here's no proof that shows your son a King.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106350" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>K.i.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106360">What wants, my sword shall more at large set down</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106370" who="A04520_01-lewis">
          <speaker>Lew.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e106380">But that may break before the truth be known.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106390" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e106400">Then this may hold till all his tight be shown.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106410" who="A04520_01-limoges">
          <speaker>Lym.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e106420">Good words sir sauce, your betters are in place.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106430" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e106440">Not you sir doughty, with your lion's case.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106450" who="A04520_01-blanche">
          <speaker>Blanch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106460">Ah joy betide his soul, to whom that spoil belonged:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106470">Ah Richard, how thy glory here is wronged. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106480" who="A04520_01-limoges">
          <speaker>Lym.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106490">Methinks that Richard's pride and Richard's fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106500">Should be a precedent t'affright you all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106510" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106520">What words are these? how do my sinews shake? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106530">My father's foe clad in my father's spoil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106540">A thousand furies kindle with revenge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106550">This heart that choler keeps a consistory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106560">Searing my innards with a brand of hate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106570">How doth Allecto whisper in mine ears? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106580">Delay not Philip, kill the villain straight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106590">Disrobe him of the matchless monument</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106600">Thy father's triumph o'er the savages,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106610">Base heardgroom, coward peasant, worse than a threshing slave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106620">What mak'st thou with the trophy of a King? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106630">Shamest thou not coistrel, loathsome dunghill swad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106640">To grace thy carcase with an ornament</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106650">Too precious for a monarch's coverture? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106660"><pb facs="10"/>Scarce can I temper due obedience</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106670">Unto the presence of my sovereign,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106680">From acting outrage on this trunk of hate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106690">But arm thee traitor, wronger of renown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106700">For by his soul I swear, my father's soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106710">Twice will I not review the morning's rise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106720">Till I have torn that trophy from thy back,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106730">And split thy heart for wearing it so long. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106740">Philip hath sworn, and if it be not done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106750">Let not the world repute me Richard's son. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106760" who="A04520_01-limoges">
          <speaker>Lym.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106770">Nay soft sir bastard, hearts are not split so soon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106780">Let them rejoice that at the end do win:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106790">And take this lesson at thy foeman's hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106800">Pawn not thy life to get thy father's skin. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106810" who="A04520_01-blanche">
          <speaker>Blan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106820">Well may the world speak of his knightly valour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106830">That wins this hide to wear a lady's favour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106840" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106850">Ill may I thrive, and nothing brook with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106860">If shortly I present it not to thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e106870" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>K. Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106880">Lordings forbear, for time is coming fast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106890">That deeds may try what words can not determine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106900">And to the purpose for the cause you come. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106910">Me seems you set right in chance of war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106920">Yielding no other reasons for your claim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106930">But so and so, because it shall be so. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106940">So wrong shall be suborned by trust of strength:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106950">A tyrant's practice to invest himself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106960">Where weak resistance giveth wrong the way. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106970">To check the which, in holy lawful arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106980">Ay, in the right of Arthur, Geoffrey's son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e106990">Am come before this city of Angiers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107000">To bar all other false supposed claim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107010">From whence, or howsoe'er the error springs. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107020">And in his quarrel on my princely word,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107030">I'll fight it out unto the latest man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107040" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107050">Know King of France, I will not be commanded</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107060">By any power or prince in Christendom,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107070">To yield an instance how I hold mine own,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107080"><pb facs="11"/> more than to answer, that mine own is mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107090">But wilt thou see me parley with the town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107100">And hear them offer me allegiance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107110">Fealty and homage, as true liege men ought. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107120" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>K. Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107130">Summon them, I will not believe it till I see it, and when I see it, I'll soon change it.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e107140">They summon the town, the citizens appear upon the walls.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107150" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>K. John</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107160">You men of Angiors, and as I take it my loyal subjects, I have summoned you to the walls: to dispute on my right, were to think you doubtful therein, which I am persuaded you are not. In few words, our brother's son, backed with the King of France, have beleaguered your town upon a false pretended title to the same: in defence whereof I your liege lord have brought our power to fence you from the usurper, to free your intended servitude, and utterly to supplant the foemen, to my right and your rest. Say then, who keep you the town for?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107170" who="A04520_01-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107180">For our lawful King.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107190" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107200">I was no less persuaded: then in god's name open your gates, and let me enter.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107210" who="A04520_01-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107220">And it please your highness we control not your title, neither will we rashly admit your entrance: if you be lawful King, with all obedience we keep it to your use, if not King, our rashness to be impeached for yielding, without more considerate trial: we answer not as men lawless, but to the behoof of him that proves lawful.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107230" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107240">I shall not come in then?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107250" who="A04520_01-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107260">No my lord, till we know more.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107270" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>K. Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107280">Then hear me speak in the behalf of Arthur son of Geoffrey, elder brother to John, his title manifest, without contradiction, to the crown and kingdom of England, with Angiers, and divers towns on this side the sea: will you acknowledge him your liege lord, who speaketh in my word, to entertain you with all favours, as beseemeth a King to his subjects, or a friend to his well-willers: or stand to the peril of your contempt, when his title is proved by the sword.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107290" who="A04520_01-citizen">
          <pb facs="11"/>
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107300">We answer as before, till you have proved one right, we acknowledge none right, he that tries himself our sovereign; to him will we remain firm subjects, and for him, and in his right we hold our town, as desirous to know the truth, as loath to subscribe before we know: more than this we cannot say, and more than this we dare not do.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107310" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>K. Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107320">Then John I defy thee, in the name and behalf of Arthur Plantagenet, thy King and cousin, whose right and patrimony thou detainest, as I doubt not, ere the day end, in a set battle make thee confess; whereunto, with a zeal to right, I challenge thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107330" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>K. John.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107340">I accept thy challenge, and turn the defiance to thy throat.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e107350">Excursions. The bastard chaseth Lymoges the ostrich Duke, and maketh him leave the lion's skin.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107360" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107370">And art thou gone misfortune haunt thy steps,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107380">And chill cold fear assail thy times of rest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107390">Morpheus leave here thy silent ebon cave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107400">Besiege his thoughts with dismal fantasies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107410">And ghastly objects of pale threatening mors. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107420">Affright him every minute with stern looks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107430">Let shadow temper terror in his thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107440">And let the terror make the coward mad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107450">And in his madness let him fear pursuit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107460">And so in frenzy let the peasant die. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107470">Here is the ransom that allaies his rage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107480">The first freehold that Richard left his son:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107490">With which I shall surprise his living foes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107500">As Hector's statue did the fainting Greeks. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e107510">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e107520">Enter the King's heralds with trumpets to the walls of Angiers: they summon the town.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107530" who="A04520_01-eng_herald">
          <speaker>Eng. her.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107540">John by the grace of God King of England, lord of Ireland, Anjou, Touraine, etc. demandeth once again of you his subjects of Angiers, if you will quietly surrender up the town into his hands?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107550" who="A04520_01-french_herald">
          <pb facs="12"/>
          <speaker>Fr. Herold.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107560">Philip by the grace of God King of France, demandeth in the behalf of Arthur Duke of Britain, if you will surrender up the town into his hands, to the use of the said Arthur. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107570" who="A04520_01-citizens">
          <speaker>Citizens.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107580">Heralds go tell the two victorious princes, that we the poor inhabitants of Angiers, require a parley of their majesties.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107590" who="A04520_01-herolds">
          <speaker>Herold's.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107600">We go.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e107610">Enter the Kings, Queen Elianor, Blanch, bastard, Lymoges, Lewis, Castilean, Pembroke, Salisbury, Constance, and Arthur Duke of Britain.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107620" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107630">Herold, what answer do the townsmen send?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107640" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107650">Will Angiers yield to Philip King of France?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107660" who="A04520_01-eng_herald">
          <speaker>Eng. her.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107670">The townsmen on the walls accept your grace.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107680" who="A04520_01-french_herald">
          <speaker>Fr. her.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e107690">And crave a parley of your majesty.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107700" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107710">You citizens of Angiers, have your eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107720">Beheld the slaughter that our English bows</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107730">Have made upon the coward fraudful French? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107740">And have you wisely pondered therewithal</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107750">Your gain in yielding to the English King? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107760" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107770">Their loss in yielding to the English King. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107780">But John, they saw from out their highest towers</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107790">The chevaliers of France and cross-bow-shot</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107800">Make lanes of slaughtered bodies through thine host,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107810">And are resolved to yield to Arthur's right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107820" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107830">Why Philip, though thou brav'st it fore the walls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107840">Thy conscience knows that John hath won the field. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107850" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107860">Whate'er my conscience knows, thy army feels</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107870">That Philip had the better of the day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e107880" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107890">Philip indeed hath got the lion's case,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107900">Which here he holds to Lymoges disgrace. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107910">Base Duke to fly and leave such spoils behind:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107920">But this thou knewest of force to make me stay. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107930">It fared with thee as with the mariner,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107940">Spying the hugy whale, whose monstrous bulk</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107950">Doth bear the waves like mountains fore the wind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107960"><pb facs="12"/> that throws out empty vessels, so to stay</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107970">His fury, while the ship doth sail away. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107980">Philip 'tis thine: and fore this princely presence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e107990">Madam, I humbly lay it at your feet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108000">Being the first adventure I achieved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108010">And first exploit your grace did me enjoin:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108020">Yet many more I long to be enjoined. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108030" who="A04520_01-blanche">
          <speaker>Blanch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108040">Philip I take it, and I thee command</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108050">To wear the same as erst thy father did:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108060">Therewith receive this favour at my hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108070">T'encourage thee to follow Richard's fame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108080" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108090">Ye citizens of Angiers are ye mute? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108100">Arthur or John, say which shall be your King? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108110" who="A04520_01-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108120">We care not which, if once we knew the right</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108130">But till we know, we will not yield our right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108140" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108150">Might Philip counsel two so mighty Kings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108160">As are the Kings of England and of France,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108170">He would advise your graces to unite</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108180">And knit your forces 'gainst these citizens,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108190">Pulling their battered walls about their ears. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108200">The town once won, then strive about the claim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108210">For they are minded to delude you both. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108220" who="A04520_01-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108230">Kings, princes, lords, and knights assembled here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108240">The citizens of Angiers all by me</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108250">Entreat your majesty to hear them speak:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108260">And as you like the motion they shall make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108270">So to account and follow their advice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108280" who="A04520_01-multiple">
          <speaker>John. Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e108290">Speak on, we give thee leave.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108300" who="A04520_01-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108310">Then thus: whereas the young and lusty knight ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108320">Incites you on to knit your kingly strengths:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108330">The motion cannot choose but please the good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108340">And such as love the quiet of the state. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108350">But how my lords, how should your strengths be knit? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108360">Not to oppress your subjects and your friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108370">And fill the world with brawls and mutinies:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108380">But unto peace your forces should be knit</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108390">To live in princely league and amity:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108400"><pb facs="13"/> do this, the gates of Angiers shall give way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108410">And stand wide open to your hearts content. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108420">To make this peace a lasting bond of love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108430">Remains one only honourable means,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108440">Which by your pardon I shall here display. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108450">Lewis the dolphin and the heir of France,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108460">A man of noted valour through the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108470">Is yet unmarried: let him take to wife</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108480">The beauteous daughter of the King of Spain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108490">Niece to K. John, the lovely lady blanch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108500">Begotten on his sister Elianor. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108510">With her in marriage will her uncle give</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108520">Castles and towers, as fitteth such a match. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108530">The Kings thus joined in league of perfect love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108540">They may so deal with Arthur Duke of Britain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108550">Who is but young, and yet unmeet to reign,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108560">As he shall stand contented every way. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108570">Thus have I boldly (For the common good)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108580">Delivered what the city gave in charge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108590">And as upon conditions you agree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108600">So shall we stand content to yield the town. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108610" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108620">A proper peace, if such a motion hold;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108630">These Kings bear arms for me, and for my right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108640">And they shall share my lands to make them friends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108650" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elian.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108660">Son John, follow this motion, as thou lovest thy mother. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108670">Make league with Philip, yield to any thing:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108680">Lewis shall have my niece, and then be sure</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108690">Arthur shall have small succour out of France. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108700" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108710">Brother of France, you hear the citizens:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108720">Then tell me, how you mean to deal herein. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108730" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Const.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108740">Why John, what canst thou give unto thy niece,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108750">That hast no foot of land, but Arthur's right? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108760" who="A04520_01-lewis">
          <speaker>Lew.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108770">By'r lady citizens, I like your choice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108780">A lovely damsel is the lady Blanch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108790">Worthy the heir of Europe for her fere. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108800" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Const.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108810">What Kings, why stand you gazing in a trance? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108820"><pb facs="13"/>Why how now lords? accursed citizens</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108830">To fill and tickle their ambitious ears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108840">With hope of gain, that springs from Arthur's loss. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108850">Some dismal planet at thy birthday reigned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108860">For now I see the fall of all thy hopes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108870" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>K. Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108880">Lady, and Duke of Britain, know you both,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108890">The King of France respects his honour more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108900">Than to betray his friends and favourers. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108910">Princess of Spain, could you affect my son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108920">If we upon conditions could agree? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108930" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108940">'Swounds madam, take an English gentleman? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108950">Slave as I was, I thought to have moved the match. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108960">Grandam you made me half a promise once,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108970">That lady Blanch should bring me wealth enough,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e108980">And make me heir of store of English land. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e108990" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elian.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109000">Peace Philip, I will look thee out a wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109010">We must with policy compound this strife. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109020" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109030">If Lewis get her, well, I say no more:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109040">But let the frolic Frenchman take no scorn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109050">If Philip front him with an English horn. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109060" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109070">Lady, what answer make you to the K. of France? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109080">Can you affect the dolphin for your lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109090" who="A04520_01-blanche">
          <speaker>Blanch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109100">I thank the King that likes of me so well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109110">To make me bride unto so great a prince:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109120">But give me leave my lord to pause on this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109130">Lest being too too forward in the cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109140">It may be blemish to my modesty. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e109150">Q. Elinor. Son John, and worthy Philip K. of France,</stage>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109160">Do you confer awhile about the dower,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109170">And I will school my modest niece so well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109180">That she shall yield as soon as you have done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109190" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Constance.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109200">Ay, there's the wretch that broacheth all this ill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109210">Why fly I not upon the beldame's face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109220">And with my nails pull forth her hateful eyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109230" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109240">Sweet mother cease these hasty madding fits:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109250">For my sake, let my grandam have her will. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109260">O would she with her hands pull forth my heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109270"><pb facs="14"/> I could afford it to appease these broils. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109280">But (Mother) let us wisely wink at all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109290">Lest farther harms ensue our hasty speech. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109300" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109310">Brother of England, what dowry wilt thou give</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109320">Unto my son in marriage with thy niece? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109330" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109340">First Philip knows her dowry out of Spain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109350">To be so great as may content a King:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109360">But more to mend and amplify the same,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109370">I give in more money thousand marks. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109380">For land I leave it to thine own demand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109390" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109400">Then I demand Volquesson, Torain, main,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109410">Poiters and Anjou, these five provinces,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109420">Which thou as King of England holdest in France:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109430">Then shall our peace be soon concluded on. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109440" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e109450">No less than five such provinces at once?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109460" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109470">Mother what shall I do? my brother got these lands</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109480">With much effusion of our English blood:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109490">And shall I give it all away at once? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109500" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elin.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109510">John give it him, so shalt thou live in peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109520">And keep the residue sans jeopardy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109530" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109540">Philip, bring forth thy son, here is my niece,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109550">And here in marriage I do give with her</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109560">From me and my successors English Kings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109570">Volquesson, Poiters, Anjou, Torain, main,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109580">And thirty thousand marks of stipend coin. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109590">Now citizens, how like you of this match? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109600" who="A04520_01-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e109610">We joy to see so sweet a peace begun.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109620" who="A04520_01-lewis">
          <speaker>Lewis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109630">Lewis with Blanch shall ever live content. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109640">But now King John, what say you to the Duke? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109650">Father, speak as you may in his behalf. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109660" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109670">K. John, be good unto thy nephew here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109680">And give him somewhat that shall please you best. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109690" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109700">Arthur, although thou troublest England's peace</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109710">Yet here I give thee Britain for thine own,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109720">Together with the earldom of Richmont,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109730">And this rich city of Angiers withal,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109740" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <pb facs="14"/>
          <speaker>Q. Elian.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109750">And if thou seek to please thine uncle John,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109760">Shalt see my son how I will make of thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109770" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109780">Now every thing is sorted to this end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109790">Let's in, and there prepare the marriage rites,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109800">Which in s. Mary's chapel presently</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109810">Shall be performed ere this presence part. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e109820">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e109830">Manent Constance and Arthur.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109840" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Art.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109850">Madam good cheer, these drooping languishments</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109860">Add no redress to salve our awkward haps,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109870">If heavens have concluded these events,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109880">To small avail is bitter pensiveness:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109890">Seasons will change, and so our present grief</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109900">May change with them, and all to our relief. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109910" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Const.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109920">Ah boy, thy years I see are far too green</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109930">To look into the bottom of these cares. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109940">But I, who see the poise that weigheth down</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109950">Thy weal, my wish, and all the willing means</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109960">Wherewith thy fortune and thy fame should mount. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109970">What joy, what ease, what rest can lodge in me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e109980">With whom all hope and hap do disagree? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e109990" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110000">Yet ladies' tears, and cares, and solemn shows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110010">Rather than helps, heap up more work for woes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110020" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Const.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110030">If any power will hear a widow's plaint,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110040">That from a wounded soul implores revenge;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110050">Send fell contagion to infect this clime,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110060">This cursed country, where the traitor's breath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110070">Whose perjury (As proud Briareus,)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110080">Beleaguers all the sky with misbelief. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110090">He promised Arthur, and he sware it too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110100">To fence thy right, and check thy foeman's pride:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110110">But now black-spotted perjure as he is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110120">He takes a truce with elnor's damned brat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110130">And marries Lewis to her lovely niece,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110140">Sharing thy fortune, and thy birthdays gift</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110150">Between these lovers: ill betide the match. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110160">And as they shoulder thee from out thine own,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110170">And triumph in a widow's tearful cares:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110180"><pb facs="15"/> so heavens cross them with a thriftless course,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110190">Is all the blood yspilt on either part,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110200">Closing the crannies of the thirsty earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110210">Grown to a love-game and a bridal feast? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110220">And must thy birthright bid the wedding banes? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110230">Poor helpless boy, hopeless and helpless too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110240">To whom misfortune seems no yoke at all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110250">Thy stay, thy state, thy imminent mishaps</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110260">Woundeth thy mother's thoughts with feeling care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110270">Why lookest thou pale? the colour flies thy face:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110280">I trouble now the fountain of thy youth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110290">And make it muddy with my doles discourse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110300">Go in with me, reply not lovely boy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110310">We must obscure this moan with melody,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110320">Lest worser wrack ensue our malcontent. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e110330">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e110340">Enter the King of England, the King of France, Arthur, bastard, Lewis, Lymoges, Constance, Blanch, Chattillion, Pembroke, Salisbury, and Elianor. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110350" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110360">This is the day, the long-desired day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110370">Wherein the realms of England and of France</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110380">Stand highly blessed in a lasting peace. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110390">Thrice happy is the bridegroom and the bride,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110400">From whose sweet bridal such a concord springs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110410">To make of mortal foes immortal friends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110420" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Const.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e110430">Ungodly peace made by another's war.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110440" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110450">Unhappy peace, that ties thee from revenge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110460">Rouse thee Plantagenet, live not to see</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110470">The butcher of the great Plantagenet. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110480">Kings, princes, and ye peers of either realms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110490">Pardon my rashness, and forgive the zeal</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110500">That carries me in fury to a deed</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110510">Of high desert, of honour, and of arms. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110520">A boon (Oh Kings) a boon doth Philip beg</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110530">Prostrate upon his knee: which knee shall cleave</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110540">Unto the superficies of the earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110550">Till France and England grant this glorious boon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110560" who="A04520_01-john">
          <pb facs="15"/>
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e110570">Speak Philip, England grants thee thy request.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110580" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e110590">And France confirms whate'er is in his power.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110600" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110610">Then Duke sit fast, I level at thy head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110620">Too base a ransom for my father's life. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110630">Princes, I crave the combat with the Duke</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110640">That braves it in dishonour of my sire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110650">Your words are past, nor can you now reverse</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110660">The princely promise that revives my soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110670">Whereat methinks I see his sinews shake:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110680">This is the boon (Dread lords) which granted once</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110690">Or life or death are pleasant to my soul;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110700">Since I shall live and die in Richard's right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110710" who="A04520_01-limoges">
          <speaker>Lym.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110720">Base bastard, misbegotten of a King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110730">To interrupt these holy nuptial rites</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110740">With brawls and tumults to a Duke's disgrace;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110750">Let it suffice, I scorn to join in fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110760">With one so far unequal to myself. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110770" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110780">A fine excuse, Kings if you will be Kings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110790">Then keep your words, and let us combat it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110800" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110810">Philip, we cannot force the Duke to fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110820">Being a subject unto neither realm:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110830">But tell me Austria, if an English Duke</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110840">Should dare thee thus, wouldst thou accept the challenge? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110850" who="A04520_01-limoges">
          <speaker>Lym.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110860">Else let the world account the ostrich Duke</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110870">The greatest coward living on the earth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110880" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110890">Then cheer thee Philip, John will keep his word,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110900">Kneel down, in sight of Philip King of France,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110910">And all these princely lords assembled here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110920">I gird thee with the sword of Normandy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110930">And of that land I do invest thee Duke:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110940">So shalt thou be in living and in land</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110950">Nothing inferior unto Austria. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e110960" who="A04520_01-limoges">
          <speaker>Lym.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110970">K. John, I tell thee flatly to thy face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110980">Thou wrongest mine honour: and that thou mayest see</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e110990">How much I scorn thy new made Duke and thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111000">I flatly say, I will not be compelled:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111010">And so farewell sir Duke of low degree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111020"><pb facs="16"/> I'll find a time to match you for this gear. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e111030">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111040" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111050">Stay Philip, let him go, the honours thine.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111060" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111070">I cannot live unless his life be mine.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111080" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. elia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111090">Thy forwardness this day hath joyed my soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111100">And made me think my Richard lives in thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111110" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>K. Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111120">Lordings let's in, and spend the wedding day</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111130">In masks and triumphs, letting quarrels cease. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e111140">Enter a Cardinal from Rome.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111150" who="A04520_01-cardinal">
          <speaker>Cardinal</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111160">Stay King of France, I charge thee join not hands</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111170">With him that stands accursed of God and men. </l>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111180">Know John, that I Pandulph Cardinal of Milan, and legate from the sea of Rome, demand of thee in the name of our holy father the Pope innocent, why thou dost (Contrary to the laws of our holy mother the church, and our holy father the Pope) disturb the quiet of the church, and disannul the election of Stephen Langhton, whom his holiness hath elected Archbishop of Canterbury: this in his holiness' name I demand of thee?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111190" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111200">And what hast thou or the Pope thy master to do to demand of me, how I employ mine own? Know sir priest, as I honour the church and holy churchmen, so I scorn to be subject to the greatest prelate in the world. Tell thy master so from me, and say, John of England said it, that never an Italian priest of them all, shall either have tithe, toll, or polling penny out of England; but as I am King, so will I reign next under God, supreme head both over spiritual and temporal: and he that contradicts me in this, I'll make him hop headless.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111210" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>K. Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111220">What K. John, know you what you say, thus to blaspheme against our holy father the Pope?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111230" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111240">Philip, though thou and all the princes of Christendom suffer themselves to be abused by a prelate's slavery, my mind is not of such base temper. If the Pope will be King of England, let him win it with the sword, I know no other title he can allege to mine inheritance.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111250" who="A04520_01-cardinal">
          <speaker>Cardinal</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111260">John, this is thine answer?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111270" who="A04520_01-john">
          <pb facs="16"/>
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111280">What then?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111290" who="A04520_01-cardinal">
          <speaker>Cardinal</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111300">Then I Pandulph of Padua, legate from the Apostolic sea, do in the name of saint Peter and his successor our holy father Pope innocent, pronounce thee accursed, discharging every of thy subjects of all duty and fealty that they do owe to thee, and pardon and forgiveness of sin to those or them whatsoever, which shall carry arms against thee, or murder thee: this I pronounce, and charge all good men to abhor thee as an excommunicate person.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111310" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111320">So sir, the more the fox is cursed the better 'a fares: if God bless me and my land, let the Pope and his shavelings curse and spare not.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111330" who="A04520_01-cardinal">
          <speaker>Cardinal</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111340">Furthermore, I charge thee Philip K. of France, and all the Kings and princes of Christendom, to make war upon this miscreant: and whereas thou hast made a league with him, and confirmed it by oath, I do in the name of our foresaid father the Pope, acquit thee of that oath, as unlawful, being made with an heretic; how sayest thou Philip, dost thou obey?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111350" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111360">Brother of France, what say you to the Cardinal?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111370" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111380">I say, I am sorry for your majesty, requesting you to submit yourself to the church of Rome.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111390" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111400">And what say you to our league, if I do not submit?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111410" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111420">What should I say? I must obey the Pope.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111430" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111440">Obey the Pope, and break your oath to God?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111450" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111460">The legate hath absolved me of mine oath:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111470">Then yield to Rome, or I defy thee here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111480" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111490">Why Philip, I defy the Pope and thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111500">False as thou art, and perjured King of France,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111510">Unworthy man to be accounted King. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111520">Givest thou thy sword into a prelate's hands? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111530">Pandulph, where I of abbots, monks, and friars</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111540">Have taken somewhat to maintain my wars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111550">Now will I take no more but all they have. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111560">I'll rouse the lazy lubbers from their cells,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111570">And in despite I'll send them to the Pope. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111580"><pb facs="17"/>Mother come you with me, and for the rest</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111590">That will not follow John in this attempt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111600">Confusion light upon their damned souls. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111610">Come lords, fight for your K. that fighteth for your good</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111620" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111630">And are they gone? Pandulph thyself shalt see</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111640">How France will fight for Rome and Romish rites. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111650">Nobles to arms, let him not pass the seas,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111660">Let's take him captive, and in triumph lead</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111670">The K. of England to the gates of Rome. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111680">Arthur bestir thee man, and thou shalt see</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111690">What Philip K. of France will do for thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111700" who="A04520_01-blanche">
          <speaker>Blanch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111710">And will your grace upon your wedding day</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111720">Forsake your bride, and follow dreadful drums? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111730">Nay, good my lord, stay you at home with me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111740" who="A04520_01-lewis">
          <speaker>Lew.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e111750">Sweet heart content thee, and we shall agree.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111760" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111770">Follow my lords, lord Cardinal lead the way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111780">Drums shall be music to this wedding day. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e111790">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e111800">Excursions. The bastard pursues Austria, and kills him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111810" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111820">Thus hath K. Richard's son performed his vows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111830">And offered Austria's blood for sacrifice</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111840">Unto his father's everliving soul. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111850">Brave Cordelion, now my heart doth say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111860">I have deserved, though not to be thine heir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111870">Yet as I am, thy base begotten son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111880">A name as pleasing to thy Philip's heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111890">As to be called the Duke of Normandy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111900">Lie there a prey to every ravening fowl:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111910">And as my father triumphed in thy spoils,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111920">And trodden thine ensigns underneath his feet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111930">So do I tread upon thy cursed self,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111940">And leave thy body to the fowls for food. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e111950">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e111960">Excursions. Arthur, Constance, Lewis, having taken Q. Elianor prisoner. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e111970" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Const.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111980">Thus hath the god of Kings with conquering arm</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e111990"><pb facs="17"/> dispersed the foes to true succession,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112000">Proud, and disturber of thy country's peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112010">Constance doth live to tame thine insolence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112020">And on thy head will now avenged be</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112030">For all the mischiefs hatched in thy brain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112040" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elinor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112050">Contemptuous dame, unreverent Duchess thou,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112060">To brave so great a Queen as Elianor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112070">Base scold, hast thou forgotten, that I was wife</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112080">And mother to three mighty English Kings? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112090">I charge thee then, and you forsooth sir boy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112100">To set your grandmother at liberty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112110">And yield to John your uncle and your King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112120" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Const.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e112130">'Tis not thy words proud Queen shall carry it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112140" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Elin.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e112150">Nor yet thy threats proud dame shall daunt my mind.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112160" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e112170">Sweet grandam, and good mother leave these braules.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112180" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Elian.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e112190">I'll find a time to triumph in thy fall.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112200" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Const.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112210">My time is now to triumph in thy fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112220">And thou shalt know that Constance will triumph. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112230" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112240">Good mother, weigh it is Queen Elinor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112250">Though she be captive, use her like herself. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112260">Sweet grandam bear with what my mother says,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112270">Your highness shall be used honourably. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e112280">Enter a messenger.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112290" who="A04520_01-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112300">Lewis my lord, Duke Arthur, and the rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112310">To arms in haste, K. John relies his men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112320">And begins the sight afresh: and swears withal</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112330">To lose his life, or set his mother free. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112340" who="A04520_01-lewis">
          <speaker>Lewis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e112350">Arthur away, 'tis time to look about.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112360" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Eli.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e112370">Why how now dame, what is your courage cold?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112380" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Const.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112390">No Elinor my courage gathers strength,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112400">And hopes to lead both John and thee as slaves:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112410">And in that hope, I hale thee to the field. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e112420">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e112430"><pb facs="18"/>Excursions. Elianor is rescued by John, and Arthur is taken prisoner. Exeunt. Sound victory.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e112440">Enter John, Elianor, and Arthur prisoner, bastard, Pembroke, Salisbury, and Hubert de Burgh. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112450" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112460">Thus right triumphs, and John triumphs in right:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112470">Arthur thou seest, France cannot bolster thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112480">Thy mother's pride hath brought thee to this fall. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112490">But if at last nephew thou yield thyself</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112500">Into the guard of thine uncle John,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112510">Thou shalt be used as becomes a prince. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112520" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112530">Uncle, my grandam taught her nephew this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112540">To bear captivity with patience. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112550">Might hath prevailed, not right, for I am King</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112560">Of England, though thou wear the diadem. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112570" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elin.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112580">Son John, soon shall we teach him to forget</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112590">These proud presumptions, and to know himself. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112600" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112610">Mother, he never will forget his claim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112620">I would he lived not to remember it. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112630">But leaving this, we will to England now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112640">And take some order with our popelings there,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112650">That swell with pride and fat of lay men's lands. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112660">Philip, I make thee chief in this affair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112670">Ransack the abbeys, cloisters, priories,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112680">Convert their coin unto my soldier's use:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112690">And whatsoever he be within my land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112700">That goes to Rome for justice and for law,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112710">While he may have his right within the realm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112720">Let him be judged a traitor to the state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112730">And suffer as an enemy to England. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112740">Mother, we leave you here beyond the seas,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112750">As regent of our provinces in France,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112760">While we to England take a speedy course,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112770">And thank our God that gave us victory. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112780">Hubert de Burgh take Arthur here to thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112790"><pb facs="18"/> be he thy prisoner: Hubert keep him safe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112800">For on his life doth hang thy sovereign's crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112810">But in his death consists thy sovereign's bliss:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112820">Then Hubert, as thou shortly hearst from me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112830">So use the prisoner I have given in charge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112840" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112850">Frolic young prince, though I your keeper be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112860">Yet shall your keeper live at your command. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112870" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e112880">As please my God, so shall become of me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112890" who="A04520_01-elianor">
          <speaker>Q. Elian.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112900">My son, to England, I will see thee shipped,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112910">And pray to God to send thee safe ashore. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112920" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112930">Now wars are done, I long to be at home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112940">To dive into the monks and abbot's bags,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112950">To make some sport among the smooth skinned nuns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112960">And keep some revel with the fanzen friars. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e112970" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112980">To England lords, each look unto your charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e112990">And arm yourselves against the Roman pride. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e113000">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e113010">Enter the King of France, Lewes his son, Cardinal Pandolph Legate, and Constance.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113020" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113030">What, every man attached with this mishap? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113040">Why frown you so, why droop ye lords of France? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113050">Methinks it differs from a warlike mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113060">To lower it for a check or two of chance. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113070">Had Lymoges escaped the bastard's spite,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113080">A little sorrow might have served our loss. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113090">Brave Austria, heaven joys to have thee there. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113100" who="A04520_01-cardinal">
          <speaker>Cardinal</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113110">His soul is safe and free from purgatory ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113120">Our holy father hath dispensed his sins,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113130">The blessed saints have heard our orisons,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113140">And all are mediators for his soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113150">And in the right of these most holy wars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113160">His holiness free pardon doth pronounce</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113170">To all that follow you 'gainst English heretics,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113180">Who stand accursed in our mother church. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e113190">Enter Constance alone.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113200" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <speaker>Philip.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113210">To aggravate the measure of our grief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113220">All malcontent comes Constance for her son. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113230">Be brief good madam, for your face imports</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113240">A tragic tale behind that's yet untold. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113250">Her passions stop the organ of her voice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113260">Deep sorrow throbbeth misbefallen events,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113270">Out with it lady, that our act may end</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113280">A full catastrophe of sad laments. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113290" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Constance.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113300">My tongue is tuned to story forth mishap:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113310">When did I breathe to tell a pleasing tale? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113320">Must Constance speak? let tears prevent her talk:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113330">Must I discourse? let Dido sigh and say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113340">She weeps again to hear the wrack of Troy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113350">Two words will serve, and then my tale is done:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113360">Elnor's proud brat hath robbed me of my son. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113370" who="A04520_01-lewis">
          <speaker>Lewis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113380">Have patience madam, this is chance of war:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113390">He may be ransomed, we revenge his wrong. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113400" who="A04520_01-constance">
          <speaker>Const.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e113410">Be it ne'er so soon, I shall not live so long.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113420" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113430">Despair not yet, come Constance, go with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113440">These clouds will fleet, the day will clear again. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e113450">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113460" who="A04520_01-cardinal">
          <speaker>Cardinal</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113470">Now Lewis, thy fortune buds with happy spring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113480">Our holy father's prayers effecteth this. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113490">Arthur is safe, let John alone with him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113500">Thy title next is fair'st to England's crown:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113510">Now stir thy father to begin with John,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113520">The Pope says I, and so is Albion thine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113530" who="A04520_01-lewis">
          <speaker>Lewis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113540">Thanks my lord legate for your good conceit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113550">'Tis best we follow now the game is fair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113560">My father wants to work him your good words. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113570" who="A04520_01-cardinal">
          <speaker>Cardinal</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113580">A few will serve to forward him in this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113590">Those shall not want: but let's about it then. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e113600">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e113610">Enter Philip leading a friar, charging him show where the abbot's gold lay.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113620" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e113630">Come on you fat Franciscan, dally no longer, but show me where the abbot's treasure lies, or die.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113640" who="A04520_01-friar">
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113650">Benedicamus domini, was ever such an injury ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113660">Sweet s. Withold of thy lenity, defend us from extremity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113670">And hear us for s. charity, oppressed with austerity. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113680">In nomini domini, make I my homily,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113690">Gentle gentility grieve not the clergy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113700" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113710">Gray-gowned good face, conjure ye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113720">Ne'er trust me for a groat</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113730">If this waist girdle hang thee not</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113740">That girdeth in thy coat. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113750">Now bald and barefoot Bungie birds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113760">When up the gallows climbing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113770">Say Philip he had words enough,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113780">To put you down with rhyming. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113790" who="A04520_01-france">
          <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113800">O pardon, oh parce, s. Francis for mercy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113810">Shall shield thee from night-spells, and dreaming of devils,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113820">If thou wilt forgive me, and never more grieve me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113830">With fasting and praying, and hail Marry saying,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113840">From black purgatory, a penance right sorry:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113850">Friar Thomas will warm you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113860">It shall never harm you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113870" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113880">Come leave off your rabble,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113890">Sirs, hang up this lozel. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113900" who="A04520_01-friar_2">
          <speaker>2. Fr. </speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113910">For charity I beg his life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113920">Saint Francis chiefest friar,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113930">The best in all our convent sir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113940">To keep a vintner's fire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113950">O strangle not the good old man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113960">My hostess oldest guest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113970">And I will bring you by and by</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e113980">Unto the prior's chest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e113990" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114000">Ay, sayest thou so, and if thou wilt the friar is at liberty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114010">If not, as I am honest man, I hang you both for company. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114020">Fr. come hither, this is the chest, though simple to behold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114030">That wanteth not a thousand pound in silver and in gold. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114040">Myself will warrant full so much, I know the abbot's store,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114050">I'll pawn my life there is no less, to have whate'er is more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114060" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114070">I take thy word, the overplus unto thy share shall come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114080"><pb facs="20"/> but if there want of full so much, thy neck shall pay the sum. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114090">Break up the coffer, friar. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114100" who="A04520_01-friar">
          <speaker>Friar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114110">O I am undone, fair Alice the nun</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114120">Hath taken up her rest in the abbot's chest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114130">Sancte benedicite, pardon my simplicity. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114140">Fie Alice, confession will not salve this transgression. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114150" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114160">What have we here, a holy nun? so keep me God in health. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114170">A smooth faced nun (For aught I know) is all the abbot's wealth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114180">Is this the nunneries chastity? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114190">Beshrew me but I think</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114200">They go as oft to venery as niggards to their drink. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114210">Why paltry friar and Pandar too, ye shameless shaven crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114220">Is this the chest that held a hoard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114230">At least a thousand pound? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114240">And is the hoard a holy whore?</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114250">Well, be the hangman nimble,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114260">He'll take the pain to pay you home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114270">And teach you to dissemble. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114280">Nun oh spare the friar Anthony,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114290">A better never was</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114300">To sing a dirige solemnly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114310">Or read a morning mass. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114320">If money be the means of this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114330">I know an ancient nun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114340">That hath a hoard these seven years,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114350">Did never see the sun;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114360">And that is yours, and what is ours,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114370">So favour now be shown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114380">You shall command as commonly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114390">As if it were your own. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114400" who="A04520_01-friar">
          <speaker>Friar</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e114410">Your honour excepted.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114420" who="A04520_01-nun">
          <speaker>Nun</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e114430">I Thomas, I mean so.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114440" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e114450">From all save from friars.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114460" who="A04520_01-nun">
          <pb facs="20"/>
          <speaker>Nun</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e114470">Good sir, do not think so.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114480" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114490">I think and see so:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114500">Why how cam'st thou here? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114510" who="A04520_01-friar">
          <speaker>Friar</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e114520">To hide her from lay men.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114530" who="A04520_01-nun">
          <speaker>Nun</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e114540">'Tis true sir, for fear.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114550" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114560">For fear of the laity: a pitiful dread</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114570">When a nun flies for succour to a fat friar's bed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114580">But now for your ransom my cloister-bred coney,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114590">To the chest that you speak of where lies so much money. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114600" who="A04520_01-nun">
          <speaker>Nun</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114610">Fair sir, within this press, of plate and money is</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114620">The value of a thousand marks, and other thing by gis. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114630">Let us alone, and take it all, 'tis yours sir, now you know it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114640" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114650">Come on sir friar, pick the lock, this gear doth cotton handsome,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114660">That covetousness so cunningly must pay the lechers ransom. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114670">What is in the hoard? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114680" who="A04520_01-friar">
          <speaker>Friar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114690">Friar Laurence my lord, now holy water help us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114700">Some witch or some devil is sent to delude us:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114710">Haud credo Laurentius, that thou shouldst be penned thus</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114720">In the press of a nun we are all undone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114730">And brought to discredence if thou be friar Laurence,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114740" who="A04520_01-friar">
          <speaker>Friar</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114750">Amor vincit omnia, so Cato affirmeth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114760">And therefore a friar whose fancy soon burneth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114770">Because he is mortal and made of mould,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114780">He omits what he ought, and doth more than he should. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114790" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114800">How goes this gear? the friar's chest filled with</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114810">A fausen nun. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114820">The nun again locks friar up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114830">To keep him from the sun. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114840">Belike the press is purgatory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114850">Or penance passing grievous:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114860">The friar's chest a hell for nuns!</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114870">How do these dolts deceive us? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114880">Is this the labour of their lives, to feed and live at ease? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114890">To revel so lasciviously as often as they please. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114900">I'll mend the fault or fault my aim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114910">If I do miss amending,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114920"><pb facs="21"/> 'tis better burn the cloisters down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114930">Than leave them for offending. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114940">But holy you, to you I speak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114950">To you religious devil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114960">Is this the press that holds the sum,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114970">To quit you for your evil? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e114980" who="A04520_01-nun">
          <speaker>Nun</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e114990">I cry peccavi, parce me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115000">Good sir I was beguiled. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115010" who="A04520_01-france">
          <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115020">Absolve sir for charity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115030">She would be reconciled. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115040" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115050">And so I shall, sirs bind them fast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115060">This is their absolution,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115070">Go hang them up for hurting them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115080">Haste them to execution. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115090" who="A04520_01-laurence">
          <speaker>Fr. Laurence.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115100">O tempus edax rerum,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115110">Give children books they tear them. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115120">O vanitas vanitatis, in this waning aetatis,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115130">At threescore wellnear, to go to this gear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115140">To my conscience a clog, to die like a dog. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115150">Exaudi me dominae, sivis me parce</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115160">Dabo pecuniam, si habeo veniam. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115170">To go and fetch it, I will dispatch it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115180">A hundred pound sterling, for my lives sparing. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e115190">Enter Peter a prophet, with people.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115200" who="A04520_01-peter">
          <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115210">Ho, who is here? S. Francis be your speed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115220">Come in my flock, and follow me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115230">Your fortunes I will read. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115240">Come hither boy, go get thee home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115250">And climb not over high,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115260">For from aloft thy fortune stands, in hazard thou shalt die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115270" who="A04520_01-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e115280">God be with you Peter, I pray you come to our house a Sunday.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115290" who="A04520_01-peter">
          <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115300">My boy show me thy hand, bless thee my boy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115310">For in thy palm I see a many troubles are ybent to dwell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115320">But thou shalt scape them all, and do full well. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115330" who="A04520_01-boy">
          <pb facs="21"/>
          <speaker>Boy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e115340">I thank you Peter, there's a cheese for your labour: my sister prays ye to come home, and tell her how many husbands she shall have, and she'll give you a rib of bacon.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115350" who="A04520_01-peter">
          <speaker>Peter</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e115360">My masters, stay at the town's end for me, I'll come to you all anon: I must dispatch some business with a friar, and then I'll read your fortunes.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115370" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e115380">How now, a prophet! sir prophet whence are ye?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115390" who="A04520_01-peter">
          <speaker>Peter</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e115400">I am of the world and in the world, but live not as others, by the world: what I am I know, and what thou wilt be I know. If thou knowest me now, be answered: if not, inquire no more what I am.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115410" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e115420">Sir, I know you will be a dissembling knave, that deludes the people with blind prophecies: you are he I look for, you shall away with me: bring away all the rabble, and you friar Laurence, remember your ransom a hundred pound, and a pardon for yourself, and the rest; come on sir prophet, you shall with me, to receive a prophet's reward.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e115430">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e115440">Enter Hubert de Burgh with three men.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115450" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e115460">My masters, I have showed you what warrant I have for this attempt; I perceive by your heavy countenances, you had rather be otherwise employed, and for my own part, I would the King had made choice of some other executioner: only this is my comfort, that a King commands, whose precepts neglected or omitted, threatneth torture for the default. Therefore in brief, leave me, and be ready to attend the adventure: stay within that entry, and when you hear me cry, God save the King, issue suddenly forth, lay hands on Arthur, set him in this chair, wherein (Once fast bound) leave him with me to finish the rest.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115470" who="A04520_01-attendant">
          <speaker>Attendant</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e115480">We go, though loath.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e115490">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115500" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e115510">My lord, will it please your honour to take the benefit of the fair evening?</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e115520">Enter Arthur to Hubert de Burgh. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115530" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115540">Gramercy Hubert for thy care of me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115550"><pb facs="22"/> in or to whom restraint is newly known,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115560">The joy of walking is small benefit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115570">Yet will I take thy offer with small thanks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115580">I would not lose the pleasure of the eye. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115590">But tell me courteous keeper if thou can,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115600">How long the King will have me tarry here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115610" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115620">I know not prince, but as I guess, not long. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115630">God send you freedom, and God save the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e115640">They issue forth.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115650" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115660">Why how now sirs, what may this outrage mean? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115670">O help me Hubert, gentle keeper help:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115680">God send this sudden mutinous approach</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115690">Tend not to reave a wretched guiltless life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115700" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e115710">So sirs, depart, and leave the rest for me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115720" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115730">Then Arthur yield, death frowneth in thy face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115740">What meaneth this? good Hubert plead the case. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115750" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115760">Patience young lord, and listen words of woe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115770">Harmful and harsh, hell's horror to be heard:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115780">A dismal tale fit for a furies tongue. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115790">I faint to tell, deep sorrow is the sound. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115800" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e115810">What, must I die?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115820" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115830">No news of death, but tidings of more hate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115840">A wrathful doom, and most unlucky fate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115850">Death's dish were dainty at so fell a feast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115860">Be deaf, hear not, it's hell to tell the rest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115870" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115880">Alas, thou wrongest my youth with words of fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115890">'Tis hell, 'tis horror, not for one to hear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115900">What is it man if it must needs be done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115910">Act it, and end it, that the pain were gone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115920" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115930">I will not chant such dolour with my tongue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115940">Yet must I act the outrage with my hand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115950">My heart, my head, and all my powers beside,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115960">To aid the office have at once denied. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115970">Peruse this letter, lines of treble woe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e115980">Read o'er my charge, and pardon when you know. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e115990" who="A04520_01-missing">
          <pb facs="22"/>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e116000">Hubert, these are to command thee, as thou tenderest our quiet in mind, and the estate of our person, that presently upon the receipt of our command, thou put out the eyes of Arthur Plantagenet. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116010" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116020">Ah monstrous damned man! his very breath infects the elements. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116030">Contagious venom dwelleth in his heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116040">Effecting means to poison all the world. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116050">Unreverent may I be to blame the heavens</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116060">Of great injustice, that the miscreant</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116070">Lives to oppress the innocents with wrong. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116080">Ah Hubert! makes he thee his instrument,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116090">To sound the trump that causeth hell triumph? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116100">Heaven weeps, the saints do shed celestial tears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116110">They fear thy fall, and cite thee with remorse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116120">They knock thy conscience, moving pity there,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116130">Willing to fence thee from the rage of hell:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116140">Hell Hubert, trust me all the plagues of hell</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116150">Hangs on performance of this damned deed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116160">This scale, the warrant of the body's bliss,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116170">Ensureth Satan chieftain of thy soul:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116180">Subscribe not Hubert, give not God's part away. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116190">I speak not only for eyes privilege,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116200">The chief exterior that I would enjoy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116210">But for thy peril, far beyond my pain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116220">Thy sweet soul's loss, more than my eyes vain lack:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116230">A cause internal, and eternal too. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116240">Advise thee Hubert, for the case is hard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116250">To lose salvation for a King's reward. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116260" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116270">My lord, a subject dwelling in the land</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116280">Is tied to execute the King's command. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116290" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116300">Yet God commands whose power reacheth further,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116310">That no command should stand in force to murder. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116320" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116330">But that same essence hath ordained a law,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116340">A death for guilt, to keep the world in awe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116350" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e116360">I plead, not guilty, treasonless and free.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116370" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <pb facs="23"/>
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e116380">But that appeal my lord concerns not me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116390" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e116400">Why thou art he that mayst omit the peril.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116410" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e116420">Ay, if my sovereign would omit his quarrel.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116430" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e116440">His quarrel is unhallowed false and wrong.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116450" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e116460">Then be the blame to whom it doth belong.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116470" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116480">Why that's to thee if thou as they proceed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116490">Conclude their judgement with so vile a deed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116500" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116510">Why then no execution can be lawful,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116520">If judges dooms must be reputed doubtful. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116530" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116540">Yes where in form of law in place and time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116550">The offender is convicted of the crime. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116560" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116570">My lord, my lord, this long expostulation,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116580">Heaps up more grief, than promise of redress;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116590">For this I know, and so resolved I end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116600">That subjects' lives on Kings commands depend. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116610">I must not reason why he is your foe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116620">But do his charge since he commands it so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116630" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116640">Then do thy charge, and charged be thy soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116650">With wrongful persecution done this day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116660">You rolling eyes, whose superficies yet</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116670">I do behold with eyes that nature lent:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116680">Send forth the terror of your movers frown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116690">To wreak my wrong upon the murderers</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116700">That rob me of your fair reflecting view:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116710">Let hell to them (As earth they wish to me)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116720">Be dark and direful guerdon for their guilt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116730">And let the black tormenters of deep Tartary</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116740">Upbraid them with this damned enterprise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116750">Inflicting change of tortures on their souls. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116760">Delay not Hubert, my orisons are ended,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116770">Begin I pray thee, reave me of my sight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116780">But to perform a tragedy indeed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116790">Conclude the period with a mortal stab. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116800">Constance farewell, tormenter come away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116810">Make my dispatch the tyrant's feasting day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116820" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116830">I faint, I fear, my conscience bids desist:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116840">Faint did I say? fear was it that I named:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116850"><pb facs="23"/> my King commands, that warrant sets me free:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116860">But God forbids, and he commandeth Kings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116870">That great commander counterchecks my charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116880">He stays my hand, he maketh soft my heart. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116890">Go cursed tools, your office is exempt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116900">Cheer thee young lord, thou shalt not lose an eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116910">Though I should purchase it with loss of life. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116920">I'll to the King, and say his will is done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116930">And of the langor tell him thou art dead,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116940">Go in with me, for Hubert was not born</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116950">To blind those lamps that nature polished so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e116960" who="A04520_01-arthur">
          <speaker>Arthur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116970">Hubert, if ever Arthur be in state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116980">Look for amends of this received gift,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e116990">I took my eyesight by thy courtesy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117000">Thou lentest them me, I will not be ingrate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117010">But now procrastination may offend</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117020">The issue that thy kindness undertakes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117030">Depart we Hubert to prevent the worst. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e117040">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e117050">Enter K. John, Essex, Salisbury, Pembroke. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e117060" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117070">Now warlike followers, resteth aught undone</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117080">That may impeach us of fond oversight? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117090">The French have felt the temper of our swords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117100">Cold terror keeps possession in their souls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117110">Checking their overdaring arrogance</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117120">For buckling with so great an overmatch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117130">The arch proud titled priest of Italy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117140">That calls himself grand vicar under God,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117150">Is busied now with Trental obsequies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117160">Mass and month's mind, dirge and I know not what,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117170">To ease their souls in painful purgatory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117180">That have miscarried in these bloody wars. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117190">Herded you not lords when first his holiness</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117200">Had tidings of our small account of him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117210">How with a taunt vaunting upon his toes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117220">He urged a reason why the English ass</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117230">Disdained the blessed ordinance of Rome? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117240"><pb facs="24"/>The title (Reverently might I infer)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117250">Became the Kings that erst have born the load,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117260">The slavish weight of that controlling priest:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117270">Who at his pleasure tempered them like wax</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117280">To carry arms on danger of his curse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117290">Banding their souls with warrants of his hand ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117300">I grieve to think how Kings in ages passed</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117310">(Simply devoted to the sea of Rome)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117320">Have run into a thousand acts of shame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117330">But now for confirmation of our state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117340">Sith we have pruned the more than needful branch</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117350">That did oppress the true well-growing stock,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117360">It resteth we throughout our territories</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117370">Be reproclaimed and invested King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e117380" who="A04520_01-pembroke">
          <speaker>Pemb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117390">My liege, that were to busy men with doubts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117400">Once were you crowned, proclaimed, and with applause</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117410">Your city streets have echoed to the ear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117420">God save the King, God save our sovereign John. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117430">Pardon my fear, my censure doth infer</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117440">Your highness not deposed from regal state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117450">Would breed a mutiny in people's minds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117460">What it should mean to have you crowned again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e117470" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117480">Pembroke, perform what I have bid thee do,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117490">Thou knowest not what induceth me to this. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117500">Essex go in, and lordings all be gone</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117510">About this task, I will be crowned anon. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e117520">Enter the bastard.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e117530" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Philip</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117540">What news, how do the abbot's chests? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117550">Are friars fatter than the nuns are fair? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117560">What cheer with churchmen, had they gold or no? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117570">Tell me, how hath thy office took effect? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e117580" who="A04520_01-philip">
          <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117590">My lord, I have performed your highness' charge:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117600">The ease-bred abbots, and the barefoot friars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117610">The monks, the priors, and holy cloistered nuns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117620">Are all in health, and were my lord in wealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117630">Till I had tithed and told their holy hoards. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117640"><pb facs="24"/>I doubt not when your highness sees my prize,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117650">You may proportion all their former pride. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e117660" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117670">Why so, now sorts it Philip as it should:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117680">This small intrusion into abbey trunks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117690">Will make the popelings excommunicate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117700">Curse, ban, and breathe out damned orisons,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117710">As thick as hailstones fore the springs approach:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117720">But yet as harmless and without effect,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117730">As is the echo of a cannon's crack</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117740">Discharged against the battlements of heaven. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117750">But what news else befell there Philip? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e117760" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117770">Strange news my lord: within your territories</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117780">Near Pomfret is a prophet new sprung up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117790">Whose divination volleys wonders forth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117800">To him the commons throng with country gifts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117810">He sets a date unto the beldames death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117820">Prescribes how long the virgin's state shall last,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117830">Distinguisheth the moouing of the heavens,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117840">Gives limits unto holy nuptial rites,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117850">Foretelleth famine, aboundeth plenty forth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117860">Of fate, of fortune, life and death he chats,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117870">With such assurance, scruples put apart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117880">As if he knew the certain dooms of heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117890">Or kept a register of all the destinies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e117900" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117910">Thou tellst me marvels, would thou hadst brought the man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117920">We might have questioned him of things to come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e117930" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117940">My lord, I took a care of had-i-wist,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117950">And brought the prophet with me to the court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117960">He stays my lord but at the presence door:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117970">Pleaseth your highness, I will call him in. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e117980" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e117990">Nay stay awhile, we'll have him here anon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118000">A thing of weight is first to be performed. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e118010">Enter the nobles and crown King John, and then cry God save the King. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118020" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118030">Lordings and friends supporters of our state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118040"><pb facs="25"/> admire not at this unaccustomed course,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118050">Nor in your thoughts blame not this deed of yours. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118060">Once ere this time was I invested King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118070">Your fealty sworn as liegemen to our state:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118080">Once since that time ambitious weeds have sprung</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118090">To stain the beauty of our garden plot:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118100">But heavens in our conduct rooting thence</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118110">The false intruders, breakers of world's peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118120">Have to our joy, made sunshine chase the storm. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118130">After the which, to try your constancy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118140">That now I see is worthy of your names,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118150">We craved once more your helps for to invest us</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118160">Into the right that envy sought to wrack. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118170">Once was I not deposed, your former choice;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118180">Now twice been crowned and applauded King? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118190">Your cheered action to install me so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118200">Infers assured witness of your loves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118210">And binds me over in a kingly care</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118220">To render love with love, rewards of worth</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118230">To balance down requital to the full. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118240">But thanks the while, thanks lordings to you all:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118250">Ask me and use me, try me and find me yours. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118260" who="A04520_01-essex">
          <speaker>Essex</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118270">A boon my lord, at vantage of your words</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118280">We ask to guerdon all our loyalties. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118290" who="A04520_01-pembroke">
          <speaker>Pemb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118300">We take the time your highness bids us ask:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118310">Please it you grant, you make your promise good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118320">With lesser loss than one superfluous hair</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118330">That not remembered falleth from your head. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118340" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118350">My word is past, receive your boon my lords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118360">What may it be? Ask it, and it is yours. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118370" who="A04520_01-essex">
          <speaker>Ess.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118380">We crave my lord, to please the commons with</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118390">The liberty of lady Constance son:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118400">Whose durance darkeneth your highness' right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118410">As if you kept him prisoner, to the end</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118420">Yourself were doubtful of the thing you have. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118430">Dismiss him thence, your highness needs not fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118440">Twice by consent you are proclaimed our King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118450" who="A04520_01-pembroke">
          <pb facs="25"/>
          <speaker>Pemb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118460">This if you grant, were all unto your good:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118470">For simple people muse you keep him close. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118480" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118490">Your words have searched the centre of my thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118500">Confirming warrant of your loyalties,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118510">Dismiss your counsel, sway my state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118520">Let John do nothing, but by your consents. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118530">Why how now Philip, what ecstasy is this? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118540">Why casts thou up thy eyes to heaven so? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e118550">There the five moons appear.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118560" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118570">See, see my lord, strange apparitions,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118580">Glancing mine eye to see the diadem</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118590">Placed by the Bishops on your highness' head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118600">From forth a gloomy cloud, which curtain-like</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118610">Displayed itself, I suddenly espied</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118620">Five moons reflecting, as you see them now:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118630">Even in the moment that the crown was placed</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118640">Can they appear, holding the course you see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118650" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118660">What might portend these apparitions,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118670">Unusual signs, forerunners of event,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118680">Presages of strange terrors to the world:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118690">Believe me lords, the object fears me much. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118700">Philip thou toldst me of a wizard but of late,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118710">Fetch in the man to descant of this show. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118720" who="A04520_01-pembroke">
          <speaker>Pemb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118730">The heaven's frown upon the sinful earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118740">When with prodigious unaccustomed signs</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118750">They spot their superficies with such wonder. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118760" who="A04520_01-essex">
          <speaker>Essex.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118770">Before the ruins of Jerusalem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118780">Such meteors were the ensigns of his wrath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118790">That hastened to destroy the faultful town. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e118800">Enter the bastard with the prophet.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118810" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e118820">Is this the man?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118830" who="A04520_01-bastard">
          <speaker>Bastard</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e118840">It is my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118850" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118860">Prophet of Pomfret, for so I hear thou art,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118870"><pb facs="26"/> that calculatest of many things to come:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118880">Who by a power replete with heavenly gift,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118890">Canst blab the counsel of thy maker's will. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118900">If fame be true, or truth be wronged by thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118910">Decide in cyphering, what these five moons</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118920">Portend this clime, if they presage at all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118930">Breath out thy gift, and if I live to see</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118940">Thy divination take a true effect,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118950">I'll honour thee above all earthly men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e118960" who="A04520_01-peter">
          <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118970">The sky wherein these moons have residence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118980">Presenteth Rome the great metropolis,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e118990">Where sits the Pope in all his holy pomp. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119000">Four of the moons present four provinces,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119010">To wit, Spain, Denmark, Germany, and France,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119020">That bear the yoke of proud commanding Rome,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119030">And stand in fear to tempt the prelates curse. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119040">The smallest moon that whirls about the rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119050">Impatient of the place he holds with them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119060">Doth figure forth this island Albion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119070">Who begins to scorn the sea and seat of Rome,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119080">And seeks to shun the edicts of the Pope:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119090">This shows the heaven, and this I do aver</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119100">Is figured in the apparitions. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119110" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119120">Why then it seems the heaven's smile on us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119130">Giving applause for leaving of the Pope. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119140">But for they chance in our meridian,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119150">Do they effect no private growing ill</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119160">To be inflicted on us in this clime? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119170" who="A04520_01-peter">
          <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119180">The moons effect no more than what I said:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119190">But on some other knowledge that I have</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119200">By my prescience, ere ascension day</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119210">Have brought the sun unto his usual height,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119220">Of crown, estate, and royal dignity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119230">Thou shalt be clean despoiled and dispossessed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119240" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119250">False dreamer, perish with thy witched news,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119260">Villain thou woundst me with thy fallacies:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119270">If it be true, die for thy tidings price;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119280"><pb facs="26"/> if false, for fearing me with vain suppose:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119290">Hence with the witch, hell's damned secretary. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119300">Lock him up sure: for by my faith I swear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119310">True or not true, the wizard shall not live. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119320">Before ascension day: who should be cause hereof? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119330">Cut off the cause, and then the effect will die. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119340">Tut, tut, my mercy serves to maim myself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119350">The root doth live, from whence these thorns spring up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119360">I and my promise passed for his delivery:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119370">Frown friends, fail faith, the devil go withal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119380">The brat shall die, that terrifies me thus. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119390">Pembroke and Essex, I recall my grant,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119400">I will not buy your favours with my fear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119410">Nay murmur not, my will is law enough ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119420">I love you well, but if I loved you better,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119430">I would not buy it with my discontent. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e119440">Enter Hubert. </stage>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119450">How now, what news with thee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119460" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119470">According to your highness strict command,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119480">Young Arthur's eyes are blinded and extinct. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119490" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e119500">Why so, than he may feel the crown, but never see it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119510" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119520">Nor see nor feel, for of the extreme pain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119530">Within one hour gave he up the ghost. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119540" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e119550">What is he dead?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119560" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e119570">He is my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119580" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e119590">Then with him dies my cares.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119600" who="A04520_01-essex">
          <speaker>Essex.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e119610">Now joy betide thy soul.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119620" who="A04520_01-pembroke">
          <speaker>Pemb.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04520_01-e119630">And heaven's revenge thy death.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119640" who="A04520_01-essex">
          <speaker>Essex.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119650">What have you done my lord? Was ever heard</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119660">A deed of more inhumane consequence? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119670">Your foes will curse, your friends will cry revenge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119680">Unkindly rage, more rough than Northern wind;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119690">To clip the beauty of so sweet a flower. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119700">What hope in us for mercy on a fault,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119710">When kinsman dies without impeach of cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119720">As you have done, so come to cheer you with,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119730">The guilt shall never be cast me in my teeth. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e119740">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e119750" who="A04520_01-john">
          <pb facs="27"/>
          <speaker>Joh.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119760">And are you gone? The devil be your guide:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119770">Proud rebels as ye are, to brave me so:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119780">Saucy, uncivil, chequers of my will. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119790">Your tongues give edge unto the fatal knife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119800">That shall have passage through your traitorous throats. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119810">But husht, breath not bugs words too soon abroad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119820">Lest time prevent the issue of thy reach. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119830">Arthur is dead, I there the corzie grows:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119840">But while he lived, the danger was the more;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119850">His death hath freed me from a thousand fears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119860">But it hath purchased me ten times ten thousand foes. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119870">Why all is one, such luck shall haunt his game,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119880">To whom the devil owes an open shame:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119890">His life a foe that levelled at my crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119900">His death a frame to pull my building down. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119910">My thoughts harped still on quiet by his end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119920">Who living aimed shrewdly at my room:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119930">But to prevent that plea, twice was I crowned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119940">Twice did my subjects swear me fealty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119950">And in my conscience loved me as their liege,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119960">In whose defence they would have pawned their lives. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119970">But now they shun me as a serpent's sting,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119980">A tragic tyrant, stern and pitiless,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e119990">And not a title follows after John,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120000">But butcher, bloodsucker, and murderer. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120010">What planet governed my nativity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120020">To bode me sovereign types of high estate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120030">So interlaced with hellish discontent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120040">Wherein fell fury hath no interest? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120050">Cursed be the crown, chief author of my care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120060">Nay cursed my will, that made the crown my care:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120070">Cursed be my birthday, cursed ten times the womb</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120080">That yielded me alive into the world. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120090">Art thou there villain, furies haunt thee still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120100">For killing him whom all the world laments. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e120110" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120120">Why here's my lord your highness' hand and seal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120130"><pb facs="27"/> charging on life's regard to do the deed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e120140" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120150">Ah dull conceited peasant, knowest thou not</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120160">It was a damned execrable deed? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120170">Showst me a seal? O villain, both our souls</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120180">Have sold their freedom to the thrall of hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120190">Under the warrant of that cursed seal. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120200">Hence villain, hang thyself, and say in hell</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120210">That I am coming for a kingdom there. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e120220" who="A04520_01-hubert">
          <speaker>Hubert</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120230">My lord, attend the happy tale I tell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120240">For heaven's health send Sathan packing hence</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120250">That instigates your highness to despair. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120260">If Arthur's death be dismal to be heard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120270">Bandy the news for rumours of untruth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120280">He lives my lord, the sweetest youth alive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120290">In health, with eye sight, not a hair amiss. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120300">This heart took vigour from this forward hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120310">Making it weak to execute your charge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04520_01-e120320" who="A04520_01-john">
          <speaker>John</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120330">What, lives he! Then sweet hope come home again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120340">Chase hence despair, the purveyor for hell. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120350">Hie Hubert, tell these tidings to my lords</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120360">That throb in passions for young Arthur's death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120370">Hence Hubert, stay not till thou hast revealed</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120380">The wished news of Arthur's happy health. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120390">I go myself, the joyfull'st man alive</l>
          <l xml:id="A04520_01-e120400">To story out this new supposed crime. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04520_01-e120410">Exeunt.</stage>
        <trailer xml:id="A04520_01-e120420">The end of the first part.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A04520_01"><item xml:id="A04520_01-john" n="78">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-john</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">78</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-philip" n="61">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-philip</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">61</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-arthur" n="25">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-arthur</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">25</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-elianor" n="24">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-elianor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">24</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-hubert" n="21">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-hubert</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">21</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-bastard" n="19">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-bastard</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">19</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-constance" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-constance</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-robert" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-robert</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-mother" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-mother</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-essex" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-essex</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-lewis" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-lewis</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-citizen" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-citizen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-cardinal" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-cardinal</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-chattilion" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-chattilion</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-limoges" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-limoges</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-peter" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-peter</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-friar" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-friar</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-blanche" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-blanche</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-nun" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-nun</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-pembroke" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-pembroke</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-france" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-france</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-boy" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-boy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-french_herald" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-french_herald</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-eng_herald" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-eng_herald</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-sals" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-sals</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-citizens" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-citizens</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-shrive" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-shrive</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-friar_2" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-friar_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-laurence" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-laurence</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-missing" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-missing</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-attendant" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-attendant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-messenger" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-herolds" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-herolds</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04520_01-multiple" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A04520_01-multiple</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

