<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><date type="creation_date">1581</date></title>
        <author></author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Madeline Burg</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A11909_00.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh.</title>
            <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>225 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2007 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99852323</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 22221.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, III, p. 1105-6.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">17639</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11909</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Seneca his tenne tragedies, translated into Englysh.</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedies. English</title>
            <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D.</author>
            <author>Heywood, Jasper, 1535-1598,</author>
            <author>Neville, Alexander, 1544-1614,</author>
            <author>Studley, John, 1545?-1590?,</author>
            <author>T. N. d. 1617,</author>
            <author>Newton, Thomas, 1542?-1607.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[4], 65, 64-217, [1] leaves.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>In Fleetstreete neere vnto Saincte Dunstans church by Thomas Marsh,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1581.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Editor's dedication signed: Thomas Newton.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>A reprinting of the following translations previously published separately: "Hercules furens", "Thyestes", and "Troas" by Jasper Heywood; "¦edipus" by Alexander Neville (a revised version); "Medea" and "Agamemnon" by John Studley; and "Octavia" (not by Seneca) by Thomas Nuce. Prints for the first time "Hippolytus" and "Hercules Oetæus" translated by Studley, and "Thebais" translated by Thomas Newton.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A11909_00-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A11909_00-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A11909_00-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A11909_00-e100040">Seneca his ten tragedies, translated into English.</p>
        <p xml:id="A11909_00-e100050">Mercurij nutrices, horae.</p>
        <p xml:id="A11909_00-e100060">Imprinted at London in Fleetstreet near unto saint Dunstan's church by Thomas marsh. 1581</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A11909_00-e100070">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To the right Worshipful, sir Thomas Henneage knight, treasurer of her majesty's chamber: Thomas Newton wisheth all abundance of felicity, and spiritual benedictions in Christ. ⁂</head>
        <p xml:id="A11909_00-e100080">You may think sir, some want of discretion in me, for thus boldly presuming to thrust into your hands these tragedies of Seneca. From which boldness, the very conscience of mine own unworthiness, might easily have dissuaded me, had not certain learned gentlemen of good credit and worship thereunto persuaded and animated me. Assuring me (Where of I thought myself afore assured) that your worship (Such is your love to learning, and the generosity of your heroical mind) would deign not only to dispense with my temerity, but also take in worth my affectionate simplicity. And yet (All this notwithstanding) well dared I not have given the adventure to approach your presence, upon trust of any singularity, that in this book hath unskilfully dropped out of mine own pen, but that I hoped the perfection of others artificial workmanship, that have travailed herein as well as myself should somewhat cover my nakednèsse 〈◊〉 pùrchase my pardon. And hard were<pb facs="3"/> the dealing, if in payment of a good round gub of gold of full weight and poise, one poor piece somewhat clipped and lighter than his fellows may not be foisted in among the rest, and pass in pay for currant coin. Theirs I know to be delivered with singular dexterity: mine, I confess to be an unfledge nestling, unable to fly: an unnatural abortion, and an unperfect Embryon: neither thoroughly laboured at Aristophanes and Cleanthes candle, neither yet exactly weighed in Critolaus his precise balance. Yet this dare I say, I have delivered mine author's meaning with as much perspicuity, as so mean a scholar, out of so mean a store, in so small a time, and upon so short a warning was well able to perform. And whereas it is by some squeamish Areopagites surmised, that the reading of these tragedies, being interlarded with many phrases and sentences, literally tending (At the first sight) some time to the praise of ambition, sometime to the maintenance of cruelty, now and then to the approbation of incontinency, and here and there to the ratification of tyranny, can not be digested without great danger of infection: to omit all other reasons, if it might please them with no forestalled judgement, to mark and consider the circumstances, why, where, and by what manner of persons such sentences are pronounced, they cannot in any equity otherwise choose, but find good cause enough to lead them to a more favourable and mild resolution. For it may not at any hand be thought and deemed the direct meaning of Sèneca himself, whose whole writings (Penned with a peerless sublimity and loftiness of style, are so far from countenancing vice, that I doubt whether there be any among all the catalogue of heathen writers, that with more gravity<pb facs="3"/> of philosophical sentences, more weightiness of sappy words, or greater authority of sound matter beateth down sin, loose life, dissolute dealing, and unbridled sensuality: or that more sensibly, pithily, and bitingly layeth down the guerdon of filthy lust, cloaked dissimulation and odious treachery: which is the drift, whereunto he leveleth the whole issue of each one of his tragedies. Howsoever and whatsoever it be, your worship's courteous acceptance shall easily counterpoise any of our imperfections. Unto whose learned censure, we humbly submit these the exercises of our blushing muses. The lord God in mercy long preserve you in health and dignity with daily increase of many his gracious gifts, already richly abounding in you: to the propagation, and advancement of his truth (Whereof ye are a zealous professor, to the honour of her majesty, to whom you are a most loyal servitor, and to the general benefit of your country, whereof you are a rare and most worthy ornament.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A11909_00-e100090">
          <dateline xml:id="A11909_00-e100100">from Butley in Cheshire<date xml:id="A11909_00-e100110">the 24. of April. 1581.</date></dateline>
          <signed xml:id="A11909_00-e100120">Your worship's most humble, Thomas Newton.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="table_of_contents" xml:id="A11909_00-e100130">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <head>The names of the tragedies of Seneca, and by whom each of them was translated.</head>
        <list xml:id="A11909_00-e100140">
          <item xml:id="A11909_00-e100150">1 Hercules furens,</item>
          <item xml:id="A11909_00-e100160">2 Thyestes,</item>
          <item xml:id="A11909_00-e100170">6 Troas,<list xml:id="A11909_00-e100180"><item xml:id="A11909_00-e100190">By Jasper Heywood.</item><item xml:id="A11909_00-e100200">1560.</item></list></item>
          <item xml:id="A11909_00-e100210">5 Oedipus,<list xml:id="A11909_00-e100220"><item xml:id="A11909_00-e100230">By Alex Nevil.</item></list></item>
          <item xml:id="A11909_00-e100240">4 Hippolytus,</item>
          <item xml:id="A11909_00-e100250">7 Medea,</item>
          <item xml:id="A11909_00-e100260">8 Agamemnon,</item>
          <item xml:id="A11909_00-e100270">10 Hercules Octaeus<list xml:id="A11909_00-e100280"><item xml:id="A11909_00-e100290">By John Studley.</item></list></item>
          <item xml:id="A11909_00-e100300">9 Octavia,<list xml:id="A11909_00-e100310"><item xml:id="A11909_00-e100320">By T. Nuce.</item></list></item>
          <item xml:id="A11909_00-e100330">3 Thebais. <list xml:id="A11909_00-e100340"><item xml:id="A11909_00-e100350">By Thomas Newton.</item></list></item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

