<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><date type="creation_date">1662</date></title>
        <author>Cavendish, Margaret</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Hannah Bredar</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A53060_00.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>356 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">11861873</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing N868.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">50022</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53060</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
            <author>Newcastle, William Cavendish, 1592-1676.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[24], 679 [i.e. 675], [4] p. : ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by A. Warren, for John Martyn, James Allestry, and Tho. Dicas ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1662.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>First edition.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Errata: p. [4] at end.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A53060_00-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A53060_00-e100020">
      <div type="frontispiece" xml:id="A53060_00-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100040">
          <figure xml:id="A53060_00-e100050">
            <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100060">Here on this figure cast a glance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100070">But so as if it were by chance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100080">Your eyes not fixed, they must not stay. </l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100090">Since this like shadows to the day</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100100">It only represents; for still,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100110">Her beauty's found beyond the skill</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100120">Of the best painter, to embrace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100130">Those lovely lines within her fure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100140">View her soul's picture, judgement, will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100150">Then read those lines which she hath written,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100160">By fancy's pencil drawn alone</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100170">Which piece but she. Can justify own. </l>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A53060_00-e100180">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100190">Plays Written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent Princess, the lady marchioness of Newcastle.</p>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100200">
          <figure xml:id="A53060_00-e100210"/>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100220">London, printed by A. Warren, for John Martin, James Allestry, and Tho. Dicas, at the bell in saint Paul's church yard, 1662.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A53060_00-e100230">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>The dedication.</head>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100240">To those that do delight in scenes and wit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100250">I dedicate my book, for those I writ;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100260">Next to my own delight, for I did take</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100270">Much pleasure and delight these plays to make;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100280">For all the time my plays a making were,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100290">My brain the stage, my thoughts were acting there. </l>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A53060_00-e100300">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>The epistle dedicatory.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A53060_00-e100310">
          <salute xml:id="A53060_00-e100320">My lord,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100330">My resolution was, that when I had done writing, to have dedicated all my works in gross to your lordship; and I did verily believe that this would have been my last work: but I find it will not, unless I die before I have writ my other intended piece. And as for this book of plays, I believe I should never have writ them, nor have had the capacity nor ingenuity to have writ plays, had not you read to me some plays which your lordship had writ, and lie by for a good time to be acted, wherein your wit did create a desire in my mind to write plays also, although my plays are very unlike those you have writ, for your lordship's plays have as it were a natural life, and a quick spirit in them, whereas mine are like dull dead statues, which is the reason I send them forth to be printed, rather than keep them concealed in hopes to have them first acted; and this advantage I have, that is, I am out of the fear of having them hissed off from the stage, for they are not like to come thereon; but were they such as might deserve applause, yet if envy did make a faction against them, they would have had a public condemnation; and though I am not such a coward, as to be afraid of the hissing serpents, or<pb facs="4"/> stinged tongues of envy, yet it would have made me a little melancholy to have my harmless and innocent plays go weeping from the stage, and whipped by malicious and hard-hearted censurers; but the truth is, I am careless, for so I have your applause I desire no more, for your lordship's approvement is a sufficient satisfaction to me</p>
        <closer xml:id="A53060_00-e100340">
          <salute xml:id="A53060_00-e100350">My lord,</salute>
          <signed xml:id="A53060_00-e100360">Your lordship's honest wife, and faithful servant, m. N. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A53060_00-e100370">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <head>To the readers.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A53060_00-e100380">
          <salute xml:id="A53060_00-e100390">Noble readers,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100400">I must ask pardon, for that I said I should not trouble you with more of my works than this book of plays; but since I have considered with myself, there is one work more, which is very fit for me to do, although I shall not be able to do it so well as the subject will deserve, being the life of my noble lord; but that work will require some time in the gathering together some several passages; for although I mean not to write of all the particulars of these times, yet for as much as is concerning that subject I shall write of, it will be requirable; but it is a work that will move so slowly, as perchance I shall not live to finish it; but howsoever, I will employ my time about it, and it will be a satisfaction to my life that I endeavour it.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A53060_00-e100410">
          <signed xml:id="A53060_00-e100420">M. N.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A53060_00-e100430">
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <head>To the readers.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A53060_00-e100440">
          <salute xml:id="A53060_00-e100450">Noble readers,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100460">The reason why I put out my plays in print, before they are acted, is, first, that I know not when they will be acted, by reason they are in English, and England doth not permit, I will not say, of wit, yet not of plays; and if they should, yet by reason all those that have been bred and brought up to act, are dead, or dispersed, and it would be an act of some time, not only to breed and teach some youths to act, but it will require some time to prove whether they be good actors or no; for if they are not bred to it whilst they be young, they will never be good actors when they are grown up to be men; for although some one by chance may have naturally, a facility to action, and a volubility of speech, and a good memory to learn, and get the parts by heart, or wrote, yet it is very unlikely, or indeed impossible, to get a whole company of good actors without being taught and brought up thereto; the other reason is, that most of my plays would seem tedious upon the stage, by reason they are somewhat long, although most are divided into first and second parts; for having much variety in them, I could not possibly make them shorter, and being long, it might tire the spectators, who are forced, or bound by the rules of civility to sit out a play, if they be not sick; for to go away before a play is ended, is a kind of an assront, both to the poet and the players; yet, I believe none of my plays are so long as ben Johnson's fox, or alchemist, which in truth, are somewhat too long; but for the readers, the length of the plays can be no trouble, nor inconveniency, because they may read as short or as long a time as they please, without any disrespect to the writer; but some of my plays are short enough; but the printing of my plays spoils them for ever to be acted; for what men are acquainted with, is despised, at lest neglected; for the newness of plays, most commonly, takes the spectators, more than the wit, scenes, or plot, so that my plays would seem lame or tired in action, and dull to hearing on the stage, for which reason, I shall never desire they should be acted; but if they delight or please the readers, I shall have as much satisfaction as if I had the hands of applause from the spectators.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A53060_00-e100470">
          <signed xml:id="A53060_00-e100480">M. N.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A53060_00-e100490">
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <head>To the readers.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A53060_00-e100500">
          <salute xml:id="A53060_00-e100510">Noble readers,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100520">Although I expect my plays will be found fault with, by reason I have not drawn the several persons presented in a circular line, or to a triangular point, making all the actors to meet at the latter end upon the stage in a flock together; likewise, that I have not made my comedies of one day's actions or passages; yet I have adventured to publish them to the world: but to plead in my plays behalf, first, I do not perceive any reason why that the several persons presented should be all of an acquaintance, or that there is a necessity to have them of one fraternity, or to have a relation to each other, or linked in alliance as one family; whenas plays are to present the general follies, vanities, vices, humours, dispositions, passions, affections, fashions, customs, manners, and practises of the whole world of mankind, as in several persons; also particular follies, vanities, vices, humours, passions, affections, fashions, customs, fortunes, and the like, in particular persons; also the sympathy and antipathy of dispositions, humours, passions, customs, and fashions of several persons; also the particular virtues and graces in several persons, and several virtues and graces in particular persons, and all these varieties to be drawn at the latter end into one piece, as into one company, which in my opinion shows neither usual, probable, nor natural. For since the world is wide and populated, and their various actions dispersed, and spread about by each particular, and plays are to present them severally, I perceive no reason they should force them together in the last act, as in one community, bringing them in as I may say by head and shoulders, making the persons of each humour, good fortunes, misfortunes, nations and ages, to have relations to each other; but in this I have not followed the steps of precedent poets, for in my opinion, I think it as well, if not better, if a play ends but with two persons, or one person upon the stage; besides, I would have my plays to be like the natural course of all things in the world, as some die sooner, some live longer, and some are newly born, when some are newly dead, and not all to continue to the last day of judgement; so my scenes, some last longer than othersome, and some are ended when others are begun; likewise some of my scenes have no acquaintance or relation to the rest of the scenes, although in one and the same play, which is the reason many of my plays will not end as other plays do, especially comedies, for in tragi-comedies I think poets do not always make all lie bleeding together; but I think for the most part they do; but the want of this swarm in the last act and scene, may make my plays seem dull and vacant, but I love ease so well, as I hate constraint even in my works; for I had rather have a dull easy life, than be forced to active gaieties, so I had rather my plays should end dully than unnecessarily be forced into one company, but some of my plays are gathered into one sheaf or bundle in the latter end. Likewise my plays<pb facs="6"/> may be condemned, because they follow not the ancient custom, as the learned says, which is, that all comedies should be so ordered and composed, as nothing should be presented therein, but what may be naturally, or usually practised or acted in the world in the compass of one day; truly in my opinion those comedies would be very flat and dull, and neither profitable nor pleasant, that should only present the actions of one day; for though Ben Johnson as I have heard was of that opinion, that a comedy cannot be good, nor is a natural or true comedy, if it should present more than one day's action, yet his comedies that he hath published, could never be the actions of one day; for could any rational person think that the whole play of the fox could be the action of one day? or can any rational person think that the alchemist could be the action of one day? as that so many several cozenings could be acted in one day, by captain face and Doll common; and could the alchemist make any believe they could make gold in one day? could they burn so many coals, and draw the purses of so many, or so often from one person, in one day? and the like is in all his plays, not any of them presents the actions of one day, although it were a day at the poles, but of many days, nay I may say some years. But to my reason, I do not perceive a necessity that comedies should be so closely packed or thrust up together; for if comedies are either to delight, or to profit, or to both, they must follow no other rule or example, but to put them into scenes and acts, and to order their several discources in a comedy, so as physicians do their cordials, wherein they mix many several ingrediences together into one electuary, as sharp, bitter, salt, and sweet, and mix them so, as they are both pleasing to the taste, and comfortable to the stomach; so poets should order the several humours, passions, customs, manners, fashions, and practice of mankind, as to intermix them so, as to be both delightful to the mind and senses, and profitable to the life; also poets should do as physicians or apothecaries, which put not only several sorts, but several kinds of drugs into one medicine, as minerals and vegetables together, which are very different; also they will mix several drugs and simples out of several climates and countries, gathered out from all the parts of the world, and upon occasion they will mix new and old simples together, although of one and the same sort and kind; so poets both in their comedies and tragedies, must, or at leastwise may, represent several nations, governments, people, customs, fashions, manners, natures, fortunes, accidents, actions, in one play; as also several times of ages to one person if occasion requires, as from childhood to manhood in one play; for poets are to describe in plays the several ages, times, actions, fortunes, accidents and humours in nature, and the several customs, manners, fashions and speeches of men: thus plays are to present the natural dispositions and practises of mankind; also they are to point at vanity, laugh at follies, disgrace baseness, and persecute vice; likewise they are to extol virtue, and to honour merit, and to praise the graces, all which makes a poet divine, their works edifying to the mind or soul, profitable to the life, delightful to the senses, and recreative to time; but poets are like preachers, some are more learned than others, and some are better orators than others, yet from the worst there may be some good gained by them, and I do not despair, although but a poetress, but that my works may be some ways or other serviceable to my readers, which if they be, my time in writing them is not lost, nor my muse unprofitable.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A53060_00-e100530">
          <signed xml:id="A53060_00-e100540">M. N.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A53060_00-e100550">
        <pb facs="6"/>
        <head>To the readers.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A53060_00-e100560">
          <salute xml:id="A53060_00-e100570">Noble readers,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100580">I cannot choose but mention an erroneous opinion got into this our modern time and men, which is, that it should be thought a crime or debasement for the nobler sort to act plays, especially on public theatres, although the Romans were of another opinion, for not only the noble youth did act in public, but some of the emperors themselves; though I do not commend it in the emperors, who should spend their times in realities, and not in feigning; yet certainly it was commendable in the noblest youths, who did practise what ought to be followed or skinned: for certainly there is no place, ways or means, so edifying to youth as public theatres, not only to be spectators but actors; for it learns them graceful behaviours and demeanours, it puts spirit and life into them, it teaches them wit, and makes their speech both voluble and tanable, besides, it gives them confidence, all which ought every man to have, that is of quality. But some will say if it would work such effects, why are not mercenary players benefited so thereby? I answer, that they only act for the lucre of gain, and not for the grace of behaviour, the sweetness of speech, nor the increasing of wit, so as they only act as parrots speak, by wrote, and not as learning gives to education; for they making not a benefit of the wit, but only by the wit receive it; not neither into their consideration, understanding, nor delight, for they make it a work of labour, and not of delight, or pleasure, or honour; for they receive it into the memory, and no farther than for to deliver it out, as servants or factors to sell, and not keep it as purchasers to their own use; that if the reason that as soon as the play is done, their wit and becoming graces are at an end, whereas the nobler sort, that act not for mercenary profit, but for honour, and becoming, would not only strive to act well upon the stage, but to practise their actions when off from the stage; besides, it would keep the youths from misemploying time with their foolish extravagancies, deboist luxuries, and base vices, all which idleness and vacant time produceth; and in my opinion, a public theatre were a shorter way of education than their tedious and expensive travels, or their dull and solitary studies; for poets teach them more in one play, both of the nature of the world and mankind, by which they learn not only to know other men, but their splits, than they can learn in any school, or in any country or kingdom in a year; but to conclude, a poet is the best tutor, and a theatre is the best school that is for youth to be educated by or in.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A53060_00-e100590">
          <signed xml:id="A53060_00-e100600">M. N.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A53060_00-e100610">
        <pb facs="7"/>
        <head>To the readers.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A53060_00-e100620">
          <salute xml:id="A53060_00-e100630">Noble readers,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100640">I know there are many scholastical and pedantical persons that will condemn my writings, because I do not keep strictly to the masculine and feminine genders, as they call them as for example, a lock and a key, the one is the masculine gender, the other the feminine gender, so love is the masculine gender, hate the feminine gender, and the furies are she's, and the graces are she's, the virtues are she's, and the seven deadly sins are she's, which I am sorry for; but I know no reason but that I may as well make them he's for my use, as others did she's, or she's as others did he's. But some will say, if I did do so, there would be no forms or rules of speech to be understood by; I answer, that we may as well understand the meaning or sense of a speaker or writer by the names of love or hate, as by the names of he or she, and better: for the division of masculine and feminine genders doth confound a scholar more, and takes up more time to learn them, than they have time to spend; besides, where one doth rightly understand the difference, a hundred, nay a thousand do not, and yet they are understood, and to be understood is the end of all speakers and writers; so that if my writings be understood, I desire no more; and as for the niceties of rules, forms, and terms, I renounce, and profess, that if I did understand and know them strictly, as I do not, I would not follow them: and if any dislike my writings for want of those rules, forms, and terms, let them not read them, for I had rather my writings should be unread than be read by such pedantical sholastical persons.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A53060_00-e100650">
          <signed xml:id="A53060_00-e100660">M. N.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A53060_00-e100670">
        <pb facs="7"/>
        <head>To the readers.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A53060_00-e100680">
          <salute xml:id="A53060_00-e100690">Noble readers.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100700">'Tis likely you will condemn my plays at being dull and flat, by reason they have not the high seasoning of poetical salt; but sugar is more commonly used amongst our sex than salt. But I fear my wit is tasteless, which I am sorry for; for though a satirical speaker is discommendable, being for the most part abusive; for bitter reproofs only are fit for rigid pedants, censuring and backbiting sit for pot companions, and sharp replies is a wit for mean persons, being in a degree of scolding; a raillery wit, for bussions and jesters which abuse under the veil of mirth, familiarity, and freedom; whereas a generous discoursitive wit, although it be free, yet it is sweet and pleasing: thus as I said satirical speakers are discommendable, yet satirical writers are highly to be praised, as most profitable, because those reprove only the generality, as the general vices, follies, and errors of mankind, pointing at no particular; and the sharpest writers are most commonly the sweetest speakers. But I have observed one general folly amongst many which is, that it is expected by most readers that the writers should speak as they write, which would be very ridiculous; as for example, a lyric poet should speak nothing but sonnets, a comedian or tragedian poet should speak nothing but set speeches, or blank verse, or such speeches which are only prover to present such and such humours, which in ordinary discourse would be improper; and though Virgil whose greatest praise is language, yet I do verily believe he did not speak in his ordinary conversation in such a style, forms and speeches, nor in such high, fine, and choice Latin, nor in such high and lofty expressions, nor apt similitudes, nor the sense of his discourse wrapped in such metaphors, as in his writings; nay eloquent speakers or orators do not always speak orations, but upon an occasion, and at set times, but their ordinary conversation is with ordinary discourses; for I do verily believe, the greatest and most eloquents orators that ever were in the world, in their ordinary conversation, conversed and spoke but as other men. Besides, in common and ordinary conversations, the most wittiest, learnedst, and eloquentest men, are forced to speak according to the wit, learning, language, and capacities of those they are in company and conversation with, unless they will speak all themselves, which will be no conversation: for in conversation every particular person must have his turn and time of speaking as well as hearing; yet such is the folly of the world, as to despise the authors of witty, learned and eloquent writings, if their conversations be as other men's, and yet would laugh at them, or account them mad, if they should speak otherwise, as out of this ordinary way; but the greatest talkers are not the best writers, which is the cause women cannot be good writers; for we for fear of being thought fools, make ourselves fools, in striving to express some wit, whereas if we had but that power over ourselves as to keep<pb facs="8"/> silence, we perchance might be thought wits, although we were fools, but to keep silence is impossible for us to do, so long as we have speech we shall talk, although to no purpose, for nothing but death can force us to silence, for we often talk in our sleep; but to speak without partiality, I do not perceive that men are free from this imperfection, nor from condemning us, although they are guilty of the same fault; but we have this advantage of men, which is, that we know this imperfection in ourselves, although we do not endeavour to mend it; but men are so partial to themselves, as not to perceive this imperfection in themselves, and so they cannot mend it; but in this, will not or cannot is as one; but this discourse hath brought me to this, that if I have spoke at any time to any person or persons impertinently, improperly, untimely, or tediously, I ask their pardon: but lest I should be impertinently tedious in this epistle, and so commit a fault in asking pardon, I leave my readers to what may be more pleasing to them.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A53060_00-e100710">
          <signed xml:id="A53060_00-e100720">M. N.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A53060_00-e100730">
        <pb facs="8"/>
        <head>To the readers.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A53060_00-e100740">
          <salute xml:id="A53060_00-e100750">Noble readers,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100760">I make no question but my plays will be censured, and those censurors severe, but I hope not malicious; but they will perchance say that my plays are too serious, by reason there is no ridiculous jest in them, nor wanton love, nor impossibilities; also 'tis likely they will say that there are no plots, nor designs, nor subtle contrivances, and the like; I answer, that the chief plots of my plays were to employ my idle time, the designs to please and entertain my readers, and the contrivance was to join edifying profit and delight together, that my readers may neither lose their time, nor grow weary in the reading; but if they find my plays neither edifying, nor delightful, I shall be sorry; but if they find either, I shall be pleased, and if they find both, I shall much rejoice, that my time hath been employed to some good use.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A53060_00-e100770">
          <signed xml:id="A53060_00-e100780">M. N.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A53060_00-e100790">
        <pb facs="9"/>
        <head>To the readers.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A53060_00-e100800">
          <salute xml:id="A53060_00-e100810">Worthy readers,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100820">I have heard that such poets that write plays, seldom or never join or sow the several scenes together; they are two several professions, at least not usual for rare poets to take that pains; like as great tailors, the master only cuts out and shapes, and his journeymen and apprentices join and sow them together; but I like as a poor tailor was forced to do all myself, as to cut out, shape, join, and sow each several scene together, without any help or direction; wherefore I fear they are not so well done but that there will be many faults found; but howsoever, I did my best endeavour, and took great pains in the ordering and joining thereof, for which I hope my learned readers will pardon the errors therein, and excuse me the worker thereof.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A53060_00-e100830">
          <signed xml:id="A53060_00-e100840">M. N.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A53060_00-e100850">
        <pb facs="9"/>
        <head>To the readers.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A53060_00-e100860">
          <salute xml:id="A53060_00-e100870">Noble readers,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100880">My lord was pleased to illustrate my plays with some scenes of his own wit, to which I have set his name, that my readers may know which are his, as not to cozen them, in thinking they are mine; also songs, to which my lords name is set; for I being no lyric poet, my lord supplied that defect of my brain with the superfluity of his own brain; thus our wits join as in matrimony, my lords the masculine, mine the feminine wit, which is no small glory to me, that we are married, souls, bodies, and brains, which is a treble marriage, united in one love, which I hope is not in the power of death to dissolve; for souls may love, and wit may live, though bodies die.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A53060_00-e100890">
          <signed xml:id="A53060_00-e100900">M. N.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A53060_00-e100910">
        <pb facs="10"/>
        <p xml:id="A53060_00-e100920">I must trouble my noble readers to write of one thing more, which is concerning the reading of plays; for plays must be read to the nature of those several humours, or passions, as are expressed by writing: for they must not read a scene as they would read a chapter; for scenes must be read as if they were spoke or acted. Indeed comedies should be read a mimic way, and the sound of their voice must be according to the sense of the scene; and as for tragedies, or tragic scenes, they must not be read in a puling whining voice, but a sad serious voice, as deploring or complaining: but the truth is there are as few good readers as good writers; indeed an ill reader is, as great a disadvantage to wit as wit can have, unless it be ill acted, for then it 'tis doubly disgraced, both in the voice and action, whereas in reading only the voice is employed; but whenas a play is well and skilfully read, the very sound of the voice that enters through the ears, doth present the actions to the eyes of the fancy as lively as if it were really acted; but howsoever writings must take their chance, and I leave my plays to chance and fortune, as well as to censure and reading.</p>
        <byline xml:id="A53060_00-e100930">m. N.</byline>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A53060_00-e100940">
        <pb facs="10"/>
        <head>To the lady marchioness of Newcastle upon her plays.</head>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100950">Terence and Plautus wits we now do scorn,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100960">Their comic socks worn out, in pieces torn,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100970">Only their rags of wit remain as toys</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100980">For pedants to admire, to teach school boys;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e100990">It is not time hath wasted all their fame,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101000">But your high fancies, and your nobler flame,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101010">Which burned theirs up in their own ashes lies,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101020">Nor phoenix like e'er out of those will rise;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101030">Old tragic buskins now are thrown away,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101040">When we read your each passion in each play,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101050">No stupid block or stony heart forbears</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101060">To drown their cheeks in seas of salter tears;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101070">Such power you have in tragic, comic style,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101080">When for to fetch a tear or make a smile,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101090">Still at your pleasure all our passions lie</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101100">Obedient to your pen, to laugh or cry;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101110">So even with the thread of nature's fashion,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101120">As you play on her heartstrings still of passion;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101130">So we are all your subjects in each play,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101140">Unwilling willingly still to obey;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101150">Or have a thought but what you make or draw</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101160">Us by the power of your wits great law;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101170">Thus emperess in sovereign power yours fits</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101180">Over the wise, and tames poetic wits. </l>
        <byline xml:id="A53060_00-e101190">W. Newcastle.</byline>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="A53060_00-e101200">
        <pb facs="11"/>
        <pb facs="11"/>
        <head>A general prologue to all my plays.</head>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101210">Noble spectators, do not think to see</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101220">Such plays, that's like Ben Jonson's alchemy,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101230">Nor fox, nor silent woman: for those plays</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101240">Did crown the author with exceeding praise;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101250">They were his masterpieces, and were wrought</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101260">By wit's invention, and his labouring thought,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101270">And his experience brought materials store,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101280">His reading several authors brought much more:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101290">What length of time he took those plays to write,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101300">I cannot guess, not knowing his wit's flight;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101310">But I have heard, Ben Jonson's plays came forth,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101320">To the world's view, as things of a great worth;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101330">Like foreign emperors, which do appear</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101340">Unto their subjects, not above once a year;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101350">So did Ben Jonson's plays so rarely pass,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101360">As one might think they long a writing was. </l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101370">But my poor plays, like to a common rout,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101380">Gathers in throngs, and heedlessly runs out,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101390">Like witless fools, or like to girls and boys,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101400">Go out to show new clothes, or such like toys:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101410">This shows my plays have not such store of wit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101420">Nor subtle plots, they were so quickly writ,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101430">So quickly writ, that I did almost cry</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101440">For want of work, my time for to employ:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101450">Sometime for want of work, I'm forced to play,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101460">And idly to cast my time away:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101470">Like as poor labourers, all they desire,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101480">Is, to have so much work, it might them tire:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101490">Such difference betwixt each several brain,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101500">Some labour hard, and offer life to gain;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101510">Some lazy lie, and pampered are with ease,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101520">And some industrious are, the world to please:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101530">Some are so quick, their thoughts do move so fast,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101540">They never stay to mould, or to forecast:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101550">Some take great pains to get, and yet are poor,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101560">And some will steal, for to increase their store:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101570">Some brains know not what subjects for to choose,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101580">And with considering, they their wit do lose:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101590">Some only in designs do spend their time,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101600">And some without designs do only rhyme;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101610"><pb facs="12"/> and some do take more pains a plot to lay,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101620">Than other some to plot, and write a play. </l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101630">As for Ben Jonson's brain, it was so strong,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101640">He could conceive, or judge, what's right, what's wrong:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101650">His language plain, significant and free,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101660">And in the English tongue, the mastery:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101670">Yet gentle Shakespeare had a fluent wit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101680">Although less learning, yet full well he writ;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101690">For all his plays were writ by nature's light,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101700">Which gives his readers, and spectators sight. </l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101710">But noble readers, do not think my plays,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101720">Are such as have been writ in former days;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101730">As Johnson, Shakespeare, Beaumont, Fletcher writ;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101740">Mine want their learning, reading, language, wit:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101750">The Latin phrases I could never tell,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101760">But Johnson could, which made him write so well. </l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101770">Greek, Latin poets, I could never read,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101780">Nor their historians, but our English speed;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101790">I could not steal their wit, nor plots out take;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101800">All my plays plots, my own poor brain did make:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101810">From Plutarch's story I ne'er took a plot,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101820">Nor from romances, nor from don Quixot,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101830">As others have, for to assist their wit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101840">But I upon my own foundation writ;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101850">Like those that have a little patch of land,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101860">Even so much whereon a house may stand:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101870">The owner builds a house, though of no show,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101880">A cottage warm and clean, though thatched and low;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101890">Vitruvius' art and skill he doth not take,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101900">For to design, and so his house to make;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101910">Nor carpenters, nor masons doth not hire,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101920">But builds a house himself, whole and entire:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101930">Materials none from foreign parts are brought;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101940">Nor hath he stone and timber with art wrought;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101950">But some sound tree, which on his ground did grow,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101960">Which he cuts down with many a labouring blow;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101970">And with his hatchet, and his saw, he cuts</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101980">His tree in many parts, those parts he puts</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e101990">In several places, beams, posts, planchers lays,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102000">And thus a house with his own stock doth raise:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102010">He steals nor borrows not of any neighbour,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102020">But lives contentedly of his own labour;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102030">And by his labour, he may thrive, and live</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102040">To be an old rich man, and then may leave</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102050">His wealth, to build a monument of fame,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102060">Which may for ever keep alive his name. </l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102070">Just so, I hope, the works that I have writ,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102080">Which are the buildings of my natural wit;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102090">My own inheritance, as nature's child,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102100">But the world's vanities would me beguile:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102110">But I have thriftly been, housewived my time,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102120">And built both cottages of prose and rhyme;</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102130"><pb facs="12"/> all the materials in my head did grow,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102140">All is my own, and nothing do I owe:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102150">But all that I desire whenas I die,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102160">My memory in my own works my lie:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102170">And whenas others build them marble tombs,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102180">To inurn their dust, and fretted vaulted rooms,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102190">I care not where my dust, or bones remain,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102200">So my works live, the labour of my brain. </l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102210">I covet not a stately, cut, carved tomb,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102220">But that my works, in fame's house may have room:</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102230">Thus I my poor built cottage am content,</l>
        <l xml:id="A53060_00-e102240">When that I die, may be my monument. </l>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

