<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A04896">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Rhodon and Iris <date type="creation_date">1631</date></title>
        <author>Knevet, Ralph</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Madeline Burg</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A04896.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Rhodon and Iris¨ A pastorall, as it vvas presented at the florists feast in Norwich, May 3. 1631.</title>
            <author>Knevet, Ralph, 1600-1671.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>41 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2005 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99843849</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 15036.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg II, 449(A*).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">8608</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04896</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Rhodon and Iris¨ A pastorall, as it vvas presented at the florists feast in Norwich, May 3. 1631.</title>
            <author>Knevet, Ralph, 1600-1671.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[76] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed [by J. Beale] for Michael Sparke, at the blew Bible in Greene-Arbour,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1631.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Dedication signed: Ra. Knevet.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A2 a4 B-I4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>A variant of the edition with E. Causon's name in the imprint.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A04896-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A04896-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A04896-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e100040"><pb facs="1"/>Rhodon and Iris.</p>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e100050">A pastorall, as it was presented at the florists feast in Norwich, may 3. 1631.</p>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e100060">Urbis et orbis gloria Flora.</p>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e100070">
          <figure xml:id="A04896-e100080"/>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e100090">London: printed for Michael spark, at the blue bible in greene-arbour. 1631.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A04896-e100100">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To the right worshipful, Mr. Nicholas Bacon of Gillingham, esquire. </head>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e100110">Noble sir:</p>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e100120">Considering your true affection to poesy, which (No doubt) proceeds from your singular perfection in that art; seeing also how fervently you are addicted to a speculation of the virtues and beauties of all flowers; I could not choose but present you with the patronage of this dramatical piece, bringing this small sacrifice to the altar of your worth, as the little birds (Having naught else) were wont to bring their feathers, and the bees their wax, to the oracle of Apollo. </p>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100130">Yet though the work doth crave nor bays, nor cedar,</l>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100140">But the mild censure of a gracious reader. </l>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100150"><pb facs="3"/>This to the proudest critic I dare tell,</l>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100160">It fears nor frankincense, nor mackerel,</l>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100170">Nor terrible tobacco, that consumes</l>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100180">Atlantic volumes in his smothering fumes. </l>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e100190">But howsoever this small pittance may seem un vorthy your acceptance, yet expecting to find your worth a protection for my weakness, I repose myself in an assured hope of your favour, and rest till a more real occasion may make you a more true owner of my service.</p>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e100200">Yours really,</p>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e100210">Ra. Knevet.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A04896-e100220">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>To his much respected friends, the society of florists.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A04896-e100230">
          <salute xml:id="A04896-e100240">Gentlemen,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e100250">To you I am to speak of the fairest of vegetals, flowers, the minions of the spring, and for their beauties, deserving the title of terrestrial stars, being of such excellency, that (If you will believe the asseveration of the wisest and the best of the sons of men) you must grant that the wisest and happiest prince that ever was, in all his glory, was not like one of them. And did not the omnipotent architect of the universe, place his protoplast in a garden, as being the most convenient and pleasant habitation for man, as yet unstained with with disobedience, and abstaining from the forbidden fruit? And was not this Eden so holy and pure a place, that Adam could no longer be tenant there then he kept his innocency? If I should expatiate in the commendation of these glorious creatures (I fear) I should be brought into a maze whence I could not easily extricate myself; therefore I will refer you that are desirous to be industrious in the indagation of their virtues and beauties, to those large volumes that are now extant, wherein their natures are amply and exactly described. How as concerning your feast, quod multi infectis oculis<pb facs="4"/><pb facs="4"/><pb facs="5"/> conspiciunt. 'tis true, many sanctimonists, that like the men of China, think themselves wiser than all the world beside, do inveigh against it (How justly I know not) but as for my part, if I did think it might be any way prejudicial, either too politic, or moral society. I should detest it as deeply as the most zealous heteroclite of them all. If it had any affinity with Bacchanalian riot, if gluttony and drunkenness ever found any entertainment there, I should utterly loathe to name it: but since it is a meeting so civil, so unspotted, that malice herself, had she a brazen face, might blush to detract from it; since it is a feast celebrated by such a conflux of gentlemen of birth and quality, in whose presence and commerce (I think) your city's welfare partly consists: I cannot but commend it (Though not so highly as it deserves) in spite of ignorance or envy. </p>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100260">But some there be that are so pure and sage,</l>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100270">That they do utterly abhor a stage,</l>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100280">Because they would be still accounted holy,</l>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100290">And know, the stage doth oft bewray their folly. </l>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100300">You could but wonder to see what distaste</l>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100310">They took, to see an hypocrite uncased:</l>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100320">O had they power, they would the author use</l>
        <l xml:id="A04896-e100330">As ill as Bacchus' priests did Orpheus. </l>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e100340">These, out of their malicious discretion (Having no other way to satisfy their unjust envy) by mere misprisions, and under pretence that I should abuse a corporation, would fain engage me in your city's hatred, which although I account it one of the meanest disasters that can betide, yet I should think myself an unworthy man to do any thing worthy of their haired. But whereas they accuse me for taxing of some private persons, I am content to refer this controversy to the arbitrement of any<pb facs="5"/> that is ingenious. But this (As I tender my own reputation, and truth herself) I must tell ye, that should I spy villainy shelter herself under a scarlet gown, I durst be so bold as to spurn her with the left foot of contempt, though not be so prodigal of that small store the muses have allotted me, as to spend a line upon so despicable a subject. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A04896-e100350">
        <pb facs="6"/>
        <head>To the book and his worthy friend the author.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A04896-e100360">
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100370">Dispers and vindicate thy maker's merits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100380">Late disesteemed by Lynx eyed censuring spirits;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100390">Whose captivated judgements now may see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100400">In this clear glass their own deformity;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100410">Whose malice found no cause to disrespect</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100420">Thy worth, but 'cause it passed their intellect:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100430">My barren muse cannot to life set forth</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100440">Thy abstruse poesy, learning and worth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100450">Th'abilities which in thy bosom lie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100460">Will be admired of posterity:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100470">Were't thou but truly known, thy worth would raise</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100480">Thee and thy muse: best poets would with bays</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100490">Crown thy rich temples, and maugre thy will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100500">Would place thee highest on Parnassus hill. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100510">Blessed be their names, thy nectar genius nourish:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100520">By such, dejected poesy shall flourish. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100530">Let no Agnostus dare to read thy lines,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100540">They're made for those can judge of high designs. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04896-e100550">
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100560">In unknown waters lest I wade too far,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100570">Let thy bright rising sun eclipse my star. </l>
        </lg>
        <signed xml:id="A04896-e100580">Ri. Pirt.</signed>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A04896-e100590">
        <pb facs="6"/>
        <head>To his friend the author</head>
        <lg xml:id="A04896-e100600">
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100610">May none but Phoebus kiss thy lines with sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100620">He'll do thee right. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100630">'Tis not for mortals once to dare to scan,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100640">Thy height 'bove man. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100650">This speaks thy fellowship with supreme gods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100660">There's naught puts odds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100670">But life's eternity: tush, thy lines shall be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100680">A saintlike canon of thy memory. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04896-e100690">
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100700">Be bold then to the world, and dumb that tongue</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100710">That dares thee wrong:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100720">Yet thus give leave to vulgar brains to clap</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100730">Agnostus cap</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100740">Upon their heads, whose brains do much less crave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100750">Than I deprave. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100760">Scorn blast their dwellings in simplicity</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100770">That spit their poison; none shall venom thee. </l>
        </lg>
        <signed xml:id="A04896-e100780">William Dennye.</signed>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A04896-e100790">
        <head>To his friend the author.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A04896-e100800">
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100810">I cannot but admire this work of thine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100820">(Rightworthy author) that methinks each line</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100830">Should gain attention from a well tuned ear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100840">And please the eye of any shall appear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100850">That apprehends it: always I'll attend</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100860">To wish this work well, as a faithful friend. </l>
        </lg>
        <signed xml:id="A04896-e100870">John Mingay.</signed>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A04896-e100880">
        <pb facs="7"/>
        <head>In librum.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A04896-e100890">
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100900">En metamorphosis dispar descendit in orbem</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100910">Illi, quam prisco descripsit tempore Naso:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100920">Humanas vertit formas in florea Naso</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100930">Corpora: sed noster contrà floralia vestit</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100940">Corpora forma hominum, cantandus laude poeta. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100950">Pingis (Naso) tuam met amorphôsin Latiali</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100960">Ample stilo: nostrum hunc pellexit at Anglica penna. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04896-e100970">
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100980">Anglica penna vehat submilis ad aethera pennis</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e100990">Angelicis anglum, qui tanta et talia finxit</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101000">Hanc metamorphôsin noster beet author, et omnes</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101010">Applaudant docti: veterem quae Naso beavit</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101020">Voce svam, canat et redimitus tempora lauro. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101030">Jamque opus exegi, quod nec jovis ira, nec ignis,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101040">Nec poterit ferrum, nec edax abolere vetustas. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A04896-e101050">
          <signed xml:id="A04896-e101060">M.s.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A04896-e101070">
        <pb facs="7"/>
        <head>Dramatis personae.</head>
        <list xml:id="A04896-e101080">
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101090">Rhodon. Shepheard. </item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101100">Adanthus a friend to Rhodon. Shepheard. </item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101110">Martagon. Shepheard. </item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101120">Cynosbatus a friend to Martag. Shepheard. </item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101130">Anthophotus. Shepheard. </item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101140">Iris sister to Anthophotus. Shepherdess. </item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101150">Violetta sister to Rhodon. Shepherdess. </item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101160">Eglantine sister to Cynosbatus. Shepherdess. </item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101170">Panas a servant to Iris. Shepherdess. </item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101180">Clematis a servant to eglantine. Shepherdess. </item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101190">Agnostus an impostor.</item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101200">Poneria a witch.</item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101210">Gladiolus a page to eglantine. </item>
          <item xml:id="A04896-e101220">Flora.</item>
        </list>
        <p xml:id="A04896-e101230">The scene is Thessaly. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="A04896-e101240">
        <pb facs="8"/>
        <head>Prologue.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A04896-e101250">
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101260">Candid spectators, you that are invited</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101270">Tô see the lily and the rose united;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101280">Consider that this comedy of ours,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101290">A nosegay is composed of sundry flowers. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101300">Which we selected with some small expense</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101310">Of time, to please each one that hath a sense:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101320">But if this glorious cynic crown contains</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101330">A head that wants a competence of brains,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101340">We could desire his absence, and be glad</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101350">That one more wise his seat or standing had. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101360">Because experience shows that such as he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101370">The greatest enemies to science be:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101380">For what the noddy cannot understand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101390">He will seek to disparage underhand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101400">Branding eternal lines with black disgrace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101410">Because they do his numbers smooth surpass. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101420">For this bold critic would have the world know it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101430">That he no small fool is, though a small poet. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101440">But with Icarean wings, why strives he thus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101450">To mount Parnassus tops with Pegasus? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101460">When 'tis most meet that he with asses meek,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101470">His pasture at the mountain's feet should seek,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101480">On thistles wild, and brakes there let him knabble,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101490">While Pegasus does make the skies his stable. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101500">But you (Judicious friends) that well descry</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101510">The strength and worth of noble poesy;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101520">That can discreetly judge of what is done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101530">We crave your favour and attention,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101540">And shall applaud the fortune of our muse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e101550">If ought worth your acceptance we produce. </l>
        </lg>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A04896-e101560">
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A04896-e101570">
        <pb facs="8"/>
        <head>Rhodon and Iris. </head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e101580">
          <head>Act. 1. Scen. 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e101590">Poneria, Agnostus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e101600" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101610">_ts the world's eye not yet asleep? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e101620" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101630">Hath love not yet put on his starry nightcap? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101640">No; nor Juno her spangled smock? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e101650" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101660">What, hath Hesperus forgotten to light heavens tapers up? </l>
            <p xml:id="A04896-e101670">Or be the chariot wheels of night o'er loaden with the leaden weights of sleep,</p>
            <p xml:id="A04896-e101680">That she delays to throw her misty veil upon the face of things?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e101690" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101700">Blind ignorance that gropest in Cimmerian darkness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101710">That liest enveloped in the shades of everlasting night,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101720">That wantest those glorious spectacles of nature,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101730">Those crystalline spheres that should illumine</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101740">Thy Microcosmus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101750">Why dost thou thus malign the guiltless light,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101760">She being the fairest creature that nature ever made? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e101770" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101780">I hate her because she is light: I say she is</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101790">The mistress of disquiet and unrest, and breeds</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101800">More troubles in the world then one of my young</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101810"><pb facs="9"/> hungry lawyers doth in a commonwealth,</l>
            <p xml:id="A04896-e101820">Or a schismatical self-conceited coxcomb in an ancient corporation.</p>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101830">O that I could ulysses-like burn out the eye</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101840">Of that celestial Polypheme;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101850">Or raise dull chaos from Demogorgon's cell</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101860">To quench the world's unnecessary luminaries. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e101870" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101880">Bold ignorance, thou idol of these times</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101890">That o'er a woollen wit, oft wear'st a satin cap:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101900">And sometimes at our Bacchanalian feasts</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101910">Appearest as brave as a canonical saint</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101920">In a calendar: I hug thy resolution, stupid devil,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101930">That dost with generous malice amply supply</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101940">What is defective in thy intellect:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101950">But if thou'lt give my faithful counsel leave</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101960">For to divert the torrent of thy wrath,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101970">Then lend a facile ear to my advice:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101980">Bend not thy bootless hate against that orb of light,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e101990">Whose mighty flames will scorch the impious wings</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102000">Of those nocturnal birds, that shall attempt</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102010">With talons most profane, to injure his bright beauty. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102020">A meaner object than this, shall satisfy</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102030">Thy wrath, and my displeasure. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102040">This is the day whereon the new society of</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102050">Florists, have determined to keep their annual festivals:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102060">Whose pompous celebration hath wont to eclipse</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102070">All feasts besides: th'olympian games,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102080">And Isthmian plays, with all those ludicrous</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102090">And ludibrious combats, are but mere puppet plays</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102100">To this grand feast, for art and nature both have tried</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102110">To make this feast surpass all feasts beside. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102120">Unite thy force with mine, than ten to one</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102130"><pb facs="9"/> we shall disturb their mirth, ere we have done. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e102140" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102150">Then mischief lend me all thy guilty nerves:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102160">Let flames of boundless fury quite dispel</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102170">Lethaean dulness from my clouded brain. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102180">Assist our great design, ye subterraneous powers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102190">That utterly abhor to view the glaring light:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102200">Let not the weakness of my crazed intellectuals,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102210">Nor yet this loathed deficience of my sense,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102220">Be prejudicial to the bent of our design:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102230">Poneria, act thy part, for I am thine. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e102240">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e102250">
          <head>Act. 1. Scen. 2.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e102260">Rhodon, Acanthus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e102270" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102280">(Rhodon) my honoured, soul-united friend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102290">Cast oft that dusky melancholy veil. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102300">Too vile a robe for thy majestic brow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102310">Blast not the pride of Hybla's happiness</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102320">With thy offensive passion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e102330" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102340">Nay, good Acanthus, did love ere offend any? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e102350" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Aca.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102360">And art not thou the map of love's calamity? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102370">Witness those crystal bowls of thy bright eyne,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102380">Which I have seen swelled up with brinish tears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102390">Prepared for sorrows bitter beverage:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102400">Witness those frequent tempests of thy sighs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102410">Which made thy breast a fiery sea of dolour:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102420">Witness those palled cheeks, whose glorious hue</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102430">Aurora late envied, and quite despairing</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102440"><pb facs="10"/> to reach thy beauty's height, with Cupid treated,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102450">And him suborned to wound thy generous heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102460">(Which no base passion ever durst assault)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102470">That now like pale Narcissus on the brink</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102480">Of the beguiling stream, thou liest a dying. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e102490" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102500">I tell thee (Brazen colosse) marble statue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102510">Whose heart loves darts could never penetrate;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102520">Love is the prince of all affections,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102530">And like the element of fire transcends</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102540">His brothers in activity and splendour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e102550" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Aca.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102560">It is a fire indeed, that doth consume</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102570">All virtuous actions; that feeds upon men's souls</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102580">Like the fiend Eurynomus upon dead carcases;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102590">That makes the microcosmus a mere chaos. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102600">It is the remora of all noble enterprises,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102610">And the Lernaean fen which breeds a Hydra,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102620">Crested with a thousand inconveniences. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102630">Let me ne'er inherit more than my father's hempland,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102640">Or ne'er be owner of more wit than some elder brothers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102650">If I think not Cupid the most pernicious deity</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102660">Among all the Olympian senators. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102670">O that I had but Stentours lungs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102680">To thunder out the vanity of that idol. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e102690" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102700">Now I hope you have railed yourself out of breath,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102710">And therefore I may now have time to speak:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102720">Thus 'tis, dear friend Acanthus, I confess</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102730">That once I loved the lady eglantine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102740">Whose rare endowments both of art and nature,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102750">Well corresponding with high birth and fortune,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102760">Did moderately attract my sincere love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102770">Which love conspiring with a strong desire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102780">To see the customs of some foreign nations,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102790"><pb facs="10"/> and know the manners of people far remote,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102800">Made me to greet the princely dame</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102810">With a personal visitation. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102820">Then my indulgent stars did me advise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102830">For to suspend my suit: whose counsel I obeyed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102840">But trust me, friend, thou wert too much mistaken,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102850">To think that love had scorched or singed so much</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102860">The wings of reason; that I must needs fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102870">And perish in the furnace of despair. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102880">Thou art a bad constructer of my thoughts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102890">If that thou think'st 'tis love which makes me sad:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102900">Yea, thou, oft-times, dost take thy marks amiss,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102910">To think me sad; perhaps, whenas my mind</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102920">(Upraised above the sphere of terrene things)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102930">Is ravished with celestial contemplation;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102940">For earthly passion hath no power at all</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102950">To work upon an elevated soul. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102960">Passions are stars to lower orbs confined;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102970">Scorching an earthly, not a heavenly mind. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102980">Yet am I not so much a Stoic, or a stock,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e102990">To plume the pinions of th'immortal soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103000">Who while she's cloistered in this cell of clay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103010">Moves with the wings of the affections:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103020">But lest she, like to heedless Icarus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103030">Should soar too high a pitch; or like young Phaeton,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103040">Should shape her course too low, Jove hath appointed</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103050">Wise virtue for to regulate her flight. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103060">Of these affections, love the empress is;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103070">Who, while she stands submiss to reason's lore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103080">Doth keep the fabric of the little world in frame. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103090">Love is the genial goddess, the Lucina</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103100">Which doth produce each honourable achievement,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103110"><pb facs="11"/> which this true axiom evidently proves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103120">Nobilitas sub amore iacet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103130">Had not the spriteful flames of love, egged on</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103140">That Theban kill-crow mighty Hercules,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103150">To brave adventures; he, perhaps, had died</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103160">As much inglorious as did base Thersites. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103170">Had not the fair Andromache beheld,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103180">From Trojan towers, Hector's valiant acts</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103190">Among the Greeks, amid the Phrygian fields;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103200">The gallant dames of Troy then might, perchance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103210">Most justly have preferred Achilles far before him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103220">'Tis this heroical passion that incends</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103230">The sparks of honour in each noble mind;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103240">Making dull sluggards study industry;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103250">And animating each unlearned head</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103260">To toil in arts and liberal sciences,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103270">Even to the high degree of rare proficience. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103280">Then cease Acanthus with thy lawless tongue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103290">True love's condition to malign or wrong. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e103300" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103310">Thou zealous patron of the winged boy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103320">Well hast thou pleaded thy blind archers case;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103330">Pray Jove thou mayst deserve a lusty fee</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103340">For this Herculean labour of thy tongue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e103350" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103360">Surcease these malapert invectives, friend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103370">Cupid is armed with fire and arrows keen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103380">To be avenged on those that shall him spleen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e103390" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103400">When Sol shall make the Eastern seas his bed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103410">When wolves and sheep shall be together fed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103420">When stars shall fall, and planets cease to wander,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103430">When Juno proves a bawd, and Jupiter a pander;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103440">When Venus shall turn chaste, and Bacchus become sober,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103450">When fruit in April's ripe, that blossomed in October;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103460"><pb facs="11"/> when prodigals shall money lend on use,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103470">And usurers prove lavish and profuse;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103480">When art shall be esteemed, and golden pelf laid down,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103490">When fame shall tell all truth, and fortune cease to frown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103500">To Cupid's yoke then I my neck will bow;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103510">Till then, I will not fear love's fatal blow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e103520" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103530">Wert thou a mere spirit, than I confess,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103540">And think, this resolution might endure;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103550">But so long as thy soul wears robes of earth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103560">Laced all with veins, that o'er a crimson deep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103570">Set forth an azure bright; needs must thy heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103580">Yield to the force of Cupid's golden dart. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e103590">
          <head>Act. 1. Scen. 3.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e103600">Clematis, eglantine.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e103610" who="A04896-clematis">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103620">O impotent desires, allay the sad consort</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103630">Of a sublime fortune, whose most ambitious flames</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103640">Disdain to burn in simple cottages,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103650">Loathing a hard unpolished bed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103660">But coveting to shine beneath a canopy</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103670">Of rich Sydonian purple; all embroidered</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103680">With purest gold, and Oriental pearls;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103690">In tesselated pavements, and guilded roofs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103700">Supported by proud artificial columns,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103710">Of polished ivory and marble; doth love delight</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103720">There; doth he, like a mighty tyrant, rage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103730">Subverting the whole edifice of reason</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103740">With his impetuous conflagration:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103750">That this is true, the gentle shepherdess</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103760"><pb facs="12"/> fair eglantine doth evidently show:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103770">For she, a sister to the great Cynosbatus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103780">Was courted lately by the shepherd Rhodon:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103790">Whose suit she entertained with due respect,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103800">Requiting love with love: but fate (It seems)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103810">Not condescending that great Hymen should</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103820">Accomplish their desires; forbade the banes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103830">And Rhodon hath relinquished his suit;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103840">And is returned to Hybla sweet; whose flowery vales</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103850">Began to droop, and wither in his absence. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103860">But eglantine remains disconsolate;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103870">Like to a turtle that hath lost her mate. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103880">See where she comes, expressing in her face</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103890">A perfect map of melancholy:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103900">I will retire, because I well descry,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103910">She's out of love with all society. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e103920">Enter Eglant. with her lute.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e103930" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103940">Address thyself sweet warbling instrument,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103950">My sorrows sad companion; to tune forth</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103960">Thy melancholy notes; somewhat to slake</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e103970">Those furious flames that scorch my tender heart. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e103980">She sings and plays upon the lute.</stage>
            <lg xml:id="A04896-e103990">
              <l xml:id="A04896-e104000">Upon the black rock of despair</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e104010">My youthful joys are perished quite,</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e104020">My hopes are vanished into air,</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e104030">My day is turned to gloomy night:</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e104040">For since my Rhodon dear is gone,</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e104050">Hope, light, nor comfort, have I none. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg xml:id="A04896-e104060">
              <l xml:id="A04896-e104070">A cell, where grief the landlord is,</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e104080">Shall be my palace of delight;</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e104090"><pb facs="12"/> where I will woo with votes and sighs,</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e104100">Sweet death to end my sorrows quite;</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e104110">Since I have lost my Rhodon dear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e104120">Death's fleshless arms why should I fear? </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e104130">Enter Cle.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e104140" who="A04896-clematis">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104150">What time shall end thy sorrows, sweetest eglantine? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e104160" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Egl.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104170">Such grief as mine cannot be cured by time. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104180">But when the gentle fates shall disembogue</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104190">My weary soul, and that celestial substance free</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104200">From irksome manacles of clay; then may I find,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104210">If not a sweet repose in blessed Elysium,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104220">Yet some refrigeration in those shades,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104230">Where Dido and Hypsiphile do wander. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e104240">Exit Egl.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e104250" who="A04896-clematis">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104260">Thou gentle goddess of the woods and mountains,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104270">That in the woods and mountain's art adored,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104280">The maiden patroness of chaste desires,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104290">Who art for chastity renowned most,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104300">Tresgrand Diana, who haste power to cure</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104310">The rankling wounds of Cupid's golden arrows;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104320">Thy precious balsam deign thou to apply,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104330">Unto the heart of woeful eglantine;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104340">Then we thy gracious favour will requite</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104350">With a young kid, than new fallen snow more white. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e104360">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e104370">
          <head>Act. 1. Scen. 4.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e104380">Cynosbatus, Martagon.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e104390" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104400">My honoured friend, most noble martagon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104410">Who whilom didst with thy imperial power</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104420">Command the mountains proud, and humble plains</l>
            <pb facs="13"/>
            <pb facs="13"/>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104430"><pb facs="14"/> of happy Thessaly: who hath eclipsed</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104440">The splendour of thy light, and clipped those wings</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104450">That did o'ershade these fields from East to West. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104460">Each shepherd that was wont to feed his flocks</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104470">Upon these fertile meads, was wont whilere</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104480">To pay the tribute of his primest lambs. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104490">But now as one couped in an angle up,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104500">Thou art compelled to satisfy thyself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104510">With a small portion of that sovereignty</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104520">Which thou didst erst enjoy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e104530" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104540">Dear friend Cynosbatus, if that the world</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104550">Had been composed in a cubic form</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104560">And not orbicular; or if this globe</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104570">Were destined to be ought else then fortunes ball,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104580">By alterations racket banded to and fro;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104590">Then justly mightst thou wonder to behold</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104600">My present state, so short of my precedent height. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104610">Nor doth this monster, change, bear sway alone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104620">O'er elements, men, beasts, and plants,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104630">But those celestial bodies that are framed</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104640">Of purer constitutions, are compelled</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104650">To be obedient to her awful doom. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104660">Rear up thy eyes unto the spangled cope,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104670">And there behold Jove's star-enchased belt,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104680">The glittering zodiac wonderfully changed</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104690">In a few thousand years:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104700">For those fixed stars, which like a diamond clear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104710">Adorn the baldric of the thunderer,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104720">Have wandered from their former stations. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104730">Witness the golden ram who now is gone astray,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104740">And shouldered hath the Cretian bull; and he</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104750">Those twins of Jove so sore hath butted,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104760"><pb facs="14"/> that they have crushed the crab, and thrust him quite</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104770">Into the den of the Nemaean lion. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104780">Thus by the change of these superior bodies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104790">Strange alterations in the world are wrought,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104800">Great empires maimed, and kingdoms brought to naught. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104810">And that auspicious lamp, who freely lends</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104820">His light to lesser fires, the prince of generation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104830">Even sol himself, is five degrees declined,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104840">Since learned Ptolemy did take his height. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104850">But if Egyptian wizards we may trust,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104860">Who in astrology wont to excel;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104870">By them 'tis told, that four times they have seen</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104880">That glorious charioteer flit from his place:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104890">Twice hath he rose (They say) where now he sets,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104900">And twice declined where he now doth rise. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104910">If these celestial powers, whose influence</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104920">Commands terrestrial substances,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104930">Be object to mutation, then needs must</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104940">Sublunar things, submit themselves to change. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104950">Then wonder not good friend Cynosbatus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104960">To see my state and power diminished thus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e104970" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104980">'Tis true dear martagon, experience shows</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e104990">That alteration every day brings forth</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105000">A new birth of effects. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105010" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105020">But I prithee friend, satisfy me in one thing. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105030" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105040">My bosom's yours, take from that cabinet</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105050">The choicest secret that can pleasure you:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105060">Tell me in what your will's to be resolved. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105070" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105080">There is a rumour spread through Thessaly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105090">That your fair sister, madame eglantine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105100">Shall be espoused to the shepherd Rhodon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105110">The prince of all the swains that dwell on Hybla. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105120" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker><pb facs="15"/>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105130">From no ill grounds this rumor sprang, though</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105140">The fates did cross what was by us intended. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105150" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Na.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105160">Then there's no expectation of my nuptial rite</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105170" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105180">No; all's dissolved. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105190" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Na.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105200">I thank my stars for that. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105210" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105220">Your reason, noble friend. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105230" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105240">A kin he is to that male spirited dame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105250">That stout virago, that proud shepherdess</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105260">Called Violetta: who complains of wrongs</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105270">Late suffered at my hands:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105280">And he's the man by whom she hopes</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105290">To be avenged on me, for this pretended injury;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105300">And had he matched your sister, sweet eglantine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105310">Then might I have had cause for to suspect</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105320">Your love not to be sound, since you accepted</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105330">So great a so of mine, for your near friend. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105340" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105350">Then I am glad the fates would not agree</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105360">That I should lose so true a friend as thee. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e105370">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e105380">
          <head>Act. 1. Scen. 3.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e105390">Rhodon. Anthophotus. Acanthus. Iris. Panace.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105400" who="A04896-anthophotus">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105410">Never till now, did my Hymettus flourish:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105420">More blessed effects hath thy sweet presence wrought,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105430">(Honoured Rhodon) then could have been produced</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105440">By moist-winged Zephyrus, or Favonius,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105450">Who fans our flowers with his gentle breath. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105460" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105470">Thanks, good Anthophotus:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105480" who="A04896-anthophotus">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105490">Nor doth our sister Iris hold herself</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105500"><pb facs="15"/> meanly engaged to you, for this your gracious visit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105510" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105520">To be the meanest servant of so sweet a saint,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105530">Is the full height and scope of my ambition. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105540" who="A04896-iris">
            <speaker>Ir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105550">Fair sir I wish you would be pleased t'imploy</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105560">Your service on an object of more worth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105570" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105580">Dissemble not, admired shepherdess;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105590">For thou art she, that art as far beyond</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105600">That light piece of beauty, Helen of Greece,</l>
            <p xml:id="A04896-e105610">In outward perfections; as she was short of thee in inward graces.</p>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105620">Yea, had those fifty Kings that did for her</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105630">Engage themselves in a long tedious war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105640">Seen but the model of thy rare beauty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105650">Drawn by the hand of but a rude painter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105660">Doubtless, they had their honours forfeited,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105670">And broke that sacred oath which they had ta'en. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105680">Their work in hand they had relinquished quite,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105690">And left the walls of wretched Troy untouched;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105700">For each attracted with thy beauty's splendour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105710">No seas nor perils would have left unpassed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105720">To find thee in the furthest angle of the world. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105730" who="A04896-iris">
            <speaker>Ir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105740">Could my perfections, valued at the highest rate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105750">But countervail a dram of your great worth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105760">Then should I think myself born under stars</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105770">Most happy and auspicious. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105780" who="A04896-anthophotus">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105790">Surcease your compliments, dear Rhodon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105800">Let empty casks, and hollow cymbals speak</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105810">That airy language, which unworthy is</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105820">Of your realities. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105830" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105840">Pardon me, gentle sir: this radiant star,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105850">My judgements feeble eyes did dazzle so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105860">That I was forced to speak what passion did inform me. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e105870"><pb facs="16"/>Enter a messenger.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105880" who="A04896-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105890">Which is the shepherd Rhodon? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105900" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105910">I am the man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105920" who="A04896-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105930">Then you are he whom Violetta greets. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105940" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105950">How fares my sister? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105960" who="A04896-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e105970">This letter shall relate what I can never utter. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e105980">Exit Messen.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e105990" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106000">Pray Jove we have good news, methinks I saw</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106010">A pallid horror settled in the face</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106020">Of the sad messenger: be't good or ill,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106030">We are resolved to see it, come what will. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e106040">He opens and reads the letter.</stage>
            <lg xml:id="A04896-e106050">
              <l xml:id="A04896-e106060">I Violetta much distressed</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e106070">By Martagon my mortal foe,</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e106080">Your succour humbly do request,</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e106090">To set me free from servile woe. </l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e106100">Our flowers he hath trampled on,</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e106110">Our gardens turned to thickets wild;</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e106120">Our fields and meads he hath o'errun,</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e106130">That we are forced to live exiled. </l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e106140">We therefore do your aid implore,</l>
              <l xml:id="A04896-e106150">Us to our freedom to restore. </l>
              <closer xml:id="A04896-e106160">
                <signed xml:id="A04896-e106170">Your distressed sister, Violetta, Violetta.</signed>
              </closer>
            </lg>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106180">'Twas for no good, that the late shag haired comet</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106190">With his erected staring looks, did overlook</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106200">Our frighted flocks, who all amazed poor wretches</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106210">At such a horrid unexpected sight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106220">Ere Hesperus 'gan from the West to peep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106230"><pb facs="16"/> half empty, did retire unto their folds again:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106240">Nor were those idle fires which late we saw,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106250">Hang like a flaming canopy above us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106260">When we did walk the round about our folds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106270">To keep the werewolf from our lambs by night. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106280">But is't possible that man should be so savage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106290">To vent his rage upon a silly woman? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e106300" who="A04896-anthophotus">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106310">It is no wonder gentle sir at all:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106320">For when Prometheus formed his man of clay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106330">'Tis said that he did to his stomach add,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106340">The raging fury of a lion fierce. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e106350" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106360">'Tis true: but histories report that a lion did,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106370">The suppliant getulian virgin spare;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106380">Scorning to make so innocent a creature</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106390">His prey or quarry. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e106400" who="A04896-anthophotus">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106410">Foul shame and infamy it is, god wot,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106420">That manly might should women weak oppose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106430">Whom they by right for life ought to defend. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e106440" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Acan.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106450">(Rhodon) do thou but say amen: and I will in</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106460">An instant raise our spriteful youth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106470">And lead them on with such a vigorous force</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106480">Against the most unhuman martagon;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106490">That we will pull the craven from his nest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106500">Disrobing him of all his borrowed plumes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106510">And repossessing Violetta of her own. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e106520" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106530">In actions of such consequence as this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106540">We must not be too precipicious,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106550">Mature deliberation must conclude</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106560">What shall be done in such a main design:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106570">The stately steed that with a full career</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106580">Attempts to mount the brow of the steep hill,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106590">Oft breaks his wind, ere he can reach the height. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106600"><pb facs="17"/>But the slow snail without or harm, or peril,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106610">In time ascends unto the mountain's top,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106620">For that true love we owe to Thessaly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106630">In which affection all we are engaged;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106640">We by a friendly treaty will endeavour</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106650">To bring th' usurper to a restitution. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106660">But if the olive branch will do no good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106670">Then let the scourge of war itself disclose;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106680">They that our friendship scorn, must be our foes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e106690" who="A04896-anthophotus">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106700">And if my right hand fail to second thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106710">Then for a peasant let me counted be. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e106720">Exeunt Rho. Antho. Iris.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e106730">Banace offers to go out, and is stayed by Acanthus. </stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e106740" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106750">Nay, stay fair nymph, I would request</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106760">A private conference with you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e106770" who="A04896-panace">
            <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106780">If that I could with my affairs dispense,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106790">I gladly should embrace your conference:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106800">But my occasions bid me haste away;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106810">Sweet sir, adieu; I can no longer stay. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e106820">Exit Pa.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e106830" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106840">I that of late was made of Scythian snow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106850">And Hyperborean ice, am now quite thawed</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106860">In the uncessant flames of hot desire. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106870">A new Vesuvius burns within my breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106880">But shall I overturn those noble trophies</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106890">Which I most firmly have on virtue sounded;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106900">Or shall I sing the wings of reason so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106910">In the outrageous flames of passion;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106920">That I must needs fall down and perish quite</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106930">In the black hideous gulf of deep despair,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106940">No: no: I will not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106950">Of this I am resolved whatsoe'ere befall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e106960">Or not to love too much, or not at all. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e106970">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A04896-e106980">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e106990">
          <pb facs="17"/>
          <head>Act. 2. Scen. 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e107000">Poneria: Agnostus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e107010" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107020">Bold foolish wickedness is that</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107030">Which walks by day, exposed to the world's eye. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107040">Sin is the daughter of the darkest night,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107050">And therefore doth abhor to come to light. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107060">Give me that coal black sin that can lie hid. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107070">Under the candid robes of seeing sanctity;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107080">Which dares put out the perspicacious eyes</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107090">Of those that shall attempt to find her out. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107100">Come dull Agnostus, let us disguise ourselves</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107110">And be prepared to act some stratagem</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107120">To eclipse the glory of these festivals. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e107130">She puts on the garment.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107140">This robe of virtue doth belong to me;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107150">This goodly veil shall hide my black intents. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107160">Thus personated, I durst undertake</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107170">To rend a well woven state in factious pieces;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107180">To win the ears of mighty potentates;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107190">And hoodwink Kings, that they should neither see</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107200">To do what's just, nor hear the piteous cries</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107210">Of those that are oppressed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107220">But that thou, Agnostus, mayst second my designs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107230">'Tis very fit thou shouldst be thus accoutered. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e107240" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107250">My dear Poneria, I am yours. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e107260">She puts on his beard.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e107270" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107280">Then first unto thy chin we must apply</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107290">This philosophical besom. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107300">Now is the old proverb really performed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107310"><pb facs="18"/> more hair than wit. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107320">How like a senator he looks? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107330">What a world of gravity's harboured in that beard? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107340">Surely the world can take him for no other</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107350">Than the third Cato that should fall from heaven. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107360">But here's the ensign of learning,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107370">The badge of the seven liberal sciences,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107380">Operculum ingenij, the silken case of wit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107390">The cap of knowledge; clap this upon thy</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107400">Empty hog shed, put this on, and then thy head</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107410">Will become a Helicon, and thy brain a Pyrene. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e107420">He puts on the Cap.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e107430" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107440">It fits me exceeding well. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e107450" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107460">Dost not perceive thy head begin to ache</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107470">With mere abundance of knowledge? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e107480" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107490">Now, methinks , I could confute a college of divines</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107500">A synod of doctors, a lycaeum of philosophers;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107510">Yet methinks my brains are not right,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107520">And somewhat too weak to maintain a paradox. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e107530" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107540">Away fond idiot, do not conceit</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107550">That this cap can infuse any thing real into thy pate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107560">That is uncapable of all art and science. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107570">Under the protection of this cap, thou mayst be bold</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107580">To traduce thy betters, to censure the best,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107590">To decide controversies without discretion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107600">To torment all companies with thy discourse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107610">And weary ears of iron with thy impertinences;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107620">Do but wear this head-piece over the coif of</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107630">Self-conceit (Always provided) that thou forgettest</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107640">Not to leave off a brazen face; and I dare</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107650">Undertake it, thou in a short time, shalt gain</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107660">More respect (Especially among plebeian coxcombs)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107670"><pb facs="18"/> then ever Pythagoras, had of his auditors. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e107680" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107690">I am thy slave, divine Poneria:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107700">O admirable rare artist that I am! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e107710" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107720">But yet, methinks , there's somewhat else to do</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107730">To make thee more accomplished and complete. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107740">'Slight, the political gown; I had as clean forgotten it ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107750">As the time since I lost my maiden ▪ head. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107760">Here 'tis: dispatch. and put it on,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107770">And then be reputed both grave, —</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107780">Learned, and wise. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107790">Doubtless it will become thee exceeding well. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e107800">He puts on the gown.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107810">Now looks he not like a main stud of a corporation? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e107820" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107830">How heavy is the burden of authority? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e107840" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107850">'Tis true, authority is heavy, I confess,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107860">But not so heavy but an ass may bear't. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107870">Since now, Agnostus, that we are well fitted</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107880">With habits meet, to act what we intend;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107890">Thou seeming like a grave and learned sire;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107900">Though thou indeed then that beest nothing less,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107910">And I like to a virtuous maiden dight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107920">Though I all virtue deeply do abhor;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107930">We thus disguised, will all the world delude,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107940">And set the flowers at odds among themselves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107950">That they in civil enmities embroiled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e107960">Shall of their pride and glories be despoiled. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e107970">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e107980">
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <head>Act. 2, scen. 2.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e107990">Martagon, Cynosbatus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108000" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108010">To hinder the conjunction of those stars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108020">We must try all our skill, Cynosbatus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108030" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108040">I jealous am of their malign aspect,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108050">And therefore hold it best to take away</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108060">That cause which may produce such bad effects;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108070">For I shall never cease t'applaud his skill,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108080">That in the shell, the cockatrice doth kill. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108090" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108100">The serpent will be hatched, I shrewdly fear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108110">Ere we the mischief can prevent, if thus</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108120">We should delay to act our purposes:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108130">For late, a certain rumor, through my ear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108140">Did strike me to the heart; when 'twas reported</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108150">That Rhodon on Hymettus hill was seen;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108160">Where by Anthophotus, and his sister Iris,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108170">He was with such solemnity received,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108180">That all surmise there is a match intended</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108190">Between the shepherd Rhodon and fair Iris. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108200" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108210">If once they be conjoined in Hymen's rites,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108220">Than all our toil's ridiculous and vain;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108230">For Hymen's obligations are (We see)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108240">Seldom by any cancelled, but by death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108250" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108260">Then let us set some stratagem abroach,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108270">The cords of their new amity to break. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108280">The tender twig may easily be broke,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108290">But who's so strong to bow the sturdy oak. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108300">Our friends will say (If we procrastinate)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108310">That, like the Trojans, we were wise too late. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e108320">Exeunt</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e108330">
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <head>Act. 2. Scen. 3.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e108340">Eglantine sola.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108350" who="A04896-missing">
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108360">Since that the gods will not my woe redress,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108370">Since men are altogether pitiless,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108380">Ye silent ghosts unto my plaints give ear;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108390">Give ear (I say, ye ghosts) if ghosts can hear:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108400">And listen to my plaints that do excel</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108410">The dolorous tune of ravished Philomel. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108420">Now let Ixion's wheel stand still a while,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108430">Let Danaus' daughters now surcease their toil:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108440">Let Sisyphus rest on his restless stone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108450">Let not the apples fly from Plotas' son;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108460">And let the full gorged vulture cease to tear</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108470">The growing liver of the ravisher;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108480">Let these behold my sorrows, and confess</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108490">Their pains do far come short of my distress. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108500">Were I but lady of more wealthy store</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108510">Then e'er the sun beheld; or had I more</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108520">Than Midas e'er desired; I would (In brief)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108530">Give all to be delivered from this grief. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108540">Rocks of rich Indian pearl, shores paved with gems,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108550">Mountains of gold, and empire's diadems,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108560">These would I give, yea, and myself to boot,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108570">Myself and these prostrating at his foot,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108580">To enjoy him whom I so dear love. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108590">Ay me, fond love, that art a sweet sour evil,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108600">A pleasant torture, a well-favoured devil. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108610">But why do I, weak wretch, prolong my grief? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108620">Why do I live, since death affords relief? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108630"><pb facs="20"/>Do thou (Sweet poniard) all my sorrow's ease,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108640">That art a medicine for all grievances,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108650">Assist my hand, thou goddess of revenge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108660">That on myself, I may myself avenge. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e108670">Enter Poneria and Agnostus.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108680" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108690">Hold, hold thy hand, fair shepherdess,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108700">Attempt not to commit a fact so horrid. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108710" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108720">What fury sent you hither, caitiffs vile,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108730">Thus to prolong my sorrow, and my toil. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108740" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108750">No fury, but your happy genius</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108760">Brought us to these uncomfortable shades,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108770">For to prevent your mischievous intent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108780" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108790">Death is a plaster for all ills (They say)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108800">What mischief then can be in death, I pray. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108810" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108820">'Tis true; death is a mortal wound that cures all wounds</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108830">Of body, and of mind: it is the soul's potion</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108840">That purgeth her from corporal pollution. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108850">But you must not your own physician prove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108860">Not be the doctor, and the patient too:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108870">For if thy soul be sickly, and grow weary</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108880">Of this unwholesome earthly habitation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108890">Because this airs spissitude suits not</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108900">With her celestial constitution,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108910">She must not like a bankrupt tenant prove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108920">That flies by night from an unprofitable farm,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108930">Before the term of his lease be expired:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108940">But stay till heaven shall give her egress free</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108950">Unto the haven of rest and happiness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108960" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108970">Were I not plunged in a grievous plight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e108980">Perhaps I would not think thy counsel light. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e108990" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109000">Art not thou the sister of Cynosbatus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109010">Lord of the silver mines, and golden mountains. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109020"><pb facs="20"/>And art not thou as fair a shepherdess</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109030">As trips upon the plains of Thessaly? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e109040" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109050">For being great, I am maligned by fate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109060">For being fair, I am unfortunate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e109070" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109080">I know thy sorrows, sweetest eglantine;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109090">Thy rhodons absence hath wrought all thy woe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109100">Who now, they say, doth beauteous Iris court. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109110">But if thou wilt make me thy instrument,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109120">I'll undertake to break the match,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109130">If not, renew the love which erst he bore to thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e109140" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109150">Do this, and I will live (Poneria)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109160">To give thy merit ample satisfaction. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109170">I will adore thy skill, and thee adorn</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109180">With what may make thee famous through all Thessaly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e109190" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109200">Then banish all these melancholy thoughts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109210">And deck thyself in thy most sumptuous weeds. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109220">Make haste unto the fane of gentle Venus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109230">A pair of turtles of a snowy hue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109240">Upon her altars offer thou to her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109250">And her beseech to intercede for thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109260">Unto her angry boy: then shalt thou find</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109270">The god and goddess to true lovers kind. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e109280" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109290">My dear Poneria, I am truly thine. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109300">But tell me, I prithee, what grave sir is this</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109310">That looks like one of Greece's sages;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109320">His reverent countenance makes me surmise</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109330">That he's a man of sublime qualities. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e109340" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109350">He is but what he seems, fair shepherdess:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109360">His head's the officine of art; his tongue</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109370">The oracle of truth; he is the man</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109380">Whom only nature hath vouchsafed to make</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109390">Her privy counsellor. </l>
            <pb facs="21"/>
            <pb facs="21"/>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109400"><pb facs="22"/>Those abstruse secrets which no mortal eye</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109410">Did ever view, he plainly can descry;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109420">He is the man that's destined to find out</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109430">That grand mysterious secret, in whose discovery</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109440">So many bold adventurous wits have perished:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109450">I mean th' elixir, the philosopher's precious stone. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109460">He is the man who by strange policies</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109470">Can break the strong confederacies of Kings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109480">And overthrow more empires by his plots,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109490">Then mighty Alexander e'er did by strength:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109500">Agnostus is his name, renowned no less</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109510">For honesty, than skill in sciences. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e109520" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109530">His silence argues something extraordinary. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e109540" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109550">Belphegor, Zazel, Astragoth, Golguth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109560">Machon Malortor. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e109570">Egl. offers to fly away, and is stayed by Po.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e109580" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109590">Ay me, Poneria. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e109600" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109610">Agnostus, not a word more for thy life. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109620">Stay, stay, sweet Eglantine, and dread no harm,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109630">This is the language which the Persian magi used</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109640">When they with their familiars did converse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109650">To which he is so frequently accustomed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109660">That oft he speaks it ere he be aware. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109670">(Agnostus) vouchsafe to use your native language,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109680">That eglantine may know what you are. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109690">I hope you know your lesson,</l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e109700">Aside.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109710">Twice twenty times and ten, etc. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e109720" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109730">Twice twenty times and ten, hath Titan run</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109740">Quite through the zodiac, since I begun</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109750">To converse with wise fiends, that I might get</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109760">The golden key of nature's cabinet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109770">By industry I got immortal same,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109780"><pb facs="22"/> for ignorance begets contempt and shame:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109790">So perfect in the magic arts I grew,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109800">That nature's secrets most abstruse I knew;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109810">The spirits of air and earth did me dread,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109820">And did at my venite come with speed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109830">The silly ghosts from graves I did forth call. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109840">The earth I make to bellow, stars to fall. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109850">The world at my great awful charms did quake,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109860">Nature herself for very fear did shake:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109870">To change midday to midnight, or to cause</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109880">Estival snows, or break the viper's jaws,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109890">Or to drive rivers back to their spring heads,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109900">And make seas stand unmoved, or to strike dead</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109910">The vernal blossom, or the harvest ear:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109920">A man would think these strange conclusions were,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109930">But I account them of small weight: I know</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109940">The use of herbs, and whatsoever grow;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109950">The cause to the effect I can apply,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109960">And work strange things by hidden sympathies. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109970">I do exactly know the compositions</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109980">Of unctuous philters, and loves potions:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e109990">Figures, suspensions, and ligations,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110000">Characters and suffumigations. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110010">For I the virtues of all simples know</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110020">From whence; effects that seem impossible I show. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110030">The gall of shriek owls, and harsh night raven's tongues</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110040">Guts of panthers, and chameleons lungs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110050">A black bulls eyes, a speckled toads dried head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110060">Frankincense, camphire, and white poppy-seed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110070">Poisonous Melanthion, and a white cock's blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110080">Sweet myrrh, bay-berries, precious balsam wood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110090">A heart's marrow that hath devoured a snake,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110100"><pb facs="23"/> and scalps which from a wild beasts jaws we take,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110110">The bone that lies ith' left side of a frog,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110120">A stone that is bitten with a mad dog. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110130">The mandrake root, the blood of a black cat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110140">A turtles liver, the brains of a bat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110150">Hyaena's heart, the cockatrice's blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110160">That are against so many evils good:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110170">The hair of a thief that hangs on a tree;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110180">The nails of ships that wracked be,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110190">The blood of a wretched man that was slain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110200">The eyes of a dragon and weasels brains. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110210">These precious simples, and a thousand more</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110220">I could produce; I have them all in store:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110230">And though they seem to men mere trifling things,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110240">Each one (I vow) overweighs ransoms of Kings. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110250">The blindness of these times cannot descry</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110260">The virtues rare that in these simples lie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e110270" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110280">Enough Agnostus: now fair shepherdess,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110290">I hope you have a fair expression</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110300">Of this learned man's sublime desert, and art? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e110310" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110320">I do admire his skill, and see (By hap)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110330">Good stuff may be beneath a fatten Cap. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e110340">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e110350">
          <head>Act. 2. Scen. 4.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e110360">Rhodon, Martagon, Violetta, Acanthus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e110370" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110380">Know Martagon, that as no dynasties can stand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110390">No empires long subsist, unless they be</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110400">Supported by the columns of true equity:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110410">So shall that government of thine decay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110420"><pb facs="23"/> since thy oppression makes the weak a prey. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e110430" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110440">'Tis no oppression for to punish those,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110450">That have transgressed the laws, as I suppose. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e110460" who="A04896-violetta">
            <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110470">The laws (Colossus) proud, unjust tyrant,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110480">That dost observe nor equity nor law,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110490">But by the torrent of ambition hurried,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110500">Dost act what lawless passion prompts thee to:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110510">What laws have I transgressed? it is thy might,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110520">That into seeming wrong hath changed our right:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110530">Had fortune been as just as was our cause,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110540">We that are censured now for breach of laws,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110550">Maugre thy viperous hate, had now been free,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110560">And for thy foul injustice censured thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e110570" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110580">And is your pride virago still so high? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110590">That it doth overtop your misery. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110600">Can't sorrow strike thee dumb, can no disaster,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110610">The liberty of thy tongue overmaster. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e110620" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110630">Nay, be assured (Proud man) not any smart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110640">Can cure the courage of a valiant heart:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110650">No force a heart of adamant can break;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110660">And losers' must, and shall have leave to speak. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e110670" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110680">No more Acanthus: hear me martagon:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110690">Wilt thou give Violetta what's her own? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110700">Wilt thou restore her right and due possessions? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110710">And make a recompense for all oppressions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110720">That happy peace with joy and plenty crowned,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110730">May in the fields of Thessaly be found? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e110740" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110750">This will I do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110760">When seas shall be drunk dry by Phoebus beams,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110770">And when the lesser stars shall drink the streams. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110780">This will I do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110790">When of my life and freedom I am weary,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110800"><pb facs="24"/> non minor est virtus quam quae rear parta tueri. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e110810" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110820">Before this guiltless woman shall endure</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110830">Such shameful injuries: thyself assure</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110840">I'll empty all these azure rivulets</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110850">Of their vermilion streams; and quite discharge</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110860">This contemned bulk of mine, of living air;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110870">And stretched upon the gelid bed of death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110880">I'll to the world this epitaph bequeath,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110890">Here lies a swain that spent his dearest blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110900">To kill a tyrant for a virgin's good. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e110910" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110920">Bold hero do thy worst, what I have won</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110930">I ne'er will part withal till life be done. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e110940" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110950">Tenacious tyrant, in whose flinty heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110960">Nor equity, nor justice ere had part:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110970">Assure thyself thy guilty soul shall feel</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e110980">Revenges hand, armed with a scourge of steel. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e110990">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A04896-e111000">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e111010">
          <head>Act. 3. Scen. 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e111020">Clematis Solo.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e111030" who="A04896-missing">
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111040">Well, if I were but once rid of her service,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111050">If I ever served lovesick mistress again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111060">I would feed all my life time on Agnus Castus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111070">And give all the world leave to let me die a maid:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111080">I even spoilt a good mother wit</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111090">With beating my head about these knick knacks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111100">Which my mistress, madam eglantine</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111110">Hath enjoined me to procure her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111120">For now seduced by the old bawd Poneria,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111130">She thinks to recover her old sweetheart Rhodon. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111140"><pb facs="24"/>Here is a catalogue as tedious as a tailor's bill,</l>
            <p xml:id="A04896-e111150">Of all the devices which I am commanded to provide, videlicet:</p>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111160">Chains, coronets, pendants, bracelets and earrings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111170">Pins, girdles, spangles, embroideries, rings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111180">Shadows, rebatos, ribbons, ruffs, cuffs and falls:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111190">Scarves, feathers, fans, masks, muffs, laces and calls;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111200">Thin tiffanies. cobweb-lawn and farthingales,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111210">Sweet-balls, veils, wimples, glasses, crisping-pins;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111220">Pots, ointments, combs, with poking-sticks and bodkins;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111230">Coifs, gorgets, fringes, rolls, fillets and hair-laces;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111240">Silks, damasks, velvet, tinsels, cloth of gold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111250">And tissue, with colours of a hundreth fold. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e111260">Enter Gladiolus</stage>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111270">But in her tires so new fangled is she,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111280">That which doth with her humour now agree,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111290">Tomorrow she dislikes, now doth she swear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111300">That a loose body is the neatest wear;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111310">But ere an hour be gone, she will protest</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111320">A straight gown graces her proportion best:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111330">Now calls she for a boisterous farthingale,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111340">Then to her hips she'll have her garments fall:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111350">Now doth she praise a sleeve that's long and wide,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111360">Yet by and by that fashion doth deride:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111370">Sometimes sh'applauds a pavement-sweeping train,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111380">And presently dispraiseth it again. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111390">Now she commends a shallow band so small,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111400">That it may seem scarce any band at all;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111410">But soon to a new fancy doth she reel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111420">And calls for one as big as a coach-wheel:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111430">She'll wear a flowery coronet today,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111440">The symbol of her beauty's sad decay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111450">Tomorrow she a waving plume will try,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111460"><pb facs="25"/> the emblem of all female lenity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111470">Now in her hat, then in her hair she's dressed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111480">For of all fashions she thinks change the best. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e111490" who="A04896-gladiolus">
            <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111500">Good fellow servant, honest Clematis,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111510">Let me conclude thy tedious tale with this;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111520">I say the rest less sea and flitting wind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111530">Are constant in respect of women kind. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e111540" who="A04896-clematis">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111550">Nor in her weeds alone is she so nice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111560">But rich perfumes she buys at any price. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111570">Storax and spiknard she burns in her chamber,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111580">And daubs herself with civit, musk and amber. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111590">With limbecks, viols, pots, her Closet's filled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111600">Full of strange liquours by rare art distilled:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111610">She hath vermilion and antimony,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111620">Ceruse and sublimated Mercury. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111630">Waters she hath to make her face to shine;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111640">Confections eke to clarify her skin;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111650">Lipsalves, and clothes of a pure scarlet dye</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111660">She hath, which to her cheeks she doth apply:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111670">Ointments wherewith she pargets o'er her face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111680">And lustrifies her beauty's dying grace. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111690">She waters for the morphews doth compose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111700">And many other things, as strange as those;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111710">Some made of daffodils, some of lees,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111720">Of scarwolf some, and some of rinds of trees,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111730">With centory, sour grapes, and tarragon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111740">She maketh many a strange lotion:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111750">Her skin she can both supple and refine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111760">With juice of lemons and with turpentine:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111770">The marrow of the hernshaw and the deer,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111780">She takes likewise to make her skin look clear:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111790">Sweet waters she distils, which she composes</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111800"><pb facs="25"/> of flowers of oranges, woodbine or roses:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111810">The virtue of jasmine and three-leaved grass,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111820">She doth imprison in a brittle glass,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111830">With civet, musk, and odours far more rare,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111840">These liquours sweet incorporated are:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111850">Lees she can make which turn a hair that's old</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111860">Or coloured ill, into a hue of gold. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111870">Of horses, bears, cats, camels, coneys, snakes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111880">Whales, herons, bitterns, strange oils she makes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111890">With which dame natures errors she corrects,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111900">Using arts help to supply all defects. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111910">She in the milk of asses baths her skin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111920">As did the beautiful Poppea, when</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111930">She tempted Nero to forsake the bed</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111940">Of great Octavia, and herself to wed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e111950" who="A04896-gladiolus">
            <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111960">If there be any gentlewoman here,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111970">That will with gracious acceptation use</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111980">The service of a tattling chambermaid,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e111990">I would advise her to make choice of this Frisketta,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112000">That is as chaste as Helen, or Corinthian Lais,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112010">As chary of bewraying secrets as was echo:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112020">O she would prove a rare privy counsellor</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112030">In some great lady's privy chamber. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112040">The perpetual motion for which artists have so laboured</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112050">Is discovered nowhere so plainly as in her tongue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112060">Which scarce finds any leisure to rest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112070">No not when she is asleep:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112080">But of her courtesy she is so charitable,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112090">And so heroically magnificent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112100">That she will both vouchsafe to commiserate</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112110">The low estate of an humble groom of the stable,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112120">And also satisfy the desire</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112130"><pb facs="26"/> of a high and mighty gentleman-usher</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112140">In a kiss or any other amorous encounter:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112150">Gentlemen believe me in few, she is a pearl,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112160">Whose worth the age cannot value. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112170">If there be any gentleman here</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112180">That will bestow a small pension upon her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112190">With a kiss or two once a fortnight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112200">To make her his intelligencer of state</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112210">In his wife's commonwealth;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112220">I will undertake he shall be able to make good</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112230">A faction against his wife,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112240">Had she an Amazons stomach, a Zenobia's,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112250">Or a Xanthippe's tongue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112260" who="A04896-clematis">
            <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112270">Out you prattling Parachito,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112280">Come you hither to abuse me. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e112290">She strikes him.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112300">Take this for your pains. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112310" who="A04896-gladiolus">
            <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112320">Now thank thy stars, that with a female signature</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112330">Did stamp thy sex, audacious strumpet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112340">Shall I draw? no, now I think on't I will not;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112350">For reason and experience shows, that no man</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112360">Ere gained repute by drawing 'gainst a woman. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112370" who="A04896-unassigned">
            <speaker>Dl.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112380">Stripling, dost think I fear a naked blade;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112390">I'll meet thee where thou dar'st, and whip thee too</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112400">For thy unruly tongue, thy sauciness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112410" who="A04896-gladiolus">
            <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112420">Well minion, remember this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112430">If I do not cry you quit for this abuse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112440">Then let me ne'er be trusted:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112450">Your mistress shall know how you have used me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112460">So she shall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112470" who="A04896-clematis">
            <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112480">Skippiake tell what you can, I weight not this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112490">I'll make you know that you have done amiss. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e112500">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e112510">
          <pb facs="26"/>
          <head>Act. 3: scen. 2.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e112520">Poneria, eglantine.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112530" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112540">Forget you not the powder for your breath,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112550" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112560">I took a dram of it this morning,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112570">According to your appointment. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112580" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112590">Your pallid cheek requires, in mine opinion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112600">A deeper tincture of vermilion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112610" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112620">And I am of the same mind:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112630">But 'twas my maid's fault. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112640">I think she goes about utterly to undo me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112650">She is as good a servant as ere was</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112660">Married to the whipping. post. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112670" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112680">I tell you true I would not for twenty crowns</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112690">That Rhodon had seen you with this face. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112700">That ceruse on your brow is extremely dull,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112710">There is no lustre, no resplendency in it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112720">'Slight I have seen often times 'a stained cloth</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112730">Over a smoky chimney in an alehouse</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112740">Present me with a better face. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112750" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112760">Nay, I could not for my heart persuade</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112770">The wicked pertinacious harlot,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112780">To lay more colour on then pleased her fancy;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112790">Bat if I live I will cashier the quean. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112800" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112810">If you do not, you are no friend to yourself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112820" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112830">How likest thou the colour of my hair. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112840" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112850">O that is exceedingly well died. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112860" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112870">Methinks the hue is not high enough. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112880" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112890">Nay, pardon me madam: 'tis passing well. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112900">The brown hue is the most incomparable colour</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112910"><pb facs="27"/> for a hair of all other. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112920">Those golden wires that on fair Hero's shoulders dangle</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112930">And those fair flaxen threads that made Jove</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112940">Dote upon fair Nonacrine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112950">May not be compared with the lovely brown. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e112960" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112970">Discreet Poneria, thy wise approbation</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112980">Doth give my fancy ample satisfaction. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e112990">But hear me Poneria, will you undertake</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113000">That I shall meet with the shepherd Rhodon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113010">As you oft have promised me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113020" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113030">Fair shepherdess I will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113040" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113050">But 'tis a thing impossible I fear. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113060" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113070">Why so good eglantine? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113080" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113090">Because I hear he deeply is engaged</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113100">To Iris, that proud damsel of Hymettus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113110" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113120">I grant he is: and since things are thus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113130">I will so act my part, that his new love</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113140">Shall be the means to renew that good will</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113150">That hath been heretofore twixt him and you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113160" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113170">Nor Circe's drugs, nor all Ulysses' wits,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113180">I tell thee beldame, can accomplish this. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113190" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113200">Good daughter undervalue not my skill,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113210">For 'tis contrived how it shall be effected,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113220">And to satisfy thy curiosity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113230">I will declare how I have laid the plot. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113240" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113250">I prithee bless my ears with this relation. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113260" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113270">I will a message bear in Iris name,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113280">Unto the shepherd Rhodon, which shall show,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113290">That she desires an amorous interview</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113300">With him, in such a privacy</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113310">That day must not be guilty of it:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113320">A solitary glade shall be the place,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113330"><pb facs="27"/> where you protected by the veil of conscious night,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113340">Instead of Iris shall present yourself</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113350">Unto the shepherd Rhodon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113360">Whom you shall entertain with sweet discourse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113370">And so comport yourself, that he shall think,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113380">You are his dearest Iris. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113390">But to assure him yours, I have provided</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113400">A precious philtre of rare efficacy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113410">Composed according to the rudiments of art. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113420">This shall you cause him to carouse</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113430">As water of inestimable worth. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113440">Which done, he is your own;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113450">And Iris then shall be forgotten clean,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113460">As one whom he had ne'er scarce known or seen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113470" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113480">'Tis bravely plotted sweet Poneria:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113490">But what hour wilt thou allot for this design. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113500" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113510">Provide yourself to meet him in the myrtle grove</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113520">Upon eleven at night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113530" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113540">Very good. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113550" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113560">Now I'll to Rhodon go, and him invite,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113570">To meet you at the appointed place this night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113580" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113590">Now most auspicious be thy stars and mine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113600">Let all good luck attend our great design. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e113610">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e113620">
          <head>Act. 2. Scen. 3.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e113630">Martagon, Cynosbatus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113640" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113650">But is the angry swain (Sayest thou) so hot,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113660">Is Rhodon grown so zealous in his sister's cause? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113670" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113680">If that his actions with his words agree,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113690"><pb facs="28"/> I must expect a sudden storm. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113700" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113710">I am resolved to take part in thy fortunes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113720">Be they the worst that ere to any fell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113730" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113740">Thanks noble friend, than here let's join our hand</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113750">In sign of most unseparable bands. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113760" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113770">But there's Acanthus a jolly swain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113780">He frets (They say) like a furious Myrmidon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113790" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113800">In braving language he exceeded so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113810">That Martagon ne'er saw so bold a foe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113820">Surcharged with swelling passion, he did vow</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113830">To take a full revenge on me and you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113840" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113850">And is the youth so filled with valorous heat? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113860">Who would have thought the frozen mountains could</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113870">Have bred so brave a hotspur. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113880" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113890">These raging lions must, Cynosbatus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113900">Be undermined by some egregious sleight;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113910">We must pitch some strong toil for these fierce beasts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113920">Where we may take them captive at our pleasure:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113930">For if we should assail them openly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113940">Much peril than we might incur thereby. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113950" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113960">What thy high judgement shall conclude to do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113970">I am resolved to condescend unto. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e113980" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e113990">Then hear what I propound. Cynosbatus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114000">Within a place nigh hand, resides</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114010">A beldame much renowned for sacred skill</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114020">In magic mysteries. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114030">She with her awful charms wonts to call forth</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114040">All sorts of noisome creatures that are bred</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114050">In sandy Lybia, or cold Scythia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114060">From whom she takes her choice of poison strong. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114070">The herbs which grow on precipitious Erix,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114080">She with her bloody sickle crops:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114090"><pb facs="28"/> and whatsoever poisonous weed springs on</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114100">The craggy top of snowy Caucasus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114110">That's sprinkled with the blood of wise Prometheus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114120">She carefully selects;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114130">Those venoms which the warlike Medians, and</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114140">The nimble Parthians, or Arabians rich,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114150">Use to anoint their deadly shafts withal. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114160">She doth by moonlight gather;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114170">Each herb that in this fertile vernal season</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114180">Puts forth its head from Ops's pregnant bosom</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114190">She searches for; whether the same be bred</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114200">In the cold forest of Hercynea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114210">Or in the deserts of parched Afrique,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114220">What flower soe'er doth in his seed or root</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114230">Strange causes of great mischief nourish,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114240">She never faileth to find out:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114250">Whether the same on banks of Tigris grows,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114260">Or on the sunburnt brink of warm Hydaspes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114270">Whose golden channels paved with precious stones;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114280">Some of these herbs she doth by twilight gather,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114290">At midnight some, and some at break of day. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114300">Nor is she ignorant how to apply</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114310">The panting heart of the dull melancholy owl,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114320">Or the breathing entrails cut from a living cat. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114330">The proudest swain that lives in Thessaly</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114340">Is glad to be obsequious to her will;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114350">For in her power it is to cure or kill. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114360">Unto this reverent sibyl let us go,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114370">And her advice request in this design;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114380">By her instructions let us our actions regulate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114390">Providing for our own security:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114400">She can divine of all events, and tell</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114410"><pb facs="29"/> whether things shall succeed or ill or well. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e114420" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114430">What thy sound judgement thinks fit to be done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114440">I condescend to, noble martagon. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e114450">
          <head>Act. 3. Scen. 4.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e114460">Rhodon, Anthophotus, Acanthus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e114470" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114480">Since that the proud usurper Martagon</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114490">Will not restore what he hath ta'en away</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114500">By force and injury from Violetta,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114510">We are resolved to put on lawful arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114520">To suage the pride of that great termagant;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114530">That of his prowess doth so vainly vaunt. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114540">Therefore dear friends address yourselves to show</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114550">Your true and faithful fortitudes, for know</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114560">An ignominious peace may not compare,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114570">With any just and honourable war. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e114580" who="A04896-anthophotus">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114590">Out upon this Fabian valour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114600">These tedious cunctations: I tell thee Rhodon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114610">I must needs chide thee for our loss of time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114620">My troops are all in perfect readiness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114630">And long to meet their foes in open field;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114640">If we deliberate a day longer</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114650">The edge of their valour (I fear) will be quite taken off. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e114660" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114670">Now fie upon that valour which depends</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114680">On circumstance of time or place,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114690">'Tis relative virtue, that like glass is brittle,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114700">Whose force soon dies and perfects very little,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e114710" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114720">Now recollect thy spirits Rhodon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114730">Let Spartan resolution spread itself</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114740"><pb facs="29"/> into each angle of thy noble heart. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114750">For now our hostile forces are assembled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114760">Covering the fields from Ossa to Olympus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114770">Their painted banners with the winds are playing:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114780">Their pampered coursers thunder on the plains:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114790">The splendour of their glistering arms repels</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114800">The bashful sunbeams back unto the clouds. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114810">Their bellowing drums and trumpets shrill,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114820">Do many sad corrantoes sound,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114830">Which danger grim and sprawling death must dance. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114840">Now therefore Rhodon, do reflect thy eye</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114850">Upon the glories of thy ancestors,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114860">And strive by emulation to transcend</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114870">Those trophies which were yet never paralleled. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e114880" who="A04896-anthophotus">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114890">Surcease this needless talk, let us to action,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114900">The loss of time consisteth in protraction. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e114910" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114920">Your noble courages, endeared friends,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114930">A good event to our designs portends. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e114940">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e114950">
          <head>Act. 3. Scen. 5.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e114960">Martagon, Cynosbatus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e114970" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114980">Within the precincts of this grove Poneria dwells,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e114990">Here nightly she hath conventicles</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115000">With her wise spirits; see how the trees are carved</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115010">With magical mysterious characters,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115020">See how the fiery fiends with their frequent resort have</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115030">Scorched the leaves, and changed the</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115040">Merry livery of the spring into a mournful hue. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115050">Behold the grass died with the swarthy gore</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115060"><pb facs="30"/> of some great sacrifice, that late was offered up</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115070">To the infernal powers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e115080" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115090">The black aspect of this strange uncouth place</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115100">Doth make my heart to quake. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e115110" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115120">Within a vault hewn from the stony bowels,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115130">Of you high precipicious rock she dwells. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115140">Cheer up (Cynosbatus) and come away,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115150">Let's to her cell, and I'll show thee the way. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A04896-e115160">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e115170">
          <head>Act. 4: scen. 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e115180">Iris, Panace, Violetta.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e115190" who="A04896-iris">
            <speaker>Ir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115200">Cursed was the wight that did in murder first</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115210">Imbrue his guilty hands: cursed was that hand</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115220">Which first was taught by damned hellish art</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115230">To forge the killing blade in Vulcan's flames:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115240">What raging fury reigns in mortal breasts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115250">That man should man pursue with deadly hate;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115260">O what malignant power hath defaced,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115270">That specious image of the gods above? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115280">Who hath inspired man with that bestial quality</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115290">Of murderous revenge? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115300">The Lybian lions seldom are at odds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115310">The tigers of Hyrcania do agree,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115320">But man to man's become a very devil:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115330">That Thracian god which is delighted most</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115340">With humane sacrifices, is now adored;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115350">Bloodthirsty Mars now bears the only sway,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115360">Who direful devastations doth affect,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115370">Peace hath forsook the earth, and fell debate</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115380"><pb facs="30"/> shaking his battered arms, now stalketh everywhere . </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115390">I hoped for nuptials sweet, of late, but now</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115400">I may have cause to fear a funeral. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115410">Hymen affrighted with the confused noise</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115420">Of brutish war, is fled I know not whither. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115430">My dearest Rhodon must depart from me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115440">And in the field engage his tender corpse</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115450">To all extremities of death, of wounds, of danger,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115460">Of sickness and unrest:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e115470" who="A04896-violetta">
            <speaker>Vi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115480">Strike not the air with this vain language, Iris,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115490">Wound not thy soul with these unseemly plaints,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115500">But be content to wait the will of Jove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115510">Who will crown our designs with blessed success. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115520">For in a cause that's honest, just, and right,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115530">The gods themselves will take up arms and fight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e115540" who="A04896-iris">
            <speaker>Ir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115550">Then o ye powers, that are the grand protectors</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115560">Of Hybla's happiness and welfare;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115570">Whether ye do delight in our flower-crowned mountains,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115580">Our odorous vales, or in our crystal fountains,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115590">Your gracious favour I implore, besceching you</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115600">To guard the person of my dearest Rhodon;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115610">Fond woman, how forgetful have I been? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115620">Here is a gem whose price doth far transcend</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115630">All estimation: my faithful Panace</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115640">Delivered thou unto my gentle shepherd,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115650">And pray him wear it for my sake. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e115660" who="A04896-panace">
            <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115670">Madam, I will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e115680" who="A04896-iris">
            <speaker>Ir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115690">It from the bowels of a cock was ta'en,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115700">And whoso wears the same (As wise men say)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115710">Shall ever be victorious in war. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e115720" who="A04896-violetta">
            <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115730">Commend me to my brother, gentle nymph,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115740">And bear this token of my love to him:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115750"><pb facs="31"/> it is the precious herb called Latice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115760">Which whosoever wears shall never want</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115770">Sufficient sustenance both for himself and his;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115780">Besides, it frustrates quite the devilish force</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115790">Of strongest poisons or enchantments. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e115800">Exit Pan.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115810">Now Iris, let us haste to Flora's fane,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115820">With our devotions let's importune her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115830">These horrid stirs and troublous broils to cease,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115840">That we again may live in happy peace. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e115850">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e115860">
          <head>Act. 4. Scen. 2.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e115870">Martagon, Cynosbatus, Poneria.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e115880" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115890">Divinest matron; god-inspired Sibyl</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115900">Do this, and be what thou canst desire. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e115910" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115920">Doubt not great martagon but I will effect it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e115930" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115940">Now dear Cynosbatus let us prepare</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115950">To resist th'impression of our foes:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115960">Since that our powerful forces ready stand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115970">To be obedient to our great command. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e115980" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e115990">With thee I am resolved to spend my breath,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116000">Indifferent in the choice of life or death. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e116010">Exeunt ma. Cy.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116020" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116030">Agnostus come forth: black cloud of ignorance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116040">Advance thy leaden pate ▪ dull camel. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116050" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116060">I cannot brook this thin and piercing air. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116070" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116080">Thou son of sleep; that hatest the lightsome day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116090">Clap on thy spectacles of judgement, and behold</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116100">How I have played my part. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116110">Thou flowest with gall (Agnostus) I confess,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116120">But thou hast a brain intolerably dry,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116130"><pb facs="31"/> as empty of wit, as the world is of conscience. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116140" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116150">What hast plucked up the flowers by the roots,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116160">Or is all Thessaly in a combustion? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116170" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116180">Surcharged with deep despite and viperous hate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116190">Their forces they against each other bend. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116200" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116210">Then I hope their painted pride shall quickly be abated. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116220" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116230">But I have a plot, old plumbeous dotard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116240">To crop the proudest flower that grows</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116250">In Hybla or Hymettus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116260" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116270">Poneria, I adore thy art and wisdom. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116280" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116290">This glass contains a rare confection:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116300">'Tis viper's blood mixed with the juice of aconite:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116310">This is the philtre, the sweet love-potion</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116320">Which Eglantine poor lovesick fool,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116330">Must commend to the shepherd Rhodon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116340">Who this night by my appointment,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116350">Is to meet her in the myrtle grove, under the</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116360">Name of Iris: now I'll to eglantine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116370">And bless her longing ears with these glad tidings. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116380" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116390">O great profound Poneria: never yet</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116400">Was any that could parallel thy wit. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e116410">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e116420">
          <head>Act. 4. Scen. 3.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e116430">Rhodon, Acanthus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116440" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116450">What hour of night is't friend Acanthus? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116460" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116470">Th'eleventh at least: for see Orion hath</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116480">Advanced very high his starry locks in our horizon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116490" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116500">Methinks the stars look very ruddy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116510">As if they did portend tempestuous weather. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116520" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker><pb facs="32"/>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116530">They do but blush to see what crimes are acted</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116540">By mortal under covert of the night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116550" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116560">Sawest thou yond star that northward fell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116570" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116580">I saw the blazing meteor stoop,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116590">And bend his course towards the humble centre. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116600" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116610">This seemed a glorious, and resplendent star,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116620">Yet was it but a gross ill tempered meteor. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116630">This meteor seemed as if it had been fixed</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116640">In an orb for a perpetuity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116650">Yet in a moment is it fallen, thou seest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116660">And who regards this foolish and ignoble fire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116670">Or looks upon the place from whence it fell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116680" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116690">He that by honourable means is raised,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116700">And hath his seat established on the square</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116710">Of never sliding virtue, cannot fall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116720" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116730">But if young Phaeton shall undertake</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116740">To guide the chariot of the great Apollo,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116750">And in that action shall miscarry, so</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116760">That the whole universe shall be engaged</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116770">To utter ruin and destruction,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116780">Then ought great Jove to have a special care</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116790">For to preserve and keep the common good. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116800">And if he shall dismount the charioteer,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116810">And with a deadly blow lay him along,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116820">The world then for his justice shall thank Jove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116830">And Phaeton's foolhardiness reprove. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116840" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116850">Who dares contest with Jove, or question what</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116860">His sovereign highness shall do or determine. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e116870">Enter Egl. Poneria.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116880" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rh.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116890">'Tis altogether wicked and unjust: (Acanthus) retire. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116900">For now methinks I see a glimpse of Iris,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116910">Who promised to meet me here this night. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e116920">Exit Ac.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116930"><pb facs="32"/>Lo how the lustre of her beauty penetrates</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116940">The en envious clouds of these nocturnal shades. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e116950" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116960">See yonder the beguiled lover walks</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116970">In vain, expecting the coming of his dear Iris,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116980">Now, eglantine remember my instructions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e116990">Have a care that your tongue betray you not. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117000">Be not too talkative in any case. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117010">Forget not the posture I so oft told you of,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117020">Under pretence that these cold nightly dews are</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117030">Offensive, you may knit your veil more close,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117040">And conceal your feature. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117050" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117060">Poneria, retire: I will address myself unto him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117070" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117080">But be sure you persuade him to take the</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117090">Potion before he sleeps;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117100">You'll remember those virtues which I told you it contains. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117110">Forget not to declare them amply. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117120" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117130">Make no doubt on't: thou hast armed me</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117140">For all assays. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e117150">Exit Pon,</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117160" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117170">Thou brightest star that shinest this night,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117180">Auspicious be thy influence to thy Rhodon. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117190">My dearest Iris, I am surcharged with joy</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117200">To meet thee here. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117210" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117220">(Dear Rhodon) who, like the vernal sun,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117230">Dost lend refreshing heats to my affections. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117240">Take't not amiss, that I have chose this hour</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117250">And unfrequented place t'enjoy thy company. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117260" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Pho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117270">Sweet Iris know that I esteem this hour of night,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117280">Since I enjoy thy sweet society,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117290">Above all the days that I e'er hitherto beheld. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117300" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117310">But from a maiden's modesty (Fair sir)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117320">It may seem much to derogate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117330">To be abroad so late at night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117340" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker><pb facs="33"/>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117350">Since no immodest act is here intended,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117360">The time cannot be prejudicial</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117370">To thy unstained modesty. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117380" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117390">Great pity 'tis indeed, sir, that true love</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117400">Should be disparaged, because 'tis so true. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117410" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117420">I tell thee, I till now was never happy:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117430">All those delights which I ere saw before,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117440">Were but mere transitory dreams,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117450">Compared with that felicity which now I find. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117460" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117470">The sudden news of this late kindled war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117480">Wherein I hear (To my great grief) you are engaged,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117490">Made me transgress the bounds of modesty so far,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117500">That I desired once more to see your face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117510">Ere your departure to the field of danger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117520" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117530">Since my good fortune and thy constant love</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117540">Have joyed me once again with thy sweet presence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117550">I bless my lot, and to the field will hasten,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117560">As ready to outface danger, as scorn death;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117570">And if I there find fortunate success,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117580">Of all my good I'll count thee patroness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117590" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117600">And here on you I do bestow this vial,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117610">Which such a precious dosis doth contain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117620">That it doth far exceed the height of value. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117630">It is a potion made by wondrous art,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117640">Nectar is no more comparable to it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117650">Than Bonniclabar is to Husquobath;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117660">And aurum potabile is as far short of it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117670">As poor metheglin is of rich canary:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117680">All the confections even from the lowest degree</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117690">Of sage-ale, to the height of aqua-celestis,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117700">Are no more like it then the beer of the Low-countries</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117710">Is to the high-country wine:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117720"><pb facs="33"/> a dram of it taken before you go to bed</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117730">Cheers the heart, prevents the incubus</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117740">And all frightful dreams; cheers the blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117750">Comforts the stomach, dispels all colics,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117760">Cures all aches, repairs the liver, helps</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117770">The lungs, rectifies the brain, quencheth</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117780">All the senses, strengthens the memory, refresheth</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117790">The spirits. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117800">Taken fasting it breaks the stone in bladder</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117810">Or kidneys, cures the gout, expels a quartane ague:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117820">Outwardly applied it kills the gangrene,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117830">And destroys the wolf, heals all sorts of wounds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117840">Bruises, boils, and sores. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117850">And not to use more multiplicity of words,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117860">I tell you gentle Rhodon you shall find,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117870">It cures all griefs of body and of mind. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117880" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117890">(Fair one) verbal expression cannot show</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117900">What I to thee for this great gift do owe:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117910">But till for all I full requital make,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117920">My constant love thou for a pledge shalt take. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e117930" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117940">But (Gentle sir) although your constitution</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117950">So well attempered seems, that no disease</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117960">Can either hurt or overthrow your health,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117970">Yet if my counsel might prevail with you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117980">I should persuade you to make trial of this</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e117990">Rare water this night before you sleep. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118000" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118010">Since thou vouchsaf'st to be my kind physician,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118020">For this time I will act a patient's part,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118030">And ere that sleep shall with his leaden keys</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118040">Lock up the portals of my drowsy eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118050">I'll taste of this most precious liquor:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118060">But lest the gealed moisture of the night</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118070"><pb facs="34"/> should prejudice thy health, (Sweet Iris)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118080">Let me conduct thee homeward. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118090" who="A04896-eglantine">
            <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118100">Since these nocturnal distillations</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118110">May be offensive to your health (Sweet Rhodon)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118120">I will be well contented to be gone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118130">Though wondrous loath from you to part so soon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118140" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118150">But in my absence be assured of this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118160">That Rhodon's heart in thy possession is. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e118170">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e118180">
          <head>Act. 4: scen. 4.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e118190">Panace sola.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118200" who="A04896-missing">
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118210">Upon this shady bank with laurels crowned,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118220">The gentle shepherd Rhodon dwells:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118230">His cottage seated is upon a crystal river,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118240">The sweetest stream that e'er in valley crept. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118250">Two precious presents I to him must bear:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118260">The one from his true love, the beauteous Iris,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118270">And that's a gem of admirable virtue;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118280">The bounty of the Eastern mines could never bestow</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118290">A jewel of such worth as this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118300">Which from the entrails of a cock was ripped;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118310">For whosoever shall possess the same,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118320">Shall be invincible in fight. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118330">But his dear sister, lovely Violetta,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118340">Commends to him this admirable plant,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118350">The noblest herb that e'er in garden grew. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118360">For, setting many precious properties aside,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118370">It is the best and strongest antidote</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118380">That art or nature ever made. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118390"><pb facs="34"/>No deadly poison can withstand its power,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118400">But is expulsed by it with great facility. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118410">These noble gifts beseeming well</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118420">Both the receivers and the giver's qualities,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118430">I will deliver to the honoured swain. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e118440">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e118450">
          <head>Act. 4. Scen. 5.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e118460">Martagon, Cynosbatus, Poneria,</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118470" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118480">Sage dame, how fares thy grand design? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118490">Dost think thy plot will take? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118500" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118510">Nay, if you doubt it, I wish it ne'er might take. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118520">Have I made hell a party in the action,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118530">And laid such snares, that more than humane force</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118540">Cannot withstand my well knit stratagem;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118550">Yet will you still torment me with these doubts? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118560" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118570">Nay gentle mother, be not so impatient. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118580" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118590">You tempt my patience, while you thus mistrust</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118600">My skill and my ability. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118610" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118620">We do adore thy matchless skill and wisdom,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118630">Thou grace and wonder of thy sex. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118640" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118650">Methinks I see the merry post at hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118660">That brings us joyful news of Rhodon's death:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118670">And not behind him much methinks I see</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118680">Another post, who comes with better news,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118690">That Rhodon's army is discouraged and discarded,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118700">Yea quite disbanded and dispersed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118710" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118720">O happy news (Divine Poneria) </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118730" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118740">Yet ye account me a mere silly dame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118750">Yea as silly as some simple simpering citizen. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118760"><pb facs="35"/>That hath but manners enough to take</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118770">The upper end of a table at a feast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118780">And to carve a capon's leg to a coxcomb. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118790" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118800">The en sybils were no more comparable to thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118810">Than an old gentlewoman is to a young chambermaid. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118820">Sweet Poneria, I am even in love with thee:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118830">Yea, I durst almost swear I should kiss thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118840">If thou hadst but three rotten teeth in thy head. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118850" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118860">Well, my masters, I hope you'll thank me</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118870">When you hear that I have made proud Rhodon</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118880">A Legier ambassador in don Pluto's court. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118890" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118900">Thy thanks, Poneria, shall be duly paid</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118910">In eye bewitching talents;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118920">We'll rip the matrice of our grandam earth</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118930">To see the place where riches are conceived;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118940">And from her pregnant womb we'll draw</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118950">A golden age for thee to live in (Dear Poneria) </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e118960" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118970">Who would leave any villainy undone,</l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e118980">Exit pone.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e118990">To be thy slave, most noble martagon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119000" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119010">Now Martagon let us go put on arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119020">And towards Hybla march in strong array. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119030">Let us deface the glory of their flowers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119040">If Rhodon be but dead, the day is ours. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A04896-e119050">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e119060">
          <head>Act. 5. Scen. 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e119070">Acanthus. Anthophotus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119080" who="A04896-anthophotus">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119090">Thou speak'st of things beyond belief, Acanthus,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119100" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119110">Too true it is, I shrewdly fear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119120">For every circumstance makes it appear</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119130"><pb facs="35"/> that Rhodon in the myrtle grove, last night,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119140">Had private conference with Iris,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119150">From whom (It seems) he took the venomed potion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119160">For now he doth, in his extremest fits,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119170">Exclaim on the untruth of woman kind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119180">Bewailing the unlucky hour that did present</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119190">Your sister Iris to his sight. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e119200">Enter Pan.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119210" who="A04896-panace">
            <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119220">Anthophotus and Acanthus, you're well met. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119230" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119240">Nay, never worse, thou wouldst say, gentle Panace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119250">If thou knew'st all. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119260" who="A04896-panace">
            <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119270">What dire disaster hath befallen you, honoured friends? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119280">How fares the noble shepherd Rhodon? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119290" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119300">Rhodon's mishap's the cause of all our sorrow:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119310">Rhodon's betrayed, poisoned, and lies at point of death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119320" who="A04896-panace">
            <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119330">Cursed be the hand that did attempt</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119340">A villainy so impious and foul. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119350">But if you love yourselves, and Rhodon's health,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119360">Conduct me to him immediately:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119370">I have an antidote that shall cure him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119380">If any breath be left within his bulk. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119390" who="A04896-anthophotus">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119400">O happy comfort! come sweet Panace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119410">To our sick friend, we'll thy conductors be. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e119420">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e119430">
          <head>Act. 5. Scen. 2.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e119440">Martagon, Cynosbatus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119450" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119460">A happy morn be this to thee (Friend Martagon,) </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119470" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119480">Nay, 'tis the happiest morn. that e'er we two beheld</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119490">Rhodon is dead;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119500">And is by this time, served up in a wooden dish,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119510"><pb facs="36"/> to feast the worms upon an earthen table;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119520">The purple bosomed rose whose glorious pride</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119530">Disdained the beauties of all other flowers, is cropped,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119540">Yea the ambitious bramble is quite withered,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119550">And now is laid in the contemned dust:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119560">Poneria's wit hath done this noble act. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119570" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119580">This is good news, I must confess, yet could I wish</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119590">That noble Rhodon had not so ignobly died. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119600" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119610">Thou art too ceremonious for a politician,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119620">And too superstitious: our duties 'tis to judge</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119630">Of the effect as it concerns the state of our affairs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119640">And not to look back on the means by which 'twas wrought. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119650">He is unfit to rule a civil state</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119660">That knows not how in some respects to favour</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119670">Murder, or treason, or any other sin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119680">Which that subtle animal, called man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119690">Doth openly protest against, for this end,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119700">That he may more freely act it in private,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119710">As his occasions shall invite him to't. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119720">But 'tis no disputing now; the deed is done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119730">We are in a fair way to victory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119740">Conquest, triumph, and renown;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119750">We have a fair beginning, and what's well begun,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119760">(If that the proverb speaks truth) is half done. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e119770">Exunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e119780">
          <head>Act. 5. Scen. 3.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e119790">Poneria. Agnostus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119800" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119810">Now Agnostus, since by the death of Rhodon</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119820">We have endeared ourselves to martagon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119830"><pb facs="36"/> 'tis meet we provide for a back winter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119840">That we purchase some eminence of place,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119850">To make us glorious in the world's ill-sighted eye,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119860">That being great we may the greater mischief do:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119870">And since a war is newly set abroach,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119880">I will a suitor be to general Martagon;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119890">To place thee in some military office</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119900">Of high regard and special consequence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119910">Where by thy ignorant conduct and base carriage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119920">Thou mayest a thousand heroic souls send packing</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119930">Unto the Stygian shore. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119940" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A04896-e119950">Nay good Poneria, I find myself unfitting for the wars.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e119960" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119970">What neither heart nor brains; out inglorious losel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119980">Thou most unwieldy burden of the earth:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e119990">I could find in my heart to kick thy soul out</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120000">Of thy carcase: art all composed of earth and water? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120010">Hast not a spark of air or fire in that bulk? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120020" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120030">Nay sweet Poneria, I am thy slave. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120040" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120050">I tell thee I will procure thee a captain's place. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120060" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A04896-e120070">But I am altogether ignorant in the words of command,</p>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120080">And know not one posture neither of musket or pike. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120090" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120100">Hast wit enough to swallow the dead pays,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120110">And to patch up thy company in a mustring day:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120120">Hast valour enough to wear a buff-jerkin</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120130">With three gold laces. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120140">Hast strength enough to support a Dutch feel</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120150">With a flaunting feather? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120160">Can thy side endure to be wedded to a rapier</l>
            <p xml:id="A04896-e120170">Hatched with gold, with hilt and hangers of the new fashion?</p>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120180"><pb facs="37"/>Canst drink, drab, and dice:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120190">Canst damn thyself into debt among</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120200">Believing tradesmen;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120210">Hast manners enough to give thy lieutenant,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120220">Ancient or sergeant leave to go before thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120230">Upon any piece of danger? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120240">Hast wit enough, in thy anger, not to draw a sword? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120250">These are the chief properties that pertain</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120260">To our modern captains; and if thou</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120270">Couldst but be taught these military rudiments,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120280">I doubt not but thou mightst prove a very</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120290">Excellent new soldier. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120300" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120310">If this be all, I hope, in time, to be as famous</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120320">As e'er was Caesar, or great Pompey. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120330" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120340">Agnostus, come along, thyself prepare</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120350">To be a servant to the god of war. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e120360">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e120370">
          <head>Act. 5. Scen. 4.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e120380">Rhodon. Acanthus. Anthophotus. Panace.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120390" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120400">This strange imposture hath amazed me so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120410">That I am almost to a statue struck,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120420">Not knowing what to speak, or what to think. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120430" who="A04896-panace">
            <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120440">Assure yourself it was a strange collusion:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120450">For this, on my fidelity, believe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120460">That 'twas not Iris whom you met last night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120470" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120480">Then 'twas some hellish hag, that, in her shape,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120490">Gave me the venomous confection</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120500">Which had undone me quite, if thou in time</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120510">Hadst not applied thy precious antidote. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120520"><pb facs="37"/>But yet, methinks , that heaven should not permit</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120530">The subtlest hellish power to counterfeit</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120540">The feature of so beautiful an angel. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120550" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120560">Doubtless it was the false Poneria's plot,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120570">Whom martagon hath lately entertained,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120580">With her companion; old Agnostus;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120590">For, know the malice of your foes is such,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120600">That if by open force they can't destroy you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120610">By hidden plots they'll seek your overthrow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120620" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120630">Then I must pardon crave of gentle Iris,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120640">To whom I did ascribe this treacherous fact. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120650" who="A04896-anthophotus">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120660">If she were guilty of so black a deed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120670">These hands should chain her to a fatal stake,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120680">And sacrifice her corpse in hideous flames,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120690">Unto the awful goddess of revenge;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120700">(Which done) I'd throw her hateful ashes up</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120710">Against the furious gusts of boisterous winds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120720">That being so dispersed, there might remain</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120730">Not the least relic of so vile a wretch. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120740" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120750">My Iris is as clear as innocency itself;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120760">And since my treacherous foes have gone about,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120770">By wicked slights, to wrong so sweet a saint,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120780">And bring me also to a shameful end,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120790">I here enjoin ye (Honourable friends)</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120800">Upon my sword to take a solemn oath,</l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e120810">He draws his sword, they lay their hands upon it, and kiss it.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120820">Never to lay down your just and lawful arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120830">Until we be avenged to the full,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120840">For such unkindly and disloyal wrongs:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120850">True honour, that with dearest blood is sought,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120860">Is like a precious gem that's cheaply bought. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120870" who="A04896-anthophotus">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120880">Ill is a life bestowed upon that wight</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120890"><pb facs="38"/> that dares not lose it to maintain the right:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120900">Him I account a base inglorious sot,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120910">That dares not honour pull from danger's throat. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e120920">Exeunt:</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e120930">
          <head>Act. 5. Scen. 5.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e120940">Martagon, Cynosbatus, Agnostus, Poneria.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120950" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120960">Lady Poneria, upon your commendation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120970">We bestow a regiment upon this gentleman. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e120980" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e120990">Thanks (Worthy martagon) believe it sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121000">Those good respects which I to your affairs owe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121010">Urged me t'importune you for his employment,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121020">Because I know him to be a tried soldier,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121030">Of great experience, worth and merit:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121040">How say you, colonel Agnostus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121050">I hope your actions shall make good my words hereafter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121060" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121070">I am at your service, madam Poneria:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121080">I am a man of action, I confess. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121090" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121100">Trust me sir, although he wants verbal expression,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121110">He is a gentleman of singular abilities. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121120" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121130">And I think no less, for they're not good words</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121140">That makes deserving soldiers, but good swords. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121150" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121160">He looks as if he had been bred, born,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121170">And brought up in a leaguer all his life time. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e121180">Enter Gladiolus.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121190" who="A04896-gladiolus">
            <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121200">Noble general; the beauteous eglantine</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121210">Wisheth all happiness to your designs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121220">Desiring that this paper may kiss your hands for her. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e121230">He opens the letter.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121240" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121250">'Tis about a place, I'll pawn my life on't:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121260"><pb facs="38"/> hear me monsieur, I understand the business:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121270">Her request is granted. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121280">She when she please, may at my hands command</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121290">A greater courtesy than this. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121300" who="A04896-gladiolus">
            <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121310">Thanks honoured sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121320" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121330">On you I bestow a captain's place. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121340" who="A04896-gladiolus">
            <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121350">Now I perceive that the readiest way to attain</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121360">Preferment in the court of Mars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121370">Is to creep into the favour of Venus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121380" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121390">I understand you are a man of real worth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121400">And very sufficient for such an office. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e121410">Enter Acanthus</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121420" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121430">Imperious martagon, that art no less</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121440">Known for thy power, than thy wickedness:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121450">In Rhodon's name I do defy thee here,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121460">Who challengeth the combat at thy hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121470">To be avenged on thee for thy foul wrongs:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121480">But if thou dar'st not in a single fight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121490">Give satisfaction to the noble shepherd;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121500">Then thee and all thy troops he doth invite,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121510">To a bloody breakfast tomorrow morn. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121520">Attended by a vigorous army he</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121530">Stands in the confines of his own dominions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121540">Swearing that he will prove it in the field,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121550">That thou a tyrant and a traitor art. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121560" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121570">Bold friend, I prithee speak ingeniously,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121580">Doth this defiance come from Rhodon's mouth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121590" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121600">Upon my life, and by the honour of a soldier it doth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121610" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121620">Then tell him, I'm resolved to be a guest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121630">More bold than welcome at his bloody feast. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121640" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121650">I will great Martagon; and misdoubt not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121660">But that your cheer shall be exceeding hot. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e121670">Exit Aca.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121680" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121690">Dissembling witch: how hast thou beguiled us? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121700" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker><pb facs="39"/>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121710">What adverse power hath crossed our plot? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121720" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121730">Didst not thou with thy deep protestations force us</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121740">To give strong credence to thy false relations,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121750">When thou affirmedst that thou hadst poisoned Rhodon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121760" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121770">The opposition of the cursed fates</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121780">Hath brought us to deserved confusion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121790" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121800">Avaunt you hag, abominable sorceress,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121810">Here I do thee on pain of death enjoin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121820">With that impostor thy companion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121830">Immediately to depart out of my dominions. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121840" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121850">Now I accursed wretch have seen too well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121860">That heaven will not be overruled by hell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121870" who="A04896-agnostus">
            <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121880">How suddenly by one contrarious gust,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121890">Is all our honour tumbled into dust. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121900" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121910">Since that our braving foe is now at hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121920">(Cynosbatus) we must not think of a retreat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121930" who="A04896-cynobastus">
            <speaker>Cy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121940">What your discretion holds fit to be done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121950">I condescend to noble martagon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e121960" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121970">Then let us meet our proud foe face to face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121980">And with our swords and spears that right maintain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e121990">Which lately we by sword and spear did gain. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e122000">Exeunt.</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A04896-e122010">
          <head>Act. 5. Scen. 6.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A04896-e122020">Rhodon, Anthophotus, Acanthus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122030" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122040">Deserving friends and fellow soldiers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122050">Now arm yourselves with Roman fortitude:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122060">First call to mind the justice of our cause,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122070">And then let each remember that true honour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122080">Which must be valued above health and life:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122090"><pb facs="39"/> consider also that we must contend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122100">Against a tyrant and a mere usurper;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122110">A person guilty of no mean offences,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122120">Which must be justly punished by our swords. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e122130">Enter Poneria, Agnostus.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122140" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122150">Thrice noble Rhodon, in whose noble breast</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122160">True pity dwells, vouchsafe a pardon</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122170">To us distressed caitives. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122180" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122190">I neither know what your offences are, nor yet yourselves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122200" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122210">I am the unfortunate Poneria,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122220">That was suborned by unjust martagon</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122230">To work thy utter ruin:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122240">I did conduct the lovesick eglantine</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122250">Unto thy presence instead of Iris:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122260">I caused her to give thee a poisonous drink,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122270">Under the pretence that it was a love-potion. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122280">I have deserved to die, and crave life at your hands. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122290" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122300">And are you the grand incendiary</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122310">That have so many mischiefs wrought in Thessaly? </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122320">Now I remember I have seen your elvish countenance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122330">Nor have I altogether forgotten your reverent mate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122340">Who with his personated gravity deludes the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122350">Being accounted a man of profound art. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122360">Acanthus, see them committed to safe custody,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122370">See you make them sure for starting. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e122380">Exeunt po. Ag. Ac.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122390" who="A04896-poneria">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122400">Nay worthy sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122410" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122420">You must away, for no entreaties can prevail. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122430" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122440">The apprehension of these wretches doth presage</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122450">Auspicious fortunes to our actions;</l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e122460">Drum beats a march within</stage>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122470">List, list, Anthophotus, our enemies are at hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122480">Their thundering drums warn us of their approach. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122490">We'll bid them nobly welcome then: this day will I</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122500"><pb facs="40"/> victorious be (I vow) or bravely die. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122510" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122520">Thy honoured resolution I commend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122530">And take it for a sign of good success. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e122540">Enter Acan.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122550" who="A04896-acanthus">
            <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122560">Arm, arm: the hostile forces are in sight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122570">And thus come marching on in proud array:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122580">The battle's led by Martagon himself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122590">Wherein are marshaled near five thousand bill men,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122600">All clad in coats of red:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122610">A furious Amazon called Tulipa,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122620">Brings on three thousand burley Swissers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122630">Arrayed in gorgeous coats of red and yellow;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122640">And these make up the van:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122650">To which are added for a forlorn hope,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122660">Two hundred melancholy gentlemen. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122670">The fierce Cynosbatus brings up the rear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122680">Wherein about two thousand soldiers be</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122690">Clad all in green, and armed with pikes of steel. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122700">Narcissus with a thousand daffodils,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122710">Clad in deep yellow coats doth flank</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122720">The right side of the battle. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122730">The left wing is by Hyacinthus led,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122740">Wherein a thousand soldiers march,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122750">Arrayed in purple coats. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e122760">Enter Martagon, Rhodon.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122770" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122780">What fury tempted thee unhappy Rhodon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122790">In hostile manner thus to invade my confines. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122800" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122810">For Violetta's sake I took up arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122820">Whom thou unjustly hast oppressed. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e122830">Music sound,</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122840" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122850">What I have done my sword shall justify. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122860" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122870">Whence comes this most harmonious melody. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e122880">Enter Flora, Iris, eglantine, Panace.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122890" who="A04896-flora">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A04896-e122900">Put up those murdering blades on pain of my displeasure,</p>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122910"><pb facs="40"/>Confine them to perpetual prison in the scabbard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122920">That they may ne'er come forth to manage civil broils. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122930" who="A04896-all">
            <speaker>All.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122940">We must obey, and will, o awful goddess. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e122950" who="A04896-flora">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122960">While in my flowery bowers I took repose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122970">I heard the noise of these tumultuous broils,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122980">Which struck me with a wonderful amazement. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e122990">Then hastily I left my banks of pleasure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123000">And hither came to end these mortal jars;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123010">Therefore I charge you both on that allegiance</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123020">And respect which you do owe to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123030">Quite to dismiss your armed bands. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123040">And you martagon, who have fair Violetta wronged,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123050">To her shall make an ample restitution,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123060">Of what you've ta'en from her;</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123070">And entertain a friendly league with Rhodon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123080">Which you Cynosbatus must also condescend to:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123090">But as for you fond madam eglantine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123100">Since you have broke the sacred laws of love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123110">And by unlawful means sought to accomplish</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123120">Your designs, and make the shepherd Rhodon</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123130">Enamoured on you:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123140">You to a vestal temple shall be confined,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123150">Where with ten years penance</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123160">You shall expiate your folly. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123170">But where be those two intruders</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123180">Poneria and Agnostus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123190">These that have crept in among us, and with false slights</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123200">Sought to o'erthrow our state. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A04896-e123210">Poneria and Agnostus brought.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123220">We banish them quite</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123230">Out of Thessaly for ever. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123240">What I have decreed you must assent unto. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e123250" who="A04896-martagon">
            <speaker><pb facs="41"/>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123260">We do, because we must. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e123270" who="A04896-flora">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123280">Rhodon, I here bestow on thee this noble shepherdess. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e123290" who="A04896-rhodon">
            <speaker>Rho.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123300">Thanks for your precious gift, renowned Queen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A04896-e123310" who="A04896-flora">
            <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123320">And now since all things are reduced to joyful peace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123330">Let us betake ourselves to sweet delights,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04896-e123340">And solemnize with mirth your nuptial rites. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A04896-e123350">
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="A04896-e123360">
        <head>Epilogue.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A04896-e123370">
          <l xml:id="A04896-e123380">Since ignorance and envy now are banished;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e123390">Since discord from among the flowers is vanished;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e123400">Since Rhodon is espoused to Iris bright;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e123410">Since war hath happy Thessaly left quite,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e123420">Let every one that loves his country's peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04896-e123430">His height of gladness with his hands express. </l>
        </lg>
        <trailer xml:id="A04896-e123440">Finis.</trailer>
        <pb facs="41"/>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A04896"><item xml:id="A04896-poneria" n="58">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-poneria</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">58</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-rhodon" n="46">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-rhodon</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">46</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-martagon" n="44">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-martagon</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">44</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-eglantine" n="33">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-eglantine</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">33</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-acanthus" n="24">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-acanthus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">24</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-cynobastus" n="23">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-cynobastus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">23</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-agnostus" n="23">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-agnostus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">23</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A04896-anthophotus" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-anthophotus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-gladiolus" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-gladiolus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-clematis" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-clematis</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-panace" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-panace</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-iris" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-iris</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-flora" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-flora</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-violetta" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-violetta</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-messenger" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-missing" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-missing</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-all" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04896-unassigned" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A04896-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

