<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A12030">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>A Yorkshire Tragedy <date type="creation_date">1606</date></title>
        <author>anon.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Madeline Burg</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A12030.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A Yorkshire tragedy. Not so new as lamentable and true. Acted by his Maiesties Players at the Globe. VVritten by VV. Shakspeare.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>16 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99842052</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 22340.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 272(a).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">6675</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12030</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A Yorkshire tragedy. Not so new as lamentable and true. Acted by his Maiesties Players at the Globe. VVritten by VV. Shakspeare.</title>
            <title type="alt">Yorkshiere tragedy.</title>
            <author>Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[32] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by R[ichard] B[radock] for Thomas Pauier and are to bee sold at his shop on Cornhill, neere tot he [sic] exchange,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1608.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Not in fact by Shakespeare.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Mostly in verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-D4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: A Yorkshiere tragedy.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A12030-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A12030-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A12030-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A12030-e100040">A Yorkshire tragedy. Not so new as lamentable and true.</p>
        <p xml:id="A12030-e100050">Acted by his majesty's players at the globe. </p>
        <p xml:id="A12030-e100060">Written by W. Shakespeare. </p>
        <p xml:id="A12030-e100070">At London printed by R. B. for Thomas Pavier and are to be sold at his shop on Cornhill, near to the exchange. 1608.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A12030-e100080">
      <div type="text" xml:id="A12030-e100090">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>All's one, or, one of the four plays in one, called a Yorkshire tragedy: as it was played by the King's majesty's players.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e100100">Enter Oliver and Ralph, two serving-men. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100110" who="A12030-oliver">
          <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100120">Sirrah Raph, my young mistress is in such a pitiful passionate humour for the long absence of her love,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100130" who="A12030-ralph">
          <speaker>Raph.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100140">Why can you blame her, why, apples hanging longer on the tree then when they are ripe, makes so many fallings. viz mad wenches because they are not gathered in time, are fain to drop of themselves, and then 'tis common you know for every man to take 'em up.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100150" who="A12030-oliver">
          <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100160">Mass thou sayest true, 'tis common indeed, but sirrah, is neither our young master returned, nor our fellow Sam come from London?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100170" who="A12030-ralph">
          <speaker>Ralph.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100180">Neither of either, as the Puritan bawd says. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100190">'Slid I hear Sam, sam's come, here's tarry, come, i'faith now my nose itches for news</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100200" who="A12030-oliver">
          <speaker>Oliue,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100210">And so does mine elbow. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100220"><pb facs="3"/>Sam calls within, where are you there? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100230" who="A12030-sam">
          <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100240">Boy look you walk my horse with discretion, I have rid him simply, I warrant his skin sticks to his back with very heat, if a should catch cold and get the cough of the lungs I were well served, were I not? What Raph and Oliver.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100250" who="A12030-ambo">
          <speaker>Am.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100260">Honest fellow Sam welcome i'faith, what tricks hast thou brought from London.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e100270">Furnished with things from London.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100280" who="A12030-sam">
          <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100290">You see I am hanged after the truest fashion, three hats, and two glasses, bobbing upon 'em, two rebato wires upon my breast, a capcase by my side, a brush at my back, an almanac in my pocket, and three ballads in my codpiece, nay I am the true picture of a common servingman.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100300" who="A12030-oliver">
          <speaker>Oliver</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100310">I'll swear thou art, thou mayst set up when thou wilt, there's many a one begins with less I can tell thee that proves a rich man ere he dies, but what's the news from London Sam. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100320" who="A12030-ralph">
          <speaker>Ralph.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100330">I that's well said, what's the news from London sirrah. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100340">My young mistress keeps such a puling for her love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100350" who="A12030-sam">
          <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100360">Why? the more fool she, ay, the more ninny hammer she.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100370" who="A12030-oliver">
          <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100380">Why Sam why?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100390" who="A12030-sam">
          <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100400">Why he's married to another long ago ▪</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100410" who="A12030-ambo">
          <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100420"> i'faith ye I est.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100430" who="A12030-sam">
          <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100440">Why, did you not know that till now? why, he's married, beats his wife, and has two or three children by her: for you must note that any woman bears the more when she is beaten.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100450" who="A12030-ralph">
          <speaker>Raph.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100460">I that's true for she bears the blows.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100470" who="A12030-oliver">
          <pb facs="3"/>
          <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100480">Sirrah Sam, I would not for two years wages, my young mistress knew so much, she run upon the left hand of her wit, and ne'er be here own woman again.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100490" who="A12030-sam">
          <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100500">And I think she was blessed in her cradle, that he never came in her bed, why he has consumed all, pawned his lands, and made his university brother stand in wax for him, there's a fine phrase for a scrivener, puh he owes more than his skins worth.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100510" who="A12030-oliver">
          <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100520">Is't possible.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100530" who="A12030-sam">
          <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100540">Nay I'll tell you moreover he calls his wife whore as familiarly as one would call mal and Dol, and his children bastards as naturally as can be, but what have we here, I thought 'twas somewhat pulled down my breeches: I quite forgotten my two potingsticks, these came from London, now any thing is good here that comes from London.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100550" who="A12030-oliver">
          <speaker>Oli.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100560">Ay, far fetched you know:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100570" who="A12030-sam">
          <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100580">But speak in your conscience i'faith, have not we as good potingsticks ith' country as need to be put ith' fire, the mind of a thing is all, the mind of a thing's all, and as thou saidst e'en now, far fetched is the best things for ladies.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100590" who="A12030-oliver">
          <speaker>Oliu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100600">Ay, and for waiting gentle women to.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100610" who="A12030-sam">
          <speaker>Sam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100620">But Ralph, what, is our beer sour this thunder?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100630" who="A12030-oliver">
          <speaker>Oli ▪</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100640">No no it holds countenance yet.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100650" who="A12030-sam">
          <speaker>Sam ▪</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100660">Why then follow me, I'll teach you the finest humour to be drunk in, I learned it at London last week.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100670" who="A12030-ambo">
          <speaker>Am ▪</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100680"> i'faith let's hear it, let's hear it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100690" who="A12030-sam">
          <speaker>Sam -</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e100700">The bravest humour, 'twould do a man good to<pb facs="4"/> be drunk in't, they call it knighting in London, when they drink upon their knees.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100710" who="A12030-unassigned">
          <speaker>Am.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100720">Faith that's excellent. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100730">Come follow me, I'll give you all the degrees on't in order. <stage xml:id="A12030-e100740">Exeunt.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e100750">Enter wife.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e100760" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100770">What will become of us? all will away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100780">My husband never ceases in expense,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100790">Both to consume his credit and his house? </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100800">And 'tis set down by heaven's just decree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100810">That riot's child must needs be beggary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100820">Are these the virtues that his youth did promise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100830">Dice, and voluptuous meetings, midnight revels,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100840">Taking his bed with surfeits. Ill beseeming</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100850">The ancient honour of his house and name:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100860">And this not all: but that which kills me most,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100870">When he recounts his losses and false fortunes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100880">The weakness of his state so much dejected,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100890">Not as a man repentant: but half mad:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100900">His fortunes cannot answer his expense:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100910">He sits and sullenly locks up his arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100920">Forgetting heaven looks downward, which makes him</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100930">Appear so dreadful, that he frights my heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100940">Walks heavily, as if his soul were earth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100950">Not penitent for those his sins are past:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100960">But vexed, his money cannot make them last. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100970">A fearful melancholy ungodly sorrow. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100980">O yonder he comes, now in despite of ills</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e100990">I'll speak to him, and I will hear him speak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101000">And do my best to drive it from his heart. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e101010"><pb facs="4"/>Enter husband. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101020" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101030">Pox o'th' last throw, it made</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101040">Five hundred angels vanish from my sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101050">I'm damned, I'm damned: the angels have forsook me</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101060">Nay 'tis certainly true: for he that has no coin</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101070">Is damned in this world: he's gone, he's gone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101080" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101090">Dear husband. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101100" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101110">Oh! most punishment of all I have a wife,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101120" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101130">I do entreat you as you love your soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101140">Tell me the cause of this your discontent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101150" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101160">A vengeance strip thee naked, thou art cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101170">Effect, quality, property ▪ thou, thou, thou. <stage xml:id="A12030-e101180">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101190" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101200">Bad, turned to worse?</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101210">Both beggary of the soul, as of the body. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101220">And so much unlike himself at first,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101230">As if some vexed spirit</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101240">Had got his form upon him. <stage xml:id="A12030-e101250">Enter husband again.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101260">He comes again:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101270">He says I am the cause, I never yet</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101280">Spoke less than words of duty, and of love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101290" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e101300">If marriage be honourable, than cuckolds are honourable, for they cannot be made without marriage.</p>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e101310">Fool: what meant I to marry to get beggars? now must my eldest son be a knave or nothing, he cannot live upo'th fool, for he will have no land to maintain him: that mortgage sits like a snaffle upon mine inheritance, and makes me chaw upon iron. My second son must be a promoter, and my third a thief, or an underputter, a slave pander.</p>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101320"><pb facs="5"/>O beggary, beggary, to what base uses dost thou put a man. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101330">I think the devil scorns to be a bawd. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101340">He bears himself more proudly, has more care on's credit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101350">Base slavish abject filthy poverty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101360" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101370">Good sir; by all our vows I do beseech you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101380">Show me the true cause of your discontent? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101390" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101400">Money, money, money, and thou must supply me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101410" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101420">Alas, I am the least cause of your discontent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101430">Yet what is mine, either in rings or jewels</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101440">Use to your own desire, but I beseech you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101450">As you're a gentleman by many bloods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101460">Though I myself be out of your respect</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101470">Think on the state of these three lovely boys</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101480">You have been father to. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101490" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101500">Puh bastards, bastards, bastards, begotten in tricks, begotten in tricks. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101510" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101520">Heaven knows how those words wrong me? but I may,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101530">Endure these griefs among a thousand more. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101540">O, call to mind your lands already mortgage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101550">Yourself wound into debts, your hopeful brother,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101560">At the university in bonds for you</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101570">Like to be ceased upon. and</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101580" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101590">Ha done thou harlot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101600">Whom though for fashion's sake I married,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101610">I never could abide? thinkst thou thy words</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101620">Shall kill my pleasures, fall of to thy friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101630">Thou and thy bastards beg: I will not bate</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101640"><pb facs="5"/> a whit in humour? midnight still I love you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101650">And revel in your company; curbed in,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101660">Shall it be said in all societies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101670">That I broke custom, that I flagged in money,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101680">No, those thy jewels, I will play as freely</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101690">As when my state was fullest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101700" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101710">Be it so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101720" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>H -</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101730">Nay I protest, and take that for an earnest,<stage xml:id="A12030-e101740">Spurns her</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101750">I will for ever hold thee in contempt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101760">And never touch the sheets that cover thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101770">But be divorced in bed till thou consent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101780">Thy dowry shall be sold to give new life</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101790">Unto those pleasures which I most affect</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101800" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101810">Sir do but turn a gentle eye on me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101820">And what the law shall give me leave to do</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101830">You shall command. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101840" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101850">Look it be done, shall I want dust and like a slave</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101860">Wear nothing in my pockets but my hands</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101870">To fill them up with nails.<stage xml:id="A12030-e101880">Holding his hands in his pockets.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101890">O much against my blood, let it be done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101900">I was never made to be a looker on:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101910">A bawd to dice? I'll shake the drabs myself</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101920">And make 'em yield, I say look it be done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101930" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e101940">I take my leave it shall. <stage xml:id="A12030-e101950">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101960" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e101970">Speedily, speedily, I hate the very hour I chose a wife a trouble trouble, three children like three evils hang upon me, fie, fie, fie, strumpet, and bastards, strumpet and bastards.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e101980">Enter three gentlemen hearing him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e101990" who="A12030-gentleman_1">
          <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102000">Still do those loathsome thoughts jar on<pb facs="6"/> your tongue. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102010">Yourself to stain the honour of your wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102020">Nobly descended, those whom men call mad</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102030">Endanger others; but he's more than mad</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102040">That wounds himself, whose own words do proclaim</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102050">Scandals unjust, to soil his better name:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102060">It is not fit I pray forsake it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102070" who="A12030-gentleman_2">
          <speaker>2 gentleman </speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102080">Good sir, let modesty reprove you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102090" who="A12030-gentleman_3">
          <speaker>3. Gentleman </speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102100">Let honest kindness sway so much with you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102110" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102120">God den, I thank you sir, how do you, adieu,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102130">I'm glad to see you, farewell instructions, admonitions. <stage xml:id="A12030-e102140">Exeun gent ▪</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e102150">Enter a servant.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102160" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e102170">How now sirrah what would you,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102180" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Servant</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e102190">Only to certify you sir, that my mistress was met by the way, by them who were sent for her up to London by her honourable uncle, your worship's late guardian.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102200" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e102210">So sir, than she is gone and so may you be:</p>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e102220">But let her look that the thing be done she wots of: or hell will stand more pleasant than her house at home.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e102230">Enter a gentle man.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102240" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102250">Well or ill met I care not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102260" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102270">No nor I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102280" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102290">I am come with confidence to chide you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102300" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102310">Who me? chide me? do't finely then: let it not move me, for if thou chidst me angry I shall strike. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102320" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102330">Strike thine own folly, for it is they</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102340">Deserve to be well beaten, we are now in private,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102350">There's none but thou and I? thou'rt fond and peevish,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102360">An unclean rioter, thy lands and credit</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102370"><pb facs="6"/> lie now both sick of a consumption</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102380">I am sorry for thee: that man spends with shame</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102390">That with his riches does consume his name:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102400">And such art thou. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102410" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102420">Peace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102430" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102440">No thou shalt hear me further:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102450">Thy fathers and forefathers worthy honours,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102460">Which were our country monuments: our grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102470">Follies in thee begin now to deface:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102480">The spring time of thy youth did fairly promise</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102490">Such a most fruitful summer to thy friends</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102500">It scarce can enter into men's beliefs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102510">Such dearth should hang on thee, we that see it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102520">Are sorry to believe it: in thy change,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102530">This voice into all places will be hurled:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102540">Thou and the devil has deceived the world. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102550" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102560">I'll not endure thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102570" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102580">But of all the worst:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102590">Thy virtuous wife right honourably allied</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102600">Thou hast proclaimed a strumpet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102610" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102620">Nay then I know thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102630">Thou art her champion thou, her private friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102640">The party you wot on. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102650" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102660">O ignoble thought. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102670">I am past my patient blood, shall I stand idle</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102680">And see my reputation touched to death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102690" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102700">Ta's galled you this, has it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102710" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102720">No monster, I will prove</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102730">My thoughts did only tend to virtuous love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102740">Love of her virtues? there it goes:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102750" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102760">Base spirit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102770">To lay thy hate upon the fruitful<stage xml:id="A12030-e102780">They fight and the husband's hurt ▪</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102790">Honour of thine own bed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102800" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu ▪</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102810">O,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102820" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102830">Wilt thou yield it yet? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102840" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102850">Sir, sir, I have not done with you,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102860" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102870">I hope nor ne'er shall do. <stage xml:id="A12030-e102880">Fight again.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102890" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102900">Have you got tricks are you in cunning with me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102910" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102920">No plain and right. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102930">He needs no cunning that for truth doth fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e102940">Husband falls down.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102950" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102960">Hard fortune, am I levelled with the ground? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102970" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e102980">Now sir you lie at mercy,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e102990" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103000">I you slave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103010" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103020">Alas that hate should bring us to our grave:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103030">You see my sword's not thirsty for your life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103040">I am sorrier for your wound than yourself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103050">You're of a virtuous house, show virtuous deeds</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103060">'Tis not your honour, 'tis your folly bleeds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103070">Much good has been expected in your life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103080">Cancel not all men's hopes, you have a wife</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103090">Kind and obedient: heap not wrongful shame</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103100">On her your posterity, let only sin be sore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103110">And by this fall, rise never to fall more ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103120">And so I leave you. <stage xml:id="A12030-e103130">Exit ▪</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103140" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103150">Has the dog left me then</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103160">After his tooth hath left me? o my heart</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103170">Would fain leap after him, revenge I say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103180">I'm mad to be revenged, my strumpet wife:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103190"><pb facs="7"/> it is thy quarrel that rips thus my flesh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103200">And makes my breast spit blood, but thou shalt bleed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103210">Vanquished? got down? unable e'en to speak? </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103220">Surely 'tis want of money makes men weak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103230">I? 'twas that o'erthrew me, I'd ne'er been down else.<stage xml:id="A12030-e103240">Exi</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e103250">Enter wife in a riding suit with a servingman.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103260" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103270">Faith mistress if it might not be presumption</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103280">In me to tell you so, for his excuse</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103290">You had small reason, knowing his abuse,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103300" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103310">I grant I had, but alas,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103320">Why should our faults at home be spread abroad:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103330">'Tis grief enough within doors: at first sight</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103340">Mine uncle could run o'er his prodigal life</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103350">As perfectly, as if his serious eye</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103360">Had numbered all his follies:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103370">Knew of his mortgaged lands, his friends in bonds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103380">Himself withered with debts: and in that minute</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103390">Had I added his usage and unkindness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103400">'Twould have confounded every thought of good:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103410">Where now, fathering his riots one his youth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103420">Which time and tame experience will shake off,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103430">Guessing his kindness to me (As I smoothed him</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103440">With all the skill I had) though his deserts</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103450">Are in form uglier than an unshaped bear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103460">He's ready to prefer him to some office</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103470">And place at court, a good and sure relief</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103480">To all his stooping fortunes 'twill be a means I hope,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103490">To make new league between us, and redeem</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103500">His virtues with his lands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103510" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103520">I should think so mistress. If he should not now<pb facs="8"/> be kind to you and love you, and cherish you up, I should think the devil himself kept open house in him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103530" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103540">I doubt not but he will now, pre the leave me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103550">I think I hear him coming. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103560" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103570">I am gone. <stage xml:id="A12030-e103580">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103590" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103600">By this good means I shall preserve my lands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103610">And free my husband out of usurer's hands:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103620">Now there is no need of sale, my uncle's kind</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103630">I hope, if ought, this will content his mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103640">Here comes my husband. <stage xml:id="A12030-e103650">Enter husband.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103660" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e103670">Now, are you come, where's the money, let's see the money, is the rubbish sold, those wisacres your lands, why when, the money, where is't, powr't down, down with it, down with it, I say powr't oath ground let's see't, let's see't.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103680" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103690">Good sir, keep but-in patience and I hope</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103700">My words shall like you well, I bring you better</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103710">Comfort than the sale of my dowry. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103720" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu ▪</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103730">Ha what's that? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103740" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103750">Pray do not fright me sir, but vouchsafe me hearing, my uncle glad of your kindness to me and mild usage ▪ for so I made it to him? has in pity</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103760">Of your declining fortunes, provided</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103770">A place for you at court of worth and credit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103780">Which so much overjoyed me</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103790" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103800">Out on thee filth, over and overjoyed.<stage xml:id="A12030-e103810">Spurns her</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103820">When I'm in torments? </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103830">Thou politic whore, subtler than nine devils, was this thy journey to Nuncke, to set down the history<pb facs="8"/> of me, of my state and fortunes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103840">Shall I that dedicated myself to pleasure, be now confined in service to crouch and stand like an old man ith' hams, my hat off, I that never could abide to uncover my head ith' church, base slut, this fruit bears thy complaints. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103850" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103860">O heaven knows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103870">That my complaints were praises, and best words</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103880">Of you, and your estate: only my friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103890">Knew of your mortgaged lands, and were possessed</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103900">Of every accident before I came. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103910">If thou suspect it but a plot in me</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103920">To keep my dowry, or for mine own good</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103930">Or my poor children's: (Though it suits a mother</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103940">To show a natural care in their reliefs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103950">Yet I'll forget myself to calm your blood:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103960">Consume it, as your pleasure counsels you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103970">And all I wish, e'en clemency affords:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e103980">Give me but comely looks and modest words. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e103990" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104000">Money whore, money, or I'll -</l>
          <stage xml:id="A12030-e104010">Enters a servant very hastily.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104020">What the devil? how now? thy hasty news?<stage xml:id="A12030-e104030">To his man</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104040" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104050">May it please you sir. <stage xml:id="A12030-e104060">Servant in a fear</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104070" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104080">What? may I not look upon my dagger? </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104090">Speak villain, or I will execute the point on thee: quick, short. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104100" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104110">Why sir a gentleman from the university stays below to speak with you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104120" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104130">From the university? so, university</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104140">That long word runs through me. <stage xml:id="A12030-e104150">Exeunt.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104160" who="A12030-wife">
          <pb facs="9"/>
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104170">Was ever wife so wretchedly beset,<stage xml:id="A12030-e104180">Wif. alone</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104190">Had not this news stepped in between, the point</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104200">Had offered violence to my breast. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104210">That which some women call great misery</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104220">Would show but little here: would scarce be seen</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104230">Amongst my miseries: I may compare</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104240">For wretched fortunes with all wives that are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104250">Nothing will please him; until all be nothing. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104260">He calls it slavery to be preferred. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104270">A place of credit, a base servitude. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104280">What shall become of me, and my poor children,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104290">Two here, and one at nurse, my pretty beggars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104300">I see how ruin with a palsy hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104310">Begins to shake the ancient seat to dust:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104320">The heavy weight of sorrow, draws my lids</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104330">Over my dankish eyes: I can scarce see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104340">Thus grief will last, it wakes and sleeps with me. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e104350">Enter the husband with the master of the college.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104360" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104370">Please you draw near sir, you're exceeding welcome.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104380" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104390">That's my doubt, I fear, I come not to be welcome.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104400" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104410">Yes howsoever.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104420" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104430">'Tis not my fashion sir to dwell in long circumstance, but to be plain, and effectual, therefore to the purpose.</p>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104440">The cause of my setting forth was piteous and lamentable , that hopeful young gentleman your brother, whose virtues we all love dear through your<pb facs="9"/> default, and unnatural negligence lies in bond executed for your debt, a prisoner all, his studies amazed his hope struck dead, and the pride of his youth muffled in these dark clouds of oppression.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104450" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104460">Hum, umh 'em.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104470" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104480">O, you have killed the towardest hope of all our university: wherefore without repentance and amends, expect Pandorus and sudden judgements to fall grievously upon you, your brother a man who profited in his divine employments might have made ten thousand souls fit for heaven, now by your careless courses cast in prison which you must answer for, and assure your spirit it will come home at length.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104490" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104500">O god o.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104510" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104520">Wise-men think ill of you, others speak ill of you, no man loves you, nay even those whom honesty condemns, condemn you: and take this from the virtuous affection I bear your brother, never look for prosperous hour, good thought, quiet sleeps, contented walks, nor anything that makes man perfect till you redeem him, what is your answer how will you bestow him, upon desperate misery, or better hopes? I suffer, till I hear your answer.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104530" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104540">Sir you have much wrought with me, I feel you in my soul, you are your art's master. I never had sense till now; your syllables have cleft me both for your words and pains I thank you: I cannot but acknowledge grievous wrongs done to my brother, mighty, mighty, mighty wrongs. Within there,</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e104550"><pb facs="10"/>Enter a servingman. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104560" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Sir Hu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104570">Fill me a bowl of wine. Alas poor brother, bruised with an execution for my sake<stage xml:id="A12030-e104580">Exit servant for wine.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104590" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104600">A bruise indeed makes many a mortal</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104610">Sore till the grave cure 'em</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e104620">Enter with wine.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104630" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104640">Sir I begin to you, you've chid your welcome:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104650" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104660">I could have wished it better for your sake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104670">I pledge you sir, to the kind man in prison. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104680" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104690">Let it be so? </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104700">Now sir if you so please<stage xml:id="A12030-e104710">Drink both.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e104720">To spend but a few minutes in a walk about my grounds below, my man here shall attend you: I doubt not but by that time to be furnished of a sufficient answer, and therein my brother fully satisfied. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104730" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104740">Good sir in that, the angels would be pleased, and the world's murmurs calmed, and I should say I set forth then upon a lucky day. <stage xml:id="A12030-e104750">Exit.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104760" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104770">O thou confused man, thy pleasant sins have 〈◊〉 he thy damnation has beggared thee, that heaven should say we must not answer, and yet made women: gives our sense's way to find pleasure, which being found confounds us, why should we know those things so much misuse us — o would virtue had been forbidden, we should then have proved all virtuous, for 'tis our blood to love what we are forbidden, had not drunkenness been forbidden what man would<pb facs="10"/> have been fool to a beast, and zany to a swine to show tricks in the mire, what is there in three dice to make a man draw thrice three thousand acres into the compass of a round little table, and with the gentleman's palsy in the hand shake out his posterity, thieves or beggars: 'tis done, I ha' don't i'faith: terrible horrible misery. — how well was I left, very well, very well.</p>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104780">My lands showed like a full moon about me, but now the moon's ith' last quarter, waning, waning, and I am mad to think that moon was mine: mine and my fathers, and my forefather's generations, generations: down goes the house of us, down, down; it sinks: now is the name a beggar, begs in me that name which hundreds of years has made this shire famous: in me, and my posterity runs out.</p>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104790">In my seed five are made miserable besides myself, my riot is now my brother's jailer, my wives sighing, my three boys penury, and mine own confusion:<stage xml:id="A12030-e104800">Tears his hair ▪</stage></p>
          <lg xml:id="A12030-e104810">
            <l xml:id="A12030-e104820">Why sit my hairs upon my cursed head? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12030-e104830">Will not this poison scatter them? o my brothers</l>
            <l xml:id="A12030-e104840">In execution among devils that stretch him: and make</l>
            <l xml:id="A12030-e104850">Him give. And I in want, not able for to live. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12030-e104860">Nor to redeem him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12030-e104870">Divines and dying men may talk of hell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12030-e104880">But in my heart her several torments dwell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12030-e104890">Slavery and misery. </l>
          </lg>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104900">Who in this case would not take up money upon his soul, pawn his salvation, live at interest:</p>
          <lg xml:id="A12030-e104910">
            <pb facs="11"/>
            <l xml:id="A12030-e104920">I that did ever in abundance dwell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12030-e104930">For me to want, exceeds the throws of hell. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e104940">Enters his little son with a top and a scourge.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104950" who="A12030-son">
          <speaker>Son.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104960">What ail you father, are you not well, I cannot scourge my top as long as you stand so: you take up all the room with your wide legs, puh you cannot make me afeard with this, I fear no vizards, nor bugbears.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e104970">Husb, takes up the child by the skirts of his long coat in one hand and draws his dagger with th'other.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e104980" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e104990">Up sir, for here thou hast no inheritance left.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105000" who="A12030-son">
          <speaker>Son.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e105010">O what will you do father, I am your white boy.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105020" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e105030">Thou shalt be my red boy, take that.<stage xml:id="A12030-e105040">Strikes him</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105050" who="A12030-son">
          <speaker>Son:</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e105060">O you hurt me father.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105070" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e105080">My eldest beggar: thou shalt not live to ask an usurer bread, to cry at a great man's gate, or follow good your honour by a couch, no, nor your brother 〈◊〉 charity to brain you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105090" who="A12030-son">
          <speaker>Son.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A12030-e105100">How shall I learn now my heads broke?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105110" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105120">Bleed bleed rather than beg beg?<stage xml:id="A12030-e105130">Stabs him.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105140">Be not thy name's disgrace:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105150">Spurn thou thy fortune's first if they be base:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105160">Come view thy second brother: fates,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105170">My children's blood shall spin into your faces, you shall see. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105180">How confidently we scorn beggary? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e105190">Exit with his son.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e105200"><pb facs="11"/>Enter a maid with a child in her arms, the mother by her asleep . </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105210" who="A12030-maid">
          <speaker>M.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105220">Sleep sweet babe sorrow makes thy mother sleep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105230">It bodes small good when heaviness falls so deep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105240">Hush pretty boy thy hopes might have been better,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105250">'Tis lost at dice what ancient honour won,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105260">Hard when the father plays away the son:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105270">No thing but misery serves in this house.</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105280">Ruin and desolation o</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e105290">Enter husband with the boy bleeding.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105300" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105310">Whore, give me that boy,<stage xml:id="A12030-e105320">Strives with her for the child.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105330" who="A12030-maid">
          <speaker>M.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105340">O help, help, out alas, murder murder,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105350" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105360">Are you gossipping, prating sturdy quean, I'll</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105370">Break your clamour with your neck down stairs:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105380">Tumble, tumble, headlong,<stage xml:id="A12030-e105390">Throws her down.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105400">So, the surest way to charm a woman's tongue</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105410">Is break her neck, a politician did it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105420" who="A12030-son">
          <speaker>Son.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105430">Mother, mother, I am killed mother. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105440">Ha, who's that cried o me my children:<stage xml:id="A12030-e105450">W. wakes.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105460">Both, both, both; bloody, bloody.<stage xml:id="A12030-e105470">Catches up the youngest.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105480" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105490">Strumpet let go the boy, let go the beggar. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105500" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105510">O my sweet husband,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105520" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105530">Filth, harlot. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105540" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105550">O what will you do dear husband,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105560" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105570">Gi'me me the bastard,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105580" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105590">Your own sweet boy,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105600" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105610">There are too many beggars. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105620" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105630">Good my husband,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105640" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105650">Dost thou prevent me still? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105660" who="A12030-wife">
          <pb facs="12"/>
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105670">O god ▪<stage xml:id="A12030-e105680">Stabs at the child in her arms.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105690" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105700">Have at his heart</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105710" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105720">O my dear boy,<stage xml:id="A12030-e105730">Gets it from her.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105740" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105750">Brat thou shalt not live to shame thy house,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105760" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105770">O heaven<stage xml:id="A12030-e105780">She's hurt and sinks down.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105790" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105800">And perish now begone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105810">There's whores enough, and want would make thee one. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e105820">Enter a lusty servant.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105830" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105840">O sir what deeds are these? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105850" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105860">Base slave my vassal:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105870">Com'st thou between my fury to question me</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105880" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Sir:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105890">Were you the devil I would hold you sir,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105900" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105910">Hold me? presumption, I'll undo thee for't,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105920" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105930">'Sblood you have undone us all sir,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105940" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105950">Tug at thy master,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105960" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105970">Tug at a monster. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e105980" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e105990">Have I no power, shall my slave fetter me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106000" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106010">Nay then the devil wrestles, I am thowne,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106020" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106030">O villain now I'll tug thee,<stage xml:id="A12030-e106040">Over comes him.</stage>now I'll tear thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106050">Set quick spurs to my vassal, bruise him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106060">Trample him, so, I think thou wilt not follow me in haste</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106070">My horse stands ready saddled, away, away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106080">Now to my brat at nurse, my sucking beggar:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106090">Fates, I'll not leave you one to trample one. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e106100">The master meets him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106110" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106120">How is't with you sir methinks you look of a distracted colour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106130" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106140">Who I sir, 'tis but your fancy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106150">Please you walk in sir, and I'll soon resolve you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106160"><pb facs="12"/> I want one small part to make up the some,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106170">And then my brother shall rest satisfied,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106180" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106190">I shall be glad to see it, sir I'll attend you. <stage xml:id="A12030-e106200">Exeu.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106210" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106220">O I am scarce able to heave up myself:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106230">Has so bruised me with his devilish weight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106240">And torn my flesh with his blood-hasty spur</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106250">A man before of easy constitution</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106260">Till now hell's power supplied; to his soul's wrong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106270">O how damnation can make weak men strong. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e106280">Enter master, and two servants.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106290" who="A12030-servant">
          <speaker>Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106300">O the most piteous deed sir since you came. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106310" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106320">A deadly greeting: has he somde up these</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106330">To satisfy his brother? here's another:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106340">And by the bleeding infants, the dead mother. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106350" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106360">O o. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106370" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106380">Surgeons, surgeons, she recovers life</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106390">One of his men all faint and bloodied. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106400" who="A12030-1_servant">
          <speaker>1. Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106410">Follow, our murderous master has taken horse</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106420">To kill his child at nurse, o follow quickly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106430" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106440">I am the readiest, it shall be my charge</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106450">To raise the town upon him<stage xml:id="A12030-e106460">Exit Mr. and servant</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106470" who="A12030-servant_1">
          <speaker>1 servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106480">Good sir do follow him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106490" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106500">O my children. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106510" who="A12030-servant_1">
          <speaker>1. Servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106520">How is it with my most afflicted mistress? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106530" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106540">Why, do I now recover? why half live? </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106550">To see my children bleed before mine eyes. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106560">A sight able to kill a mother's breast</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106570">Without an executioner, what art thou mangled too? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106580" who="A12030-yyyy_1">
          <speaker>1 ▪ servant</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106590">I thinking to prevent what his quick mischiefs had so soon acted; came and rushed upon him</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106600"><pb facs="13"/> we struggled, but a fouler strength than his</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106610">O'er threw me with his arms, then did he bruise me</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106620">And rent my flesh, and robbed me of my hair</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106630">Like a man mad in execution</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106640">Made me unfit to rise and follow him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106650" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106660">What is it has beguiled him of all grace? </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106670">And stole away humanity from his breast? </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106680">To slay his children, purposed to kill his wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106690">And spoil his servants. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e106700">Enters two servants.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106710" who="A12030-ambo">
          <speaker>Ambo sir,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106720">Please you leave this most accursed place, a surgeon waits within. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106730" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106740">Willing to leave it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106750">'Tis guilty of sweet blood, innocent blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106760">Murder has taken this chamber with full hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106770">And will ne'er out as long as the house stands.<stage xml:id="A12030-e106780">Exeunt</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e106790">Enter husband as being thrown off his horse, and falls:</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106800" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106810">O stumbling jade the spavin overtake thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106820">The fifty diseases stop thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106830">O, I am sorely bruised, plague founder thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106840">Thou runnest at ease and pleasure, heart, of chance</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106850">To throw me now within a flight o'th' town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106860">In such plain even ground, 'sfoot, a man may dice upon't, and throw away the meadows, filthy beast. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106870"><stage xml:id="A12030-e106880">Cry within</stage>follow, follow, follow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106890" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106900">Ha? I hear sounds of men; like hue and cry:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106910">Up, up, and struggle to thy horse, make on</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106920"><pb facs="13"/> dispatch that little beggar and all's done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106930" who="A12030-knight">
          <speaker>Knight</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106940">Here, this way, this way:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e106950" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106960">At my back? o,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106970">What fate have I, my limbs deny me go,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106980">My will is bated, beggary claims a part. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e106990">O could I here reach to the infant's heart. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e107000">Enter m. of the college, 3. Gentlemen, and others with halberds. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e107010">Find him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107020" who="A12030-all">
          <speaker>All.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107030">Here, here, yonder, yonder. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107040" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107050">Unnatural, flinty, more than barbarous:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107060">The Scythians in their marble hearted fates,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107070">Could not have acted more remorseless deeds</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107080">In their relentless natures, than these of thine:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107090">Was this the answer I long waited on,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107100">The satisfaction for thy prisoned brother? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107110" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107120">Why, he can have no more on's then our skins,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107130">And some of 'em want but flaying. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107140" who="A12030-gentleman_1">
          <speaker>1. Gentleman </speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107150">Great sins have made him impudent:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107160" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107170">Has shed so much blood that he cannot bluff</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107180" who="A12030-gentleman_2">
          <speaker>2. Gentleman</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107190">Away with him, bear him a long to the justices:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107200">A gentleman of worship dwells at hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107210">There shall his deeds be blazed:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107220" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107230">Why all the better,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107240">My glory 'tis to have my action known,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107250">I grieve for nothing, but I missed of one:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107260" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107270">There's little of a father in that grief:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107280">Bear him away. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e107290">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e107300"><pb facs="14"/>Enters a knight with two or three gentlemen. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107310" who="A12030-knight">
          <speaker>Knight</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107320">Endangered so his wife? murdered his children? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107330" who="A12030-gentleman_4">
          <speaker>4. Gentleman </speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107340">So the cry comes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107350" who="A12030-knight">
          <speaker>Knight</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107360">I am sorry I ere knew him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107370">That ever he took life and natural being</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107380">From such an honoured stock, and fair descent;</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107390">Till this black minute without stain or blemish ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107400" who="A12030-gentleman_4">
          <speaker>4 gent.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107410">Here come the men. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e107420">Enter the master of the college and the rest, with the prisoner.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107430" who="A12030-knight">
          <speaker>Knight</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107440">The serpent of his house? I'm sorry for this time that I am in place of justice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107450" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107460">Please you sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107470" who="A12030-knight">
          <speaker>Knight</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107480">Do not repeat it twice I know too much, would it had ne'er been thought on:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107490">Sir I bleed for you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107500" who="A12030-gentleman_4">
          <speaker>4 gent.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107510">Your father's sorrows are alive in me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107520">What made you show such monstrous cruelty ▪ 〈◊〉 a word sir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107530">I have consumed all, played away long acre,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107540">And I thought it the charitablest deed I could do</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107550">To cozen beggary: and knock my house o'th' head. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107560" who="A12030-knight">
          <speaker>Knight</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107570">O in a cooler blood you will repent it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107580" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107590">I repent now, that ones left unkilled,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107600">My brat at nurse. O I would full fain have weaned him</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107610" who="A12030-knight">
          <speaker>Knight</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107620">Well, I do not think but in to morrow's judgement. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107630">The terror will sit closer to your soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107640"><pb facs="14"/> when the dread thought of death remembers you to further which, take this sad voice from me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107650">Never was act played more unnaturally. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107660" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107670">I thank you sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107680" who="A12030-knight">
          <speaker>Knight</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107690">Go lead him to the jail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107700">Where justice claims all, there must pity fail. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107710" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107720">Come come, away with me. <stage xml:id="A12030-e107730">Exit prisoner.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107740" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107750">Sir, you deserve the worship of your place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107760">Would all did so: in you the law is grace,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107770" who="A12030-knight">
          <speaker>Knight</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107780">It is my wish it should be so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107790">Ruinous man, the desolation of his house, the blot</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107800">Upon his predecessors honoured name:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107810">That man is nearest shame that is past shame. <stage xml:id="A12030-e107820">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e107830">Enter husband with the officers, the master and gentlemen as going by his house.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107840" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu ▪</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107850">I am right against my house, seat of my ancestors: I hear my wife's alive; but much endangered:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107860">Let me entreat to speak with her</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107870">Before the prison gripe me. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A12030-e107880">Enter his wife brought in a chair.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107890" who="A12030-gentleman">
          <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107900">See here she comes of herself,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107910" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107920">O my sweet husband, my dear distressed husband, now in the hands of unrelenting laws,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107930">My greatest sorrow, my extremest bleeding,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107940">Now my soul bleeds. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107950" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107960">How now? kind to me? did I not wound thee, left thee for dead. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e107970" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107980">Tut far greater wounds did my breast feel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e107990">Unkindness strikes a deeper wound than steel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108000"><pb facs="15"/> you have been still unkind to me:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108010" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108020">Faith, and so I think I have:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108030">I did my murders roughly out of hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108040">Desperate and sudden, but thou hast devised</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108050">A fine way now to kill me, thou hast given mine eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108060">Seven wounds a piece; now glides the devil from</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108070">Me, departs at every joint, heaves up my nails ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108080">O catch him new torments, that were ne'er invented,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108090">Bind him one thousand more you blessed angels</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108100">In that pit bottomless, let him not rise</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108110">To make men act unnatural tragedies</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108120">To spread into a father, and in fury,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108130">Make him his children's executioners:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108140">Murder his wife, his servants, and who not? </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108150">For that man's dark, where heaven is quite forgotten. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108160" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108170">O my repentant husband. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108180" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108190">My dear soul, whom I too much have wronged,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108200">For death I die, and for this have I longed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108210" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108220">Thou shouldst not (Be assured) for these faults die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108230">If the law could forgive as soon as I,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108240" who="A12030-unassigned">
          <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108250">What sight is yonder? <stage xml:id="A12030-e108260">Children laid out.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108270" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108280">O our two bleeding boys laid forth upon the threshold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108290" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Hu ▪</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108300">Here's weight enough to make a heartstring crack</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108310">O were it lawful that your pretty souls</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108320">Might look from heaven into your father's eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108330">Then should you see the penitent glasses melt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108340">And both your murders shoot upon my cheeks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108350">But you are playing in the angel's laps,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108360">And will not look on me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108370"><pb facs="15"/> who void of grace, killed you in beggary. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108380">O that I might my wishes now attain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108390">I should then wish you living were again:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108400">Though I did beg with you, which thing I feared,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108410">O 'twas the enemy my eyes so bleared. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108420">O would you could pray heaven me to forgive ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108430">That will unto my end repentant live. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108440" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108450">It makes me e'en forget all other sorrows</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108460">And leave part with this. Come will you go,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108470" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108480">I'll kiss the blood I spilt and then I go:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108490">My soul is bloodied, well may my lips be so. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108500">Farewell dear wife, now thou and I must part,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108510">I of thy wrongs repent me with my heart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108520" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108530">O stay thou shalt not go:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108540" who="A12030-husband">
          <speaker>Husband</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108550">That's but in vain, you see it must be so. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108560">Farewell ye bloody ashes of my boys,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108570">My punishments are their eternal joys. </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108580">Let every father look into my deeds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108590">And then their heirs may prosper while mine bleeds. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108600" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108610">More wretched am I now in this distress,<stage xml:id="A12030-e108620">Exeunt</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108630">Then former sorrows made me. <stage xml:id="A12030-e108640">Husband with hol●●●●</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108650" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108660">O kind wife be comforted,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108670">One joy is yet unmurdered:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108680">You have a boy at nurse your joy's in him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108690" who="A12030-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108700">Dearer than all is my poor husband's life:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108710">Heaven give my body strength, which yet is faint</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108720">With much expense of blood, and I will kneel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108730">Sue for his life, number up all my friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108740">To plead for pardon my dear husband's life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A12030-e108750" who="A12030-master">
          <speaker>Master</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108760">Was it in man to wound so kind a creature? </l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108770"><pb facs="16"/>I'll ever praise a woman for thy sake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108780">I must return with grief my answer's set:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108790">I shall bring news weighs heavier than the debt:</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108800">Two brothers: one in bond lies overthrown</l>
          <l xml:id="A12030-e108810">This, on a deadlier execution. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer xml:id="A12030-e108820">Finis.</trailer>
        <pb facs="16"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A12030"><item xml:id="A12030-husband" n="75">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-husband</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">75</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-wife" n="38">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-wife</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">38</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-master" n="19">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-master</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">19</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-gentleman" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-gentleman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-servant" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-servant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A12030-sam" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-sam</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-oliver" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-oliver</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-knight" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-knight</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-son" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-son</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-ambo" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-ambo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-ralph" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-ralph</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-gentleman_4" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-gentleman_4</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-gentleman_1" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-gentleman_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-maid" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-maid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-unassigned" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-gentleman_2" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-gentleman_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-servant_1" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-servant_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-gentleman_3" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-gentleman_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-1_servant" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-1_servant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-yyyy_1" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12030-all" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A12030-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

