<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>2 Bell in Campo<date type="creation_date">1662</date></title>
        <author>Cavendish, Margaret</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A53060_19.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>356 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">11861873</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing N868.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">50022</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53060</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
            <author>Newcastle, William Cavendish, 1592-1676.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[24], 679 [i.e. 675], [4] p. : ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by A. Warren, for John Martyn, James Allestry, and Tho. Dicas ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1662.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>First edition.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Errata: p. [4] at end.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A53060_19-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A53060_19-e100020">
      <div n="2" type="play" xml:id="A53060_19-e100030">
        <pb facs="318" n="607"/>
        <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A53060_19-e100040">
          <list xml:id="A53060_19-e100050">
            <head>The actors names.</head>
            <item xml:id="A53060_19-e100060">The lord general, and many commanders. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_19-e100070">Monsieur la gravity.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_19-e100080">Monsieur le companion.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_19-e100090">Monsieur comrade.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_19-e100100">Doctor educature.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_19-e100110">Doctor comfort, and divers gentlemen, messengers, servants, officers and others. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_19-e100120">Lady Victoria, and many heroics. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_19-e100130">Lady Jantils.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_19-e100140">Lady passionate.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_19-e100150">Doll pacify.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_19-e100160">Nell careless, city wives and others. </item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A53060_19-e100170">
          <pb facs="319" n="608"/>
          <head>The second part of bell in Campo.</head>
          <head type="sub">Act i.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e100180">
            <head>Scene 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e100190">Enter doctor comfort, and doll Pacify.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100200" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100210">Good master priest go comfort my old lady.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100220" who="A53060_19-comfort">
              <speaker>Doctor comfort.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100230">If you will comfort me, I will strive to comfort her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100240" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100250">So we shall prove the crumbs of comfort.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100260" who="A53060_19-comfort">
              <speaker>Doctor comfort.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100270">But is my lady so sad still?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100280" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100290">Faith today she hath been better than I have seen her, for she was so patient as to give order for blacks; but I commend the young lady madam Jantil, who bears out the siege of sorrow most courageously, and on my conscience I believe will beat grief from the fort of her heart, and become victorious over her misfortunes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100300" who="A53060_19-comfort">
              <speaker>Doctor comfort.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100310">Youth is a good soldier in the warfare of life, and like a valiant cornet or ensign, keeps the colours up, and the flag flying, in despite of the enemies, and were our lady as young as madam Jantil, she would grieve less, but to lose an old friend after the loss of a young beauty is a double, nay a triple affliction, because there is little or no hopes to get another good husband, for though an old woman may get a husband, yet ten thousand to one but he will prove an enemy, or a devil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100320" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100330">It were better for my lady if she would marry again, that her husband should prove a devil than a mortal enemy, for you can free her from the one though not from the other, for at your words, the great devil will avoid or vanish, and you can bind the lesser devils in chains, and whip them with holy rods until they roar again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100340" who="A53060_19-comfort">
              <speaker>Doctor comfort.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100350">Nay, we are strong enough for the devil at all times, and in all places, neither can he deceive us in any shape, unless it be in the shape of a young beauty, and then I confess he overcomes us, and torments our hearts in the fire of love, beyond all expression.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100360" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100370">If I were a devil I would be sure to take a most beautiful shape to torment you, but my lady will torment me if I stay any longer here.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e100380">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e100390">
            <pb facs="319" n="609"/>
            <head>Scene 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e100400">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100410" who="A53060_19-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100420">Sir, you being newly come from the army, pray what news?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100430" who="A53060_19-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100440">I suppose you have heard how our army was forced to fight by the enemies provocations, hearing the lord general lay sick, whereupon the general's lady the lady Victoria, caused her Amazonians to march towards the masculine army, and to entrench some half a mile distance therefrom, which when the masculine army heard thereof, they were very much troubled thereat, and sent a command for them to retreat back, fearing they might be a disturbance, so a destruction unto them by, doing some untimely or unnecessary action; but the female army returned the masculine army an answer, that they would not retreat unless they were beaten back, which they did believe the masculine sex would not, having more honour than to fight with the female sex; but if the men were so base, they were resolved to stand upon their own defence; but if they would let them alone, they would promise them upon the honour of their words not to advance any nearer unto the masculine army, as long as the masculine army could assault their enemies, or defend themselves, and in this posture I left them.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e100450">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e100460">
            <head>Scene 3.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e100470">Enter the lady Victoria, and her heroickesses. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100480" who="A53060_19-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady Victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100490">Noble heroickesses, I have intelligence that the army of reformations begins to flag, wherefore now or never is the time to prove the courage of our sex, to get liberty and freedom from the female slavery, and to make ourselves equal with men: for shall men only sit in honour's chair, and women stand as waiters by? shall only men in triumphant chariots ride, and women run as captives by? shall only men be conquerors, and women slaves? shall only men live by fame, and women die in oblivion? no, no, gallant heroics raise your spirits to a noble pitch, to a deaticall height, to get an everlasting renown, and infinite praises, by honourable, but unusual actions: for honourable fame is not got only by contemplating thoughts which lie lazily in the womb of the mind, and prove abortive, if not brought forth in living deeds; but worthy heroickesses, at this time fortune desires to be the midwife, and if the gods and goddesses did not intend to favour our proceedings with a safe deliverance, they would not have offered us so fair and fit an opportunity to be the mothers of glorious actions, and everlasting fame, which if you be so unnatural to strangle in the birth by fearful cowardice, may you be blasted with infamy, which is worse than to die and be forgotten; may you be whipped with the torturing tongues of our own sex we left behind us, and may you be scorned and neglected by the masculine sex, whilst other women are<pb facs="320" n="610"/> preferred and beloved, and may you walk unregarded until you become a plague to yourselves; but if you arm with courage and fight valiantly, may men bow down and worship you, birds taught to sing your praises, Kings offer up their crowns unto you, and honour enthrone you in a mighty power.</p>
              <lg xml:id="A53060_19-e100500">
                <l xml:id="A53060_19-e100510">May time and destiny attend your will,</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_19-e100520">Fame be your scribe to write your actions still;</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_19-e100530">And may the gods each act with praises fill. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100540" who="A53060_19-all_women">
              <speaker>All the women.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100550">Fear us not, fear us not, we dare and will follow you wheresoever and to what you dare or will lead us, be it through the jaws of death.</p>
            </sp>
            <div type="prayer" xml:id="A53060_19-e100560">
              <head>The prayer.</head>
              <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100570" who="A53060_19-victoria">
                <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
                <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100580">Great Mars thou god of war, grant that our squadrons may like unbroken clouds move with entire bodies, let courage be the wind to drive us on, and let our thick swelled army darken their sun of hope with black despair, let us pour down showers of their blood, to quench the fiery flames of our revenge. </p>
                <lg xml:id="A53060_19-e100590">
                  <l xml:id="A53060_19-e100600">And where those showers fall, their deaths as seeds</l>
                  <l xml:id="A53060_19-e100610">Sown in time's memory sprout up our deeds;</l>
                  <l xml:id="A53060_19-e100620">And may our acts triumphant got lands make,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A53060_19-e100630">Which fame may wear for our heroics sake. </l>
                </lg>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e100640">Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e100650">
            <head>Scene 4.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e100660">Enter doctor comfort, and doll Pacify.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100670" who="A53060_19-comfort">
              <speaker>Doctor comfort.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100680">Doll, how doth our lady since the burying of my patron?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100690" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100700">Faith she begins now to have regard to her health, for she take jackalato every morning in her bed falling, and then she hath a mess of Gelly broth for her breakfast, and drinks a cup of sack before dinner, and eats a whitewine caudle every afternoon, and for her supper she hath new laid eggs, and when she goes to bed, she drinks a hearty draught of muskadine to make her sleep well; besides, if she chances to wake in the night, she takes comfortable spirits, as Angelica, aniseeds, besor, aquamirabilis, and the like hot waters, to comfort her heart, and to drive away all melancholy thoughts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100710" who="A53060_19-comfort">
              <speaker>Doctor comfort.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100720">Those things will do it if it be to be done, but I am sorry that my lady hath sold all my patron's horses, saddles, arms, clothes, and such like things at the drums head, and by outcries, to get a little the more money for them, I fear the world will condemn her, as believing her to be covetous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100730" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100740">O that's nothing, for what she loses by being thought covetous, she will regain by being thought rich, for the world esteems and respects nothing so much as riches.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e100750">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A53060_19-e100760">
          <pb facs="320" n="611"/>
          <head>Act ii.</head>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e100770">
            <head>Scene 5.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e100780">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100790" who="A53060_19-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100800">Pray sir what news from the army? you are newly come from thence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100810" who="A53060_19-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100820">I suppose you have heard how the effeminate army was some half a mile from the masculine armies; but the masculine army being very earnest to fight, not only to get victory and power, but to revenge each others losses, as their friends slain in the former battle, which thoughts of revenge did so fire their minds and inflame their spirits, that if their eyes had been as much illuminated as their flaming spirits were, there might have been seen two blazing armies thus joining their forces against each other; at last began a cruel fight, where both the armies fought with such equal courages and active limbs, as for a long time neither side could get the better, but at the last the army of faction broke the ranks and files of the army of reformation, whereupon every squadron began to fall into a confusion, no order was kept, no charge was heard, no command obeyed, terror and fear ran maskerd about, which helped to rout our army, whereupon the enemy killed many of our men, and wounded many more, and took numbers of prisoners; but upon this defeat came in the female army, in the time that some of the enemy was busy in gathering up the conquered spoils, others in pursuit of the remainders of our men, others were binding up the prisoners, others driving them to their quarters like a company of sheep to a market there to be sold; but whenas some of the commanders perceived a fresh army coming towards them, their general commanded the trumpets to sound a retreat to gather them together, and also made haste to order and settle his men in battle array, and desirous their general was to have all the prisoners slain; but the female army came up so fast and so close to prevent that mischief, as they had not time to execute that design; but their general encouraged his soldiers, and bid them not to be disheartened, persuading them not to lose what they had got from an army of men to an army of boys, for said he they seem to be no other by the appearance of their shapes and statures; but when the female army came to encounter them, they found their charge so hot and furious as made them give place, which advantage they took with that prudence and dexterity, as they did not only rout this army of faction, killing and wounding many, and set their own countrymen at liberty, and recovered their losses, and gained many spoils, and took numbers of prisoners of their enemies with bag and baggage, but they pursued those that fled into their trenches, and beat them out of their works, and took possession thereof, where they found much riches; these trenches being taken, the lady Victoria took possession, and made them her quarters, calling all her female soldiers to enter therein by the sound of flutes, which they always used instead of trumpets, and their drums were kettledrums; but upon this victory<pb facs="321" n="612"/> the masculine sex of the army of reformation was much out of countenance, being doubly or trebly overcome, twice by their enemy, and then by the gallant actions of the females which outdid them, yet they thought it best to take their advantage whilst the victory was fresh and flourishing, and their enemies weak and fearful, to lay siege to the next towns in the enemy's country; whereupon the lady Victoria and her female soldiers hearing of the army of reformations designs, for they had sent the men to their own quarters as soon as the battle was won and victory got; also the masculine prisoners they sent to the men's quarters, not intermixing themselves with the men, but as I said they hearing the design they had to besiege the towns were much enraged for not making them of their councils, whereupon they sent a messenger like as an ambassador to tell the masculine army they did wonder at their ingratitude, that they should forget so much their relievers as to go upon any warlike design without making them acquainted therewith, striving as it were to steal the victory out of their hands, but said they, since we are become victorious over our enemies, and masters, and mistresses of the field, by our own valiant actions and prudent conducts, we will maintain our power by our own strengths, for our army is become now numerous, full and flourishing, formed, and conformable by our discipline, skilful by our practice, valiant by our resolutions, powerful by our victory, terrible to our enemies, honourable to our friends, and a subject of envy to the masculine sex; but your army is weak and decrepit, sitter for an hospital than for a field of war, your power is lost, your courage is cold, your discipline disorderous, and your command slighted, despised by your enemies, pitied by your friends, forsaken of good fortune, and made subject unto our effeminate sex, which we will use by our power like slaves. But when our lord general who was recovered out of sickness, and all his commanders about him heard this message, which was delivered in a full assembly, according as the lady Victoria had commanded the message should be, the men could not choose but smile at the women's high and mighty words, knowing they had all sweet and gentle dispositions and complying natures, yet they were at a stand which to be pleased at most, as in hearing them disparage their masculine sex, or in advancing their own female sex by their self commendations, but howsoever so well pleased the men were with the women's gallant actions, that every man was proud that had but a female acquaintance in the female army; but our lord general was mightily taken with their bravadoes, and much mirth amongst the commanders was about it; but when they were to advise what to do in the affairs of war, and the warring women, the general told them he made no question but that most men known by experience that women were won by gentle persuasions and fair promises, and not by rigid actions or angry frowns, besides said he, all noble natures strive to assist the weakest in all lawful actions, and that he was no gallant man that submits not to a woman in all things that are honourable, and when he doth dissent it must be in a courtly manner, and a complimental behaviour and expression, for that women were creatures made by nature, for men to love and admire, to protect and defend, to cherish and maintain, to seek and to sue to, and especially such women which have outdone all their sex, which nature ever made before them; wherefore said he, 'tis fit to these women above all others we should yield ourselves prisoners, not only in love but in arms; wherefore let us treat fairly with them, and give them their own<pb facs="321" n="613"/> conditions. But in the mean time the lady Victoria thought it best not to lose my opportunity with talking out the time, wherefore she besieged a considerable fort, a place which was at it were the key that unlocked the passage into the heart of the enemy's kingdom, and at this siege they were when became away, but the general and his council had sent a messenger unto them, but what his message was I cannot give you an account.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e100830">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e100840">
            <head>Scene 6.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e100850">Enter two men in mourning.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100860" who="A53060_19-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 man. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100870">Now my lord is entombed, our lady will enanchor herself by his ash.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100880" who="A53060_19-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 man.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100890">'Tis strange so young and beautiful a lady should bury herself from the world, and quit all the pleasures thereof, to live with dead ashes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100900" who="A53060_19-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 man.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100910">A grieved mind, melancholy thoughts, and an oppressed heart, considers not the body, nor the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100920" who="A53060_19-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 man.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100930">But yet I think 'tis an example that few of her sex will imitate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100940" who="A53060_19-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 man.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100950">Because few of the female sex can truly grieve or be melancholy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e100960" who="A53060_19-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 man.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e100970">No, it is that few of the female sex can truly and constantly love.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e100980">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e100990">
            <head>Scene 7.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101000">The tomb being thrust on the stage, enter madam Jantil and a company of mourners, but the lady Jantil was attired in a garment of rich cloth of gold girt loosely about her, and a mantle of crimson velvet lined with powdered ermins over that, her woman bearing up the train thereof being long, her hair all unbound hung loose upon her shoulders and back, upon her head a rich crown of jewels, as also pendant jewels in her ears, and on her wrists costly bracelets; when she came in she goeth towards the tomb, and bows with great respect and devotion thereto, thou speaks, directing her speech to every several figure. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101010">These following verses or speeches were written by my lord marquess of Newcastle.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e101020" who="A53060_19-jantel">
              <speaker>Lady Iantil.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101030">Pallas and Mercury at thy death mourned,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101040">So as to marble statues here they're turned;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101050">Mars sheaths his sword, and begs of thee a room,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101060">To bury all his courage in thy tomb;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101070"><pb facs="322" n="614"/> Hymen amazed stands, and is in doubt,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101080">Thy death his holy fire hath put out;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101090">What various shape of fortune thou didst meet,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101100">Thou scornest her frowns and kicks he with thy feet,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101110">Now sound aloud the trumpet of good fame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101120">And blow abroad his everlasting name. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101130">After this she directs her speech to the outward figures about the tomb.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101140">The Cardinal virtues pillars of thy fame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101150">Weep to see now each but an empty name</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101160">Only for painters and for carvers be,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101170">When thy life sustained them more than they thee;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101180">Each capital a sadder virtue bears,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101190">But for the graces would be drowned in tears;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101200">Faith strengthens fortitude lest she should faint,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101210">Hope comforts prudence as her only saint;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101220">And charity to justice doth advance</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101230">To counsel her, as patience Temperance;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101240">But woeful counsellors they are each one,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101250">Since grief for thy death turned them all to stone. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101260">Then putting off her rich garments and ornaments before mentioned, as she was undressing she spoke thus.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101270">Now I depose myself, and here lay down,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101280">Titles, not honour, with my richer crown;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101290">This crimson velvet mantle I throw by,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101300">There case and plenty in rich ermins lie;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101310">Off with this glittering gown which once did bear</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101320">Ambition and fond pride lie you all there;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101330">Bracelets and pendants which I now do wear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101340">Here I divest my arms and so each ear;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101350">Cut off these dangling tresses once a crime,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101360">Urging my glass to look away my time;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101370">Thus all these worldly vanities I wave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101380">And bury them all in my husband's grave. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101390">After this she calls for her other garments, which was a pure white light silk loose garment, girt about her with a white silk cord, and then puts on a thin black veil over it, and then takes a book in her hand, but speaks as they were a putting on those latter garments.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101400">More of my lord marquess's, are these.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e101410" who="A53060_19-jantel">
              <speaker>Lady Iantel.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101420">Put on that pure and spotless garment white,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101430">To show my chaster thoughts, my souls delight;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101440"><pb facs="322" n="615"/> cord of humility about my waste,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101450">A veil of obscure mourning about me cast;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101460">Here by this sadder tomb shall be my station,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101470">And in this book my holy contemplation. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101480">She turns herself to her servants.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101490">Farewell my servants, farewell every one,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101500">As you all love me pray leave me alone. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101510">They all go forth weeping.</stage>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101520">When they were all gone and she alone, she turns herself to the tomb.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101530">No dust shall on thy marble ever stay,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101540">But with my sadder sighs I'll blow 't away;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101550">And the least spot that any pillar bears,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101560">I'll wash it clean with grief of dropping tears;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101570">Sun fly this hemisphere, and feast my eyes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101580">With melancholy night, and never rise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101590">Nor by reflection, for all light I hate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101600">Therefore no planet do illuminate;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101610">The twinkling stars that in cold nights are seen,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101620">Clouds muster up and hide them as a screen,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101630">The centric fire raise vapours from the earth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101640">Get and be midwife for those fogs their birth;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101650">Then chilling colds freeze up thy pores without,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101660">That trembling earthquakes nowhere may get out;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101670">And that our mother earth may nothing wear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101680">But snow and icicles to curl her hair;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101690">And so dame nature barren nothing bring,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101700">Wishing a chaos, since despairs a spring;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101710">Since all my joys are gone, what shall I do,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e101720">But with the whole world ruined with me too? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101730">Here ends my lord marquess's verses.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101740">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A53060_19-e101750">
          <pb facs="323" n="616"/>
          <head>Act iii:</head>
          <div n="8" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e101760">
            <head>Scene 8.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101770">Enter the lady Victoria, and many of her Amazons, then enters a messenger from the masculine army. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e101780" who="A53060_19-messenger">
              <speaker>Messenger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e101790">May it please your excellence, our lord general and the rest of the commanders have sent you and your heroics a letter, desiring it may be read in a full assembly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e101800" who="A53060_19-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e101810">One of you take the letter and read it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101820">One of the women takes the letter and reads it to all the company.</stage>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:id="A53060_19-e101830">
              <body xml:id="A53060_19-e101840">
                <head>The letter.</head>
                <opener xml:id="A53060_19-e101850">
                  <salute xml:id="A53060_19-e101860">To the most excellent of her sex, and her most worthy heroickesses.</salute>
                </opener>
                <p xml:id="A53060_19-e101870">You goddesses on earth, who have the power and dominion over men, 'tis you we worship and adore, we pray and implore your better opinions of us, than to believe we are so unjust as to take the victory out of your fair hands, or so vainglorious as to attribute it to ourselves, or so ungrateful as not to acknowledge our lives and liberties from your valours, wisdoms, and good fortune, or so imprudent as to neglect your power, or so ill-bred as to pass by you without making our addresses, or so foolish as to go about any action without your knowledge, or so unmannerly as to do anything without your leave; wherefore we entreat you and pray you to believe that we have so much honour in us, as to admire your beauties, to be attentive to your discourses, to dote on your persons, to honour your virtues, to divulge your sweet graces, to praise your behaviours, to wait your commands, to obey your directions, to be proud of your favours, and we wear our lives only for your service, and believe we are not only taken captives by your beauties, but that we acknowledge we are bound as your slaves by your valours: wherefore we all pray that you may not misinterpret our affections and care to your persons, in believing we sent you away because we were weary of you, which if so, it had been a sin unpardonable, but we sent you away for your safety, for heaven knows your departure was our hell, and your absence our torments; but we confess our errors, and do humbly beg our pardons, for if you had accompanied us in our battles, you had kept us safe, for had we fought in your presence, our enemies had never overcome us, since we take courage from your eyes, life from your smiles, and victory from your good wishes, and had become conqueror by your encouragements, and so we might have triumphed in your favours, but hereafter your rules shall be our methods, by which we will govern all our actions, attending only wholly your directions, yet give us leave humbly to offer our advice as subjects to their Princess if you think fit, we think it best to follow close the victory, lest that our enemies recruit their forces, with a sufficient strength to beat us out of<pb facs="323" n="617"/> what we have gained, or at least to hinder and oppose our entrance, and hopes of conquering them, where if you will give us leave we will besiege and enter their towns, and raze their walls down to the ground, which harbour their disorders, offending their neighbours kingdoms; yet we are not so ambitious as to desire to be commanders, but to join our forces to yours, and to be your assistants, and as your common soldiers; but leaving all these affairs of war to your discretion, offering ourselves to your service,</p>
                <closer xml:id="A53060_19-e101880">We kiss your hands, and take our leaves for this time.</closer>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e101890">All the women fall into a great laughter, ha, ha, ha, ha.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e101900" who="A53060_19-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e101910">Noble heroickesses, by your valours, and constant, and resolute proceedings, you have brought your tyrants to be your slaves; those that commanded your absence, now humbly sue your presence, those that thought you a hindrance have felt your assistance, the time is well altered since we were sent to retreat back from the masculine army; and now nothing to be done in that army without our advice, with an humble desire they may join their forces with ours: but gallant heroickesses, by this you may perceive we were as ignorant of ourselves as men were of us, thinking ourselves shifdels, weak, and unprofitable creatures, but by our actions of war we have proved ourselves to be every way equal with men; for what we want of strength, we have supplied by industry, and had we not done what we have done, we should have lived in ignorance and slavery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e101920" who="A53060_19-all_female_commanders">
              <speaker>All the female commanders.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e101930">All the knowledge of ourselves, the honour of renown, the freedom from slavery, and the submission of men, we acknowledge from you; for you advised us, counselled us, instructed us, and encouraged us to those actions of war: wherefore to you we owe our thanks, and to you we give our thanks.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e101940" who="A53060_19-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e101950">What answer will you return to the masculine army?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e101960" who="A53060_19-all_commanders">
              <speaker>All the commanders.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e101970">What answer you will think best.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e101980" who="A53060_19-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e101990">We shall not need to write back an answer, for this messenger may deliver it by word of mouth; wherefore sir pray remember us to your general and his commanders, and tell them, that we are willing upon their submissions to be friends, and that we have not neglected our good fortune, for we have laid siege to so considerable a fort, which if taken, may give an easy passage into the kingdom, which fort we will deliver to their forces when they come, that they may have the honour of taking it; for tell them, we have got honour enough in the battle we fought, and victory we did win.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102000">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="9" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e102010">
            <pb facs="324" n="618"/>
            <head>Scene 9.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102020">Enter monsieur la gravity, monsieur companion, and monsieur comrade.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102030" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102040">We are bound to curse you monsieur gravity, for retarding our visits to the widows, for I told you we should come too late if we did not go before their husbands were buried</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102050" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102060">But I do not hear they have made a promise to marry any as yet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102070" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102080">That's all one unto us, but the noblest, youngest, richest, and fairest widow is gone; for though she is not promised or married, yet she is encloistered, and that is worse than marriage; for if she had been married there might have been some hopes her husband would have died, or been killed, or some ways or other death would have found to have taken him away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102090" who="A53060_19-comerade">
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102100">Let us comfort ourselves with hopes, that it is but a lady's humour, which she will be soon weary of, for when her melancholy fit is over, she will come forth of her cloister, and be fonder to marry than if she had never gone in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102110" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102120">Well, since she is gone, let us assault the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102130" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102140">What, the old woman that hath never a tooth in her head?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102150" who="A53060_19-comerade">
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102160">Why, she is rich, and she will kiss the softer for having no bones in her mouth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102170" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102180">The devil shall kiss her before I will; besides, an old woman is thought a witch.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102190" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102200">Pish, that is because they are grown ill-favoured with age, and all young people think whatsoever is ill-favoured belongs to the devil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102210" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102220">An ancient man is a comely sight, being grave and wise by experience, and what he hath lost in his person, he hath gained in his understanding; besides, beauty in men looks as unhandsome as age in women, as being effeminate; but an old woman looks like the picture of envy, with hollow eyes, fallen checks, lank sides, black pale complexion, and more wrinkles than time hath minutes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102230" who="A53060_19-comerade">
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102240">Nay by your favour, some old women look like the full moon, with a red, swelled, great, broad face, and their bodies like as a spongy cloud, thick and gross, like our fat hostess.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102250" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102260">Gentlemen, why do you rail against ancient women so much, since those that are wise will never marry such boys as you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102270" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102280">It is to be observed, that always old girls match themselves with young boys.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102290" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102300">None but fools will do so.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102310" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102320">Why did you or any man else ever know a wise old woman, or a chaste young woman in their lives? for the one dotes with age, the other is corrupted with flattery, which is a bawd to self-conceit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102330" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102340">Grant it be so, yet it is better to marry an old doting fool, than a wanton young filly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102350" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <pb facs="324" n="619"/>
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102360">For my part, I think now it is the best way to marry none, since madam Jantil is gone, but to live like the Lacedmonians, all in common.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102370" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102380">I am of another opinion, wherefore if you will go along with me to the old widow madam passionate, and help to countenance my suit, I shall take it as an act of friendship.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102390" who="A53060_19-comerade">
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102400">Come, we will be thy pillars to support thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102410">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="10" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e102420">
            <head>Scene 10.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102430">Enter Nell careless, and doll Pacify.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102440" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102450">What, doth thy lady resolve to live an anchoret?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102460" who="A53060_19-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102470">I think so.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102480" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102490">How doth she pass away her time in her solitary self?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102500" who="A53060_19-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102510">Why, as soon as she rises she goeth to my lord's tomb, and says her prayers, than she returns and eats some little breakfast, as a crust of bread and a draught of water, than she goeth to her gallery and walks and contemplates all the forenoon, then about twelve o'clock at noon she goeth to the tomb again and says more prayers, then returns and eats a small dinner of some spoon-meats, and most of the afternoon she sits by the tomb and reads, or walks in the cloister, and views the pictures of my lord that are placed upon the walls, then in the evening she says her evening prayers at the tomb, and eats some light supper, and then prays at the tomb before she goeth to bed, and at midnight she rises and takes a white waxen torch lighted in her hand, and goeth to the tomb to pray, and then returns to bed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102520" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102530">Faith she prays often enough in the day, she shall not need to pray at midnight; but why doth she rise just at midnight?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102540" who="A53060_19-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102550">I know not, unless she is of that opinion which some have been of, which is that the souls or spirits of the dead rise at that hour out of their graves and tombs, to visit the face of the earth, and perhaps my lady watches or hopes to converse by that means with my lord's ghost: for since she cannot converse with him living, she desires to converse with him dead, or otherwise she would not spend most of her time at this tomb as she doth; but how doth thy lady spend her time now?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102560" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102570">Faith as a lady should do, with nourishing her body with good hearty meats and drink. And though my lady doth not pray at midnight, yet she converses with spirits at that time of night.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102580" who="A53060_19-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102590">What spirits?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102600" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102610">Marry spirits distilled from wine and other cordials, which she drinks when she wakes, which is at midnight; but do you watch fast and pray as thy lady doth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102620" who="A53060_19-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102630">No truly, for I feed with the rest of my lady's servants, which live within the house without the cloister, and they eat and drink more liberally.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102640">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="11" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e102650">
            <pb facs="325" n="620"/>
            <head>Scene 11.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102660">Enter monsieur la gravity, monsieur companion, and monsieur comrade, as to madam passionates house; enter madam passionates gentleman usher. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102670" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102680">Sir, we come to kiss the hands of the lady passionate, if you please to inform your lady of us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102690" who="A53060_19-gentleman_usher">
              <speaker>Gentleman usher.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102700">I shall, if't please you to enter into another room.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102710">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="12" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e102720">
            <head>Scene 12.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102730">Enter Doll Pacify, as to her lady madam passionate in her chamber where her cabinets were. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102740" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102750">Madam, there are three gentlemen come to visit you, desiring you would give them leave to kiss your hands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102760" who="A53060_19-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102770">Shut down the lid of the seller of strong-waters, and rid away the loose things that lie about, that my chamber may appear in some order.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102780">The maid sets things in order, whilst the old lady is trimming herself in the looking-glass.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102790" who="A53060_19-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102800">Bring in those gentlemen?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102810">The maid goes out, then enters with the gentlemen; the two young men speak to each other the time that monsieur la gravity is saluting. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102820" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102830">I marry sir, here is a comfortable smell indeed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102840" who="A53060_19-comerade">
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102850">Faith the smell of these spirits overcomes my spirits, for I am ready to swoon.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102860">Then they go and salute the lady.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102870" who="A53060_19-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102880">Pray gentlemen sit down.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102890">They sit.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102900">Truly I have had so great a wind in my stomach as it hath troubled me very much.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102910">Companion speaks softly to comrade.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102920" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102930">Which to express the better, she rasps at every word to make a full stop.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102940" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102950">Perchance madam you have eaten some meat that digests not well.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e102960">Speaks aside.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102970" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <pb facs="325" n="621"/>
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e102980">A toad.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e102990" who="A53060_19-passionate">
              <speaker>Lady passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103000">No, truly I cannot guess what should cause it, unless it be an old pippin, and that is accounted a great restorative.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103010">She fetches a great sigh.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103020">But I believe it is the drugs of my sorrow which stick in my stomach: for I have grieved mightily for my dead husband rest his soul; he was a good man, and as kind a husband as ever woman had.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103030" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103040">But the destinies madam are not to be controlled, death seizes on all, be it early or late; wherefore every one is to make their life as happy as they can; since life is so short; and in order to that, you should choose a new companion to live withal; wherefore you must marry again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103050" who="A53060_19-passionate">
              <speaker>Lady passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103060">'Tis true, the destinies are not to be controlled as you say, wherefore if my destiny be to marry, I shall marry, or else I shall die a widow.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103070">Monsieur companion aside softly, as in the ear of monsieur comrade.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103080" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103090">She will lay the fault of her second marriage on destiny, as many the like foolish actions are laid to destiny's charge, which she was never guilty of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103100" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103110">If I should guess at your destiny, I should judge you will marry again, by the quickness of your eyes which are fair and lovely.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103120">She simpers.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103130" who="A53060_19-passionate">
              <speaker>Lady passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103140">O sir you flatter me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103150" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103160">He be sworn that he doth.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103170">Aside.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103180" who="A53060_19-passionate">
              <speaker>Lady passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103190">But my eyes were good, as I have been told, both by my glass and friends, when I was young, but now my face is in the autumnal.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103200">Softly to comrade aside. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103210" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103220">Nay faith, it is in the midst of winter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103230" who="A53060_19-passionate">
              <speaker>Lady passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103240">But now you talk of eyes, that young gentleman's eyes (Points to companion) do so resemble my husbands as I can scarce look off from them, they have a good aspect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103250" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103260">I am glad they have an influence upon your ladyship.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103270">She speaks as softly to herself.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103280" who="A53060_19-passionate">
              <speaker>La. passion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103290">By my faith wittily answered, I dare say he is a notable youth.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103300">Sir, for resemblance of him which is dead, I shall desire your continued acquaintance.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103310">Companion softly to comrade.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103320" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103330">She woos me with her husband's dead skull.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103340">I shall render my service to your ladyship.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103350"><pb facs="326" n="622"/>She bows him thanks with simpering and smiling countenance, and a bridled head. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103360">Monsieur la gravity softly to himself. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103370" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103380">Those young youths I perceive will be my ruin if not prevented. Madam, will your ladyship honour me so much as to give me the private hearing of a few words.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103390" who="A53060_19-passionate">
              <speaker>Lady passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103400">Yes sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103410">She removes with him a little space.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103420" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103430">Madam, although I am not such a one as I could wish myself for your sake, yet I am a gentleman, and what I want in person or estate, my affection, respect, and tender regard to your person, worth, and merit shall make good; besides madam, my years suiting to your ladyships will make the better agreement in marriage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103440" who="A53060_19-passionate">
              <speaker>Lady passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103450">Sir you must excuse me; for though you merit a better wife than I, yet I cannot answer your affections; wherefore I desire you will desist in your suit, for I am resolved, if I do marry, to please my fancy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103460" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103470">If your ladyship cannot love me, heaven forbid I should marry you; wherefore I wish your ladyship such a husband as you can fancy best, and love most.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103480">They return to the two other gentlemen, they all take their leaves.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103490">Madam your most humble servant.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103500">They go through the stage, and come upon it again, as it were at the street door.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103510" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103520">Where is our coach?</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103530">Enter a footman.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103540">Call the coach to the door?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103550">Enter Doll Pacify as from her lady to monsieur companion.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103560" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103570">Sir, pray give me leave to speak a word or two with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103580" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103590">As many as you please.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103600" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103610">Sir, my lady desires your company tomorrow to dinner, but she desires you will come alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103620" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103630">Pray give your lady thanks for her favours, and tell her if I can possibly I will wait on her ladyship.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103640">Doll Pacify goes out. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103650" who="A53060_19-comerade">
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103660">Now what encouragement have you from the old lady?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103670" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103680">Faith so much as I am ashamed of it, for she invites me to come alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103690" who="A53060_19-comerade">
              <pb facs="326" n="623"/>
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103700">On my life if thou wilt not woo her, she will woo thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103710" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103720">Like enough; for there is nothing so impudent as an old woman, they will put a young man be he never so deboist out of countenance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103730" who="A53060_19-comerade">
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103740">But faith consider of it, for she is rich.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103750" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103760">So is the devil, as poets say, Pluto the god of riches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103770" who="A53060_19-comerade">
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103780">I grant it, and is not he best served? for every one bows with respect, nay worships and adores riches, and they have reason so to do, since all are miserable that have it not, for poverty is a torment beyond all sufferance, which causes many to hang themselves, either in the chain of infamy, or in a hempen rope, or to do act; against the strict laws of a commonwealth which is to commit self-murder; besides, poverty is the slave and drudge, the scorn and reproach of the world, and it makes all younger brothers sherks, and mere cheats, whereas this old lady's riches will not only give you an honest mind, and create noble thoughts, but will give you an honourable reputation in the world: for every one will think you wise although you were a fool, valiant although you were a coward, and you shall have the first offers of all offices, and all officers will be at you devotion, they will attend you as slaves, the lawyers will plead on your side, and judges will give sentence according as you desire, courtiers will flatter you, and divines will pray for you in their pulpits, and if your old lady die, and leave you her wealth, you shall have all the young beautiful virgins in the kingdom gather to that city, town, or village where you live, omitting no art that may prefer them to your affection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103790" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103800">You say well, and I could approve of your counsel, if she would die soon after I had married her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103810" who="A53060_19-comerade">
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103820">Why, put the case she should live a great while, as the truth is old women are tough, and endure long, yet you will have her estate to please yourself withal, which estate will buy you fine horses, great coaches, maintain servants and great retinues to follow you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103830" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103840">But she is so devilish old.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103850" who="A53060_19-comerade">
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103860">Why, let her keep her age to herself, whilst you keep a young mistress to yourself, and it is better to have an old wife that will look after your family, and be careful and watchful therein, and a young mistress, than a young wife, which will be a tyrannical mistress, which will look after nothing but vanities, and love servants, whilst you poor wretch look like a contented cuckold, and so out of countenance as you dare not show your face, whilst she spends your estate running about with every vain idle fellow to plays, masks, balls, exchanges, taverns, or meets at a private friends private lodging, also making great feasts and entertainments, where after dinner and supper, there must be gaming at cards and dice; where for her honour, or at least seeming so, to lose five hundred or a thousand pounds away, and when they rise with or from their losses, singing with a feigned voice, as if it were a trifle not to be considered or considerable, thus if you marry an old and rich lady you may live and spend her estate, but if you marry for youth and beauty, your wife will live and spend your estate; besides, the husband of an old lady lives like the great Turk, having a seraglio, but marrying a young wife you live like a prisoner never durst show your head.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103870" who="A53060_19-la_gravity">
              <pb facs="327" n="624"/>
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103880">He gives you good counsel, and let me advise you to go to this lady as she hath invited you, for I perceive she hath a young tooth in her old head by refusing me, and there is none so fit to pull it out as you are, wherefore go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103890" who="A53060_19-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e103900">Well gentlemen, I will try if my reason and your counsel can prevail in my choice.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103910">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A53060_19-e103920">
          <head>Act iv.</head>
          <div n="13" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e103930">
            <head>Scene 13.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103940">Enter madam Jantil in her habit with a white taper lighted in her hand, the tomb bring thrust upon the stage she goeth to the tomb, then kneels down and seems as praying, after that she rises, holding out the torch with the other hand speaks as follow. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e103950">These verses being writ by my lord, the marquess of Newcastle.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e103960" who="A53060_19-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e103970">Welcome sad thoughts that's heaped up without measure,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e103980">They're joys to me and wealthy sons of treasure;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e103990">Were all my breath turned into sighs 'twould ease me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104000">And showers of tears to bathe my griefs would please me;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104010">Then every groan so kind to take my part,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104020">To vent some sorrows still thus from my heart;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104030">But there's no vacuum, oh my heart is full,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104040">As it vents sorrows new griefs in doth pull;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104050">Is there no comfort left upon the earth? </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104060">Let me consider vegetable birth;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104070">The new born virgin lily of the day,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104080">In a few hours dies, withers away;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104090">And all the odoriferous flowers that's sweet,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104100">Breath but a while, and then with death do meet;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104110">The stouter oak at last doth yield, and must</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104120">Cast his rough skin and crumble all to dust;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104130">But what do sensitives? alas they be,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104140">Beasts, birds and flesh to die as well as we;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104150">And harder minerals though longer stay</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104160">Here for a time, yet at the last decay,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104170">And die as all things else that's in this world,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104180">For into death's arms every thing is hurled;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104190">Alas poor man thou'rt in the worst estate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104200">Thou diest as these, yet an unhappier fate;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104210">Thy life's but trouble still of numerous passions,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104220">Torments thyself in many various fashions;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104230"><pb facs="327" n="625"/> condemned thou art to vexing thoughts within;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104240">When beasts both live and die without a sin;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104250">Oh happy beasts than grazing look no higher,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104260">Or are tormented with thoughts flaming fire;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104270">Thus by thyself and others still annoyed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104280">And made a purpose but to be destroyed</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e104290">Poor man. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104300">Here ends my lord marquess's verses.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104310">Muses some short time, then kneels to the tomb again and prays as to herself, then rises and bows to the tomb, so</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104320">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="14" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e104330">
            <head>Scene 14.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104340">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104350" who="A53060_19-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104360">What news sir of our armies abroad?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104370" who="A53060_19-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104380">Why sir thus, in the time of our masculine armies recruiting, the female army had taken the fort they besieged, where upon the taking of that fort, many considerable towns and strong holds surrendered, and submitted to the female army; whereupon the lady Victoria sent to her husband to bring his army, when the general and all the masculine army came to the female army, much mirth and jesting there was betwixt the heroics and heroickesses, and so well they did agree, as the female army feasted the masculine army, and then gave the possession of the surrendred towns to the lord general, and the lady Victoria, and all her army kept themselves in and about the fort, laying all their victorious spoils therein, and whilst the masculine army is gone to conquer the kingdom of faction, they stay there upon the frontiers, passing their time in heroic sports, as hunting the stags, wild boars, and the like, and those that have the good fortune to kill the chase, is brought to the fort and trenches in triumph, and is Queen until another chase is killed; but we hear the masculine army goeth on with victorious success.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104390" who="A53060_19-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104400">I am very glad to hear it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104410">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="15" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e104420">
            <head>Scene 15.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104430">Enter Doll Pacify, and Nell careless.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104440" who="A53060_19-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104450">O Doll, I hear thy lady is married, and not only married, but she hath married a very young man, one that might be her grandson, or son at least.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104460" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <pb facs="328" n="626"/>
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104470">Yes, yes, my lady doth not intend to live with the dead as your lady doth, but to have the company and pleasure of that which hath most life, which is a young man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104480" who="A53060_19-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104490">Her marriage was very sudden.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104500" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104510">So are all inconsiderated marriages, but happy is the wooing that is not long a doing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104520" who="A53060_19-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104530">If I had been your lady, I would have prolonged the time of my wooing, for the wooing time is the happiest time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104540" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104550">Yes, if she had been as young as you or your lady, but time bids my lady make haste.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104560">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="16" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e104570">
            <head>Scene 16.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104580">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104590" who="A53060_19-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104600">Do you hear the news.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104610" who="A53060_19-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104620">What news?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104630" who="A53060_19-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104640">Why the news is that all the kingdom of faction hath submitted to the kingdom of reformation, and that the armies are returning home.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104650" who="A53060_19-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104660">I am glad of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104670">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="17" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e104680">
            <head>Scene 17.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104690">Enter madam passionate alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104700" who="A53060_19-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104710">O unfortunate woman that I am, I was rich, and lived in plenty, none to control me, I was mistress of myself, estate and family, all my servants obeyed me, none durst contradict me, but all flattered me, filling my ears with praises, my eyes with their humble bow; and respectful behaviours, devising delightful sports to entertain my time, making delicious meats to please my palate, sought out the most comfortable drinks to strengthen and increase my spirits, thus did I live luxuriously, but now I am made a slave, and in my old age which requires rest and peace, which now heaven knows I have but little of, for the minstrels keep me waking, which play whilst my husband and his whores dance, and he is not only contented to live riotously with my estate, but sits amongst his wenches and rails on me, or else comes and scoffs at me to my face; besides, all my servants slight and neglect me; following those that command the purse, for this idle young fellow which I have married first seized on all my goods, then let leases for many lives out of my lands, for which he had great fines, and now he cuts down all my woods, and sells all my lands of inheritance, which I foolishly and fondly delivered by deed of gift, the first day I married, divesting myself of all power, which power had I kept in my own hands I might have been used better, whereas now<pb facs="328" n="627"/> when he comes home drunk, he swears and storms, and kicks me out of my warm bed, and makes me sit shivering and shaking in the cold, whilst my maid takes my place; but I find I cannot live long, for age and disorders bring weakness and sickness, and weakness and sickness bring death, wherefore my marriage bed is like to prove my grave, whilst my husband's curses are my passing bell, hay ho.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104720">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="18" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e104730">
            <head>Scene 18.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104740">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104750" who="A53060_19-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104760">I hear the army is returning home.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104770" who="A53060_19-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104780">Yes, for they are returned as far back as to the effeminate army, and all the masculine commanders have presented all the female commanders with their spoils got in the kingdom of faction, as a tribute to their heroical acts, and due for their assistance, and safety of their lives and country.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104790" who="A53060_19-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104800">And do not you hear what privileges and honours the King and his counsel hath resolved and agreed upon to be given to the female army, and the honours particularly to be given the lady Victoria?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104810" who="A53060_19-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104820">No.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104830" who="A53060_19-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104840">Why then I will tell you some, the lady Victoria shall be brought through the city in triumph, which is a great honour, for never any one makes triumphs in a monarchy but the King himself; then that there shall be a blank for the female army to write their desires and demands; also there is an armour of gold and a sword a making, the hilt being set with diamonds, and a chariot all gilt and embroidered to be presented to the lady Victoria, and the city is making great preparation against her arrival.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104850" who="A53060_19-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104860">Certainly she is a lady that deserves as much as can be given either from Kings, states, or poets.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104870">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="19" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e104880">
            <head>Scene 19.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104890">Enter the lady Jantil as being sick brought by two men in a chair, and set by the tomb of her dead lord, and many servants and friends about her weeping. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104900" who="A53060_19-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104910">Where is my secretary?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104920" who="A53060_19-secretary">
              <speaker>Secretary.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104930">Here madam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104940" who="A53060_19-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104950">Read the will I caused you to write down.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e104960" who="A53060_19-missing">
              <pb facs="329" n="628"/>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e104970">The will read.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104980">I Jantil the widow of Seigneur Valeroso, do here make a free gift of all these following.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e104990">Item, all my husband's horses and saddles and whatsoever belongs to those horses, with all his arms, pikes, guns, drums, trumpets, colours, wagons, coaches, tents, and all he had belonging to the war, to be distributed amongst his officers of war, according to each degree, I freely give.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105000">Item, all his library of books I give to that college he was a pupil in when he was at the university.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105010">Item, to all his servants I give the sum of their yearly wages to be yearly paid them during their lives.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105020">Item, I give two hundred pounds a year pension to his chaplin doctor educature during his life.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105030">Item, I give a hundred pound a year pension to his steward during his life.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105040">Item, I give fifty pound a year pension to his secretary during his life.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105050">Item, I give a hundred pound per annum, for the use and repair of this tomb of my dead husbands.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105060">Item, I give a thousand pounds a year to maintain ten religious persons to live in this place or house by this tomb.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105070">Item, I give three thousand pounds to enlarge the house, and three thousand pounds more to build a chapel by my husband's tomb.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105080">Item, two hundred pounds a year I give for the use and repair of the house and chapel.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105090">Item, I give my maid Nell careless a thousand pound to live a single life.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105100">Item, I give the rest of my estate which was left me by my husband seigneur Valeroso to the next of his name.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e105110">These following speeches and songs of hers, my lord the marquess of Newcastle writ. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e105120" who="A53060_19-jantel">
              <speaker>Iantil.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105130">So 'tis well</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105140">Oh death hath shaked me kindly by the hand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105150">To bid me welcome to the silent grave;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105160">'Tis dead and nuns sweet death how thou dost court me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105170">Oh let me clap thy fallen cheeks with joy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105180">And kiss the emblem of what once was lips,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105190">Thy hollow eyes I am in love withal,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105200">And thy balled head beyond youths best curled hair,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105210">Prithee embrace me in thy colder arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105220">And hug me there to sit me for thy mansion;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105230">Then bid our neighbour worms to feast with us,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105240">Thus to rejoice upon my holy day;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105250">But thou art slow, I prithee hasten death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105260">And linger not my hopes thus with thy stay,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105270">'Tis not thy fault thou sayest, but fearful nature</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105280">That hinders thus death's progress in his way;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105290">O foolish nature thinks thou canst withstand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105300">Death's conquering and inevitable hand;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105310">Let me have music for divertisement,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105320"><pb facs="329" n="629"/> this is my mask, death's ball, my soul to dance</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105330">Out of her frail and fleshly prison here;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105340">O could I now dissolve and melt, I long</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105350">To free my soul in slumbers with a song;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105360">In soft and quiet sleep here as I lie,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105370">Steal gently out oh soul, and let me die. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e105380">Lies as asleep .</stage>
            <lg type="song" xml:id="A53060_19-e105390">
              <head>Song.</head>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105400">O you gods pure angels send her,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105410">Here about her to attend her;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105420">Let them wait and here condole,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105430">Till receive her spotless soul;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105440">So serene it is and fair,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105450">It will sweeten all the air;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105460">You this holy wonder hears,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105470">With the music of the spheres;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105480">Her souls journey in a trice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105490">You'll bring safe to paradise;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105500">And rejoice the saints that say,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105510">She makes heavens holiday. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e105520">The song ended she opens her eyes, then speaks.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105530">Death hath not finished yet his work, he's slow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105540">But he is sure, for he will do't at last;</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105550">Turn me to my dear lord, that I may breathe</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105560">My last words unto him, my dear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105570">Our marriage joined our flesh and bone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105580">Contracted by those holy words made one;</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105590">But by our loves we joined each others heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105600">And vowed that death should never us depart;</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105610">Now death doth marry us, since now we must,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105620">Ashes to ashes be mingling our dust,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105630">And our joyed souls in heaven married then,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105640">When our frail bodies rise, we'll wed again;</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105650">And now I am joyed to lie by thy loved side,</l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105660">My soul with thy soul shall in heaven reside. </l>
            <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105670">For that is all my</l>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e105680">In this last word she dies, which when her servants saw, they cried out she is dead, she is dead.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e105690">Here ends my lord marquess's writing.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e105700"><pb facs="330" n="630"/>Doctor educature says thus. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e105710" who="A53060_19-educature">
              <speaker>Doctor educature.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105720">She is dead; she is dead, the body hence convey,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_19-e105730">And to our mistress our last rights we'll pay. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e105740">So they laid her by her husband upon the tomb, and drawing off the tomb go out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e105750">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A53060_19-e105760">
          <head>Act v.</head>
          <div n="20" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e105770">
            <head>Scene 20.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e105780">Enter citizens wives and their apprentices.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e105790" who="A53060_19-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 citizens wife. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105800">Where shall we stand to see this triumphing?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e105810" who="A53060_19-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 citizens wife. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105820">I think neighbour this is the best place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e105830" who="A53060_19-yyyy_3">
              <speaker>3 citizens wife. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105840">We shall be mightily crowded there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e105850" who="A53060_19-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 citizens wife. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105860">For my part I will stand here, and my apprentice Nathaniel shall stand by me, and keep off the crowd from crowding me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e105870" who="A53060_19-nathaniel">
              <speaker>Nathaniel.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105880">Truly mistress that is more than I am able to do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e105890" who="A53060_19-yyyy_3">
              <speaker>3 citizens wife. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105900">Well neighbour if you be resolved to stand here, we will keep you company. Timothy stand by me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e105910" who="A53060_19-timothy">
              <speaker>Timothy.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105920">If you stand here mistress the squibs will run under your clothes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e105930" who="A53060_19-yyyy_3">
              <speaker>3 citizens wife. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105940">No matter Timothy, let them run where they will.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e105950">They take their stand.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e105960" who="A53060_19-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 citizens wife. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105970">I hope neighbour none will stand before us, for I would not but see this lady Victoria for any thing, for they say she hath brought articles for all women to have as many husbands as they will, and all tradesmen's wives shall have as many apprentices as they will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e105980" who="A53060_19-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 citizens wife. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e105990">The gods bless her for it.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106000">Enter a crowd of people.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106010">She is coming, she is coming.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106020">Officers come.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106030">Stand up close, make way.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106040"><pb facs="330" n="631"/>Enter many prisoners which march by two and two, then enter many that carry the conquered spoils, then enters the lady Victoria in a gilt chariot drawn with eight white horses, four on a breast, the horses covered with cloth of gold, and great plumes of feathers on their heads. </stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106050">The lady Victoria was adorned after this manner; she had a coat on all embroidered with silver and gold, which coat reached no further than the calves of her legs, and on her legs and feet she had buskins and sandals embroidered suitable to her coat; on her head she had a wreath or garland of laurel, and her hair curled and loosely flowing; in her hand a crystal bolt headed with gold at each end, and after the chariot marched all her female officers with laurel branches in their hands, and after them the inferior she soldiers, then going through the stage, as through the city, and so entering again, where on the midst of the stage as if it were the midst of the city, the magistrates meet her, so her chariot makes a stand, and one as the recorder speaks a speech to her.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106060">Victorious lady, you have brought peace safety and conquest to this kingdom by your prudent conduct and valiant actions, which never any of your sex in this kingdom did before you. Wherefore our gracious King is pleased to give you that which was never granted nor given to any before, which is to make you triumphant, for no triumph is ever made in monarchies, but by the Kings thereof; besides our gracious King hath caused an act to be made and granted to all your sex, which act I have order to declare, as</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106070">First, that all women shall hereafter in this kingdom be mistress in their own houses and families.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106080">Secondly, they shall sit at the upper end of the table above their husbands.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106090">Thirdly, that they shall keep the purse.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106100">Fourthly, they shall order their servants, turning from, or taking into their service what number they will, placing them how they will, and ordering them how they will, and giving them what wages they will or think fit.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106110">Fiftly, they shall buy in what provisions they will.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106120">Sixtly, all the jewels, plate, and household furniture they shall claim as their own, and order them as they think good.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106130">Seventhly, they shall wear what fashioned clothes they will.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106140">Eightly, they shall go abroad when they will, without control, or giving of any account thereof.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106150">Ninthly, they shall eat when they will, and of what they will, and as much as they will, and as often as they will.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106160">Tenthly, they shall go to plays, masks, balls, churchings, christenings, preachings, whensoever they will, and as fine and bravely attired as they will.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106170">Lastly, that they shall be of their husband's counsel.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106180">When those were read, all the women cried out, God save the King, God save the King, and heaven reward the lady Victoria.</stage>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106190"><pb facs="331" n="632"/>Then an act was read concerning the lady Victoria. </stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106200">As for you most gallant lady, the King hath caused to be enacted, that</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106210">First, all poets shall strive to set forth your praise.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106220">Secondly, that all your gallant acts shall be recorded in story, and put in the chief library of the kingdom.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106230">Thirdly, that your arms you fought in, shall be set in the King's armoury.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106240">Fourthly, that you shall always wear a laurel garland.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106250">Fiftly, you shall have place next to the King's children.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106260">Sixtly, that all those women that have committed such faults as is a dishonour to the female sex, shall be more severely punished than heretofore, in not following your exemplary virtues, and all those that have followed your example shall have respective honour done to them by the state.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106270">Seventhly and lastly, your figure shall be cast in brass, and then set in the midst of the city armed as it was in the day of battle.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106280">The lady Victoria rises up in her chariot, and then bows herself to the magistrates. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e106290" who="A53060_19-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106300">Worthy sir, the honour and privileges my gracious King and sovereign hath bestowed upon me, is beyond my merit.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106310">Then was read the acts concerning the rest of the female army.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106320">Our gracious King hath caused to be enacted, as</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106330">First, all the chief female commanders shall have place, as every lords wife shall take place of an Earls wife that hath not been a soldier in the army; every knights wife before a baron's wife that hath not been a soldier in the army; an esquires wife before a knight's wife; a doctor's wife before an esquires wife that hath not been soldiers in the army; a citizen's wife before a doctor's wife; a yeoman's wife before a citizen's wife that hath not been a soldier in the army; and all tradesmen's wives that have been soldiers in the army shall be free in all the corporations in this kingdom, these acts during their lives, and all the chief commanders shall be presented according to their quality and merit.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106340">All the female soldiers cried out, God save the King, God save the King.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106350">After this the lady Victoria is drawn on her chariot, and the rest walk after all. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106360">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="21" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e106370">
            <pb facs="331" n="633"/>
            <head>Scene 21.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106380">Enter Doll Pacify, and Nell careless.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e106390" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106400">O Nell, I hear thy lady is dead, and hath left thee a thousand pound.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106410">Nell weeps. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e106420" who="A53060_19-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106430">What dost thou weep for joy of thy thousand pound, or for grief of thy lady's death?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e106440" who="A53060_19-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106450">I wish my lady had lived, although I had begged all my life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e106460" who="A53060_19-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106470">I am not of your mind, I had rather live well myself, as to live in plenty, than to live poor for the life of anybody , and if upon that condition my lady would leave me a thousand pound, I care not if she died tomorrow; but my young master hath robbed me of all: but Nell, for all thou art left a thousand pound, it is upon such a condition, as for my part, had it been to me, I should not thank the giver, for they say it is given thee upon condition to live a single life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e106480" who="A53060_19-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106490">Truly I have seen so much sorrow in my lady, and so much folly in your lady concerning husbands, that had not my lady enjoined me to live a single life, I would never have married; wherefore my lady's generosity did not only provide for my bodily life, and for my plentiful living, but provided for the tranquillity of my mind, for which I am trebly obliged to reverence her memory.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106500">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="22" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_19-e106510">
            <head>Scene 22.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106520">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e106530" who="A53060_19-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106540">The lady Victoria hath been at court, and hath had public audience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e106550" who="A53060_19-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106560">Yes, and the lady Victoria and her she officers and commanders have distributed all their spoils got in these wars amongst the common she soldiers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e106570" who="A53060_19-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106580">All the ladies that went not with the army look most pitifully out of countenance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e106590" who="A53060_19-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106600">Yes, and they are much troubled that the heroics shall take place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e106610" who="A53060_19-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106620">The lord general seems to be very proud of his lady, methinks he looks upon her with a most pleased eye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_19-e106630" who="A53060_19-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_19-e106640">He hath reason, for never man had so gallant and noble a lady, not more virtuous and loving a wife than the lord general hath.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_19-e106650">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A53060_19-e106660">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A53060_19"><item xml:id="A53060_19-compagnion" n="24">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-compagnion</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">24</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-doll_pacify" n="20">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-doll_pacify</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">20</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-la_gravity" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-la_gravity</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-passionate" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-passionate</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-gentleman_2" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-gentleman_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-nell_careless" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-nell_careless</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-comerade" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-comerade</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-yyyy_1" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A53060_19-victoria" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-victoria</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-gentleman_1" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-gentleman_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-yyyy_2" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-yyyy_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-jantel" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-jantel</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-comfort" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-comfort</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-yyyy_3" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-yyyy_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-timothy" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-timothy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-educature" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-educature</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-all_women" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-all_women</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-all_commanders" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-all_commanders</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-missing" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-missing</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-gentleman_usher" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-gentleman_usher</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-messenger" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-nathaniel" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-nathaniel</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-secretary" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-secretary</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_19-all_female_commanders" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_19-all_female_commanders</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

