<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1 Bell in Campo<date type="creation_date">1662</date></title>
        <author>Cavendish, Margaret</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A53060_18.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>356 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">11861873</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing N868.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">50022</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53060</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
            <author>Newcastle, William Cavendish, 1592-1676.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[24], 679 [i.e. 675], [4] p. : ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by A. Warren, for John Martyn, James Allestry, and Tho. Dicas ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1662.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>First edition.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Errata: p. [4] at end.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A53060_18-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A53060_18-e100020">
      <div n="1" type="play" xml:id="A53060_18-e100030">
        <pb facs="303" n="578"/>
        <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A53060_18-e100040">
          <list xml:id="A53060_18-e100050">
            <head>The actors names.</head>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100060">The lord general.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100070">Seigneur Valeroso.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100080">Monsieur la Hardy.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100090">Monsieur companion.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100100">Monsieur comrade.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100110">Monsieur la gravity.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100120">Captain Ruffell.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100130">Captain Whiffell, and several other gentlemen. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100140">Doctor educature.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100150">Doctor comfort.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100160">Stewards, messengers and servants. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100170">Lady Victoria.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100180">Madam Jantil.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100190">Madam passionate.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100200">Madam Ruffell.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100210">Madam Whiffell.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100220">Doll pacify, madam Passionate's maid. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_18-e100230">Nell careless, madam Jantil's maid, other servants and heroickesses. </item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <pb facs="303" n="577"/>
        <pb facs="304" n="578"/>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A53060_18-e100240">
          <pb facs="304" n="579"/>
          <head>The first part of bell in Campo.</head>
          <head type="sub">Act i.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e100250">
            <head>Scene 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e100260">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100270" who="A53060_18-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100280">You hear how this kingdom of reformation is preparing for war against the kingdom of faction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100290" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100300">Yea, for I hear the kingdom of faction resolves to war with this kingdom of reformation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100310" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100320">'Tis true, for there are great preparations of either side, men are raised of all sorts and ages fit to bear arms, and of all degrees to command and obey, and there is one of the gallantest and noblest persons in this kingdom, which is made general to command in chief, for he is a man that is both valiant and well experienced in wars, temperate and just in peace, wise and politic in public affairs, careful and prudent in his own family, and a most generous person.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100330" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100340">Indeed I have heard that he is a most excellent soldier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100350" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100360">He is so, for he is not one that sets forth to the wars with great resolutions and hopes, and returns with maskerd fears, and despairs; neither is he like those that take more care, and are more industrious to get gay clothes, and fine feathers, to flaunt in the field, and vapour in their march, than to get useful and necessary provision; but before he will march, he will have all things ready, and proper for use, as to fit himself with well-tempered arms, which are light to be worn, yet musket proof; for he means not to run away, nor to yield his life upon easy terms unto his enemy; for he desires to conquer, and not vaingloriously to show his courage by a careless neglect or a vain carelessness; also he chooses such horses as are useful in war, such as have been made subject to the hand and heel, that have been taught to trot on the haunches, to change, to gallop, to stop, and such horses as have spirit and strength, yet quiet and sober natures; he regards more the goodness of the horses than the colours or marks, and more the fitness of his saddles than the embroidery; also he takes more care that his waggons should be easy to follow, and light in their carriage, than to have them painted and gilded; and he takes greater care that his tents should be made, so as to be suddenly put up, and as quickly pulled down, than for the setting and embroidering his arms thereupon; also he take more care to have useful servants than numerous servants; and as he is industrious and careful for his particular affairs, so he is for the general affairs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100370" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <pb facs="305" n="580"/>
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100380">A good soldier makes good preparations, and a good general doth both for himself and army, and as the general hath showed himself a good soldier by the preparations he had made to march, so he hath shown himself a wise man by the settlement he hath made, in what he hath to leave behind him; for I hear he hath settled and ordered his house and family.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100390" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100400">He hath so, and he hath a fair young and virtuous lady that he must leave behind him, which cannot choose but trouble him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100410" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100420">The wisest man that is, cannot order or have all things to his own contentment.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e100430">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e100440">
            <head>Scene 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e100450">Enter the lord general, and the lady Victoria his wife. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100460" who="A53060_18-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100470">My dear heart, you know I am commanded to the wars, and had I not such wife as you are, I should have thought fortune had done me a favour to employ my life in heroical actions for the service of my country, or to give me a honourable death, but to leave you is such a cross as my nature sinks under; but wheresoever you are there will be my life, I shall only carry a body which may sight, but my soul and all the powers thereof will remain with thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100480" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100490">Husband, I shall take this expression of love but for feigning words, if you leave me; for 'tis against nature to part with that we love best, unless it be for the beloveds preservation, which cannot be mine, for my life lives in yours, and the comfort of that life in your company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100500" who="A53060_18-general">
              <speaker>Lord general.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100510">I know you love me so well, as you had rather part with my life than I should part from my honour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100520" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100530">'Tis true, my love persuades me so to do, knowing fame is a double life, as infamy is a double death; nay I should persuade you to those actions, were they never so dangerous, were you unwilling thereunto, or could they create a world of honour, fully inhabited with praises; but I would not willingly part with your life for an imaginary or supposed honour, which dies in the womb before it is born; thus I love you the best, preferring the best of what is yours; but I am but in the second place in your affections, for you prefer your honour before me; 'tis true, it is the better choice, but it shows I am not the best beloved, which makes you follow and glue to that and leave me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100540" who="A53060_18-general">
              <speaker>Lord general.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100550">Certainly wife my honour is your honour, and your honour will be buried in my disgrace, which heaven avert; for I prefer yours before my own, insomuch as I would have your honour to be the crown of my glory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100560" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100570">Then I must partake of your actions, and go along with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100580" who="A53060_18-general">
              <speaker>Lord general.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100590">What to the wars?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100600" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100610">To any place where you are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100620" who="A53060_18-general">
              <speaker>Lord general.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100630">But wife you consider not, as that long marches, ill lodgings, much watching, cold nights, scorching days, hunger and danger are<pb facs="305" n="581"/> ill companions for ladies, their acquaintance displeases; their conversation is rough and rude, being too boisterous for ladies; their tender and strengthless constitutions cannot encounter nor grapple therewith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100640" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100650">'Tis said, that love overcomes all things: in your company long marches will be but as a breathing walk, the hard ground feel as a featherbed, and the starry sky a spangled canopy, hot days a stove to cure cold agues, hunger as fasting days or an eve to devotion, and danger is honour's triumphant chariot.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100660" who="A53060_18-general">
              <speaker>Lord general.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100670">But nature hath made women like China, or porcelain, they must be used gently, and kept warily, or they will break and fall on death's head: besides, the inconveniences in an army are so many, as put patience herself out of humour; besides, there is such inconveniences as modesty cannot allow of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100680" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100690">There is no immodestly in natural effects, but in unnatural abuses; but contrive it as well as you can, for go I must, or either I shall die, or dishonour you; for if I stay behind you, the very imaginations of your danger will torture me, sad dreams will affright me, every little noise will sound as your passing bell, and my fearful mind will transform every object like as your pale ghost, until I am smothered in my sighs, shrouded in my tears, and buried in my griefs; for whatsoever is joined with true love, will die absented, or else their love will die, for love and life are joined together; as for the honour of constancy, or constant fidelity, or the dishonour of inconstancy, the lovingest and best wife in all story that is recorded to be, the most perfectest and constantest wife in her husband's absence was Penelope, Ulysses wife, yet she did not barricado her ears from love's soft alarms; but parled and received amorous treaties, and made a truce until she and her lovers could agree and conclude upon conditions, and questionless there were amorous glances shot from loving eyes of either party; and though the siege of her chastity held out, yet her husband's wealth and estate was impoverished, and great riots committed both in his family and kingdom, and her suitors had absolute power thereof; thus though she kept the fort of her chastity, she lost the kingdom, which was her husband's estate and government, which was a dishonour both to her and her husband; so if you let me stay behind you, it will be a thousand to one but either you will lose me in death, or your honour in life, where if you let me go you will save both; for if you will consider and reckon all the married women you have heard or read of, that were absented from their husbands, although upon just and necessary occasions, but had some ink of aspersions flung upon them, although their wives were old, ill-favoured, decrepit and diseased women, or were they as pure as light, or as innocent as heaven; and wheresoever this ink of aspersions is thrown, it sticks so fast, that the spots are never rubbed out, should it fall on saints, they must wear the marks as a badge of misfortunes, and what man had not better be thought or called an uxorious husband, than to be despised and laughed at, as being but thought a cuckold? the first only expresses a tender and noble nature, the second sounds as a base, cowardly, poor, dejected, forsaken creature; and as for the immodesty you mentioned, there is none, for there can be no breach of modesty, but in unlawful actions, or at least unnecessary ones; but what law can warrant, and necessity doth enforce, is allowable amongst men, pure before angels, religious before gods, when unchoosing persons, improper places, unfit times, condemn those actions that<pb facs="306" n="582"/> are good in themselves, make them appear base to men, hateful to angels, and wicked to gods, and what is more lawful, fitting, and proper, than for a man and wife to be inseparable together?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100700" who="A53060_18-general">
              <speaker>Lord general.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100710">Well, you have used so much rhetoric to persuade, as you have left me none to deny you, wherefore I am resolved you shall try what your tender sex can endure; but I believe when you hear the bullets fly about you, you will wish yourself at home, and repent your rash adventure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100720" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100730">I must prove false first, for love doth give me courage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100740" who="A53060_18-general">
              <speaker>Lord general.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100750">Then come along, I shall your courage try.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100760" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100770">He follow you, though in death's arms I lie.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e100780">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e100790">
            <head>Scene 3.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e100800">Enter the two former gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100810" who="A53060_18-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100820">Well met, for I was going to thy lodging to call thee to make up the company of good fellows, which hath appointed a meeting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100830" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100840">Faith you must go with the odd number, or get another in my room, for I am going about some affairs which the lord general hath employed me in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100850" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100860">I perceive by thee that public employments spoil private meetings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100870" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100880">You say right, for if every one had good employment, vice would be out of fashion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100890" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100900">What do you call vice?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100910" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100920">Drinking, wenching, and gaming.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100930" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100940">As for two of them, as drinking and wenching, especially wenching, no employment can abolish them, no, not the most severest, devotest, nor danger: for the statesman divines, and soldiers, which are the most and greatest employed, will leave all other affairs to kiss a mistress.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100950" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100960">But you would have me go to a tavern and not to a mistress.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100970" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e100980">Why, you may have a mistress in a tavern if you please.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e100990" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101000">Well, if my other affairs will give me any leisure, I will come to you.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101010">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e101020">
            <head>Scene 4.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101030">Enter four or five other gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101040" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101050">The lord general was accounted a discreet and wise man, but he shows but little wisdom in this action of carrying his wife along with him to the wars, to be a clog at his heels, a chain to his hands, an encumbrance in his march, obstruction in his way; for she will be always<pb facs="306" n="583"/> puling and sick, and whining, and crying, and tired, and froward, and if her dog should be left in any place, as being forgotten, all the whole army must make a halt whilst the dog is fetched, and trooper after trooper must be sent to bring intelligence of the dogs coming, but if there were such a misfortune that the dog could not be found, the whole army must be dispersed for the search of it, and if it should be lost, than there must seem to be more lamentation for it than if the enemy had given us an entire defeat, or else we shall have frowns instead of preferments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101060" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101070">The truth is, I wonder the general will trouble himself with his wife, when it is the only time a married man hath to enjoy a mistress without jealousy, a sprightly sound wench, that may go along without trouble, with bag and baggage, to wash his linen, and make his field bed, and attend to his call, when a wife requires more attendance than sentries to watch the enemy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101080" who="A53060_18-gentleman_3">
              <speaker>3 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101090">For my part I wonder as much that any man should be so fond of his wife as to carry her with him; for I am only glad of the wars, because I have a good pretence to leave my wife behind me; besides an army is a quiet, solitary place, and yields a man a peaceable life compared to that at home: for what with the faction and mutiny amongst his servants, and the noise the women make, for their tongues like as an alarum beat up quatres in every corner of the house, that a man can take no rest; besides every day he hath a set battle with his wife, and from the army of her angry thoughts, she sends forth such volleys of words with her gunpowder anger, and the fire of her fury, as breaks all the ranks and files of content, and puts happiness to an utter rout, so as for my part I am forced to run away in discontent, although some husbands will stay, and fight for the victory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101100" who="A53060_18-gentleman_4">
              <speaker>4 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101110">Gentlemen, gentlemen, prey condemn not a man for taking his lawful delight, or for ordering his private affairs to his own humour, every man is free to himself, and to what is his, as long as he disturbs not his neighbours, nor breaks the peace of the kingdom, nor disorders the commonwealth, but submits to the laws, and obeys the magistrates without dispute; besides gentlemen, 'tis no crime nor wonder, for a man to let his wife go along with him when he goeth to the wars, for there hath been examples; for Pompey had a wife with him, and so had Germanicus, and so had many great and worthy heroics, and as for Alexander the great he had a wife or two with him; besides, in many nations men are not only desired, but commanded by the chiefs to let their wives go with them, and it hath been a practice by long custom, for women to be spectators in their battles, to encourage their fights, and so give fire to their spirits; also to attend them in their sicknesses, to cleanse their wounds, to dress their meat; and who is fitter than a wife? what other woman will be so lovingly careful, and industriously helpful as a wife? and if the Greeks had not left their wives behind them, but had carried them along to the Trojan wars, they would not have found such disorders as they did at their return, nor had such bad welcome home, as witness Agamemnon's; besides, there have been many women that have not only been spectators, but actors, leading armies, and directing battles with good success, and there have been so many of these heroics, as it would be tedious at this time to recount; besides the examples of women's courage in death, as also their wise conduct, and valiant actions in wars are many, and pray give me leave to speak without your being offended thereat, it is not noble, nor the part of a gentleman, to censure,<pb facs="307" n="584"/> condemn, or dispraise another man's private actions, which nothing concerns him, especially when there is so gallant a subject to discourse of as the discipline and actions of these wars we are entering into.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101120" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101130">Introth sir, you have instructed us so well, and have chid us so handsomely, as we are sorry for our error, and ask pardon for our fault, and our repentance shall be known by that we will never censure so again.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101140">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A53060_18-e101150">
          <head>Act ii.</head>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e101160">
            <head>Scene 5.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101170">Enter captain Whiffell, and madam Whiffell his wife. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101180" who="A53060_18-whiffell">
              <speaker>Captain Whiffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101190">I have heard our general's lady goeth with the general her husband to the wars, wherefore I think it fit for the rest of the commanders, if it were only for policy, to let our general see that we approve of his actions so well, as to imitate him in ours, carrying our wives along with us, besides the general's lady cannot choose but take it kindly to have our wives wait upon her, wherefore wife it is fit you should go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101200" who="A53060_18-whiffell">
              <speaker>Madam Whiffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101210">Alas husband I am so tender, that I am apt to catch cold if the least puff of wind do but blow upon me; wherefore to lie in the open fields will kill me the first night, if not, the very journey will shatter my small bones to pieces.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101220" who="A53060_18-whiffell">
              <speaker>Captain Whiffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101230">Why, our general's lady is a very fine young lady, and she ventures to go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101240" who="A53060_18-whiffell">
              <speaker>Madam Whiffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101250">There let her venture, for you must excuse me, for I will stay at home, go you where you please.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101260" who="A53060_18-whiffell">
              <speaker>Captain Whiffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101270">Well wife consider it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101280">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e101290">
            <head>Scene 6.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101300">Enter captain Ruffell, and his wife madam Ruffell.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101310" who="A53060_18-ruffell">
              <speaker>Captain Ruffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101320">Wife prepare yourself to follow the army, for 'tis now the fashion for wives to march, wherefore pack up and away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101330" who="A53060_18-ruffell">
              <speaker>Madam Ruffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101340">What with a knapsack behind me as your trull? not I, for I will not disquiet my rest with inconveniences, nor divert my pleasures with troubles, nor be affrighted with the roaring cannons, nor endanger my life with every potgun, nor be frozen up with cold, nor stewed to a jelly with heat, nor be powdered up with dust, until I come to be as dry<pb facs="307" n="585"/> as a neats-tongue; besides, I will not venture my complexion to the wroth of the sun, which will tan me like a sheep's skin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101350" who="A53060_18-ruffell">
              <speaker>Captain Ruffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101360">Faith wife, if you will not go, I will have a laundry-maid to ride in my wagon, and lie in my tent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101370" who="A53060_18-ruffell">
              <speaker>Madam Ruffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101380">Prithee husband take thy kitchen maid along too, for she may have as much grease about her as will serve to make soap to wash your linen with, and while you ride with your laundry-maid in your wagon, I will ride with my gentleman-usher in my coach.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101390" who="A53060_18-ruffell">
              <speaker>Captain Ruffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101400">Why wife, it is out of love that I would have thee go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101410" who="A53060_18-ruffell">
              <speaker>Madam Ruffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101420">And 'tis out of love that I will stay at home; besides, do you think I mean to follow your general's lady as a common trooper doth a commander, to feed upon her reversions, to wait for her favour, to watch for a smile; no, no, I will be generalissimo myself at home, and distribute my colours to be carried in the hats of those that will fight in my quarrel, to keep or gain the victory of my favour and love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101430" who="A53060_18-ruffell">
              <speaker>Captain Ruffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101440">So I may chance to be a cuckold before I return home.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101450" who="A53060_18-ruffell">
              <speaker>Madam Ruffell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101460">You must trust to fortune for that, and so I wish you a good journey.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101470">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e101480">
            <head>Scene 7.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101490">Enter seigneur Valeroso and his friend monsieur la Hardy, to take their leaves of their wives, madam Jantil, and madam passionate, madam Jantil young and beautiful, madam passionate in years. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101500" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101510">I cannot choose but take it unkindly that you will go without me; do you mistrust my affection? as that I have not as much love for you as the general's lady hath for her husband; or do you desire to leave me? because you would take a mistress along with you, one that perchance hath more beauty than you think me to have; with whom you may securely, and freely sit in your tent, and gaze upon; or one that hath more wit than I, whose sweet, smooth, and flattering words may charm your thoughts, and draw your soul out of your ears to sit upon her lips, or dancing with delight upon her tongue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101520" who="A53060_18-valeroso">
              <speaker>Seigneur Valeroso.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101530">Prithee wife be not jealous, I vow to heaven no other beauty can attract my eyes but thine, nor any sound can please my brain, but what thy charming tongue sends in; besides, I prize not what thy body is, but how thy soul's adorned, thy virtue would make me think thee fair, although thou wert deformed, and wittier far than Mercury, hadst thou Midas' ears, but thou hast all that man can wish of women kind, and that is the reason I will leave thee safe at home; for I am loath to venture all my wealth and happiness in fortune's unconstant bark, suffering thy tender youth and sex to float on the rough waves of chance, where dangers like to Northern winds blow high, and who can know but that fatal gusts may come, and overwhelm thee, and drown all my joys? wherefore for my sake keep thyself safe at home.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101540" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <pb facs="308" n="586"/>
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101550">I shall obey you, but yet I think it were not well I should be a long time from you, and at a great distance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101560" who="A53060_18-valeroso">
              <speaker>Seigneur Valeroso.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101570">I will promise you, if I perceive the war is like to be prolonged, and that there be garrison-towns so safe as you may securely live in, I will send for you, placing you so where sometimes I may visit you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101580" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101590">Pray do not forget me so much as to cancel your promise.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101600" who="A53060_18-valeroso">
              <speaker>Seigneur Valeroso.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101610">Forget the sweet? I should sooner forget life, and if I do whilst I have memory, heaven forget me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101620" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101630">I must ask you a question, which is to know why you will take an under command, being so nobly born, and bearing a high title of honour yourself, and being master of a great estate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101640" who="A53060_18-valeroso">
              <speaker>Seigneur Valeroso.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101650">To let the world see my courage is above my birth, wealth, or pride, and that I prefer inward worth before outward title, and I had rather give my life to the enemy on honourable terms, than basely to stay at home in time of general wars, out of an ambitious discontent: for valour had rather have dangers to fight with, than offices to command in.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101660">Seigneur Valeroso and his lady whispers, while the other two Monsieur la Hardy and his lady speaks. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101670" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101680">Why should you go to the wars now you are in years, and not so fit for action as those that are young, and have their strengths about them? besides, we have lived a married pair above these thirty years, and never parted, and shall we now be separated when we are old?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101690">She weeps.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101700" who="A53060_18-la_hardy">
              <speaker>Monsieur la Hardy.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101710">Alas wife, what would you have me do? when I am commanded out I must obey; besides, I would not have my country fight a battle whilst I live, and I not make one, for all the world, for when I cannot fight, my body shall serve to stop a breach; wherefore leave your crying wife, and fall to praying for our safe return, and here my noble friend is desirous you should stay with his lady to comfort one another, and to divert melancholy and the longing hours of our return.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101720" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101730">Farewell, I fear I shall never see you again, for your absence will soon kill me.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101740">She cries.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101750">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="8" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e101760">
            <head>Scene 8.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101770">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101780" who="A53060_18-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101790">Oh you are welcome from the army, what news?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101800" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101810">Why our army marched until they came unto the frontiers of the kingdom, where they found the army of the enemy ready to encounter them, the lord general seeing they must of necessity fight a battle, thought best to call a council of war, that there might be nothing of<pb facs="308" n="587"/> ill conduct laid to his charge, but that all might be ordered by a wise and experienced council, whereupon he made an election of counsellors, joining together three sorts, as grave, wife, and prudent men, subtle and politic men, and valiant, skilful, martial men, that the cold temper of the prudent, might allay the hot temper of the valiant, and that the politic might be as ingenious to serve them together by subtle devices, and to make traps of stratagems to catch in the enemy, and at this council many debates there were, but at last they did conclude a battle must be fought; but first they did decree that all the women should be sent into one of their garrison towns, some two days' journey from the army, the reasons were, that if they should be overcome by their enemies, the women might be taken by their enemies, and made slaves, using or abusing them as they pleased; but when the women were sent away, they did not shed tears of sorrow, but sent such volleys of angry words, as wounded many men's hearts; but when they were almost at the town that was to be their abode, the general's lady, was so extremely incensed against the counsellors, by reason they decreed her departure with the others, as she strove to raise up the spirits of the rest of her sex to the height of her own; but what the issue will be I know not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101820" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101830">Have you been with the King?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101840" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101850">Yes, I was sent to give him an account of the army.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101860">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="9" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e101870">
            <head>Scene 9.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101880">Enter the lady Victoria and a number of women of all sorts with her, she takes her stand upon a heap of green turfs, as being in the fields before the garrison town, and then speaks to those women. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101890" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady Victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101900">Most heroical spirits of most chaste and loving wives, mistresses, sisters, children or friends, I know you came not from your several houses and homes into this army merely to enjoy your husbands, lovers, parents and friends in their safe and secure garrisons, or only to share of their troublesome and tedious marches, but to venture also in their dangerous and cruel battles, to run their fortunes, and to force destiny to join you to their periods; but the masculine sex hath separated us, and cast us out of their companies, either out of their loving care and desire of preserving our lives and liberties, lest we might be destroyed in their confusions, or taken prisoners in their loss, or else it must be out of jealousy we should eclipse the fame of their valours with the splendour of our constancy; and if it be love, let us never give the pre-eminence, for then we should lose that prerogative that belongs to the crown of our sex; and if it be through jealous mistrust of their fame, it were poor for us to submit and quit that unto men, that men will not unto us, for fame makes us like the gods, to live for ever; besides, those women that have stayed at home will laugh at us in our return, and their effeminate lovers and carpet knights, that cowardly and luxuriously coin excuses to keep and stay them from the wars,<pb facs="309" n="588"/> will make lampons of us for them to sing of our disgrace, saying, our husbands, lovers, and friends were so weary of us, as they were forced to take that pretence of affectionate love to be rid of our companies; wherefore if you will take my advice, let us return, and force those that sent us away to consent that we shall be partakers with them, and either win them by persuasions, or lose ourselves by breaking their decrees; for it were better we should die by their angry frowns, than by the tongue of infamy.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101910">All the women call to her.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101920" who="A53060_18-all_women">
              <speaker>All the women.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101930">Let us return, let us return.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e101940">Lady Victoria waves her hand to them to keep silence. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101950" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101960">Noble heroickesses, I am glad to hear you speak all as with one voice and tongue, which shows your minds are joined together, as in one piece, without seam or rent; but let us not return unfit to do them service, so we may cause their ruin by obstruction, which will wound us more than can their anger; wherefore let us strive by our industry to render ourselves useful to their service.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101970" who="A53060_18-all_women">
              <speaker>All the women.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e101980">Propound the way, and set the rules, and we will walk in the one, and keep strictly to the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e101990" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102000">Then thus, we have a body of about five or six thousand women, which came along with some thirty thousand men, but since we came, we are not only thought unuseful, but troublesome, which is the reason we were sent away, for the masculine sex is of an opinion we are only fit to breed and bring forth children, but otherwise a trouble in a commonwealth, for though we increase the commonwealth by our breed, we encumber it by our weakness, as they think, as by our incapacities, as having no ingenuity for inventions, nor subtle wit for politicians; nor prudence for direction, nor industry for execution; nor patience for opportunity, nor judgement for counsellors, nor secrecy for trust; nor method to keep peace, nor courage to make war, nor strength to defend ourselves or country, or to assault an enemy; also that we have not the wisdom to govern a commonwealth, and that we are too partial to sit in the seat of justice, and too pitiful to execute rigorous authority when it is needful, and the reason of these erroneous opinions of the masculine sex to the effeminate, is, that our bodies seem weak, being delicate and beautiful, and our minds seem fearful, being compassionate and gentle natured, but if we were both weak and fearful, as they imagine us to be, yet custom which is a second nature will encourage the one and strengthen the other, and had our educations been answerable to theirs, we might have proved as good soldiers and privy counsellors, rulers and commanders, navigators and architectors, and as learned scholars both in arts and sciences, as men are; for time and custom is the father and mother of strength and knowledge, they make all things easy and facile, clear and propitious; they bring acquaintance, and make friendship of every thing; they make courage and fear, strength and weakness, difficulty and facility, dangers and securities, labours and recreations, life and death, all to take and shake as it were hands together; wherefore if we would but accustom ourselves we may do such actions, as may gain us such a reputation, as men might change their opinions, insomuch as to believe we are fit to be copartners in their governments,<pb facs="309" n="589"/> and to help to rule the world, where now we are kept as slaves forced to obey; wherefore let us make ourselves free, either by force, merit, or love, and in order, let us practise and endeavour, and take that which fortune shall proffer unto us, let us practise I say, and make these fields as schools of martial arts and sciences, so shall we become learned in their disciplines of war, and if you please to make me your tutoress, and so your generaless, I shall take the power and command from your election and authority, otherwise I shall most willingly, humbly, and obediently submit to those whom you shall choose.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102010" who="A53060_18-all_women">
              <speaker>All the women.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102020">You shall be our generaless, our instructress, ruler and commanderess, and we will every one in particular, swear to obey all your commands, to submit and yield to your punishments, to strive and endeavour to merit your rewards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102030" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102040">Then worthy heroickesses, give me leave to set the laws and rules I would have you keep and observe, in a brass tablet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102050" who="A53060_18-all_women">
              <speaker>All the women.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102060">We agree and consent to whatsoever you please.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e102070">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="10" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e102080">
            <head>Scene 10.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e102090">Enter the lady Jantil alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102100" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102110">How painful is true love absented from what is loved, 'tis strange that that which pleaseth most should be the greatest torment.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e102120">Enter madam passionate.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102130" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102140">What, all times walking by yourself alone? when your lord returns I will complain, and tell him what dull company you are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102150" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102160">I hope I shall not be from him so long, for he promised to send for me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102170" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102180">Nay faith, when you go, as old as I am, I will travel with you to see my husband too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102190" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102200">You will be so much the more welcome, by how much you were unexpected.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102210" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102220">You look pale on the sudden, are not you well?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102230" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102240">Yes, only on a sudden I had a chill of cold that seized on my spirits.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102250" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102260">Beshrew me, their coldness hath nipped the blood out of your cheeks and lips.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102270" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102280">If they had been painted, they would have kept their colour.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e102290">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A53060_18-e102300">
          <pb facs="310" n="590"/>
          <head>Act iii.</head>
          <div n="11" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e102310">
            <head>Scene 11.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e102320">Enter the lady Victoria with a great company of women, after a table of Brass carried before her, she stands upon the heap of turfs, and another woman that carried the table, wherein the laws and rules are inscribed; she bids her read them. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102330" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102340">Noble heroics, these are the laws our generaless hath caused to be inscribed and read for every one to observe and keep.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102350">First, be it known, observed and practised, that no woman that is able to bear arms, shall go unarmed, having arms to wear, but shall wear them at all times, but when they put them off to change their linen; they shall sleep, eat and rest, and march with them on their bodies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102360" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102370">Give me leave noble heroics to declare the reason of this law or command, as to wear an iron or steel habit, and to be so constantly worn, is, that your arms should not feel heavy, or be troublesome or painful for want of use, as they will be when you shall have an occasion to put them on; and certainly, for want of practice, more masculine soldiers are overcome by their arms, than by their enemies, for the unaccustomedness makes them so unwieldy, as they can neither defend themselves, nor assault their foes, whereas custom will make them feel as light, as their skins on their flesh, or their flesh on their bones, nay custom hath that force, as they will feel as if their bodies were naked, whenas their arms are off, and as custom makes the cold and piercing air to have no power over the naked bodies of men, for in cold countries' as well as hot, men have been accustomed to go naked, and have felt no more harm, nor so much, by the cold, than those that are warmly clothed, so custom will make your arms seem as light as if you had none on, when for want of use their weight will seem heavy, their several pieces troublesome and encumbersome, as their gorgets will seem to press down their shoulders, their back and breastplates and the rest of the several pieces to cut their waste, to pinch their body, to bind their thighs, to tie their arms, and their headpiece to hinder their breath, to darken their sight, and to stop their hearing, and all for want of use and custom; but enough of this, read on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102380" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102390">Secondly, be it known, observed and practised, that every company must watch by turns, whether they have enemies near or no, and at all times, and whosoever drinks any thing but water, or eats any thing but bread, all the time they are on the watch shall be punished with fasting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102400" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102410">Give me leave to declare the reason of this law, the reason is, that strong drinks, and nourishing meats send many vapours to the brain, which vapours are like several keys, which lock up the senses so fast, as neither loud noises, bright lights, nor strong scents can enter either at the ears, eyes, or nostrils, insomuch as many times their enemies send death to break them asunder.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102420" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <pb facs="310" n="591"/>
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102430">Thirdly, be it known, observed and practised, that none of the troopers march over corn fields if it can be avoided, unless the enemy should be behind, and then the more spoil the better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102440" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102450">The reason of this is, that it were a great imprudence to destroy through a careless march of horse and foot, that which would serve to feed and nourish us in the winter time, and in our winter quarters, when it is laid in the barns and granaries, by the labour and the industry of the farmers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102460" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102470">Fourthly, be it known, observed and practised, that none shall plunder those things which are weighty of carriage, unless it be for safety or necessity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102480" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102490">The reason is of this, that all that is heavy in the carriage is a hindrance in our march.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102500" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102510">Fiftly, be it known, observed and practised, that no soldiers shall play at any game for money or drink, but only for meat to eat.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102520" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102530">The reason of this is, that those that play for drink, the winners will be drunk, and those that are drunk are unfit for service; besides, many disorders are caused by drunkenness; and to play for money, the losers grow choleric, and quarrels proceed therefrom, which quarrels many times cause great mutinies through their side taking, and factious parties, besides, having lost their money and not their appetites, they become weak and faint for want of that nourishing food, their money should get them, having nothing left to buy them victuals withal; besides, it forces them to forage further about, where by straggling far from the body of the army, they are subject to be catched by the enemy, but when they play for meat their winnings nourish their bodies, making them strong and vigorous, and when their appetites are satisfied, and their stomachs are filled, their humours are pleasant, and their minds courageous; besides, it is the nature of most creatures, either to distribute or at least to leave the remaining pieces to the next takers, so that the losers may have a share with the winners, and part of what was their own again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102540" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102550">Sixtly, be it known, observed and practised, that no captains or colonels, shall advance beyond their company, troop, regiment or brigade, but keep in the middle of the first rank, and the lieutenant, or lieutenant colonel to come behind in the last rank.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102560" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102570">The reason of this is, that colonels and captains going a space before their troops, companies or regiments, for to encourage and lead on their soldiers, do ill to set themselves as marks for the enemy to shoot at, and if the chief commanders should be killed, the common soldiers would have but faint hearts to fight, but for the most part they will run away, as being afraid and ashamed to see the enemy, when their chief commander is killed, and if they have no officer or commander behind them, the common soldiers will be apt to run away, having no worthy witnesses or judges, to view and condemn their base cowardly actions, which otherwise they are ashamed of, choosing rather to fight their enemies than to make known their fears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102580" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102590">Seventhly, be it known, observed and practised, that none of the army lie in garrison towns, but be always entrenched abroad.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102600" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102610">The reason of this is, that towns breed or beget a tenderness of bodies, and laziness of limbs, luxurious appetites, and soften the natural dispositions, which tenderness, luxury, effeminacy, and laziness,<pb facs="311" n="592"/> corrupts and spoils martial discipline, whereas the open fields, and casting up trenches makes soldiers more hardy, laborious and careful, as being more watchful.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102620">Eightly, be it known, observed and practised, that none unless visibly sick to be idle, but employed in some masculine action, as when not employed against an enemy; and that they are not employed about the works, forts or trenches, but have spare time to employ themselves, in throwing the bar, tripping, wrestling, running, vaulting, riding, and the like exercise.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102630" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102640">Ninthly, be it known, observed and practised, that every commander when free from the enemy's surprisals, shall train their men thrice a week at least, nay every day if they can spare so much time, as putting their soldiers into several ranks, files and figures, in several bodies apart, changing into several places, and the like.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102650" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102660">The reason of this is, that the soldiers may be expert and ready, and not be ignorant when they encounter their enemies, for many a battle is lost more through the ignorance of the soldiers, not being well and carefully trained by their commanders, or having such commanders that know not how to train or draw them up, there are more battles I say lost thus, than for want of men or courage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102670" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102680">Tenthly, be it known, observed and practised, that every morning when encamped, that every commander shall make and offer in the midst of his soldiers a prayer to Mars, another to Pallas, a third to fortune, and a fourth to fame; these prayers to be presented to these gods and goddesses with great ceremony, both from the commander and common soldiers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102690" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102700">The reason of this is, that ceremony strikes a reverence and respect into every breast, raising up a devotion in every heart, and devotion makes obedience, and obedience keeps order, and order is the strength and life to an army, state, or commonwealth; and as for the prayers presented to these particular gods and goddess, is, that Mars would give us courage and strength, Pallas give us prudent conduct, fortune give us victory, and fame give us glory and renown.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102710" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102720">Eleventh, be it known, observed and practised, that the most experienced, practised, and ingenioust commanders shall preach twice a week of martial discipline, also those errors that have been committed in former wars, and what advantages have been taken, to be cited in their sermons, as also what was gained or lost by mere fortune.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102730" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102740">Twelfthly, be it known, observed and practised, that when the army marches, that the soldiers shall sing in their march the heroical actions done in former times by heroical women.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102750" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102760">The reason of this is, that the remembrance of the actions of gallant persons inflames the spirit to the like, and begets a courage to a like action, and the reason of singing of heroical actions only of women, is that we are women ourselves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102770" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102780">Thirteenthly, be it known, observed and submitted to, that no council shall be called, but that all affairs be ordered and judged by the generaless herself.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102790" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102800">The reason of this is, that all great councils, as of many persons, confounds judgements, for most being of several opinions, and holding strongly and stiffly, nay obstinately thereunto, as every one thinking themselves<pb facs="311" n="593"/> wisest, cause a division, and wheresoever a division is there can be no final conclusion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102810" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102820">Fourteenthly, be it known, observed and practised, that none of this effeminate army admits of the company of men, whilst they are in arms or warlike actions, not so much as to exchange words, without the generaless her leave or privilege thereto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102830" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102840">The reason of this is, that men are apt to corrupt the noble minds of women, and to alter their gallant, worthy, and wise resolutions, with their flattering words, and pleasing and subtle insinuations, and if they have any authority over them, as husbands, fathers, brothers, or the like, they are apt to fright them with threats into a slavish obedience; yet there shall be chosen some of the most inferior of this female army, to go into the masculine army, to learn their designs, and give us intelligence of their removals, that we may order our encampings and removings according as we shall think best; but these women shall neither be of the body of our army, nor keep amongst the army, nor come within the trenches, but lie without the works in huts, which shall be set up for that purpose.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102850" who="A53060_18-reader">
              <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102860">Lastly, whosoever shall break any of these laws or order, shall be put to death, and those that do not keep them strictly, shall be severely punished.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102870" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102880">But I am to advise you noble heroics, that though I would not have a general council called to trouble our designs in war with tedious disputes, and unnecessary objections, and over cautious doubts, yet in case of life and death, there shall be a jury chosen to sit and judge their causes, and the whole army shall give their votes, and the most voices shall either condemn, or reprieve, or save them, lest I should hereafter be only called in question, and not the rest, as being not accessary thereunto; and now you have heard these laws or order, you may assent or dissent therefrom as you please, if you assent, declare it by setting your hands thereto, if you dissent, declare it by word of mouth, and the tables shall be broken.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102890" who="A53060_18-all_women">
              <speaker>All the women.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102900">We assent, and will set our hands thereto.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e102910">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="12" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e102920">
            <head>Scene 12.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e102930">Enter doctor educature the lady Jantil's chaplin, and Nell careless her maid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102940" who="A53060_18-educature">
              <speaker>Doctor educature.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102950">Nell, how doth your good lady?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102960" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102970">Faith she seems neither sick nor well, for though her body seems in health, her mind seems to be full of trouble, for she will rise in the midst of the night, and walk about her chamber only with her mantle about her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e102980" who="A53060_18-educature">
              <speaker>Doctor educature.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e102990">Why doth she so?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103000" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103010">I asked her why she broke her sleep so as to walk about, and she answered me, that it was frightful dreams that broke her sleep, and would not let her rest in quiet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103020" who="A53060_18-educature">
              <speaker>Doctor educature.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103030">Alas she is melancholic in the absence of my lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103040">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="13" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e103050">
            <pb facs="312" n="594"/>
            <head>Scene 13.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103060">Enter the lady Victoria and a number of other women. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103070" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady Victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103080">Now we are resolved to put ourselves into a warlike body, our greatest difficulty will be to get arms; but if you will take my advice we may be furnished with those necessaries, as thus, the garrison we are to enter is full of arms and ammunition, and few men to guard them, for not only most of the soldiers are drawn out to strengthen the general's army, and to fight in the battle, but as many of the townsmen as are fit to bear arms; wherefore it must of necessity be very slenderly guarded, and when we are in the town, we will all agree in one night, when they shall think themselves most secure, to rise and surprise those few men that are left, and not only disarm them and possess ourselves of the town and all the arms and ammunition, but we will put those men out of the town or in safe places, until such time as we can carry away whatsoever is useful or needful for us, and then to go forth and entrench, until such time as we have made ourselves ready to march, and being once master or mistress of the field we shall easily master the peasants, who are for the most part naked and defenceless, having not arms to guard them, by which means we may plunder all their horses, and victual ourselves out of their granaries; besides, I make no question but our army will increase numerously by those women that will adhere to our party, either out of private and home discontents, or for honour and fame, or for the love of change, and as it were a new course of life; wherefore let us march to the town and also to our design, but first I must have you all swear secrecy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103090" who="A53060_18-all_women">
              <speaker>All the women.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103100">We are all ready to swear to what you will have us.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103110">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="14" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e103120">
            <head>Scene 14.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103130">Enter madam Jantil alone as rising out of her bed, her mantle wrapped about her, and in her night linen. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103140" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e103150">I saw his face pale as a lily white,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e103160">His wounds fresh bleeding blood like rubies bright;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e103170">His eyes were looking steadfastly on me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e103180">Smiling as joying in my company;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e103190">He moved his lips as willing was to speak,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e103200">But had no voice, and all his spirits weak;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e103210">He shaked his hand as if he bid farewell,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e103220">That brought the message which his tongue would tell;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e103230">He's dead, he's dead, asunder break my heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e103240">Let's meet in death, though wars our lives did part. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103250">After she had walked silently a turn or two about her chamber her eyes being sixth on the ground, she returned as to her bed.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103260">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="15" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e103270">
            <pb facs="312" n="595"/>
            <head>Scene 15.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103280">Enter a gentleman, and another meets him as in great haste.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103290" who="A53060_18-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103300">What news? what news?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103310" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103320">Sad news, for there hath been a battle fought betwixt the two armies, and our army is beaten, and many of our gallant men slain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103330" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103340">I am sorry for that.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103350">The second gentleman goeth out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103360">Enter a third gentleman.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103370" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103380">Sir I suppose you are come newly from the army, pray report the battle?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103390" who="A53060_18-gentleman_3">
              <speaker>3 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103400">Truly I came not now from the army, but from the town the generals heroical lady and the rest of the heroics did surprise, seize and plunder.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103410" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103420">What the garrison town they were sent to for safety?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103430" who="A53060_18-gentleman_3">
              <speaker>3 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103440">Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103450" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103460">And doth their number increase?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103470" who="A53060_18-gentleman_3">
              <speaker>3 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103480">Oh very much, for after the suprisal of the town the women in that town did so approve of their gallant actions, as every one desired to be enlisted in the roll, and number of the Amazonian army, but in the mean time of the forming of their army, intelligence was brought of the battle which was fought, and that there was such loss of both sides as each army retired back, being both so weak as neither was able to keep the field, but that the loss was greater on the reformed army, by reason there was so many of their gallant men slain, but this news made many a sad heart and weeping eyes in the female army; for some have lost their husbands, some their fathers, others their brothers, lovers and friends.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103490" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103500">Certainly this will fright them out of the field of war, and cause them to lay by their heroic designs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103510" who="A53060_18-gentleman_3">
              <speaker>3 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103520">I know not what they will do, for they are very secret to their designs, which is strange, being all women.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103530">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A53060_18-e103540">
          <pb facs="313" n="596"/>
          <head>Act iv.</head>
          <div n="16" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e103550">
            <head>Scene 16.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103560">Enter two women like Amazons.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103570" who="A53060_18-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 woman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103580">Our generaless seems to be troubled, perceiving how heavily this female army takes their losses.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103590" who="A53060_18-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 woman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103600">She hath reason, for it may hinder or at least obstruct her high designs.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103610">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="17" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e103620">
            <head>Scene 17.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103630">Enter the lady Victoria and her Amazons, she takes her stand and speaks to them. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103640" who="A53060_18-victoria">
              <speaker>Lady Victoria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103650">Noble heroics, I perceive a mourning veil over the face of this female army, and it becomes it well; for 'tis both natural and human to grieve for the death of our friends; but consider constant heroics, tears nor lamentations cannot call them out of the grave, no petitions can persuade death to restore them, nor threats to let them go, and since you cannot have them alive being dead, study and be industrious to revenge their quarrels on their enemies lives, let your justice give them death for death, offer upon the tombs of your friends the lives of their foes, and instead of weeping eyes, let us make them weep through their veins; wherefore take courage, cast off your black veil of sorrow, and take up the firematch of rage, that you may shoot revenge into the hearts of their enemies, to which I hope fortune will favour us; for I hear that as soon as the masculine army have recovered strength there will be another battle fought, which may be a means to prove our loves to our friends, our hate to our enemies, and an aspiring to our honour and renown; wherefore let us employ our care to fit ourselves for our march.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103660" who="A53060_18-all_women">
              <speaker>All the women.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103670">We shall follow and obey you, where, and when, and how you please.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103680">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="18" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e103690">
            <pb facs="313" n="597"/>
            <head>Scene 18.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103700">Enter doctor educature, and Nell careless; the doctor weeps. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103710" who="A53060_18-educature">
              <speaker>Doctor educature.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103720">Doth my lady hear of my lords death?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103730" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103740">The messenger or intelligencer of my lords death is now with her.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103750">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="19" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e103760">
            <head>Scene 19.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103770">Enter madam Jantil, and a gentleman intelligencer; the lady seems not disturbed; but appears as usually. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103780" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103790">How died my lord?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103800" who="A53060_18-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103810">Madam, he fought with so much courage, as his actions will never die, and his valour will keep alive the memory of this war: for though he died, his death was crowned with victory, he digged his grave out of his enemies sides, and built his pyramid with heaps of their bodies, the groans of those he slew did ring his dying knell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103820" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103830">What became of his body?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103840" who="A53060_18-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103850">He gave order before the armies joined to fight, that if he were killed, his body should be sought out, and delivered to you: for he said it was yours whilst he lived, and he desired it might be disposed of by you when he was dead; his desires and commands were obeyed, and his body is coming in a litter leapt in cerecloth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103860" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103870">Worthy sir, I give you many thanks for your noble relation, assuring myself it is true because you report it, and it is my husband that is the subject and ground of that honourable relation, whom I always did believe would outact all words.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103880" who="A53060_18-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103890">He hath so madam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103900" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103910">Sir, if I can at any time honourably serve you, I shall be ready whensoever you will command me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103920" who="A53060_18-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103930">Your servant madam.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103940">(He was going forth and returns)</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103950">If your ladyship hath not heard of monsieur la Hardy's death, give me leave to tell you he is slain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e103960" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e103970">I am sorry, and for his lady, for she loved him most passionably.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103980">The gentleman goes out.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e103990"><pb facs="314" n="598"/>Enter as running and calling out doll Pacify, madam Passionate's maid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104000" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104010">Help, help, my lady is dead, my lady is fallen into a swoon at the report of my masters being killed.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104020">The lady goeth out and the maid, then they enter straight again with two or three servants more, bringing in the lady passionate as in a swoon. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104030" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104040">Alas poor lady, her spirits are drowned in sorrow, and grief hath stopped her breath; loosen her garments, for she is swelled with troubled thoughts, her passions lie on heaps, and so oppress life, it cannot stir, but makes her senseless.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104050">Upon the losing of her garments she revives, and cries out.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104060" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104070">O my husband, my husband!</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104080">She swounds again.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104090" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104100">Bow her forward, bow her forward.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104110">Madam passionate revives again. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104120" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104130">O let me die, let me die, and bury, bury me with him.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104140">'Swounds again.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104150" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104160">Alas poor lady, put her to bed, for her life will find most case there.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104170">The servants goes out with madam passionate.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104180">Madam Jantil alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104190" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104200">O life what art thou? and death where dost thou lead us, or what dissolvest thou us into?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104210">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="20" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e104220">
            <head>Scene 20.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104230">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104240" who="A53060_18-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104250">I wonder there is no news or messenger come from the army yet, when there usually comes one every day.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104260">Enter a messenger.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104270" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104280">Oh sir, what news?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104290" who="A53060_18-messenger">
              <speaker>Messenger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104300">Faith there hath been nothing acted since the last battle, but<pb facs="314" n="599"/> it is said there will be another battle very suddenly, for the enemy provokes our men to fight, by reason our lord general lies sick of his wounds, having had a favour, caused by the anguish of his hurts, and by his sickness the enemies hope to gain an advantage of his absence, but he hath put a deputy in his place to command in chief until he recovers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104310" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104320">What is become of the female army?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104330" who="A53060_18-messenger">
              <speaker>Messenger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104340">I hear they are marched towards the masculine army, but upon what design I cannot understand.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104350">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="21" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e104360">
            <head>Scene 21.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104370">Enter madam Jantil, and her maid Nell careless.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104380" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104390">Call my steward.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104400">The maid goes out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104410">The lady walks in a musing posture, her eyes fixed on the ground.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104420">Enter the steward weeping.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104430" who="A53060_18-steward">
              <speaker>Steward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104440">O madam, that I should live to hear this cursed news of my dear lord and master's death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104450" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104460">Life is a curse, and there's none happy but those that die in the womb before their birth, because they have the least share of misery; and since you cannot weep out life, bear it with patience; but thy tears have almost washed out the memory of what I was to say, but this it is, that I would have you sell all my jewels, plate, and household furniture to the best advantage, and to turn off all my servants, but just those to attend my person, but to reward all of them with something more than their wages, and those servants that are old, and have spent their youth with my lords predecessors and in his service, but especially those he favoured most, give them so much during their lives as may keep them from the miseries of necessity, and vexations of poverty. Thirdly, I would have you hire the best and curious't carvers or cutters of stones to make a tomb after my direction; as first I will have a marble piece raised from the ground about half a man's height or something more, and something longer than my husband's dead body, and then my husband's image carved out of marble to be laid thereupon, his image to be carved with his armour on, and half a head-piece on the head, that the face might be seen, which face I would have to the life as much as art can make it; also let there be two statues, one for Mercury, and another for Pallas, these two statues to stand at his head, and the hands of these statues to join and to be laid under as carrying the head of my husband's figure, or as the head lay thereupon, and their hands as his pillow; on the right side of his figure, let there be a statue for Mars, and the hand of Mars's statue holding the right hand of my husband's figure, and on the left hand a statue for Hymen, the hand on the place of the heart of my husband's figure, and at the feet of the figure let<pb facs="315" n="600"/> there be placed a statue for fortune also, about a yard distance from the tomb; at the four corners thereof, let there be four marble pillars raised of an indifferent height, and an arched marble cover thereupon, and let all the ground be paved underneath with marble, and in the midst on the outside of the marble roof let the statute of fame be placed in a flying posture, and as blowing a trumpet; then some two yards' distance square from those pillars, let the ground be paved also with marble, and at the four corners four other marble pillars raised as high as the former, with capitals at top, and the body of those pillars round, and the statues of the four Cardinal virtues placed on those capitals, sitting as in a weeping posture, and at the feet of those pillars the statues of the graces embracing each pillar; as the statue of charity, the pillar whereon the statue of justice sits, and the statue of patience, the pillar of temperance, and the statute of hope, the pillar of prudence, and the statue of faith, the pillar of fortitude; then set a grove of trees all about the outside of them, as laurel, myrtle, cypress, and olive, for in death is peace, in which trees the birds may sit and sing his elegy; this tomb placed in the midst of a piece of ground of some ten or twenty acres, which I would have encompassed about with a wall of brick of a reasonable height, on the inside of the wall at one end, I would have built a little house divided into three rooms, as a gallery, a bedchamber, and a closet, on the outside of the wall a house for some necessary servants to live in, to dress my meat, and to be ready at my call, which will be but seldom, and that by the ring of a bell, but the three rooms I would have furnished after this manner, my chamber and the bed therein to be hung with white, to signify the purity of chastity, wherein is no colours made by false lights; the gallery with several colours intermixed, to signify the varieties, changes, and encumbrances of life; my closet to be hung with black, to signify the darkness of death, wherein all things are forgotten and buried in oblivion; thus will I live a signification, not as a real substance but as a shadow made betwixt life and death; from this house which shall be my living tomb, to the tomb of my dead husband, I would have a cloister built, through which I may walk freely to my husband's tomb, from the injuries of the weather, and this cloister I would have all the sides thereof hung with my husband's pictures drawn to the life by the best painters, and all the several accidents, studies and exercise of his life; thus will I have the story of his life drawn to the life: see this my desire speedily, carefully, and punctually done, and I shall reward your service as a careful and diligent steward and servant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104470" who="A53060_18-steward">
              <speaker>Steward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104480">It shall be done, but why will not your ladyship have my lords figure cast in brass?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104490" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104500">Because the wars ruin tombs before time doth, and metals being useful therein are often taken away by necessity, and we seldom find any ancient monuments but what are made of stone, for covetousness is apt to rob monuments of metal, committing sacrileges on the dead, for metals are soonest melted into profit, but stone is dull and heavy, creeping slowly, bringing but a cold advantage, wherein lies more pains than gains.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104510" who="A53060_18-steward">
              <speaker>Steward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104520">But your ladyship may do all this without selling your jewels, plate, and household furniture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104530" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104540">It is true, but I would not let so much wealth lie dead in vanity, when exchanging them for money, I can employ it to some good use.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104550" who="A53060_18-steward">
              <pb facs="315" n="601"/>
              <speaker>Steward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104560">Your ladyship hath forgotten to give order for blacks.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104570" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104580">No I have not, but I will give no mourning until my husband's body be carried to the tomb; wherefore I have nothing more to employ you in at this time, but only to send hither my chaplain doctor educature. </p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104590">The steward goes out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104600">Enter doctor educature.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104610" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104620">Doctor, although it is not the profession of a divine to be an historian, yet you knowing my husband's life and natural disposition best, being in his childhood under you tutorage, and one of his family ever since, I know none so proper for that work as you; and though you are naturally an eloquent orator, yet the bare truth of his worthy virtues and heroical actions will be sufficient to make the story both profitable, delightful, and famous; also I must entreat you to choose out a poet, one that doth not merely write for gain, or to express his own wit, so much as to endeavour to pencil with the pen virtue to the life, which in my lord was so beautiful as it was beyond all draughts, but the theme will inspire his muse, and when both these works are writ, printed and set out, as divulged to the world as a pattern for examples, which few will be able to imitate, than I would have these books lie by me as registers of memory, for next unto the gods my life shall be spent in contemplation of him; I know I shall not need to persuade you to do this, for your affection to his memory is ready of itself; but love and duty binds me to express my desires for his fame leaving nothing which is for my part thereunto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104630" who="A53060_18-educature">
              <speaker>Doctor educature.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104640">Madam, all the service I can do towards the memory of my dear pupil; and noble lord and patron, shall be most devoutly observed and followed; for heaven knows, if I had as many lives to dispose of as I have lived years, I would have sacrificed them all for to have redeemed his life from death.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104650">Doctor educature goes out. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104660">Madam Jantil alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104670" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104680">When I have interred my husband's body, and all my desires thereunto be finished, I shall be at some rest, and like an executrix to myself executing my own will, distributing the rites and ceremonies, as legacies to the dead, thus the living gives the dead; but oh my spirits are tired with the heavy burden of melancholy, and grow faint for want of rest, yet my senses invite me thereunto, yet I cannot rest in my bed, for frightful dreams disturb me; wherefore I will lie down on this floor, and try if I can get a quiet sleep on the ground, for from earth I came, and to earth I would willingly return.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104690">She lays herself down upon the ground, on one side of her arm bowing, leaning upon her elbow, her forehead upon the palm of her hand bowing forwards, her face towards the ground; but her grief elevating her passion, thus speaks.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e104700" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104710">Weep cold earth, through your pores weep,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104720">Or in your bowels my salt tears fast keep;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104730"><pb facs="316" n="602"/> inurn my sighs which from my grief is sent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104740">With my hard groans build up a monument;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104750">My tongue like as a pen shall write his name,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104760">My words as letters to divulge his fame;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104770">My life like to an arch over his ashes bend,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104780">And my desires to his grave descend;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104790">I warn thee life keep me not company,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104800">I am a friend to death thy enemy;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104810">For thou art cruel, and every thing torments,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104820">Wounding with pain all that the world presents;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104830">But death is generous and sets us free,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104840">Breaks off our chains, and gives us liberty;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104850">Heals up our wounds of trouble with sweet rest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104860">Draws our corrupted passions from our breast;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104870">Lays us to sleep on pillows of soft case,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104880">Rocks us with silence nothing hears nor sees. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104890">She fetches'a great sigh.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104900">O that I may here sleep my last. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104910">After a short slumber she wakes.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e104920">If it were not for dreams sleep would be a happiness next unto death; but I find I cannot sleep a long sleep in death, I shall not die so soon as I would.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104930">Love is so strong and pure it cannot die,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104940">Lives not in sense, but in the soul doth lie;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104950">Why do I mourn? his love with mins doth dwell,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104960">His love is pleased mine entertains it well;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104970">But mine would be like his one embodied,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_18-e104980">Only an essence or like a godhead. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e104990">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="22" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e105000">
            <head>Scene 22.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e105010">Enter doctor comfort, and doll Pacify.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105020" who="A53060_18-comfort">
              <speaker>Doctor comfort.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105030">How doth our lady Doll?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105040" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105050">Today she began to sit up, but yet she is very weak and faint.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105060" who="A53060_18-comfort">
              <speaker>Doctor comfort.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105070">Heaven help her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105080" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105090">You that are heavens almoner, should distribute heaven's gifts out of the purse of your mouth, and give her single godly words instead of single silver pence, to buy her some heavenly food to feed her famished mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105100" who="A53060_18-comfort">
              <speaker>Doctor comfort.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105110">Thou are a full-fed wench.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105120" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105130">If I were no better fed than you feed me, which is but once a week, as on Sundays, I should be starved.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105140" who="A53060_18-comfort">
              <speaker>Doctor comfort.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105150">You must fast and pray, fast and pray.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e105160">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A53060_18-e105170">
          <pb facs="316" n="603"/>
          <head>Act v.</head>
          <div n="23" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e105180">
            <head>Scene 23.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e105190">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105200" who="A53060_18-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105210">All the young gallants in the town are preparing themselves with fine clothes and feathers to go a-wooing to the two rich widows, the lady Jantil, and the lady passionate. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105220" who="A53060_18-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105230">Riches are the loadstone of affection, or at least professions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105240" who="A53060_18-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105250">The truth is, riches draw more suitors, than youth, beauty, or virtue.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e105260">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="24" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e105270">
            <head>Scene 24.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e105280">Enter two or three gentlemen, monsieur comrade, monsieur companion, and monsieur la gravity.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105290" who="A53060_18-comerade">
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105300">For heaven's sake let us go and address ourselves to the two rich widows.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105310" who="A53060_18-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105320">For my part I will address myself to none but the young widow, the lady Jantil, and to her let us go without delay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105330" who="A53060_18-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105340">It will be uncivil to go so soon after their husband's death, for their husbands are not yet laid in their graves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105350" who="A53060_18-compagnion">
              <speaker>Monsieur companion.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105360">If they were we should come too late, for I knew a man which was a great friend of mine, who was resolved to settle himself in a married course of life, and so he went a-wooing to a widow, for a widow he was resolved to marry, and he went a-wooing to one whose husband was but just cold in his grave, but she told him she was promised before, so he wooed another whilst she followed her husband's corpse, but she told him he came too late, whereat he thought with the third not to be a second in his suit, and so expressed his desires in her husband's sickness, she told him she was very sorry that she had passed her word before to another, for if she had not, she would have ma le him her choice, whereat he cursed his imprudence, and wooed the fourth on her wedding day, who gave him a promise after her husband was dead to marry him, and withal she told him, that if she had been married before, it had been ten to one but he had spoke too late, for said she, when we are maids we are kept from the free conversation of men, by our parents or guardians, but on our wedding day we are made free and set at liberty, and like as young heirs on the day of one and twenty we make promises like bonds for two or three lives: wherefore I fear we shall miss of our hopes, for these two widows will be promised before we address our suit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105370" who="A53060_18-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105380">No no, for I am confident all do not so, for some<pb facs="317" n="604"/> love to have the freedoms of their wills, for every promise is a bondage to those that make a conscience to keep their promise, besides, it is not only variety that pleaseth women, but new changes, for stale acquaintance is as unpleasant as want of change, and the only hopes I have to the end of my suit, is, that I am a stranger and unknown, for women fancy men beyond what they are when unknown, and prize them less than their merits deserve, when they are acquainted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105390" who="A53060_18-comerade">
              <speaker>Monsieur comrade.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105400">Well, we will not stay, but we will do our endeavour to get admittance.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e105410">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="25" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_18-e105420">
            <head>Scene 25.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e105430">Enter madam passionate as very ill, sitting in a chair groaning, enter madam Jantil as to see her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105440" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105450">Madam, how do you find your health?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105460" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105470">Very bad, for I am very ill, but I wonder at your fortitude, that you can bear such a cross as the loss of your husband so patiently.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105480" who="A53060_18-jantel">
              <speaker>Madam Iantil.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105490">O madam I am like those that are in a dropsy, their face seems full and fat, but their liver is consumed, and though my sorrow appears not outwardly, yet my heart is dead within me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105500" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105510">But your young years is a cordial to restore it, and a new love will make it as healthful as ever it was.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e105520">Enter Doll Pacify the lady Passionat's maid, with a porringer of caudle. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105530" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105540">Pray madam eat something, or otherwise you will kill yourself with fasting, for you have not eaten any thing since the beginning of your sorrow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105550" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Lady passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105560">O carry that caudle away, carry it away, for the very sight doth overcome my stomach.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105570" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105580">Pray madam eat but a little.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105590" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Lady passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105600">I care not for it, I cannot eat it, nor will not eat it: wherefore carry it away, or I will go away.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e105610">Both the ladies go out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e105620">Enter Nell careless madam Jantil's maid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105630" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105640">Prithee if thy lady will not eat this caudle, give it me, for I have an appetite to it; but I wonder you will offer your lady any thing to eat, but rather you should give her something to drink, for I have heard sorrow is dry, but never heard it was hungry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105650" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105660">You are mistaken, for sorrow is sharp, and bites upon the stomach, which causes an eager appetite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105670" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105680">I am sure weeping eyes make a dry throat.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e105690">[she eats and talks between each spoonful.]</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105700" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <pb facs="317" n="605"/>
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105710">But melancholy thoughts make a hungry stomach: but faith if thou wert a widow, by thy eating thou wouldst have another husband quickly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105720" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105730">Do you think I would marry again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105740" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105750">Heaven forbid that a young woman should live a widow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105760" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105770">Why, is it a sin for a young woman to live a widow?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105780" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105790">I know not what it would be to you, but it would be a case of conscience to me if I were a widow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105800" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105810">By thy nice conscience thou seemest to be a Puritan.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105820" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105830">Well, I can bring many proofs: but were it not a sin, it is a disgrace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105840" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105850">Where lies the disgrace?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105860" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105870">In the opinion of the world, for old maids and musty widows are like the plague shunned of by all men, which affrights young women so much, as by running from it they catch hold on whatsoever man they meet, without consideration of what or whom they are, by which many times they fall into poverty and great misery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105880" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105890">You teach a doctrine, that to escape one mischief they fall on another, which is worse than the first; wherefore it were better to live a musty widow as you call them, than a miserable wife; besides, a man cannot intimately love a widow, because he will be a cuckold, as being made one by her dead husband, and so live in adultery, and so she live in sin herself by cuckolding both her husbands, having had two.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105900" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105910">I believe if you were a widow you would be tempted to that sin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105920" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105930">Faith but I should not, for should I commit that sin, I should deserve the hell of discontent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105940" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105950">Faith you would marry if you were young, and fair, and rich.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105960" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105970">Those you mention would keep me from marrying: for if any would marry me for the love of youth and beauty, they would never love me long, because time ruins both soon; and if any one should marry me merely for my riches, they would love my riches so well and so much as there would be no love left for me that brought it, and if my husband be taken prisoner by my wealth, I shall be made a slave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e105980" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e105990">No, not if you be virtuous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106000" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106010">Faith there is not one in an age that takes a wife merely for virtue, nor values a wife any thing the more for being so; for poor virtue fits mourning unregarded and despised, not any one will so much as cast an eye towards her, but all shun her as you say they do old maids or musty widows.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106020" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106030">Although you plead excellently well for not marrying, yet I make no question but you would willingly marry if there should come a young gallant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106040" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106050">What's that, a fool that spends all his wit and money on his clothes? or is it a gallant young man, which is a man enriched with worth and merit?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106060" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106070">I mean a gallant both for bravery and merit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106080" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106090">Nay, they seldom go both together.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106100" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106110">Well, I wish to heaven that Hymen would give thee a husband, and then that Pluto would quietly take him away to see whether you<pb facs="318" n="606"/> would marry again, oh I long for that time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106120" who="A53060_18-nell_careless">
              <speaker>Nell careless.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106130">Do not long too earnestly, lest you should miscarry of your desires.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e106140">Enter madam passionate, whereat Nell careless hearing her come, she runs away. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106150" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106160">Who was it that run away?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106170" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106180">Nell careless madam Jantil's maid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106190" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106200">O that I could contract a bargain for such an indifferent mind as her young lady hath, or that the pleasures of the world could bury my grief.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106210" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106220">There is no way for that madam, but to please yourself still with the present times, gathering those fruits of life that are ripe, and next to your reach, not to endanger a fall by climbing too high, nor to stay for that which is green, nor to let it hang whilst it is rotten with time, nor to murmur for that which is blown down by chance, nor to curse the weather of accidents for blasting the blossoms, nor the birds and worms of death, which is sickness and pain, for picking and eating the berries, for nature allows them a part as well as you, for there is nothing in the world we can absolutely possess to ourselves; for time, chance, fortune and death, hath a share in all things, life hath the least.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106230" who="A53060_18-passionate">
              <speaker>Madam passionate.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106240">I think so, for I am weary of mine.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e106250">The lady goes out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e106260">Enter a man.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106270" who="A53060_18-man">
              <speaker>Man.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106280">Mistress Dorothy, there are two or three gentlemen that desire to speak with one of the widow's maids, and you belong to one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106290" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106300">Well, what is their business?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106310" who="A53060_18-man">
              <speaker>Man.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106320">I know not, but I suppose they will only declare that to yourself.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e106330">She goeth out, and enters again as meeting the gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106340" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pascify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106350">Gentlemen, would you speak with me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106360" who="A53060_18-la_gravity">
              <speaker>Monsieur la gravity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106370">Yes, for we desire you will help us to the honour of kissing your lady's hands, thereon to offer our service.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_18-e106380" who="A53060_18-doll_pacify">
              <speaker>Doll pacify.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_18-e106390">Sir, you must excuse me, for the sign of widowhood is not as yet hung out, mourning is not on, nor the scutcheons are not hung over the gate, but if you please to come two or three days hence I may do you some service, but now it will be to no purpose to tell my lady, for I am sure she will receive no visits.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_18-e106400">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A53060_18-e106410">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A53060_18"><item xml:id="A53060_18-jantel" n="29">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-jantel</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">29</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-victoria" n="27">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-victoria</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">27</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-doll_pacify" n="23">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-doll_pacify</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">23</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-gentleman_1" n="17">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-gentleman_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">17</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-nell_careless" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-nell_careless</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-gentleman_2" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-gentleman_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-passionate" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-passionate</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-reader" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-reader</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-ruffell" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-ruffell</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-general" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-general</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A53060_18-all_women" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-all_women</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-yyyy_1" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-gentleman_3" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-gentleman_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-whiffell" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-whiffell</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-educature" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-educature</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-gentleman" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-gentleman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-valeroso" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-valeroso</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-steward" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-steward</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-comfort" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-comfort</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-la_gravity" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-la_gravity</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-messenger" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-comerade" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-comerade</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-man" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-man</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-compagnion" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-compagnion</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-gentleman_4" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-gentleman_4</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-yyyy_2" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-yyyy_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_18-la_hardy" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_18-la_hardy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

