<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A13848">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Tempe Restored <date type="creation_date">1632</date></title>
        <author>Townshend, Aurelian</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Hannah Bredar</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A13848.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Tempe restord. A masque presented by the Queene, and foureteene ladies, to the Kings Maiestie at Whitehall on Shrove-Tuesday. 1631.</title>
            <author>Townshend, Aurelian, fl. 1601-1643.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>12 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99853706</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 24156.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 454.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">19100</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13848</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Tempe restord. A masque presented by the Queene, and foureteene ladies, to the Kings Maiestie at Whitehall on Shrove-Tuesday. 1631.</title>
            <title type="add">Balet comique de la royne.</title>
            <author>Townshend, Aurelian, fl. 1601-1643.</author>
            <author>Jones, Inigo, 1573-1652.</author>
            <author>Beaujoyeulx, Baltasar de, d. ca. 1587.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[2], 19, [1] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by A[ugustine] M[athewes] for Robert Allet [i.e. Allot], and George Bakek [i.e. Baker],</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1631 [i.e. 1632]</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The songs are by Aurelian Townshend, whose name appears on C3r. The rest is by Inigo Jones, with portions derived from: Beaujoyeulx, Baltasar de. Balet comique de la royne.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The play was performed on 14 Feb. 1632.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Quire B comes in three states involving rearrangement and some resetting of type. See "Aurelian Townshend's poems and masks" (ed. E.K. Chambers), p. 118-9.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Masques -- Early works to 1800.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A13848-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A13848-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A13848-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A13848-e100040">Tempe restored.</p>
        <p xml:id="A13848-e100050">A masque presented by the Queen, and fourteen ladies, to the King's majesty at Whitehall on Shrove-tuesday. 1631.</p>
        <p xml:id="A13848-e100060">London: printed by A. m. for Robert Allet, and George Bakek. 1631.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A13848-e100070">
      <div type="text" xml:id="A13848-e100080">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>Tempe restored</head>
        <div type="argument" xml:id="A13848-e100090">
          <head>The argument.</head>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e100100">Circe by her allurements enamoured a young gent. on her person, who a while lived with her in all sensual delights until upon some jealousy conceived, she gave him to drink of an enchanted cup, and touching him with her golden wand transformed him into a lion. After some time she remembering her former love, retransformed him into his former shape. Which he reasuming took the first occasion by flight to quit the place and coming into the presence of his majesty, whose sight frees him from all fear he relates the story of his fortune.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e100110">When Circe had notice of her lovers escape it,<pb facs="3"/> put her into a furious anger and then into a lamentation or love passion. But being consolated by her nymphs; she commands that all such delights be prepared as may sweeten her sorrow: and presently all the voluntary beasts under her subjection are introduced to make her sport. After which the way being first prepared by harmony, and the influences; divine beauty accompanied with fourteen stars of a happy constellation, descends to the music of the spheres and joineth with heroic virtue, where in presence of love and Cupid, Circe knowing the design of the destinies on this glorious interview, voluntarily delivers her golden rod to Minerva. So all the enchantments being dissolved. Tempe which for a time had been possessed by the voluntary beasts of Circe's court; is restored to the true followers of the muses. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="description_of_scene" xml:id="A13848-e100130">
          <head>The description of the scene.</head>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e100140">In the upper part of the border serving for ornament to the scene, was painted a fair compartment of scrolls and quadratures, in which was written Tempe Restauratum. On each side of this, lay a figure bigger than the life, the one a woman with wings on her head like Mercury and a pen in her hand: the other a man looking down in a<pb facs="3" n="3"/> book lying open before him, and a torch lighted in his hand: that figured invention; this knowledge. Near to these were children holding ugly masks before their faces in action as if they would affright them; others riding on tame beasts and some blowing such writhe trumps as make confused noise, in the corners sat other children hardening of darts in lamps. But invention and knowledge seem not to be diverted from their study by these childish bugbears. In the midst of the two sides of this border in short nieces sat two ugly figures, the one a woman with a forked tongue, and snaky locks, and the under part of a satire, this hag held in her hand a smiling vizard crowned with roses, and was figured for envy, under the mask of friendship. On the other side was sitting as horrid a man satire with a wreath of poppy on his head, and a frog sitting on the fore part thereof; and above a bat flying, this represented curious ignorance. The rest of the border was filled up with several fancies, which lest I should be too long in the description of the frame, I will go to the picture itself, and indeed these shows are nothing else but pictures with light and motion.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e100150">A curtain being drawn up, the lightsome scene appeared, showing a delicious place by nature and art; where in a valley environed with<pb facs="4" n="4"/> hills afar off was seated, a prospect of curious arbours of various forms. The first order of marble pilasters. Between which were nieces of rock work and statues; some spurting water received into vases beneath them, and others standing on pedestals. On the returns of these pilasters run slender cornishments. From which was raised a second order of gracious terms with women's faces which bear up the ornaments. Under this to a leaning height was a Ballestrata enriched. All this second story seemed of silver work mixed with fresh Verdure's which on the tops of these arbours covered some of the returns, in the form of tips with tender branches dangling down: others were covered flat and had flower pots of gold for finishing: behind these appeared the tops of slender trees, whose leaves seemed to move with a gentle breath coming from the far off hills.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e100160">Out of this pleasant place comes in haste, a young gentleman, looking often back, as if he feared a pursuit; and being come into the midst of the room, looking still distractedly about him, he wipes his face with an handkercher, and then advanceth towards the state, and speaks.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A13848-e100170">
          <head>The fugitive favourite.</head>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100180">Was I a lion! that am now afraid! </l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100190">I fear no danger; nor I fear no death;</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100200"><pb facs="4" n="5"/> but to be retransformed, into a beast:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100210">Which while I was, although I must confess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100220">I was the bravest: what could she do less,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100230">That saw me subject, to no base desire:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100240">Yet was there in me, a Promethean fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100250">That made me covet to be man again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100260">Governed by reason, and not ruled by sense. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100270">Therefore I shun this place of residence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100280">And fly to virtue: in whose awful sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100290">She dares not come, but in a mask, and crouch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100300">As low as I did, for my liberty. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100310">Her bower is pleasant, and her palace rich;</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100320">Her fare delicious; and her language fine;</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100330">But shall the soul, the minion of the gods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100340">Stoop to her vassals? Or stand by and starve,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100350">While they sit swelling, in her chair of state? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100360">'Tis not her rod, her philters, nor her herbs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100370">(Though strong in magic) that can bound men's minds;</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100380">And make them prisoners, where there is no wall. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100390">It is consent that makes a perfect slave:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100400">And Sloth that binds us to lusts easy trades,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100410">Wherein we serve out our youth's prenticeship,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100420">Thinking at last, love should enfranchize us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100430">Whom we have never, either served or known:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100440">
            <quote xml:id="A13848-e100450">He finds no help, that uses not his own.</quote>
          </l>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e100460">The further part of the scene opening, there appears seated on the side of a fruitful hill, a sumptuous palace, with an open terrace before<pb facs="5" n="6"/> there appears seated on the side of a fruitful hill, a sumptuous palace, with an open terrace before it, and a great stair of return, descending into the lower grounds; the upper part environed with walls of marble, alongst which were planted, cypress trees. From the foot of the hill, Circe attended by the naiads, and dryads comes forth in fury, for the escape of the young gentleman, her lover; and having traversed the stage with an angry look, sings to her lute.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A13848-e100470">
          <head>The song of Circe, represented by madam Comacke.</head>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e100480" who="A13848-circe">
            <speaker>Cir:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100490">Dissembling traitor, now I see the cause,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100500">Of all thy fawning, was but to be free:</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100510">Was not for nothing, thou hadst teeth and claws,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100520">For thou hast made a cruel prey of me. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A13848-e100530">
          <head>Her 4 nymphs.</head>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100540">Ingratitude is apt, to slink away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100560">And shun that bounty which it cannot pay. </l>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e100570" who="A13848-circe">
            <speaker>Circe:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100580">And he is gone (Ay me) is stolen from hence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100590">And this poor casket of my breast, hath left</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100600">Without a heart: that should for recompense,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100610">Have locked in two: oh most inhumane theft! </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A13848-e100620">
          <head>Her four nymphs.</head>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100630">Send not your sighs, after a fickle mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100640">That sails the faster for such gales of wind. </l>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e100650" who="A13848-circe">
            <pb facs="5" n="7"/>
            <speaker>Circe.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100660">Then take my keys! and show me all my wealth. </l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100670">Lead me abroad! Let me my subjects view! </l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100680">Bring me some physic! though that bring no health! </l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100690">And feign me pleasures, since I find none true. </l>
          </sp>
          <lg xml:id="A13848-e100700">
            <head>Chorus.</head>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100710">Ye willing servants! And ye souls confined</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100730">To several shapes, by powerful herbs and art,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100740">Appear, transformed each in your several kind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100750">And strive to temper the distempered heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e100760">Of sullen Circe, stung with Cupid's dart. </l>
          </lg>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e100770">Her song ended, she sits, and before her are presented all the antimasques, consisting of Indians, and barbarians, who naturally are bestial, and others which are voluntaries, and but half transformed into beasts.</p>
          <list xml:id="A13848-e100780">
            <head>Here come forth all the antimasques.</head>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100790">7. Indians adoring their Pagole.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100800">1. Idol.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100810">1. Hare.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100820">2. Hounds.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100830">4. Lions.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100840">3. Apes.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100850"><pb facs="6" n="8"/>An ass like a Pedante, teaching them pricksong.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100860">6. Barbarians.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100870">5. Hogs.</item>
          </list>
          <list xml:id="A13848-e100880">
            <head>The last antimasque.</head>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100890">2. Indians.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100900">2. Hounds.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100910">2. Apes.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100920">1. Ass.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100930">2. Lions.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100940">2. Barbarians.</item>
            <item xml:id="A13848-e100950">2. Hogs.</item>
          </list>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e100960">The anti masques being passed; Circe and her nymphs retire towards the palace from whence she came, and the scene returning into the vale of Tempe.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e100970">Harmony comes forth attended by a chorus of music, and under her conducts fourteen influences of the stars, which are to come. She with the chorus goes up to the state and sings.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A13848-e100980">
          <head>Harmony presented by mrs. Shep.</head>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e100990">Not as myself, but as the brightest star,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101000">That shines in heaven, come to reign this day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101010"><pb facs="6" n="9"/>And these the beams and influences are</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101020">Of constellations, whose planetic sway,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101030">Though some foresee, all must alike obey. </l>
          <lg xml:id="A13848-e101040">
            <head>Chorus.</head>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101050">Such a conjunction, of auspicious lights,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101060">Meet but in honour, of some regal rights. </l>
          </lg>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A13848-e101070">
          <head>Harmony and her choir.</head>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101080">Ladies! lend us your ears. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101090">And let no lover's sigh be heard! </l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101100">Or suit, (Though just) be now preferred</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101110">A consort of the spheres,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101120">Admits no whisper, nor no sound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101130">But what is descant, to their ground:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101140">Nor can we hold ye long,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101150">For there are stars to rise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101160">That far above, our song</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101170">Are music to all eyes. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A13848-e101180">They retire.</stage>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A13848-e101190">
          <head>A saraband.</head>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101200">If any beauty here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101210">In her own glass appear</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101220">Or lover's eye, most clear? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101230">Looking but up, she may with small ado</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e101240">Perceive that flatters, and her servant too. </l>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e101250"><pb facs="7" n="10"/>Her song ended they retire with a sarabant and the fourteen influences fall into their dance. Which being passed they are placed on the degrees by the lords and ladies where they sit to see the masque. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A13848-e101260">
          <head>The highest sphere; Mr. Laneere represents</head>
          <lg xml:id="A13848-e101270">
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101280">When divine beauty, will vouchsafe to stoop,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101290">And move to earth: 'tis fit the heavenly spheres,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101300">Should be her music: and the starry troop,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101310">Shine round about her, like the crown she wears. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A13848-e101320">
            <head>Chorus.</head>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101330">No mortal breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101340">Can entertain:</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101350">So great a guest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101360">And such a train. </l>
          </lg>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e101370" who="A13848-unassigned">
            <speaker>Mr. Laneere.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101380">I cannot blame ye if ye gaze,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101390">And give small ear to what I say:</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101400">For such a presence will amaze,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101410">And send the senses all one way. </l>
          </sp>
          <lg xml:id="A13848-e101420">
            <pb facs="7" n="11"/>
            <head>Chorus.</head>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101430">The music that ye hear, is dull,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101440">But that ye see, is sweet indeed:</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101450">In every part exact, and full,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101460">From whence there doth an air proceed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101470">On which th' intelligences feed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101480">Where fair and good, inseparably conjoined,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101490">Create a Cupid, that is never blind. </l>
          </lg>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e101500">Then the scene is changed into an Oriental sky, such as appears at the sun rising, and afar off a landscape and a calm sea which did terminate the horizon; in the hither part was a heaven with a citadel, and opposite to that, were broken grounds and craggy rocks.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e101510">In the midst of the air the eight spheres in rich habits were seated on a cloud, which in a circular form was on each side continued unto the highest part of the heaven, and seemed to have let them down as in a chain.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e101520">To the music of these spheres there appeared two other clouds descending, and in them were discovered eight stars; these being come to the middle region of the sky, another greater cloud came down above them; which by little and little descending, discovered other glistering<pb facs="8" n="12"/> stars to the number of six: and above all in a chariot of goldsmith's works richly adorned with precious gems, sat divine beauty, over whose head, appeared a brightness, full of small stars that environed the top of the chariot, striking a light round about it.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e101530">The eight stars that first descended being by this time passed the spheres came forth, and the clouds on which they sat with a swift morion returning up again, and the other still descending showed a pleasing contention between them as they passed. When divine beauty and her attendants were lighted, that great cloud that bore them flies up again, leaving the chariot standing on the earth.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e101540">This sight altogether was for the difficulty of the engining and number of the persons the greatest that hath been seen here in our time. For the apparitions of such as came down in the air, and the chorus standing beneath arrived to the number of fifty persons all richly attired, showing the magnificence of the court of England. In the description of the several habits of the main masques and masquers and chorus with all the persons employed, would make a book alone as big as this, and ask more time in setting down then can be now spared; only thus<pb facs="8" n="13"/> much the Queen's majesties was in a garment of watchet satin with stars of silver embroidered and embossed from the ground, and on her head a crown of stars mixed with some small falls of white feathers. And the ladies were in the same manner. The stuff was rich and the form noble, and all suiting to the magnificence of so great a Queen.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e101550">The Queen and the ladies dance their entry; after which harmony, and the highest sphere sing, assisted by all the chorus together.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A13848-e101560">
          <head>The song.</head>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e101570" who="A13848-unassigned">
            <speaker>Mirs Sheperd.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101580">How rich is earth? and poor the skies? </l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101590">Deprived of heavenly beauty's eyes? </l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101600">Whose image men adore. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e101610" who="A13848-laneere">
            <speaker>Mr. Laneere.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101620">Heroic virtue, is that kind</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101630">Of beauty, that attracts the mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101640">And men should most implore. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e101650" who="A13848-spheres">
            <speaker>The spheres.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101660">Janus was happy that could see,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101670">Two ways at once: and happier he</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101680">That round about him kept</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101690">Watches, that never slept. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e101700" who="A13848-chorus">
            <pb facs="9" n="14"/>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101710">But we most happy, that behold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101720">Two that have turned this age to gold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101730">Making old Satur's reign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101740">In theirs, come back again. </l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101750">And since more, th'object, then the sight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101760">Makes every seer blessed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101770">How are we ravished with delight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101790">That see the best. </l>
          </sp>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e101800">The maskers dance their main dance, which done, and the Queen seated under the state by his majesty, the scene is again changed into a shady wood, and a new heaven appears differing in shape and colour from the other. In the midst of which Jove sitting on an eagle is seen hovering in the air with a glory beyond him. And at that instant Cupid from another part of the heaven comes flying forth, and having passed the scene, turns soaring about like a bird, and at the same time Pallas, Circe and her four nymphs appear on the stage: the great chorus consisting of five and thirty musicians standing below to assist them.</p>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e101810" who="A13848-cupid">
            <speaker>Cupid:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101820">It is but justice, to torment a heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101830">That tortured thousands: and my gentle reign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101840">So wronged with acting of a tyrant's part,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101850">I must restrain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101860"><pb facs="9" n="15"/> my power abused; and right my injured train. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e101870" who="A13848-jupiter">
            <speaker>Jupiter.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101880">Thou claimest her subjects: and I claim the soil,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101890">As sovereign lord: the hecatombs she brings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101900">Though great oblations, yet deduced from spoil,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101910">Are sordid things:</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101920">And sent of earth: virtue pure incense brings. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e101930" who="A13848-circe">
            <speaker>Circe:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101940">The gods, more freedom did allow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101950">When Jove turned Io to a cow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e101960" who="A13848-pallas">
            <speaker>Pallas:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101970">Are mortal creatures, grown so proud</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e101980">To tax the sky, for every cloud:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e101990" who="A13848-circe">
            <speaker>Circe:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102000">Man-maid, be gone! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e102010" who="A13848-pallas">
            <speaker>Pallas:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102020">Though I could turn thee, to a stone</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102030">I'll beg thy peace:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e102040" who="A13848-jupiter">
            <speaker>Jupiter:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102050">Dear daughter cease! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e102060" who="A13848-circe">
            <speaker>Circe:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102070">Cease dreadful Jove! Finding thy drift,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102080">My bounty, shall prevent thy gift:</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102090">This matchless pair,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102100">I make, my heir:</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102110">All I possess, I here, resign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102120"><pb facs="10" n="16"/> thou hast thy and I have mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e102130" who="A13848-jupiter">
            <speaker>Jupiter:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102140">She gives but what she can not keep. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e102150" who="A13848-cupid">
            <speaker>Cupid:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102160">Then was the wound I gave her deep. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A13848-e102170" who="A13848-unassigned">
            <speaker>Both:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102180">Was I whose power none can withstand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A13848-e102200">That opened both her heart, and hand. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A13848-e102210">
          <head>The valediction.</head>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e102220">How would they mourn, to lose ye quite! </l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e102230">That are so loath, to say, goodnight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e102240">Yet we may plead, in our excuse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e102250">Should you, these loans of love forsake</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e102260">The gods themselves, such sums would take</l>
          <l xml:id="A13848-e102270">And pay us, use. </l>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e102280">When this was passed, the eagle with love flew up, and Cupid took his flight through the air, after which the heavens close. Palas and Circe returns into the scene with the nymphs, and chorus; and so concluded the last intermedium. After which the Queen and her ladies began the revels, with the King and his lords, which continued all the night.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A13848-e102290">
          <head>The allegory.</head>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e102300">In the young gentleman, who Circe had first enamoured on her person, and after, through<pb facs="10" n="17"/> jealousy conceived, transformed into a lion. And again remembering her former love, retransformed into his former shape, is figured an incontinent man, that striving with his affections, is at last by the power of reason persuaded to fly from those sensual desires, which had formerly corrupted his judgement.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e102310">Circe here signifies desire in general, the which hath power on all living creatures, and being mixed of the divine and sensible, hath divers effects, leading some to virtue, and others to vice. She is described as a Queen, having in her service, and subjection, the nymphs, which participate of divinity, figuring the virtues, and the bruit beasts, denoting the vices. The description of her person, of extraordinary beauty, and sweetness of her voice, shows that desire is moved either by sight or hearing, to love virtue, or the contrary, and the beautiful aspect of her enchanted palace, glistering with gold, and precious ornaments, that desire cannot be moved without appearance of beauty, either true of false.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e102320">The dryads, and naiads, nymphs of the woods, and waters, that is to say; the good spirits defused through all the universe, are servants to this Queen, and live with her in all liberty<pb facs="11" n="18"/> and pleasure whose employment is to gather the most exquisite herbs, and flowers of the earth for the service of their mistress; figuring the virtues and sciences, by which the desire of man's spirits are prepared and disposed to good, the beasts, in part transformed, who contrary to their natures, make her sport, represents unto us that sensual desire makes men lose their virtue and valour, turning parasites and slaves to their brutish affections. That these intemperate beasts of Circe's court, should for a time possess Tempe. The happy retreat of the Muses and their followers, is meant, the enchantments of vicious impostures, that by false means, seek to extirpate the true lovers of science and virtue, to whom of right only that place belongs.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e102330">That divine beauty accompanied with a troop of stars of a happy constellation joining with heroic virtue should dissolve the enchantments, and Circe voluntarily deliver her golden rod to Minerva, is meant that a divine beam coming from above, with a good inclination, and a perfect habit of virtue made, by the harmony of the irascible and concupiscible parts obedient to the rational and highest part of the soul. Making man only a mind using the body<pb facs="11" n="19"/> and affections as instruments; which being his true perfection, brings him to all the happiness which can be enjoyed here below.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e102340">In heroic virtue is figured the King's majesty, who therein transcends as far common men, as they are above beasts, he truly being the prototype to all the kingdoms under his monarchy, of religion, justice, and all the virtues joined together.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e102350">So that corporeal beauty, consisting in symmetry, colour, and certain unexpressable graces, shining in the Queen's majesty, may draw us to the contemplation of the beauty of the soul, unto which it hath analogy.</p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e102360">All the verses were written by Mr. Aurelian Townesend. </p>
          <p xml:id="A13848-e102370">The subject and allegory of the masque, with the descriptions, and apparatus of the scenes were invented by Inigo Jones, surveyor of his majesty's work.</p>
          <trailer xml:id="A13848-e102380">Finis.</trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A13848-e102390">
      <div type="list" xml:id="A13848-e102400">
        <pb facs="12"/>
        <list xml:id="A13848-e102410">
          <head>The names of the influences represented by</head>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102420">Lo. Herbert.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102430">Lo. Ellesmere.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102440">Lo. Rich. of Holl.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102450">Mr. hen. Howard of Berk.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102460">Lo. Grey of Stam.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102470">Mr. Phil. Herbert.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102480">Mr. Ch. Cavendish.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102490">La. Ma. Villiers</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102500">La. Eliza Cecil.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102510">La. Al. Egerton.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102520">La. Eliza Fielding.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102530">La. Fran Howard of Berk.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102540">La. Eliza Grey of Stam.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102550">La. Diana Cecil.</item>
        </list>
        <list xml:id="A13848-e102560">
          <head>The names of the masquers. The queen's majesty.</head>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102570">Coun. Oxford.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102580">Coun. Canarvan.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102590">La. Ann. Russell.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102600">La. Ann. Cavendish.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102610">La. Ma. Russell.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102620">Mrs. Vict Cary.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102630">Mrs. Weston.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102640">Coun. Carlisle.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102650">Coun. Newport.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102660">La. Ka. Egerton.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102670">La. Ann. Fielding.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102680">La. Howard.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102690">Mrs. Padget.</item>
          <item xml:id="A13848-e102700">Mrs. Soph. Cary.</item>
        </list>
        <pb facs="12"/>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A13848"><item xml:id="A13848-circe" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A13848-circe</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13848-unassigned" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A13848-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13848-jupiter" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A13848-jupiter</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13848-cupid" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A13848-cupid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13848-pallas" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A13848-pallas</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13848-spheres" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A13848-spheres</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13848-laneere" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A13848-laneere</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13848-chorus" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A13848-chorus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

