<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A19346">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Cid<date type="creation_date">1637</date></title>
        <author>Corneille, Pierre</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A19346.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The Cid a tragicomedy, out of French made English: and acted before their Majesties at court, and on the Cock-pit stage in Drury-lane by the servants to both their Majesties.</title>
            <author>Corneille, Pierre, 1606-1684.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>42 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2007 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99844350</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 5770.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 525(a).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">9154</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19346</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The Cid a tragicomedy, out of French made English: and acted before their Majesties at court, and on the Cock-pit stage in Drury-lane by the servants to both their Majesties.</title>
            <title type="alt">Cid. English</title>
            <title type="alt">Le Cid.</title>
            <author>Corneille, Pierre, 1606-1684.</author>
            <author>J. R. fl. 1635-1640,</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[84] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by Iohn Haviland for Thomas Walkly, and are to be sold at his shop at the Flying Horse neare Yorke house,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1637.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>A translation of: Corneille, Pierre. Le Cid.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Translator's dedication signed: Rutter.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-C12 D6.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>With a final imprimatur leaf; the last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Cid, -- ca. 1043-1099 -- Drama -- Early works to 1800.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A19346-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A19346-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A19346-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A19346-e100040"><pb facs="1"/>The Cid, a tragicomedy, out of French made English: and acted before their majesties at court, and on the cockpit stage in Drury-lane, by the servants to both their majesties.</p>
        <p xml:id="A19346-e100050">
          <figure xml:id="A19346-e100060"/>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="A19346-e100070">London, printed by John Haviland for Thomas Walkly, and are to be sold at his shop at the flying horse near York house, 1637.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="frontispiece" xml:id="A19346-e100080">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <p xml:id="A19346-e100090">
          <figure xml:id="A19346-e100100">
            <p xml:id="A19346-e100110">Honi soit qvi mal y pence.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A19346-e100120">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To the right honourable, my singular good lord and master, Edward, Earl of Dorset, lord chamberlain to the Queen, counsellor of estate to his majesty, and knight of the most noble order of the garter.</head>
        <p xml:id="A19346-e100130">To give your lordship a testimony of my readiness to obey you, I no sooner was commanded by you to translate this poem than I went about it. And certainly your commands gave life to the work, which else despair of performance, or the consideration to whom it must be presented, would have stifled in its first birth. For how could I hope any thing from mine own sufficiency, being little exercised in the French tongue, and<pb facs="3"/> finding such a contumacy in their phrase to our manner of speaking; or how should I not fear such a judge as your lordship, who are not only a perfect understander, but an exact speaker of both languages. So that what we with much labour compass, is your daily exercise. For if that which Augustus attributed to Vinicius, that he had Solus ingenium in numerato, can snit with any man, it does with your lordship, whose wit we have so often seen ready told out, and fit for any emanation: and with which you have justly purchased every man's wonder and astonishment. It was therefore aptly and truly said by a noble man of your own rank and order, that when you spoke in any business you imposed oblivion on what was said before you, and silence on any man that should speak after you. It behooves me then (Since I must fear your judgement) to fly to that sweetness of your disposition (The temper of your virtues) with which you use to receive the offers that come from a grateful heart. Un less I should presume to think that your lord ship cannot without delight survey the person of D. Roderigo in this play, with whom you life has held some proportion, for like him you have ever preferred your honour to your affections, and your King and country to an thing besides: which you did not so much, because<pb facs="3"/> the place you are in requires it, but out of an inbred affection delivered to you from your ancestors, who with their happy counsels have no less confirmed this kingdom than D. Diego is here said by his arms to have supported Castille. In fine, my lord, I hope you will look with more content upon this piece, when you shall read there some places of my lords your son's translation, from whose attendance, if I have borrowed this time, I must account it upon your lordship's service, from whom I have received all I have, which is the glory to be esteemed,</p>
        <closer xml:id="A19346-e100140">
          <salute xml:id="A19346-e100150">My lord,</salute>
          <signed xml:id="A19346-e100160">Your honours most faithful most obedient servant. Rutter.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A19346-e100170">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <head><pb facs="4"/>To the reader.</head>
        <p xml:id="A19346-e100180">The place of a prologue let this leaf take up; which would gently advise you to suspend your censure of this translation, till you be skilled in both the languages; for from the ignorant in either I may suffer. Some places in the original I have changed, but not many: two scenes I have left out, as being soliloquies and little pertinent to the business: some things I have added, but scarce discernible: where he would give me leave, I have followed close both the sense and words of the author, but many things are received wit in one tongue which are not in another. The play itself, being a true history, though like a romance (Since this age consists of such play-seers) I would willingly propose to be imitated of our undertakers in the like kind, I mean for the conveyance, and (As I may call it) the Oeconomy of it: for what concerns the wit and natural expressions in it; I know I speak to deaf people, whose<pb facs="5"/> tares have been furred with 'So many hyperboles, which it the wit in fashion, though the same in<note anchored="true" n="*" place="margin" xml:id="A19346-e100190">Sen. Rhet. ●ua 1. sub ●●nem.</note> Seneca's days, were accounted madness. But if they knew how dissenting with a right care any affected speech is, they would rather trespass the other way, and not strain nature beyond what we find it commonly is. But this is no fit porch for the temple of love, I'll shut it up, and open you the pleasant way, into which you had rather enter.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A19346-e100200">
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <p xml:id="A19346-e100210">
          <pb facs="6"/>
          <list xml:id="A19346-e100220">
            <head>The names of the actors.</head>
            <item xml:id="A19346-e100230">D. Fernando the first King of Castille. </item>
            <item xml:id="A19346-e100240">D. Urraca the infanta of Castille. </item>
            <item xml:id="A19346-e100250">D. Diego the father of Roderigo.</item>
            <item xml:id="A19346-e100260">D. Gomes the count of Gormas, father to Cimena.</item>
            <item xml:id="A19346-e100270">D. Roderigo the lover of Cimena.</item>
            <item xml:id="A19346-e100280">D. Sancho in love with Cimena.</item>
            <item xml:id="A19346-e100290">
              <list xml:id="A19346-e100300">
                <head>Courtiers.</head>
                <item xml:id="A19346-e100310">D. Arias</item>
                <item xml:id="A19346-e100320">D. Alonso</item>
              </list>
            </item>
            <item xml:id="A19346-e100330">Cimena D. Rod. and D. San. Mistress.</item>
            <item xml:id="A19346-e100340">Leonora governess to the infanta.</item>
            <item xml:id="A19346-e100350">Elvira servant to Cimena.</item>
            <item xml:id="A19346-e100360">A page.</item>
            <item xml:id="A19346-e100370">Attendants.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="A19346-e100380">The scene</p>
        <p xml:id="A19346-e100390">Seville.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A19346-e100400">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A19346-e100410">
        <pb facs="6"/>
        <head>A tragicomedy.</head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A19346-e100420">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e100430">
            <head>Act i. scene i.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e100440">Count. Elvira.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e100450" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100460">Amongst all the youthful lovers which adore</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100470">Your daughter's beauty, and implore my aid,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100480">Don Roderigo and don Sancho strive</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100490">Who shall show most the fire her beauties raised. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100500">But yet Cimena is indifferent</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100510">To both their loves, and with an equal eye</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100520">Beholds them both, nor does she take away</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100530">Or add ought to their hopes, but still expects</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100540">A husband from your choice alone designed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e100550" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100560">She does her duty, both of them deserve her,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100570">Both sprung from brave and noble families,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100580">Both young, yet such as in their faces show</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100590">Th' illustrious virtue of their ancestors,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100600">But above all, in Roderigo's face</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100610">There's not a line which speaks not a brave man;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100620">His family has been fruitful still in soldiers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100630"><pb facs="7"/> as if they had been born ith' midst of laurels. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100640">His father's valour, in his time, unequalled,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100650">(Whilst his strength lasted) was a prodigy. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100660">The furrows in his forehead seem to be</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100670">Th' ingravements of his noble actions,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100680">And Roderigo's person seems to promise</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100690">The virtues of his father. In conclusion,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100700">My daughter if she love him shall please me;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100710">Go entertain her with it, but be sure</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100720">You hide m' intentions, and discover hers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100730">At my return we'll speak of it together,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100740">Time calls me now to wait upon the council,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100750">Where the King means to choose a governor</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100760">Unto the prince his son, or rather seat me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100770">In that high place of honour, for my merits</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100780">Forbid me to expect an opposition. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e100790">
            <head>Scene ii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e100800">Elvira. Cimena.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e100810" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100820">How welcome news will this be to our lovers? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100830">How fortune has provided, that all things</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100840">Should sort to their contentment? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e100850" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100860">How now Elvira? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100870">What in conclusion must I hope or fear? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100880">What must become of me? what says my father? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e100890" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100900">Only two words, enough to charm your senses,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100910">You cannot love Roderigo, more than he</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100920"><pb facs="7"/> does value him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e100930" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100940">Prithee speak truth Elvira,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100950">Th' excess of this my happiness does stagger</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100960">My faith in it; may I believe thy words? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e100970" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100980">Nay he went farther, he approves his love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e100990">And will command you meet with his desires,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101000">This you will find 'Soon as the council rises,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101010">And that don Diego meeting time, and place</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101020">Fit for his purpose, shall propose the business;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101030">Fear not but your desires will be contented. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101040" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101050">I cannot tell, but yet methinks my soul</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101060">Does not receive this joy; but all confounded</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101070">Expects what moment will present to me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101080">A divers face from this my happiness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101090">And cross my present fortune. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101100" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101110">You will find</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101120">This fear of yours most happily deceived. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101130" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101140">Well, let us go then, and attend the issue. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e101150">
            <head>Scene iii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e101160">Infanta. Leonora. Page.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101170" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101180">Go boy, look out Cimena, and from me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101190">Tell her, her presence was expected sooner,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101200">My friendship must complain of this her sloth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101210" who="A19346-leonora">
              <pb facs="8"/>
              <speaker>Leonora.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101220">I perceive, madam, that all days alike</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101230">You're sad and pensive, and the same desire</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101240">To know how her love goes, still presses you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101250" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101260">How should it not? when I myself have made her</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101270">Receive the hurt wherewith her soul is wounded,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101280">She loves don Roderigo by my means,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101290">And by my means he has vanquished her disdain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101300">Then since to take they I have laid the snare,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101310">To free they unto me belongs the care. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101320" who="A19346-leonora">
              <speaker>Leonora.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101330">And yet i'th midst of all their good success</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101340">One may perceive in you a kind of sorrow;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101350">Why should that love which lifts them up with joy</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101360">Weigh your great heart down with a heavy sadness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101370">And th' interest which you have in their love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101380">Make you unhappy, when themselves are blessed? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101390">But I'm too forward, and grow indiscreet. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101400" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101410">To stifle it increases more my grief! </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101420">Leonora, thou shalt know it, and now hear</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101430">What a strange conflict I have had within me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101440">And when th' hast heard it, pitying my weakness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101450">Admire my virtue, love is such a tyrant</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101460">As will spare none, this gentleman, this lover</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101470">Which I've bestowed on her, I love myself. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101480" who="A19346-leonora">
              <speaker>Leonora.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101490">You madam? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101500" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101510">Lay thy hand upon my heart</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101520">And feel now how it pants at th' hearing of</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101530">The name of its own conqueror. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101540" who="A19346-leonora">
              <speaker>Leonora.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101550">Pardon me, madam,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101560">If blaming of your love, I do forget</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101570"><pb facs="8"/> my due respect; is he a match for you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101580">A private gentleman? can you a Princess</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101590">In a point of such consequence forget</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101600">Whose child you are? what will the King say, think you? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101610">Do you remember, madam, whose you are? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101620" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101630">Yes, yes, Leonora, and will rather die</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101640">Than do a thing unworthy of my birth:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101650">Though I could tell thee that in noble soul's</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101660">Merit alone ought to produce true love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101670">And if my passion would fly to excuses,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101680">Many examples might authorise it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101690">Yet I'll not follow that in which my honour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101700">Must be engaged. If I have much of love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101710">I have much more of courage, and methinks </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101720">A noble true disdain tells me that I,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101730">The daughter of a King, should deem all others</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101740">Below my love, unless it were a monarch:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101750">But when I see my heart is not of force</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101760">To make its own defence, I give away</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101770">That which I dare not take: 'Stead of myself</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101780">I put Cimena fast into his fetters,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101790">And kindle their fire to put out mine own. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101800">Be not amazed then, if with distraction</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101810">I still expect their marriage; you see</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101820">All my repose only depends on it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101830">If love do live on hope, it dies with it;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101840">'Tis a fire, that not nourished will go out,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101850">And spite of my ill fortune, if Cimena</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101860">Marry don Roderigo, my long hopes</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101870">Dying, my mind will be at ease; till then</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101880">I'm still in torment; till his day of marriage</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101890">Roderigo is my love, whom though I labour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101900">To lose, I cannot choose but grieve to lose him;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101910">I find my soul divided in two parts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101920">My heart with honour fired as well as love:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101930"><pb facs="9"/> this Hymen's fatal, I both wish, and fear it. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101940">Nor can I hope for any perfect joy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101950">Since whether he obtain his love, or no,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101960">So many baits my love and honour have,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101970">In stead of comfort I must find a grave. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e101980" who="A19346-leonora">
              <speaker>Leonora.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e101990">After this, madam, I have naught to say,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102000">Unless it be to grieve for your misfortunes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102010">Before I blamed you, now I pity you:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102020">But since your virtue has made good itself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102030">So strongly 'gainst the powerful charms and force</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102040">Of love and honour, and beat back th' assault</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102050">Of this, and bait of that, in a short time</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102060">'Twill give you ease of all, in the meanwhile </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102070">Cast your firm hope on heaven, which has more justice</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102080">Than to let virtue be a sufferer long. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102090" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102100">My best of hopes is to cast off all hope. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102110" who="A19346-page">
              <speaker>Page.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102120">Madam, Cimena's come, as you commanded. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102130" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102140">Go, entertain her in the gallery. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102150" who="A19346-leonora">
              <speaker>Leonora.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102160">But will you still remain in these sad fancies? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102170" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102180">No, I will 'Spite of all my grief, put on</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102190">A face of gladness. Go, I'll follow you. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102200">Just heaven, from whence I do expect my aid,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102210">Put now at length some period to my evils;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102220">Assure mine honour with some ease of love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102230">I seek my happiness in another's bliss,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102240">To which give speed good heaven, or more strength</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102250">To my yet feeble soul, which ne'er can be</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102260">(Till Hymen have bound them) at liberty. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e102270">
            <pb facs="9"/>
            <head>Scene iv.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e102280">Count de Gormas. D. Diego.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102290" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102300">Well sir, you have got the day, the Kings high favour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102310">Has lifted you to that which was my due,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102320">He has made you governor to the prince of Castille. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102330" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102340">This honour which he has done my family,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102350">Shows he is just, and knows well how to pay</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102360">With recompense, past services. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102370" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102380">Though Kings</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102390">Be great, they are like us, and as much subject</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102400">To be deceived, as we, and this his choice</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102410">Makes us (Which are his servants) see, how ill</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102420">He recompences present services. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102430" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102440">Pray let's no more of this: perhaps to advance</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102450">My business, favour did as much as merit:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102460">And happily you had been the better choice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102470">But yet the King thought me more fit for him:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102480">You may to th' honour which the King has done me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102490">Add one more if you please, in joining both</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102500">Our families by sacred marriage. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102510">Roderigo loves your daughter, whom he has made</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102520">The chiefest object of's affections,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102530">Give your consent, and take him for your son. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102540" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102550">O sir, Roderigo must look higher now,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102560"><pb facs="10"/> the splendour of this honour newly done you</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102570">Ought to put greater thoughts into his heart. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102580">Look to your office well; govern the prince,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102590">Show him the way how he may rule a province,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102600">Make people everywhere obey his law,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102610">Teach him to love the good, to awe the bad,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102620">Add to these virtues, those of a general,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102630">Instruct him how to harden his soft body</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102640">With pain and travel, till he leave himself</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102650">Without a rival in the art of war,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102660">To sit continued days and nights on horseback,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102670">To take his rest in's arms: to force a rampire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102680">And not to owe a victory but to himself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102690">Show him this by example, and remember</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102700">You ought to represent what you would teach. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102710" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102720">To instruct him by example, this I'll say</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102730">In spite of envy, let him read my life,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102740">And by that story learn to tame fierce nations. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102750">To set on any place, to range an army,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102760">And lay his ground of honour on his actions. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102770" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102780">Living examples move more forcibly</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102790">Than books, in which a prince scarce learns his duty:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102800">But what I pray has all your long years done</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102810">That one day of my actions has not equalled? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102820">If you were valiant once, I still am so,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102830">This arm's the firm supporter of Castille,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102840">My sword once drawn has made Granado tremble,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102850">Arragon quake; without me other laws</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102860">You must have had, and other princes served:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102870">Each day, each instant, to my eternal glory,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102880">Has piled up victory on victory. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102890">The prince to set an edge upon his valour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102900">Marching by me shall be victorious,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102910">Far from your cold instructions, he shall learn</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102920"><pb facs="10"/> (Though to my valour they're preferred by some)</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102930">In seeing my actions, how to overcome. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e102940" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102950">In vain you tell me that I know already,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102960">I've seen you fight, and under me command. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102970">When age hath shrunk my sinews up with cold,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102980">Your youth and valour have supplied my place. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e102990">But not to make so many words of nothing,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103000">You are what I was once, and yet the King</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103010">Betwixt our deserts has put a difference. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103020" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103030">That which was my desert, you have obtained. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103040" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103050">He that has got it, sure has best deserved it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103060" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103070">He that can best discharge it, best deserves it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103080" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103090">'Tis no good sign though to be put beside it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103100" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103110">Like an old courtier, by much suit you got it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103120" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103130">My honourable actions stood for me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103140" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103150">Come, come, the King thus honoured your grey hairs</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103160" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103170">He prized my valour, when he gave it me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103180" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103190">If so, the honour had been mine, not yours. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103200" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103210">He that could not obtain't, did not deserve it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103220" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103230">Not I deserve it, mean you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103240" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103250">No, not you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103260" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103270">Take that, rash dotard, for thy impudence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103280" who="A19346-diego">
              <pb facs="11"/>
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103290">Nay make it up, and after this affront. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103300">Take my life too. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103310" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103320">What dost thou hope to do thou feeble fool,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103330">Thy sword is mine, but yet I scorn to take it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103340">Go now and bid the prince read o'er thy life,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103350">And let him not omit this part of it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103360">In which he'll find the just revenge I take</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103370">Of this thine insolence, a fair example. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103380" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103390">Will you then spare my life? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103400" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103410">I'm satisfied;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103420">Mine eyes cry shame unto mine hands for this. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103430" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103440">Then you do scorn to take it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103450" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103460">If I should,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103470">I did but cut the thread of three days lasting. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103480" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103490">Rage and despair! must I needs live thus long,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103500">To see this, one day of my infamy</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103510">Blast all the trophies of my former years,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103520">Oh fatal dignity! which art to me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103530">No other than a precipice, from whence</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103540">Mine honour headlong falls unto the earth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103550">Let him that has disarmed me take the place</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103560">Of governor to the prince, for I that am</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103570">A man dishonoured, am not fit for it. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103580">And thou my sword, that hangest here for a show,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103590">The glorious instrument of my actions past,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103600">But now the idle ornament of my age,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103610">Go to his hands that can tell how to use thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103620">Be then my sons, who, if he be my own,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103630">Cannot but have a sense of my dishonour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103640"><pb facs="11"/> and though he love Cimena, yet 'tis fit</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103650">His love give place to the more ardent fire</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103660">Of valour, animated by an affront,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103670">Which, though it fell on me, did yet result</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103680">On him: and see, he's here, Roderigo tell me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103690">Hast th' any courage? </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e103700">
            <head>Scene v.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e103710">Roderigo. Diego.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103720" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103730">Any man but my father</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103740">Should quickly find I have. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103750" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103760">Well said, my boy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103770">I now perceive my blood runs in thy veins,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103780">This noble anger says thou art my son;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103790">My youth revives in me from this thy heat. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103800">Thou shalt revenge me son. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103810" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103820">Of what, or whom? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103830" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103840">Of an affront so cruel, that our honours</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103850">Suffer together in it. 'twas, Roderigo,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103860">A box o'th ear, which on th'insolent giver</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103870">I had revenged, but that my feeble age</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103880">Failed my strong heart. This sword then, which my arm</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103890">Knew not to wield, take thou, and with it punish</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103900">The arrogant that wronged me, and be sure</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103910">Thou kill, or die, for such a stain as this</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103920">Is never washed, but in the offender's blood. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103930">But let me tell thee, I do send thee now</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103940"><pb facs="12"/> to combat with a man whom I have seen</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103950">All on a gore, in midst of a fought battle,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103960">Making himself a rampire of slain men. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103970" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e103980">Pray sir his name, let him be what he will. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e103990" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104000">To tell thee more then; besides that he is</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104010">The bravest soldier, and the best commander</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104020">That I have seen; he is —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104030" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104040">For heaven's sake what? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104050" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104060">The father to Cimena. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104070" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104080">The? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104090" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104100">Reply not,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104110">I know thy love, but yet remember son,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104120">He that can live contemned, doth not deserve</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104130">To breathe an hour; thou knowest th' affront was given</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104140">To me, to thee I leave the just revenge;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104150">The sense of honour, and the fire that springs</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104160">From thence, should put out the less heat of love;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104170">Revenge me, and thyself, show thyself worthy</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104180">Of me thy father, now o'erborne with miseries,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104190">Which whilst I go to moan, haste thou to punish. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e104200">
            <head>Scene vi.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104210" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo</speaker>
              <stage xml:id="A19346-e104220">Alone.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104230">Struck to the very heart, with a blow as fatal</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104240">As unforeseen; what shall I do? I must</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104250"><pb facs="12"/> revenge my father, and provoke my mistress,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104260">Either betray my honour, or my love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104270">It were a better choice for me to die</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104280">Than to do either:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104290">If I revenge my father, I must lose</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104300">My love; if not, I must live infamous;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104310">How can I live, having lost all I live for? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104320">But infamy pursues me after death. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104330">On then my soul, and rather choose to die</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104340">Losing thy love, than live ingloriously,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104350">And start not at the name of the offender,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104360">Because he is the father of thy mistress,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104370">But rather think thine own received the offence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104380">And thou art bound to give the recompense. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A19346-e104390">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e104400">
            <head>Act ii. scene i.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e104410">Don Arias. the count of Gormas. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104420" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104430">I must needs say, when I did give th' affront</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104440">My blood was overheated, and my hand</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104450">Somewhat too ready, but now who can help it? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104460">Since it is done, it cannot be recalled. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104470" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104480">Faith, let your courage stoop to the Kings will,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104490">He takes the business much to heart, and being</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104500">So highly incensed, believe it he'll proceed</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104510">With his full power, and then what defence</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104520">Can you make for yourself, when th' affront,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104530"><pb facs="13"/> and it's high quality shall be aggravated</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104540">By the person of th' offended, and the place. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104550">These will require of you, my lord, submissions</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104560">Beyond all ordinary satisfaction. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104570" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104580">Then let him take my life, 'tis in his power. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104590" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104600">Abate some of your heat, and hear what's reason,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104610">Will you not seek to appease a prince that loves you</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104620">He says, I'll ha' this done, will not you do it? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104630" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104640">Sir, to preserve my honour, I cannot think</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104650">'Tis such a crime, somewhat to disobey,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104660">But were it greater, what I've done for him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104670">Would be more than enough to make my excuse. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104680" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104690">Suppose you've done all that a man can think</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104700">In the King's service: is he bound to thank you? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104710">Can a prince be beholding to a subject? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104720">You are too much o'erweening, you must know,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104730">He that best serves his King does but his duty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104740">If you think otherwise, you are undone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104750" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104760">I shall believe you when I find it so. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104770" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104780">You can't but fear the power of the King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104790" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104800">One day destroys not such a man as I am. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104810">Let him arm all his power to punish me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104820">The state shall rather perish, than I suffer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104830" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104840">Do you so little fear the sovereign power? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104850" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104860">What? of that sceptre? which if not for me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104870">Had ere now fallen out of his hand: my person</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104880"><pb facs="13"/> is sir, of so much consequence to the King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104890">That if my head fall, his crown cannot stand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104900" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104910">My lord, give reason leave to settle you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104920">Think on't a little. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104930" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104940">The thought's already taken. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104950" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104960">What shall I say then? I must give him an account. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e104970" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104980">This: that I know not how to give consent</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e104990">To mine own shame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105000" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105010">But my lord imagine,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105020">Kings will be absolute. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105030" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105040">Let they be so,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105050">The die is cast sir, let's talk no more on't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105060" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105070">Then I must take my leave, since my persuasions</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105080">Can do no good: though you be covered o'er</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105090">With laurels, yet my lord, take heed of thunder. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105100" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105110">I'll wait it without fear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105120" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105130">It will come home. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105140" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105150">If it do, D. Diego's satisfied. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105160">How little am I scared with these poor threats? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105170">My honour once engaged, a thousand deaths</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105180">Presented to me in the most hideous forms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105190">Cannot once startle me. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e105200">
            <pb facs="14"/>
            <head>Scene ii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e105210">Roderigo. Count de Gormas.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105220" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105230">My lord a word. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105240" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105250">Speak. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105260" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105270">Resolve me of a doubt, do you know</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105280">Don Diego well? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105290" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105300">I do. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105310" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105320">And that he was</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105330">The spirit and the glory of his time,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105340">Do you know this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105350" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105360">Perhaps he might be so. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105370" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105380">And that this ardour which mine eyes do bear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105390">Do you know it is his blood it represents? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105400" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105410">What's that to me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105420" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105430">Some distance from this place</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105440">I'll make you know it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105450" who="A19346-count">
              <pb facs="14"/>
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105460">Presumptuous boy! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105470" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105480">Be not so hot, I know I'm young, but yet</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105490">In noble souls, valour prevents their years. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105500" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105510">But who has led thee to that vanity? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105520">To set thee upon me, thou that didst never</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105530">Bear arms, perhaps thou knowest not who I am. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105540" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105550">Yes: and I know a stouter man than I</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105560">Would tremble at the hearing of thy name. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105570">Thy head is covered o'er with laurels, where</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105580">Victory perches, and from thence reads to me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105590">The fate of my destruction: I do challenge</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105600">Like a rash youth, a man enured to conquest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105610">Yet having heart enough, I shan't want strength,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105620">Or if I should, wearing my father's cause</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105630">Upon my sword and arm, they cannot fail me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105640" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105650">This courage which appears in thy discourse,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105660">I have been long acquainted with, and hoping</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105670">To see the honour of Castille in thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105680">'Twas in my thoughts to give my daughter to thee;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105690">I know thy love, and am amazed to see</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105700">It's motions to give place unto thy honour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105710">And meaning to find out a perfect man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105720">And complete cavalier for my son in law,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105730">I'm not mistaken in the choice I've made. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105740">But here my pity intervenes, and though</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105750">I wonder at thy courage, yet I grieve</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105760">To see thy rashness: do not seek thy death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105770">Prithee excuse my valour from a combat</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105780">So far unequal. If thou fallest by me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105790">'Twill be no honour to me. To o'ercome</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105800"><pb facs="15"/> where there's no danger, will be a triumph</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105810">Where there's no glory: for thou wilt be thought</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105820">To have with ease been ruined, and myself</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105830">Shall alone feel the grief that I have done it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105840" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105850">Th' hast seconded th' affront thou gavest my father,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105860">With a pity worse than that, dar'st thou deprive me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105870">Of my honour, and yet fearest to take my life? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105880" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105890">Leave me good youth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105900" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105910">Let's go, and talk no more on't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105920" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105930">Art thou so weary of thy life? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105940" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105950">Art thou</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105960">So afraid to die? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e105970" who="A19346-count">
              <speaker>Count.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105980">Come then, thou dost no more</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e105990">Than is thy duty, he's a degenerate son</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106000">That will outlive one jot his father's honour. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e106010">
            <head>Scene iii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e106020">Infanta. Cimena.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106030" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106040">Be not so grieved, Cimena, dry thine eyes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106050">Use now thy constancy in this misfortune,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106060"><pb facs="15"/> thou'lt see't clear up after a little tempest:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106070">Thy happiness is but clouded for a while,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106080">And some small time will make thee no great loser. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106090" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106100">What can I hope now, but continual troubles,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106110">A storm so sudden coming o'er this calm</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106120">Threatens a certain shipwreck to our loves:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106130">'Tis passed all doubt, I perish in the haven. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106140">I loved, was loved again, our friends agreed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106150">And I no sooner had told you the news,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106160">But in an ill hour sprung their fatal quarrel,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106170">Which when I heard, I knew my hopes were ruined:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106180">Cursed ambition, honour pitiless,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106190">Under whose tyranny the bravest souls</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106200">Do ever suffer: how many tears and sighs</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106210">Must I pay for you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106220" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106230">Thou hast no reason</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106240">To fear their quarrel, which on a sudden born,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106250">Will as soon die: there's too much noise of it</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106260">To let it live. The King shall take it up,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106270">And for thy sake I'll see't shall go no farther. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106280" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106290">This business will admit no composition,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106300">Th' affronts to honour never are repaired,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106310">Wisdom or power can prevail little here;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106320">This wound will not be healed, it may be covered,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106330">And stifled hate nourishes secret fires</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106340">Within the breast, but such as burn more fiercely. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106350" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106360">But th' holy knot which shall once join Cimena</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106370">To Roderigo, will dissolve the hatred</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106380">Of both their fathers, and the bonds of love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106390">As being more strong, will quickly stop their discord. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106400" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106410">Rather do desire, than hope it, madam,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106420"><pb facs="16"/> don Diego is too haughty, and I know</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106430">My father well, of what a spirit he is. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106440">I feel my tears run, which I would retain:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106450">What's past, torments me, and I fear the sequel. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106460" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106470">Dost thou fear what a weak old man can do? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106480" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106490">Roderigo is not weak. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106500" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106510">But he's too young. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106520" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106530">Valiant young men are ever very sudden. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106540" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106550">But that thou needest not fear. He loves thee too well</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106560">To anger or displease thee, one poor word</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106570">Out of thy mouth, will quickly stay his heat. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106580" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106590">If he do not obey, how great's my grief? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106600">And if he do, what will men say of him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106610">That being a gentleman, he could put up</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106620">Such an affront? so that if he resist,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106630">Or else give way to his affection,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106640">I cannot but be troubled, or ashamed</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106650">At his too much respect, or just denial. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106660" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106670">Cimena's generous, and though she be</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106680">Engaged, she cannot suffer a base thought. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106690">But if I make a prisoner of this lover</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106700">Until this business be ta'en up betwixt them,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106710">Will not your love turn into jealousy? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106720" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106730">Ah, madam, in this case I have no such thought. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106740" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106750">Boy, look out Roderigo, bring him hither. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106760" who="A19346-boy">
              <pb facs="16"/>
              <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106770">He, and the count of Gormas</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106780" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106790">Good God, I tremble! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106800" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106810">Speak. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106820" who="A19346-boy">
              <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106830">Went out together. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106840" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106850">Alone? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106860" who="A19346-boy">
              <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106870">Alone, and as it seemed, they went to quarrel. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106880" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106890">Ay me, my fear's, they're fighting by this time. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106900" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106910">Let's spend no more time then, but go look 'em out. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e106920">
            <head>Scene iv.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e106930">King. D. Arias. D. Alonso. D. Sancho.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106940" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106950">Is he so vain, has he so little reason,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106960">That he dares think his crime yet pardonable? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e106970" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106980">I treated long with him on your behalf,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e106990">I did (Sir) my devoir, but obtained nothing. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107000" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107010">Just heaven! can a subject be so rash</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107020"><pb facs="17"/> to have so little care to please his master? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107030">Has strucken don Diego, scorned his King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107040">In my own court he means to give me laws:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107050">Be he never so good a soldier or commander,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107060">I'll make him know what 'tis to disobey. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107070">I would ha' treated him with all fair means,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107080">But since he has abused my patience,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107090">Go some of you and look him out, and whether</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107100">He do resist, or not, make sure of him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107110" who="A19346-sancho">
              <speaker>D. Sancho.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107120">Perhaps some little time will bring him in. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107130">He was taken boiling in his choler, sir,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107140">And a stout heart will hardly yield to reason,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107150">In the first motion of its rage and heat. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107160">Here's no man, that not thinks he is to blame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107170">But yet so high a spirit is not brought</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107180">At first so easily to confess his fault. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107190" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107200">Don Sancho, hold your peace, and let me tell you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107210">He that shall take his part is alike faulty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107220" who="A19346-sancho">
              <speaker>D. Sancho.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107230">I obey sir, and am silent, but with favour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107240">A word in his defence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107250" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107260">What can you say? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107270" who="A19346-sancho">
              <speaker>D. Sancho.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107280">Sir, that a soul accustomed to great actions,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107290">Cannot abase itself too low submissions. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107300">It knows not how to do it without shame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107310">And that's the word which troubles most the count. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107320">He finds it somewhat hard to do his duty. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107330">He would obey if he had less of courage;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107340">If you'd command, that he being used to arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107350">Should with his sword repair this injury,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107360">I'll undertake he shall make satisfaction. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107370" who="A19346-king">
              <pb facs="17"/>
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107380">You are too bold sir, but your age I pardon,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107390">Thinking it to proceed from heat of youth. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107400">A prudent King knows better how to husband</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107410">His subjects' blood, then so to venture 'em. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107420">For mine, I mean my care shall still conserve'em . </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107430">As the head cares for th' members which do serve it. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107440">You speak sir, as a soldier, but I must</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107450">Do as a King, and whatsoever the count</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107460">Does say or think, I'm sure he cannot lose</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107470">Ought of his honour in obeying me:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107480">Th' affront he did to him whom I have made</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107490">Governor to my son, does touch me nearly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107500">And this his insolence hath quarrelled me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107510">And th' choice I made: so if he do submit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107520">I am the man he satisfies. But no more,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107530">Don Arias, by an advice of late received,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107540">I hear the Moors mean shortly to surprise us. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107550" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107560">Dare the Moors stir? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107570" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107580">Their vessels are discovered</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107590">At the river's mouth, and you know how easily</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107600">At a full sea they may come up. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107610" who="A19346-arias">
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107620">The battles</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107630">They've lost already, should make they lose the heart</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107640">To set on such a conqueror as you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107650" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107660">They cannot but with jealousy look on,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107670">Seeing me rule in Andalusia,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107680">And this fair country, which I took from them,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107690">Keeps their designs awake. It is the reason,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107700">Why here in Seville I have placed my throne,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107710">That being near 'em I may be more ready</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107720">To meet with their attempts. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107730" who="A19346-arias">
              <pb facs="18"/>
              <speaker>D. Arias.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107740">Sir, they have learned,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107750">At the great charge of their own heads by this time,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107760">How much your presence does assure your conquest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107770">Y' have nothing sir, to fear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107780" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107790">Nor to neglect:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107800">Too much assurance still draws danger with it:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107810">The enemy which we now think to destroy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107820">If he can take his time, may annoy us. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107830">But yet since I'm not certain of my news,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107840">I would not stir up in my subjects' hearts</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107850">Vain panic terrors, or this present night</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107860">Affright the city with a false alarm:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107870">Let the haven be well guarded, and the walls,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107880">And for this night it shall suffice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107890" who="A19346-alonso">
              <speaker>D. Alonso</speaker>
              <stage xml:id="A19346-e107900">Enters again.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107910">Sir, the count is dead,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107920">Roderigo's hand has satisfied his father. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107930" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107940">I divined what would follow, when I first</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107950">Heard of th' affront, and would ha' then prevented it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107960" who="A19346-alonso">
              <speaker>D. Alonso.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107970">Sir, here's Cimena, who presents her grief</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e107980">Upon her knees, with tears demanding justice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e107990" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108000">Although my soul suffer with his misfortunes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108010">Th' affront he did, deserved the punishment,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108020">Which though it were most just, yet can't I lose</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108030">Without regret, a servant of his merit. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e108040">
            <pb facs="18"/>
            <head>Scene v.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e108050">King. D. Arias. D. Diego. Cimena. D. Sancho. D. Alonso.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108060" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108070">Justice, sir, justice, I ask it on my knees. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108080" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108090">O sir give ear to my defence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108100" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108110">Revenge my father's death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108120" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108130">Of him that punished the highest insolence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108140" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108150">Roderigo, sir,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108160" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108170">Has done the office of an honest man. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108180" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108190">Has killed my father. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108200" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108210">Has revenged his own. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108220" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108230">A King owes justice to his subjects' blood. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108240" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108250">A just revenge can fear no punishment. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108260" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108270">Rise both of you, and speak without disturbance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108280">I bear a part, Cimena, in thy sufferings. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108290">Trouble her not, when she has done, I'll hear you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108300" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108310">My father's slain, sir, and these eyes have seen</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108320"><pb facs="19"/> his blood gush out in bubbles; that dear blood</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108330">Which has so oft preserved your walls, so oft</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108340">Been fired to gain you battles, and which yet</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108350">Reeks with just anger, to have been spilt for any</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108360">But you the King, which war durst never draw,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108370">Roderigo in your court has made to flow</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108380">Upon the earth, and for his first essay,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108390">Has ta'en away the firm prop of your state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108400">Breathless, and pale, I came unto the place,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108410">And found him dead! Dead! pardon sir, my grief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108420">My voice does fail me, let my tears speak the rest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108430" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108440">Daughter, take comfort, and be confident</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108450">Thou hast a King will be a father to thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108460" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108470">You've done my miseries, sir, too much honour. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108480">Thither I came amazed, and found him dead,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108490">He spoke naught to me, but the more to move me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108500">His spilt blood wrote my duty on the dust. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108510">Rather his worth reduced to that poor state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108520">Spoke to me through his wound and hastened me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108530">To this pursuit, and to be heard the better,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108540">Of the most just of Kings, borrowed my voice. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108550">Suffer not sir, such rage to pass unpunished</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108560">Before your eyes, and let not heady youth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108570">Lave themselves in the blood of your best soldiers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108580">And brave their memories. If you permit it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108590">You'll have, but few that will desire to serve you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108600">In fine my father's dead, I demand justice</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108610">Rather for yours, than my own interest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108620">You are engaged i' th' loss of such a man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108630">Revenge it then, and require blood for blood. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108640">Sacrifice D. Diego, and his family</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108650">To yourself, to the people, to Castille,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108660">What can be dear enough to satisfy</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108670">For my dead father? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108680" who="A19346-king">
              <pb facs="19"/>
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108690">D. Diego answer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e108700" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108710">How happy is the man sir? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108720">Who parts no sooner with his strength than life,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108730">Since to the valiant, age is most unhappy</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108740">Accompanied with weakness; I that have</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108750">Gotten such glory by my former actions,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108760">Whom victory has ever waited on</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108770">See myself now, for having lived too long</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108780">Affronted, and o'ercome. And that which neither</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108790">Combat, nor siege, nor ambushes could do,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108800">Nor all your enemies, nor mine to boot,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108810">The pride of one man in your court has done</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108820">Almost before your face, and sullied</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108830">The reverence, and honour of my age,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108840">Advantaged by his youth, and by my weakness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108850">And so sir, these my hairs which have grown white</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108860">Under my helmet, and my blood, which has</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108870">So oft for you been spent, should ha' descended</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108880">Unto the grave with cureless infamy. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108890">Had I not got a son to save my honour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108900">Who lending me his hand has slain the count. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108910">If to show courage, and a sense of wrong,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108920">If to revenge a blow o'th face deserve</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108930">Severely to be punished, let it fall</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108940">On me that tempest, whatsoe'er it be,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108950">For the arms fault, we punish oft the head,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108960">I am the head, sir, he is but the arm,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108970">And if Cimena do complain that he</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108980">Has slain her father, I must answer her,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e108990">Had I been able, he had never done it. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109000">Sacrifice then this head, which age will take,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109010">The arm sir, may hereafter do you service. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109020">And let Cimena's wrong be satisfied</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109030">At my own blood's expense, and I shall be</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109040"><pb facs="20"/> so far from thinking it an unjust censure,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109050">That dying with mine honour, I shall die</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109060">Without t regret. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109070" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109080">Th' affair is of importance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109090">And merits to be heard in a full counsel. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109100">Don Sancho, wait upon Cimena home,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109110">Don Diego's word shall be his surety. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109120">Let his son be looked out. I'll do you justice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109130" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109140">'Tis just great sir to cut off murderers. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109150" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109160">Daughter, take truce a little with your griefs. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109170" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109180">To give them truce, is to increase them more. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A19346-e109190">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e109200">
            <head>Act iii. Scene i.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e109210">D. Roderigo. Elvira.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109220" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109230">What mean you Roderigo? whither would you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109240" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109250">I would pursue the course of my sad fortune. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109260" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109270">But this is a strange boldness, to appear</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109280">In the same place which you have filled with mourning,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109290">Come you to affront the ghost of the dead count? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109300">Have not you slain him? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109310" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <pb facs="20"/>
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109320">His life was my disgrace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109330">Mine honour at my hands required dis death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109340" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109350">But in the house of death to look for refuge,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109360">Did ever homicide make that his asilum? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109370" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109380">Did never any murderer present</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109390">Himself unto his judge? never wonder at me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109400">I come to seek for that I gave another,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109410">That's death; my love Cimena is my judge. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109420">When I deserved her hate, I deserved death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109430">And for that cause I stand here to receive</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109440">My sentence from her mouth, death from her hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109450" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109460">Fly rather from her sight, and do not meet</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109470">With the first motions of her grief and anger,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109480">Why, would you more inflame her present passion? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109490" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109500">No, that dear object which I durst displease,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109510">To punish me cannot have too much passion;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109520">I should be happy if I could augment it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109530">And hasten so my death from her fair hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109540" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109550">Cimena's at the court, bathed in her tears,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109560">And will return thence with much company. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109570">For heaven's sake fly: what will men's censures say</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109580">If you're discovered here? they must report</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109590">Cimena to have received into her house</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109600">Th' assassin of her father. Hark, she comes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109610">It is her voice: at least, Roderigo,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109620">To save her reputation, hide yourself. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e109630">
            <pb facs="21"/>
            <head>Scene ii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e109640">D. Sancho. Cimena. Elvira.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109650" who="A19346-sancho">
              <speaker>D. Sancho.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109660">I madam, never think of any other</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109670">But bloody sacrifices: your anger's just</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109680">And your grief lawful, for my part madam</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109690">I'll neither go about to pacify</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109700">Or comfort you; but if my present service</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109710">Can be of use to you; employ my sword</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109720">To cut out your revenge; from your commands</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109730">My heart takes courage, and my arm its strength. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109740" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109750">O me unfortunate! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109760" who="A19346-sancho">
              <speaker>D. Sancho.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109770">Madam accept my service. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109780" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109790">I shall offend the King then who has promised</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109800">To do me justice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109810" who="A19346-sancho">
              <speaker>D. Sancho.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109820">But you know, justice</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109830">Is so slow paced and languishing, that seldom</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109840">It overtakes the crime; the wrong was done</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109850">By th'sword, then let a cavalier revenge it</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109860">By the sword again: it is the readiest way. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109870" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109880">'Tis the last remedy, but if it must</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109890">Arrive at that, and this your noble pity</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109900">Of my misfortunes do continue with you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109910">I shall then give you the freedom you desire. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109920" who="A19346-sancho">
              <pb facs="21"/>
              <speaker>D. Sancho.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109930">It is the only happiness I wish,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109940">So having hopes to see't, I take my leave. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e109950">
            <head>Scene iii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e109960">Cimena. Elvira.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e109970" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109980">At length I find I'm free to open to thee</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e109990">The sadness of my soul, and to give way</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110000">To my deep sighs, which else would stifle me. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110010">My father's dead, Eluira, the first sword</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110020">That Roderigo used has cut his thread,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110030">Weep, weep mine eyes, melt into tears my brain</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110040">Half of my life, the other half has slain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110050">And 'tis me to revenge on what is left,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110060">That part of which by this I am bereft. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110070" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110080">Quiet yourself, sweet madam. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110090" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110100">How unfitly</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110110">Thou bid'st me to be quiet, when at once</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110120">I must bewail my loss, and th'hand that made it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110130">Or what is't I can hope for in this life</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110140">But torments, near to be redressed by time,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110150">If loving th' author, I pursue the crime. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110160" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110170">Can you then love the man that killed your father? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110180" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110190">Love him, Eluira? more than that I adore him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110200">My love stands up against the sense, I should have</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110210"><pb facs="22"/> of a slain father, and would quite o'erbear it. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110220">I find my lover in mine enemy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110230">And spite of all my anger, in my heart</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110240">Roderigo makes his part good 'gainst my father:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110250">Yet though my love has these advantages,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110260">I'll not advise with it about my duty. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110270">Nothing is dearer to me than Roderigo,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110280">My heart would take his part, but then my honour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110290">Tells me I had a father, which he slew. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110300" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110310">But do you mean to prosecute him, madam? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110320" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110330">O cruel meaning! cruel prosecution! </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110340">To which I'm forced. I ask his head, and yet</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110350">Fear to obtain it. I would ha' him punished,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110360">And yet my death, I know, must wait on his. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110370" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110380">Fie, madam, quit this tragical design,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110390">Be not so cruel to yourself. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110400" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110410">Shall I see</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110420">My father die between my arms? his blood</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110430">Crying vengeance to me, and shan't I hear him? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110440">Shall my heart think, because 'tis charmed by love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110450">That nothing's due unto a father's death</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110460">But childish tears? or shall I suffer love</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110470">To steal into my heart, and thrust out honour? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110480" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110490">Believe me, madam, you may well be pardoned,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110500">If you preserve unto yourself a man</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110510">You cannot parallel, and one you love. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110520">You've done enough to ha' been with the King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110530">Never press it farther, be not obstinate. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110540" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110550">Then is my glory lost; no, it behooves</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110560">I be revenged. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110570" who="A19346-elvira">
              <pb facs="22"/>
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110580">But you love Roderigo,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110590">He can't displease you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110600" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110610">No I'll swear he can't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110620" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110630">These things considered, madam, what can you do? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110640" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110650">To save mine honour, and to put an end</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110660">To all my griefs at once, I am resolved</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110670">First to pursue him unto death, and then</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110680">To die myself. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e110690">
            <head>Scene iv.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e110700">Roderigo to them.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110710" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110720">To save the trouble of</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110730">Pursuing me, behold I'm here before you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110740">Glut yourself with the pleasure of my death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110750" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110760">What place is this, Elvira? who is this? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110770">Roderigo in my house! before my face! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110780" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110790">Spare not my blood, but taste the sweetness of</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110800">My death, and your revenge, without resistance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110810" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110820">Ay me! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110830" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110840">Hear me Cimena. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110850" who="A19346-cimena">
              <pb facs="23"/>
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110860">I die. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110870" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110880">A word</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110890" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110900">Away and let me die. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110910" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110920">And afterwards</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110930">Make me no answer but with this my sword. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110940" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110950">That sword be smeared with th' blood of my dead father. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110960" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110970">My Cimena</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e110980" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e110990">Fie, take away that object</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111000">Which to mine eyes upbraids thy crime, and life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e111010" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111020">Look on it rather to increase thy hate</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111030">T'excite thine anger, and to speed my death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e111040" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111050">'Tis died in my own blood. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e111060" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111070">Plunge it in mine,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111080">And make it lose the colour so of thine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e111090" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111100">What cruelty is this, which in one day</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111110">Father and daughter both deprives of life,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111120">One by the sword, the other by the sight? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111130">Remove that object of my hate, thy sword,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111140">Thou wouldst be heard of her thou meanest to kill. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e111150" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111160">I do obey, yet with the same desire</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111170">To die by thee. For from my affection</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111180">Never expect a cowardly repentance</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111190">Of a good action, the box o'th ear</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111200">Thy father gave, dishonoured mine, thou knowest</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111210"><pb facs="23"/> how home that touches any man of spirit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111220">I shared in the affront and went to seek</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111230">The author, having found him I revenged</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111240">Mine and my father's honour: were't to do</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111250">Again I'd do't, yet think not but thy love</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111260">Held out against my father, and myself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111270">A combat long enough, and made me doubt</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111280">Whether I should displease thee or sit down</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111290">By th' injury received. I held my hand</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111300">And blamed myself for too much violence:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111310">And without doubt thy beauty had o'er swayed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111320">Had I not cast in balance, that a man</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111330">Dishonoured never could be worthy thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111340">That she who loved me when my fame stood clear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111350">Would hate me, stained with infamy. 'tis true,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111360">I did thee an affront, and 'tis as true</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111370">I ought to do it both to save my honour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111380">And merit thee. But having thus acquitted</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111390">My father and myself, 'tis only you</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111400">That I now come to satisfy, and make</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111410">A present of my blood. I know the thought</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111420">Of a slain father, arms thy hate against me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111430">Nor will I rob thee of thy sacrifice</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111440">Here, offer to the blood already shed</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111450">The blood of him, that glories to have shed it,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e111460" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111470">True Roderigo, (Though thine enemy)</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111480">That thou didst shun disgrace, I cannot blame thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111490">And whatsoever face my griefs put on</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111500">I not accuse thee, but my own misfortune. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111510">I know what honour, after such an out rage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111520">Demands of any brave and generous spirit. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111530">Thou didst thy duty but in doing it</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111540">Thou taught'st me mine. The same regard thou hadst</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111550">To vindicate thine own, and father's honour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111560">Falls now one me, and the more t'afflict me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111570"><pb facs="24"/> of thee I must require, what I have lost;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111580">It is thy interest makes me despair,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111590">Had any other hand, or sad misfortune</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111600">Deprived me of my father, I had found</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111610">My comfort in thy sight, the only charm</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111620">Against my griefs: when by so dear a hand</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111630">My tears had been wiped off: but now I must</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111640">Lose him and thee too, and what's more cruel,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111650">I'm bound myself to labour thy destruction,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111660">For never look from my affection</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111670">The least resentment for thy punishment;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111680">For though our love would speak in favour of thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111690">Mine honour yet must go as high as thine;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111700">Thou in my wrong showd'st thyself worthy me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111710">I in thy death will appear worthy thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e111720" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111730">Never defer then longer what your honour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111740">Requires of you. It demands my head,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111750">To stay till justice give't you, will delay</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111760">As well your glory, as my punishment. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111770">I shall die happy, dying by your hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e111780" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111790">Away, I'm thy accuser, not thy headsman,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111800">Is't fit for me to take the head thou offer'st? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111810">'Tis of another that I must obtain it;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111820">I must pursue thy crime, not punish it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e111830" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111840">Though love speak to thee in my favour, yet</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111850">The bravery of thy mind ought to answer mine,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111860">Which trust me (My Cimena) cannot be,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111870">If to revenge thou borrowest other hands. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111880">For my revenge I used none but my own,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111890">And thou for thine, must use thy hand alone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e111900" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111910">Cruel! to be so obstinate in this,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111920">If without help thou didst revenge thyself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111930"><pb facs="24"/> why dost thou offer't me? I'll follow thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111940">My courage is too great to let thee bear</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111950">The least part in my glory, neither shall</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111960">Mine, or my father's honour stoop so low</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111970">As to thy love, or thy despair to owe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e111980" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e111990">Hard point of honour! can I by no way</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112000">Obtain this grace? punish me in the name</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112010">Of thy dead father, or our dearest love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112020">Either do't in revenge, or else in pity. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112030">'Twill to thy lover prove a gentler fate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112040">To die thus by thy hand, than to live with thy hate. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112050" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112060">Away, I hate thee not. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112070" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112080">Thou ought'st to hate me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112090" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112100">I can't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112110" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112120">But fearest thou not the blame and scandal</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112130">Which men will raise, when they shall know my crime,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112140">And the continuance of thy love; no, rather</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112150">Force they to silence, and without more words,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112160">By my death give thy reputation life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112170" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112180">It will live better, if I let thee live;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112190">I'll ha' the voice of the most black mouthed envy</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112200">Admire my glory, and pity my hard sufferings,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112210">When they shall know, that though I love thy person,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112220">I prosecute thy crime. Go Roderigo,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112230">And let the darkness of the night conceal</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112240">Thy parting hence, mine honour cannot run</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112250">A greater hazard, than if men shall know</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112260">That I have kept thee company so long. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112270" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112280">'Tis death to hear this. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112290" who="A19346-cimena">
              <pb facs="25"/>
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112300">Away. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112310" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112320">But what, are you resolved to do. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112330" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112340">Spite of this loving fire which would restrain</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112350">That of my anger, I shall do my best</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112360">To have full vengeance for my father's death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112370">And yet in spite of this so cruel honour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112380">My desire is to have my desires crossed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112390" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112400">O miracle of love! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112410" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112420">But heaped with griefs. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112430" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112440">How many tears will these our fathers cost us? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112450" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112460">Who would ha' thought it Roderigo?</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112470">Who</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112480" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112490">Cimena would ha' said it? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112500" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112510">That our joys</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112520">Should be so nigh us and so quickly lost. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112530" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112540">And that so near the port a sudden storm</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112550">Should shipwreck all our hopes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112560" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112570">Go Roderigo,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112580">And think I cannot, dare not, hear thee longer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112590" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112600">I go then to draw out a dying life,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112610">Till thy pursuit shall bring it to an end. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112620" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112630">If I obtain th' effect, I sadly vow</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112640">Not to draw breath one minute after thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112650">Adieu, and have a care thou be not seen. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e112660">
            <pb facs="25"/>
            <head>Scene v.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e112670">D. Diego. D. Roderigo.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112680" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112690">At length I see what all my industry</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112700">Could not effect, chance offers to me, this</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112710">Must be my son. Roderigo, blessed be heaven</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112720">That gives me leave to see thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112730" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112740">Ay me! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112750" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112760">Do not confound my joys with these sad accents,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112770">But give me leave to praise thy early valour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112780">Which shows the noble stock from which thou sprang'st</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112790">The first stroke of thy sword, has equalled all</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112800">That mine could do, and thy brave youthful spirit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112810">Has reached the glory of thy ancestors. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112820">Prop of my age, and fullness of my joy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112830">Touch these white hairs, whose honour thou hast saved,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112840">Come kiss this cheek; and view the place which thou</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112850">Being affronted, rescud'st from disgrace. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112860" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112870">The honour's due to you, heaven be my witness</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112880">That coming from you, I could do no less,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112890">I hold myself most happy, that the first</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112900">Trial of my poor valour should please him</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112910">To whom I owe my life, but in these pleasures</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112920"><pb facs="26"/> have not a jealousy of me, because</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112930">After you, I dare satisfy myself</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112940">Give me leave to despair; 'tis all I ask. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112950">Let not your praise flatter me out of that. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e112960" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112970">By, from so brave a heart banish this weakness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112980">Think there are mistresses enough ith' world,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e112990">But no more than one honour; love, is but</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113000">A little pleasure, honour is a duty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113010" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113020">What say you, sir? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113030" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113040">That which thou ought'st to know. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113050" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113060">Would you then shame me with inconstancy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113070">A coward soldier, and a perjured lover,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113080">Run the same course of infamy alike. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113090">Cannot I be thought generous unless</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113100">I be perfidious. Alas my bonds</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113110">Are too fast tied, to be so soon undone</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113120">And since I can nor have, nor leave my love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113130">The death I mean to seek is my best comfort. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113140" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113150">This is no time to seek out death. Thy King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113160">Thy country needs thy aid, the fleet we feared</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113170">That entered on the river, is now ready</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113180">To take the city by surprise. The Moors</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113190">Are come in silence almost to our walls,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113200">The court is in an uproar, and the people</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113210">Call to take arms. Nothing but cries are heard</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113220">I'th midst of these calamities, my fortune</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113230">Has favoured me so much to let me see,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113240">Five hundred of my friends, within my house,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113250">Who hearing of the affront was given me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113260">Offered their lives to vindicate mine honour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113270">Thou hast prevented them, but their brave valours</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113280"><pb facs="26"/> will better be employed against the Moors;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113290">Go march i'th head of them; where honour calls thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113300">Impeach the landing of the enemy. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113310">And if thou must seek death, go find it there;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113320">But rather crowned with victory return,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113330">And by thy valour force e'en justice self</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113340">To pardon, and Cimena to be silent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113350">If thou dost love her, think thy coming home</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113360">A conqueror, must regain her heart, or nothing. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113370">But time's too precious to be spent in talk,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113380">I stay thee in discourse, when thou shouldst fly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113390">Come follow me to my house: let the King see</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113400">What he has lost ith' count, he has found in thee. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A19346-e113410">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e113420">
            <head>Act iv. scene i.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e113430">Cimena. Elvira.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113440" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113450">But is this true, Elvira? art thou sure on't? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113460" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113470">How hard it is to be faith in you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113480">When every man extolls the glorious actions</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113490">Of this young Heros: the Moors before him</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113500">Appeared, but to their shame. They quickly landed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113510">But quicker was their flight. Three hours fight</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113520">Left to our men a victory entire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113530">And two Kings prisoners. Their leaders valour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113540">Could meet with nothing durst stand in its way. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113550" who="A19346-cimena">
              <pb facs="27"/>
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113560">And was't Roderigo's hand that did these wonders. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113570" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113580">The two Kings which he vanquished are his prize. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113590" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113600">Whence couldst thou gather this strange news, Elvira? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113610" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113620">From those who sound his praises up and down,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113630">The people, who with one voice do salute him</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113640">Their guardian angel, saver of their country. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113650" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113660">How does the King look, upon this his valour? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113670" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113680">Roderigo dares not yet appear in court,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113690">But don Diego, in the conqueror name,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113700">Has made a present of these crowned captives,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113710">And all he does demand, is, that the King</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113720">Would deign to see the hand that freed his country. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113730" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113740">But has he got no wound? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113750" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113760">I know not that. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113770">Why change you colour so? resume your spirits. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113780" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113790">Let me resume my anger, which my love</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113800">Has so enfeebled; must my care for him</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113810">Make me forget myself? peace, peace my love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113820">And let my anger work; though he have vanquished</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113830">Two Kings, he has not overcome my duty. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113840">These mourning habits, where I read my miseries,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113850">Are the first fruits his valour did produce,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113860">And though all tongues should speak in his defence</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113870">All objects here do represent his crime. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113880">Veil, cypress, and these blacks sad memories</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113890">Of my dead father, keep a little up</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113900">Mine honour 'gainst my passion, and when love</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113910"><pb facs="27"/> shall get the power of me, tell my heart</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113920">I owe a duty to a father slain. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113930" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113940">Be not transported so: the Infanta's here. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e113950">
            <head>Scene ii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e113960">Infanta. Cimena. Leonora. Elvira.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e113970" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113980">I come not here, Cimena, with faint comforts</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e113990">To plead against thy grief, but with sad sighs</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114000">To mingle with thy tears. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114010" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114020">Nay rather, madam,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114030">Share in the common joy, and fully taste</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114040">The happiness, kind heaven has sent to you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114050">I only am designed for grief; the dangers</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114060">From which you're rescued by Roderigo's hand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114070">And all your safeties purchased by his arms. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114080">To me alone bequeath these tears and sighs,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114090">'Tis he has saved the city, served his King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114100">And only ruined me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114110" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114120">'Tis true, Cimena,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114130">He has done wonders. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114140" who="A19346-cimena">
              <pb facs="28"/>
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114150">Yes the unwelcome news,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114160">Has pierced my ears already, I can hear</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114170">How the voice goes, and that he's famed no less</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114180">A valiant soldier, than a luckless lover. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114190" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114200">How comes this news to be unwelcome to you? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114210">Was not the man they praised your servant once? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114220">And had not he your heart? in honouring him</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114230">They honour much your choice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114240" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114250">I needs must say</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114260">His honours are but due, and yet to me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114270">Each praise of him, is a new punishment,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114280">For I can't choose but know how great my loss is,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114290">Finding the value of the thing I lose</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114300">The more his merit, and my love increases,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114310">The more my duty gets advantage of me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114320">And spite of my affection puts me on</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114330">To prosecute his crime. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114340" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114350">But will you, madam,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114360">Believe the counsel of a faithful friend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114370" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114380">Not to obey you were a sin unpardonable. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114390" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114400">Though yesterday pursuing your revenge,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114410">You did so much that all the court admired</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114420">Your height of spirit, and bewailed your love;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114430">Yet the same way is not now to be taken. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114440">Roderigo's now the only hope and stay</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114450">Of all Castille. The terror of the Moors. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114460">His valour has restored us what before</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114470">It took away, in him your father seems</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114480">To live again, and in a word pursuing</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114490">His death, you go about the public ruin,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114500"><pb facs="28"/> what? to revenge a father, is it lawful</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114510">To give your country up to its enemies? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114520">And are we to be punished for his fault? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114530">I say not this, that I would have you marry</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114540">The man you're bound to prosecute. I'd rather</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114550">You should avoid that envy, and deprive</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114560">Him of your love, but not us of his life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114570" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114580">Ah, madam, give my spirit it's full course,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114590">Though my heart make a faction against me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114600">Though he be loved by the King, adored by th' people,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114610">Though he be compassed with the stoutest soldiers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114620">He overwhelm his laurel, with my cypress. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114630" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114640">I must confess, it is a mark of spirit</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114650">To prosecute the life you loved so dear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114660">Yet I should think, it were more noble fat</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114670">To give up to the public interest</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114680">The private ones of blood. For credit me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114690">Cimena, 'tis enough, to leave to love him:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114700">Banish him from your heart and he will find</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114710">A heavy punishment. Your country's good</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114720">Requires this, besides you must not think</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114730">The King should grant you your request. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114740" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114750">He may. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114760">Refuse me if he please, but I must speak. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114770" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114780">Consider well, Cimena, what it is</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114790">You go about, and think of it at leisure. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e114800">
            <pb facs="29"/>
            <head>Scene iii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e114810">King. D. Diego. D. Arias. D. Roderigo.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114820" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114830">Thou brave descendent of a noble race,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114840">Who have been still supporters of my kingdom,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114850">(Who's valour the first proof of thine has equalled)</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114860">My power is too narrow for thy merit. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114870">To free thy country of so rude a foe</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114880">As are the Moors, before myself could give</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114890">Order for their repulse, is such an act</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114900">As flies beyond all thought of recompense. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114910">But the two captived Kings which thou hast taken,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114920">Shall give thee thy reward, they both have named thee</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114930">Their Cid before me; which in their tongue sounds</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114940">As much as lord in ours, and this fair title</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114950">I will not envy thee; from henceforth be</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114960">Their Cid, that at thy name the Moors may tremble. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114970">And that my subjects hearing it may know</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e114980">Thy value, and how much to thee I owe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e114990" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115000">Let not your majesty confound your servant</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115010">With too much shame, to set so high a prize</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115020">Upon so poor a service. I must blush</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115030">To see such honour done so slender merit. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115040"><pb facs="29"/>My debt to you, sir, and my country is</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115050">The blood I live by, and the air I breathe;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115060">And when I lose they for so fair an object,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115070">I do, sir, but the duty of a subject. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e115080" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115090">Few of those whom their duty binds to serve me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115100">Can so acquit themselves, as thou hast done,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115110">Suffer then thy just praises, and at full</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115120">Relate the story of thy victory. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e115130" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115140">Sir, you have heard how in this urgent danger,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115150">Which put the city in so great a tumult,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115160">A company of my friends met at my fathers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115170">Moved me to go upon this enterprise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115180">But I crave pardon of your majesty:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115190">For daring to employ they without leave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115200">The danger was at hand, so were my friends;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115210">The hazard of my head, made me I durst not</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115220">Appear at court, and I had rather lose</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115230">My life in the defence of the whole state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115240">Than give it up unto Cimena's plaints. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e115250" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115260">I must excuse the heat of thy revenge,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115270">The state defended speaks in thy defence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115280">Henceforth Cimena moves me but in vain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115290">Whom if I hear 'tis but to give her comfort;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115300">But on with your relation. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e115310" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115320">Under me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115330">This troop advanced with such a confidence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115340">And so good order, that where ere they passed</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115350">They diffused courage through the lookers on,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115360"><pb facs="30"/> which so much moved 'em that although at first</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115370">We numbered but five hundred, ere we reached</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115380">The port, we were increased into three thousand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115390">Two thirds of these when I arrived, I hid</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115400">Ith' bottom of our ships, which there I found,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115410">The rest, whose number every hour increased,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115420">Lay close to the ground, and in deep silence passed</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115430">The greatest part of that fair night away. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115440">To th' guard I gave command to do the like,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115450">Affirming stoutly that I had your order,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115460">For what I did. At length the glimmering star light</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115470">Made us discover thirty sail coming up</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115480">With a full tide, for the swollen sea at once</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115490">Poured both itself, and them into our haven,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115500">We let they pass discovering none of us</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115510">Ith' haven, or the walls, and this our silence</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115520">Made them so confident of our surprise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115530">That presently they landed, fiercely running</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115540">To meet the ruin which awaited them. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115550">Then rose we up, having received the signal</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115560">From those within our ships;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115570">Who starting up in arms, did so confound</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115580">The Moors, that they were frighted ere half landed. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115590">They came to pillage, but they met with war</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115600">At sea and land, we bore they down before us,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115610">Many we slew ith' place before they could</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115620">Fall into rank or make the least resistance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115630">When suddenly in spite of our endeavours,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115640">Their princes rallied their dispersed troops,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115650">And from a shame they felt, to die so tamely,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115660">They took new courage, and restored their ranks,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115670">With their swords drawn, making their fight on foot,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115680">Then fell the bravest of our soldiers</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115690">Mixed with their captains, the land, the water,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115700">Their fleet, our haven, seemed a field of slaughter</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115710">Where death did only triumph; blood, and darkness</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115720"><pb facs="30"/> covered the place; what had their valour been,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115730">Who fought thus in the dark, had they been seen. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115740">Ay, on all sides encouraged our own men;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115750">Some I made fall upon the foe, and others</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115760">I kept from falling from us, those that came</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115770">I ranged in order, put they on the places</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115780">Which they were to make good; but what was done</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115790">We had no means to know, till the first light</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115800">Showed us our victory, and their loss. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115810">They seeing a new supply come to our aid,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115820">Fled now more fiercely, than before they fought. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115830">They got into their ships, and cut their cables,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115840">Disorderly retreating, and not minding</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115850">Whether their Kings retired or stayed behind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115860">Fear more prevailing, made them lose their duty. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115870">They came in with the flood, and with the ebb. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115880">They went away. In the mean time their Kings,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115890">And some few of their men engaged amongst us,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115900">Sold their lives dear enough; I bid 'em yield,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115910">But while they had a sword to fight, they would not,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115920">Till seeing their soldiers fall about their feet</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115930">And that alone they must defend themselves,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115940">They asked who was our leader, I was named,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115950">They yield themselves to me. So was this battle</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115960">Ended for want of men to fight it out. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e115970">And thus, sir, when we are about your service</l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e115980">To them D. Alonso.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e115990" who="A19346-alonso">
              <speaker>D. Alonso.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116000">Sir, here's Cimena come to ask you justice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e116010" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116020">What shall I do? I would not have her see thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116030"><pb facs="31"/> in stead of thanks I must dismiss thee from me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116040">But ere thou leavest the court, return again</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116050">Unto thy King's embraces. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e116060" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116070">'Tis strange, she should</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116080">Pursue the man thus, whom she fain would save. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e116090" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116100">I'm told she is in love with him. I'll try,</l>
              <stage xml:id="A19346-e116110">Cimena ent.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116120">Make show as you were sad. At length Cimena,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116130">Content yourself, for your desires have met</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116140">With their success. Though Roderigo's valour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116150">Ha'got the better of the Moors. Himself</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116160">Has perished with the wounds he there received,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116170">Give thanks to heaven that has given you vengeance;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116180">Her colour's changed already. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e116190" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116200">But, sir, mark</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116210">Her swoonings, and by them how she betrays</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116220">The secrets of her soul, surely she loves him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e116230" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116240">Is Roderigo dead then? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e116250" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116260">No, no, he lives,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116270">And still remains thy true, and constant lover,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116280">Thou shalt enjoy him, take thy mirth again. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e116290" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116300">Sir, we as often faint with joy as sadness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116310">And when excess of that surprises us,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116320">It soon confounds our senses. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e116330" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116340">Thou wouldst feign</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116350"><pb facs="31"/> that to do thee a courtesy we should</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116360">Believe impossibles; but here thy sadness</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116370">Has showed itself too plain. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e116380" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116390">Well, sir, you may</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116400">Add this too, if you please, to my misfortunes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116410">And call my swoonings the effects of grief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116420">I must confess, I grieved to see myself</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116430">Robbed of the life I sue for. If he die</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116440">Of wounds he has received for is countries good,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116450">My vengeance is lost, and my designs betrayed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116460">I ask his death, but not a glorious one;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116470">I would not have him die ith' bed of honour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116480">But on a scaffold, that his name may rot,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116490">And his memorial perish, 'tis no shame</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116500">To say I love his victory, by it</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116510">He has assured the state, and rendered me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116520">A noble sacrifice, in stead of flowers</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116530">Crowned with victorious bays, and such a one,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116540">As I'd have offered to my father's ghost. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116550">But why, alas, am I transported so? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116560">Roderigo needs not fear what I can do. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116570">What can a virgin's tears despised and scorned. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116580">Your kingdom is to him a place of free</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116590">Security, and he shall triumph over me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116600">As o'er his enemies, the blood oth' Moors</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116610">Shall choke up justice here, which must be made</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116620">A trophy to the victor's crimes; whilst I</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116630">Amongst the rest, adorn his victory. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e116640" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116650">Sweet heart you're too much hurried with your passions. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116660">We, when we render justice use to cast</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116670">Each thing in balance, Roderigo killed</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116680">Thy father, but he gave the first offence. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116690"><pb facs="32"/>Equity binds me then, to show some sweetness</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116700">To the first injured. But before thou accuse him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116710">Ask counsel of thy heart. Of which he's master. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116720">I'm sure thy love, secretly thanks thy King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116730">Whose favour keeps so brave a lover for thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e116740" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116750">For me! my enemy the author of</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116760">My miscries, the murderer of my father. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116770">Is my just suit so slighted that I'm thought</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116780">To be obliged because I am not heard? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116790">Sir, since my tears cannot obtain it of you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116800">Let the sword, I beseech you, give me justice</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116810">By that I'm injured and by that I crave</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116820">To be revenged. Of all your cavaliers</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116830">I ask his head, to him that brings it me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116840">As to the conqueror I give myself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116850">The combat ended, he shall be my husband,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116860">This, I beseech your majesty may be published</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116870">By your authority. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e116880" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116890">This country's custom,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116900">More ancient than good, under the colour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116910">Of punishing unjust attempts, has robbed</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116920">The state of its best soldiers, and often</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116930">The success does not answer the intent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116940">The guilty scape, and kill the innocent;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116950">I must dispense with Roderigo's blood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116960">It is more precious to me, than so slightly</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116970">To be exposed to hazard, though his spirit</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116980">Forced him to do an outrage, yet in freeing</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e116990">His country from the Moors, h'has freed himself. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117000" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117010">How, sir, for him must you reverse your laws,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117020"><pb facs="32"/> which have so often been observed? what will</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117030">The people, or the tongue of envy say,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117040">Hearing he lives by your protection? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117050">And that it only serves him for a colour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117060">To hide his cowardice. These are favours, sir,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117070">Which bring dishonour, with 'em to the takers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117080">The count durst do a wrong, my son durst punish,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117090">Let him maintain the honour he has won. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117100" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117110">Since you will have it so, let it be done,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117120">But if Roderigo be exposed to all</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117130">That will come in to fight for such a prize ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117140">He must be sure to want no enemies. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117150">I will have only one t'incounter him. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117160">Choose whom you will, Cimena, and choose wisely,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117170">But after this, urge me to nothing farther. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117180" who="A19346-sancho">
              <speaker>D. Sancho.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117190">An't please your majesty to let the lists</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117200">Be opened, I shall be th' undertaker;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117210">Madam, you know your promise, I beseech you</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117220">Let me obtain the grace to be your champion. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117230" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117240">What say you, Cimena, shall he be the man? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117250" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117260">Sir, I have promised him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117270" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117280">Be ready than tomorrow. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117290" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117300">Defer it not so long, sir;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117310">A man of courage is at all times ready. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117320" who="A19346-king">
              <pb facs="33"/>
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117330">Shall he no sooner be returned from one,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117340">But he must enter on another fight? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117350" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117360">He has ta'en breath, sir, in recounting it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117370" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117380">Howe'er , an hour or two let him repose,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117390">But lest I should be thought to countenance</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117400">Proceedings of this bloody nature, neither</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117410">Myself nor any of my court shall see it performed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117420">Do you look to it, and take care that both</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117430">Present themselves, as befits men of arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117440">The combat done, bring me the conqueror,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117450">I mean myself to give him to Cimena. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117460" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117470">That were t'impose too heard a law upon me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117480" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117490">Thy love dares not avow this thy complaint,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117500">If Roderigo conquer, thou must have him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117510">Never dispute my sentence or repine,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117520">Who ere is victor, I will make him thine. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A19346-e117530">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e117540">
            <pb facs="33"/>
            <head>Act. v. scene i.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e117550">D. Roderigo. Cimena.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117560" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117570">What Roderigo, in the open day! </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117580">Whence comes this boldness? do you mean t'undo</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117590">Me, and mine honour? Fie, retire yourself. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117600" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117610">Madam, I go to die, and therefore come</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117620">Before my death, to take my last farewell,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117630">My love does owe you this: and my thralled heart</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117640">Dares not depart your kingdom without leave. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117650" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117660">You go to die? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117670" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117680">Nay, more, I run; as soon</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117690">As I have ta'en my leave, the count's revenged. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117700" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117710">You go to die! And is don Sancho then</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117720">A man so terrible, that you need fear him? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117730">Who has made you so weak? or him so valiant? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117740">Roderigo goes to fight, and thinks himself</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117750">Already dead. He that nor feared the Moors,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117760"><pb facs="34"/> nor yet my father, going to encounter</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117770">Don Sancho, trembles at it. Does your spirit</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117780">Fail you at greatest need? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e117790" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117800">'Tis not to the combat</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117810">That I go now, but to my punishment. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117820">For when you seek my death, my love cannot</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117830">Defend a life against you. My heart is still</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117840">The same, but not my arm, when it should guard</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117850">That which displeases you. This night already</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117860">Had been my last, if for my private quarrel</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117870">The fight had been: but since 'twas for the King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117880">His people, and my country, had I left</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117890">Myself defenceless, I'd betrayed them all:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117900">I must confess, I did not hate my life</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117910">So much as with false treachery to part from't. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117920">Now, since no interest but mine own is in it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117930">And you demand my death, I accept your sentence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117940">For which you've made choice of another hand. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117950">(It seems i not deserved to die by yours)</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117960">I shall not go to exchange blow, for blow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117970">I owe him more respect that fights for you</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117980">And since it is your honour which he fights for,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e117990">I'll open him my breast, in his, adoring</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118000">Your hand, from which I'll welcome my destruction. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e118010" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118020">If the just violence of a fatal duty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118030">Which makes me to pursue thee 'gainst my will,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118040">Prescribe unto thy love so hard a law,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118050">That thou wilt not defend thyself'gainst him</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118060">That fights for me. Take head lest thou forget</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118070">That both thy life, and glory fall together,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118080">And howsoever Roderigo has lived</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118090">Being slain, he will be thought a vanquished man. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118100"><pb facs="34"/>Honour was dearer once than I was to you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118110">When in my father's blood you imbrued your hands,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118120">It made you then in spite of your affection</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118130">Renounce the hope of ere enjoying me;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118140">But now you value it so little that</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118150">You care not who it is that conquers you. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118160">See how unseasonable your virtue is,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118170">Why were you valiant once and are not now? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118180">Were you so only to do me an outrage? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118190">Or will you be so cruel to my father,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118200">That having conquered him, you will submit</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118210">Yourself to any hand. No Roderigo</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118220">Defend thy honour, though thou slight thy life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e118230" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118240">Mine honour cannot need any defence</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118250">More than it has already. He that could</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118260">Defeat the Moors, and kill the count of Gormas,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118270">Has not an enemy besides to fear. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118280">No, no, Roderigo knows whate'er you think,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118290">How in this fight to die and save his honour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118300">That none shall dare to think he wanted courage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118310">Only they'll say he did adore Cimena. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118320">He would not live, having deserved her hate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118330">How he gave way unto the cruel fate</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118340">Which forced his mistress to pursue his death. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118350">She asked his head, and his great heart conceived</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118360">He should commit a crime, if he denied it. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118370">T'acquit his honour he renounced his love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118380">T'acquit his mistress he renounced his life. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118390">Thus shall you see my glory in this combat</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118400">Shine more than ere it did. My willing death</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118410">Shall have this honour, that no man but I</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118420">Could for the wrong done to you satisfy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e118430" who="A19346-cimena">
              <pb facs="35"/>
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118440">Since nor thy love, nor honour can prevail</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118450">To hold thee from thy ruin, dear Roderigo,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118460">If ere I loved thee, I conjure thee now</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118470">To do thy best, if for no other end</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118480">To free me from don Sancho, let me not</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118490">Be given up to th' object of my loathing. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118500">What shall I say more? go defend thyself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118510">And if thy love be not congealed to ice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118520">Be victor where Cimena is the price,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118530">Adieu! this last word makes me blush for shame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e118540" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118550">Is there an enemy now, that I can fear? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118560">Moors, and Castilians, or whate'er you be,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118570">Whom Aragon, or Spain thinks valiant,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118580">Appear, and make one army of yourselves,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118590">My soul encouraged thus shall throw me on you. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118600">For so sweet hopes, what is't I dare not meet with? </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e118610">
            <pb facs="35"/>
            <head>Scene ii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e118620">Infanta. Leonora.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e118630" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118640">Is it to me you come now Leonora? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e118650" who="A19346-leonora">
              <speaker>Leonora.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118660">Madam, I come to testify the joy</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118670">I feel, to see your heart at rest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e118680" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118690">My heart? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118700">Can rest come to a heart that's filled with griefs? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e118710" who="A19346-leonora">
              <speaker>Leonora.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118720">If love do live on hope, and die with it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118730">Roderigo cannot trouble you any longer,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118740">You know the combat where he is engaged</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118750">By his Cimena, there he must or die,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118760">Or be her husband, but whatever happen,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118770">Whether he live, or die, your hope is dead. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e118780" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118790">But how canst thou assure me it is dead,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118800">If upon these conditions Roderigo</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118810">Do entertain the combat, have not I</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118820">Inventions enough to break it off? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118830"><pb facs="36"/>Love the sweet author of my punishment,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118840">Can teach the wits of lovers many slights. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e118850" who="A19346-leonora">
              <speaker>Leonora.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118860">Hope you to breed a discontent between 'em,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118870">Which a father's death cannot. Cimena shows</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118880">By her conduct of this affair, that hate</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118890">Causes not her pursuit, 'tis true sh' has got</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118900">The combat granted, but to take her part</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118910">Whom has she chosen, not an expert man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118920">Or one already famous for his actions. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118930">Don Sancho serves her turn, who till this time</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118940">Did never put on arms; she loves in him</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118950">His small experience. This her sudden choice</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118960">Must make you see, she sought for such a combat</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118970">As might enforce her duty to be silent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e118980">And yet assure Roderigo's conquest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e118990" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119000">I see it well enough, and yet my heart</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119010">Strives with Cimena's, who shall most adore him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119020">What had I best resolve on, Leonora? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e119030" who="A19346-leonora">
              <speaker>Leonora.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119040">Madam, bethink yourself of whom you're born,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119050">A King, heaven owes you, and you love a subject. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e119060" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119070">No, no, my thoughts are off from their first object,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119080">I love not Roderigo as a gentleman,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119090">He that I love now, is the valiant Cid,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119100">The master of two Kings. And yet I mean</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119110">T'o'ercome myself, not for the fear of blame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119120">But that I won't disturb so fair a flame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119130">And though they would now crown him, yet I should not</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119140">Resume the gift which I have given another</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119150"><pb facs="36"/> then since thou sayest Roderigoe's victory</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119160">Is certain, let's go give him to Cimena. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119170">And thou that knowest how far my love has run,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119180">Come, see me finish what I have begun. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e119190">
            <head>Scene iii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e119200">Cimena. Elvira.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e119210" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119220">What shall I do Elvira? all my hopes</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119230">Are lost, and I have nothing left but fears,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119240">I dare not give consent to my own wishes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119250">I've caused two rivals to take arms for me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119260">Whatever happens. Sorrow is my lot;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119270">For think the best, I can of fate obtain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119280">My father's unrevenged or lover slain. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e119290" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119300">From both sides you will find reason of comfort,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119310">Either you have revenge or Roderigo</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119320">However destiny disposes of you</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119330">It saves your honour, and provides y'a husband. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e119340" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119350">What? the object of my hate, or of my anger? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119360">Roderigo's, or my father's murderer,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119370">From this or that, I must expect a husband</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119380">Died in the blood of him I held most dear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119390">I fear the issue worse than any death. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119400"><pb facs="37"/>Go vengeance, or my love that troublest me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119410">Thou hast not sweets I'm sure to make me amends,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119420">And thou the powerful mover of that fate</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119430">Which does me all this violence, determine</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119440">This combat equally, without advantage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119450">That neither be the victor, or the vanquished. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e119460" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119470">That were to handle you with too much cruelty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119480">If when the fight were done, you should be bound</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119490">A new to demand justice, and ne'er leave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119500">With rigour to pursue the man you love. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119510">No, it were better that his unmatched valour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119520">Should get him victory, and silence you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119530">And that the King, according to his law</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119540">Should force you to comply with your own wishes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e119550" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119560">Dost think though he be conqueror that I will</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119570">Yield myself his? my duty is too strong,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119580">And my loss over great. He may o'ercome</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119590">Don Sancho easily, but not so soon</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119600">The glory of Cimena. Though a monarch</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119610">Have promised me unto his victory</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119620">Mine honour, (Rather than I'll be his prize)</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119630">Shall raise him up a thousand enemies. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e119640" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119650">Take heed, lest heaven for this strange pride of yours</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119660">Suffer you not to be revenged at all. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119670">What? mean you to refuse this happiness</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119680">That you may when you please sit down with honour? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119690">What is't you would pretend? what can you hope? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119700">Will your lover's death restore your father to you</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119710">Or is your father's death so small a mischief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119720">That you'd heap up loss on loss, grief upon grief. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119730">Well, do, continue in this stubborn humour. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119740">You scarce deserve the man they have destined for ye</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119750">And heaven being weary of its too much favour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119760"><pb facs="37"/> in stead of him, will wed you to don Sancho. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e119770" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119780">The griefs Elvira, I sustain already,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119790">Need not thy fatal augury to augment they,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119800">I would, if possible, avoid them both,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119810">If not, Roderigo has my best of wishes. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119820">Not that my love inclines me more to him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119830">But lest he failing, I should be don Sancho's. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119840">The thought of that, makes me to wish him well. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119850">What's this Elvira? See 'tis done already. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A19346-e119860">
            <head>Scene iv.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e119870">D. Sancho. Cimena. Elvira.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e119880" who="A19346-sancho">
              <speaker>D. Sancho.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119890">At your feet, madam, I present this sword. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e119900" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119910">What that yet reaking with Roderigo's blood? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119920">Traitor, how dar'st thou come into my sight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119930">When thou hast ravished from me, all I loved? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119940">Shine now at full my love, thou needest not fear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119950">My father's satisfied. One only blow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119960">Has to mine honour given security,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119970">To my soul despair, to my love liberty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e119980" who="A19346-sancho">
              <speaker>D. Sancho.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e119990">Hear me with better temper. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e120000" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120010">Darest thou yet</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120020"><pb facs="38"/> speak to me? Cursed murderer of that Heros</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120030">Which I do most adore. Go, thou hast slain him</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120040">Perfidiously, for otherwise that man</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120050">Could never fall by such a hand as thine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e120060" who="A19346-elvira">
              <speaker>Elvira.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120070">But hear him, madam. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e120080" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120090">What wouldst thou have me hear? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120100">Can I doubt, when my eyes are satisfied,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120110">I have obtained the mischief which I sought for,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120120">And my just suit has had too good success,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120130">Pardon dear love, it's bloody cruelty. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120140">Think though a lover, yet I was a daughter. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120150">If on thy blood I have revenged my father. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120160">For thy revenge I will exhaust my own,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120170">My soul has nothing now, that should retain it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120180">It shall go after thine, to ask it pardon. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120190">And thou that think'st t'obtain me by his death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120200">Disloyal minister of my cruel fate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120210">Hope nothing at my hands. Thou hast done me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120220">No service, only hastened on my death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e120230" who="A19346-sancho">
              <speaker>D. Sancho.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120240">'Tis a strange passion will not give me hearing. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e120250" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120260">What wouldst thou have me hear thee, whilst with boasting</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120270">Thou paintest out to me my own fatal crime,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120280">And his misfortunes, that thy cruel story</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120290">May kill me in thy sight. No, I can die</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120300">Without thy help. My soul can find out death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120310">Instructed by no aid but her own mischiefs. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e120320"><pb facs="38"/>To them the King. D. Diego. D. Arias. D. Alonso.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e120330" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120340">Sir, I need not now dissemble any longer</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120350">What never art of mine could hide from you</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120360">I loved, you know, yet to revenge my father</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120370">I would proscribe the head I held so dear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120380">By that your majesty might easily see,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120390">I meant my love should give place to my duty. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120400">In fine roderigoe's dead. His death has changed</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120410">Her, who was once his mortal enemy</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120420">To an afflicted lover. That revenge</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120430">I to my father ought, and to my love</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120440">These tears which now I shed; don Sancho has</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120450">In taking of my part quite ruined me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120460">And yet for doing so I'm made his prize. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120470">Sir, if kind pity ever moved a King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120480">Now of your grace revoke this cruel law,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120490">Though he have slain the man I loved so dear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120500">I'll give him all I have for his reward,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120510">So he will leave me to myself, and that</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120520">I may bewail (The time I have to live)</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120530">My father, and my lover, in a cloister. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e120540" who="A19346-diego">
              <speaker>D. Diego.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120550">Now you perceive she loves, sir, and not thinks</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120560">'Tis such a crime to a vow her lawful love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e120570" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120580">Sweet heart mistake not, Roderigo lives</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120590"><pb facs="39"/> don Sancho has made thee a false report. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e120600" who="A19346-sancho">
              <speaker>D. Sancho.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120610">Sir, not by me, but by her too much heat</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120620">She was deceived: for had she given me leave;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120630">I should have told her, that her noble lover,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120640">When he disarmed me, bade me banish fear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120650">For that (Said he) I'd rather leave the conquest</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120660">Uncertain, than I'd spill a drop of blood</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120670">That's ventured for Cimena, but since I</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120680">Am by my duty called to attend the King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120690">Go you and entertain her in my stead,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120700">And at her feet offer your life and sword. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120710">Which when I came to do, the sword deceived her,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120720">With which seeing me return, she thought that I</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120730">Had been the victor. Presently her anger</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120740">Betrayed her love, with such impatience</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120750">That I had not a minute's audience. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120760">For my part though I am a vanquished man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120770">And though the interest of my love be great</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120780">Yet I repute myself in this my loss</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120790">To be a gainer, loving my distress</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120800">Which brings so fair a flame, so good success. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e120810" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120820">You must not be ashamed of such a love</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120830">Cimena, or seek means to disavow it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120840">Your honour's disengaged, your duty quit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120850">Your father satisfied; what would you more? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120860">Must you still put Roderigo in new danger,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120870">You see heaven otherwise disposes of him. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120880">And since that it has done so much for him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120890">Do you too something for yourself, and take</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120900">Him for your husband that I offer you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120910">And whom I know you love. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A19346-e120920"><pb facs="39"/>To them infanta. Roderigo. Leonora.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e120930" who="A19346-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120940">Come Cimena,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120950">Dry thy eyes: and receive with a glad heart</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120960">This noble conqueror, from thy Princess's hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e120970" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120980">Great sir, be not offended if before you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e120990">The duty which I owe to love, do cast me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121000">Here at her feet. I come not to demand</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121010">The prize which I have won, but once more yet</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121020">To offer you my life. My love shall not</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121030">Or plead the combats law, or the Kings will,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121040">If all that's done cannot appease your anger,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121050">Tell me what means is left to satisfy. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121060">Must I encounter yet a thousand rivals,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121070">Travail from one end of the earth to th' other</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121080">Or force a camp myself, or rout an army,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121090">If at length I may expiate my crime,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121100">I shall attempt all this: but if your honour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121110">Be still inexorable, and nothing can</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121120"><pb facs="40"/> appease it but my death; behold my head</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121130">I cast it at your feet. Take it yourself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121140">And arm no other hand for your revenge,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121150">Since none but yours can do't. Yet let my death</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121160">Be all my punishment, and let me not</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121170">Be banished from your memory, but say</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121180">If any time you call to mind my pain</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121190">Had he not loved me, he had not been slain,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e121200" who="A19346-cimena">
              <speaker>Cimena.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121210">Rise Roderigo. Sir, I must needs say</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121220">My love has showed itself too much, for me</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121230">Now to deny it. Roderigo has</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121240">Such virtues, as I know not how to hate. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121250">And you're my King. I cannot but obey you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121260">But is there here any appearance of</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121270">A marriage, if it be, it is a sad one,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121280">That one day should begin, and end my mourning,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121290">That having laid my father in his grave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121300">I should lay Roderigo in my bed:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121310">That were to hold intelligence with's murderer,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121320">And soil my honour with eternal shame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e121330" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121340">Time often makes that lawful, which at present</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121350">Seems not to be so. Roderigo, has won thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121360">And his thou must be. But though his valour</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121370">Have made you his, yet I should do you wrong</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121380">So soon to give him the reward he fought for. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121390">Take if you will a year, to end your mourning. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121400">In the mean time Roderigo shall take arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121410">And having under his command my army,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121420">Shall carry back the war unto the Moors</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121430">Which they brought hither, that they all may tremble</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121440">At this brave name of Cid, which they have given thee</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121450">They've called thee lord already, and they would</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121460">Make thee their King. But let not (Roderigo)</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121470"><pb facs="40"/> thy great exploits, take off thy loyalty;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121480">Return, if possible, more worthy of her,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121490">And let thy deeds set such a price upon thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121500">That she may court thy marriage as an honour. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e121510" who="A19346-roderigo">
              <speaker>Roderigo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121520">For my Cimena, sir, and for your service,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121530">What can you bid me do I won't accomplish? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121540">And though I hardly can endure her absence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121550">Yet are the hopes you give sufficient happiness. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19346-e121560" who="A19346-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121570">Rely upon thy valour and my promise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121580">And now thou hast thy mistress heart already,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121590">This point of honour (Which is the last thing)</l>
              <l xml:id="A19346-e121600">Let time o'er come, thy valour, and thy King. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A19346-e121610">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A19346-e121620">
      <div type="license" xml:id="A19346-e121630">
        <pb facs="41"/>
        <p xml:id="A19346-e121640">This tragicomedy, called, the valiant Cid, translated out of French, as it was acted before the King and Queen at court, may be printed.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A19346-e121650">
          <signed xml:id="A19346-e121660">Henry Herbert.</signed>
          <dateline xml:id="A19346-e121670">
            <date xml:id="A19346-e121680">janu. 12. 1637.</date>
          </dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="imprimatur" xml:id="A19346-e121690">
        <pb facs="41"/>
        <p xml:id="A19346-e121700">Imprimatur.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A19346-e121710">
          <signed xml:id="A19346-e121720">Tho. Wykes.</signed>
          <dateline xml:id="A19346-e121730">
            <date xml:id="A19346-e121740">Jan. 26. 1637.</date>
          </dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="illustration" xml:id="A19346-e121750">
        <pb facs="42"/>
        <p xml:id="A19346-e121760">
          <figure xml:id="A19346-e121770">
            <p xml:id="A19346-e121780">Honi soit qvi mal y pence</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <pb facs="42"/>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A19346"><item xml:id="A19346-cimena" n="87">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-cimena</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">87</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19346-roderigo" n="55">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-roderigo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">55</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19346-count" n="36">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-count</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">36</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19346-diego" n="36">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-diego</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">36</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19346-king" n="34">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-king</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">34</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19346-infanta" n="32">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-infanta</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">32</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19346-elvira" n="27">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-elvira</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">27</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A19346-arias" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-arias</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19346-sancho" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-sancho</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19346-leonora" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-leonora</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19346-alonso" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-alonso</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19346-boy" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-boy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19346-page" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19346-page</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

