<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A06270">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>A Larum for London, or The Siege of Antwerp <date type="creation_date">1602</date></title>
        <author>anon.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nayoon Ahn</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A06270.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A larum for London, or The siedge of Antwerpe. VVith the ventrous actes and valorous deeds of the lame soldier. As it hath been playde by the right Honorable the Lord Chamberlaine his Seruants.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>26 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2004 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99857242</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 16754.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 192.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">22934</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06270</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A larum for London, or The siedge of Antwerpe. VVith the ventrous actes and valorous deeds of the lame soldier. As it hath been playde by the right Honorable the Lord Chamberlaine his Seruants.</title>
            <title type="alt">Larum for London</title>
            <title type="alt">Siedge of Antwerpe.</title>
            <title type="add">The spoyle of Antwerpe.</title>
            <author>Gascoigne, George, 1542?-1577.</author>
            <author>Lodge, Thomas, 1558?-1625,</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[52] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed [by Edward Allde] for William Ferbrand, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head Alley, ouer against the Tauerne doore, neere the Royall-Exchange,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1602.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Possibly in part by Thomas Lodge.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Based on: Gascoigne, George. The spoyle of Antwerpe.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-F4 G2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A06270-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A06270-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A06270-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A06270-e100040">Alarm for London, or the siege of Antwerp. With the venturous acts and valorous deeds of the lame soldier. As it hath been played by the right honourable the lord chamberlain his servants.</p>
        <p xml:id="A06270-e100050">London, printed for William Ferbrand, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head alley, over against the tavern door, near the Royal-exchange. 1602.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="A06270-e100060">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>Prologus.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e100070">Enter time.</stage>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100080">Round through the compass of this earthly ball,</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100090">The massy substance hanging in the sky,</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100100">Hath fleeting time pursued this froward age;</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100110">And searched the world's corrupt enormities. </l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100120">Here found I some, despite my hoary scalp,</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100130">There sound I courtiers laughed my course to scorn,</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100140">In that place dainty mouthed damsels scoff,</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100150">Sticking my feathers with their borrowed plumes,</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100160">As though my beauty were not good enough. </l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100170">And now this fair concourse here met together,</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100180">That have calm leisure to behold their faults,</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100190">Within my furrowed bosom deep ingrained:</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100200">Like a steel forged impression (Fixed firm)</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100210">Are met together: you will scorn my wants,</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100220">Laugh at my lament, look basely, fume and frown</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100230">But do so, do so, your proud eyes shall see</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100240">The punishment of city cruelty:</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100250">And if your hearts be not of adamant,</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100260">Reform the mischief of degenerat minds,</l>
        <l xml:id="A06270-e100270">And make you weep in pure relenting kind. </l>
        <trailer xml:id="A06270-e100280">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A06270-e100290">
      <div type="text" xml:id="A06270-e100300">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>A alarm for London, or the siege of Antwerp: with the virtuous acts and valorous deeds of the same soldier.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e100310">Enter Sancto Danila and two other captains.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e100320" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dani.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100330">So, leave me now, and in mine absence, see</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100340">That not a soldier perch upon the walls;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100350">Lest by the citizens they be espied,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100360">And thereupon they grow suspicious,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100370">Be gone, and give the sentinels in charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100380">They have an eye unto the Southern port:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100390">And hear ye? if that any forces come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100400">Let them be straight received into the castle,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100410">But with as little tumult as you may. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e100420" who="A06270-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100430">It shall be done my lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e100440">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e100450" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100460">We must be secret, as befits the care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100470">And expedition of so great a cause;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100480">Antwerp is wealthy, but withal secure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100490">Our soldiers want the crowns they surfeit with,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100500">And therefore she must spare from forth her store,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100510">To help her neighbours; nay she shall be forced,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100520">To strip her of her pouches, and on the backs</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100530">Of Spanish soldiers, hang her costliest robes. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100540">The plot already is determined of,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100550">And say Cornelius do but keep his word;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100560">These swilling epicures shall taste of death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100570"><pb facs="3"/> whilst we survive to rifle their rich coffers. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e100580">Enter Cornelius.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100590">Here comes the man, welcome Cornelius,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100600">I see you make religion of your word. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e100610" who="A06270-cornelius">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100620">Speak softly good my lord lest ye be heard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100630">The citizens are scouting here about. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e100640" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100650">Not one Gernelius dare approach so near,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100660">The castle shot keeps them in greater awe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100670">And for discovery by the eye, fear not;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100680">Within this valley we may talk at large,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100690">And no man see us: say are you resolved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100700">To stand firm friend unto the Spaniard? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100710">And sancto Damla vows you shall partake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100720">Both spoil and honour with the best of us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e100730" who="A06270-cornelius">
          <speaker>Co●.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100740">Suppose my lord I gave you my consent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100750">In all the world there's not (At my command)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100760">Above six hundred Almains; you yourself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100770">Are in the castle scarce a thousand strong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100780">And what are these to sack so great a town? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100790">So populous and large as Antwerp is. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100800">The citizens (Were they but politic,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100810">Careful and studious to preserve their peace)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100820">Might an hours warning, fill their streets,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100830">With forty thousand well appointed soldiers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e100840" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100850">Ay, but they are remiss and negligent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100860">Their bodies used to soft effeminate silks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100870">And their nice minds set all on dalliance;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100880">Which makes them fat for slaughter, fit for spoil:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100890">But say 'twere otherwise that in their peace</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100900">And days of plenty, whilst they flourished</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100910">They had foreseen the danger might ensue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100920">And exercise themselves in feats of arms;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100930">Yet we being sole commander of the castle,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100940">And that commanding them, what let is there,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100950">(Were we much weaker) but we might prevail? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100960"><pb facs="3"/>When once the a alarm sounds (Like silly mice)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100970">They'll hide them in the crevice of their walls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100980">And some for ignorance, will stand amazed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e100990">And some will be so tender of their flesh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101000">As they will scorn to bear the weight of steel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101010">No, no brave Almaigne if men ever had</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101020">A fit occasion to enrich themselves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101030">And fill the vast world with their echoing fame;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101040">Now is that instant put into our hands;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101050">And now may we be lords of this proud town ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101060">My mind divines no less, and till my feet</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101070">Tread a venturous measure in their streets,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101080">I shall be sick to think upon the deed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e101090" who="A06270-cornelius">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101100">I wish my lord as much as you detain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101110">But such an enterprise must be well grounded,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101120">Lest in performance there be found defect. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e101130" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101140">What patient eye can look upon yond turrets,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101150">And see the beauty of that flower of Europe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101160">And in't be ravished with the sight of her? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101170">O she is amorous as the wanton air. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101180">And must be courted: from her no 〈◊〉 comes</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101190">A breath, as sweet as the Arabian spice. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101200">Her garments are embroidered with pure gold;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101210">And every part so rich and sumptuous,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101220">As India's not to be compared to her,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101230">She must be courted, ●ary herself invites,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101240">And beckons us unto her sportful bed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101250">What is he then more lumpish than rude iron,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101260">By such a lodestar may not be attempted? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101270">O brave Cornelius, if within thy veins,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101280">There be that heat of vallout? I presume;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101290">Let us forslow no time till we obtain</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101300">To revel in that bower of earthly bliss. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e101310" who="A06270-cornelius">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101320">My lord, what lies in me ye shall dispose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101330">My regiment of Almains, and myself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101340">Will on the first assault revolt to you;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101350"><pb facs="4"/> mean space I'll give you close intelligence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101360">Of any thing the citizens pretend:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101370">But as I said, what makes this to the spoil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101380">Of such a might city as this is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101390">Unless we be confirmed with more supply? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e101400" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101410">Behold this scroll and be resolved in that,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101420">From Mastricht first there comes a thousand horse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101430">Beside five hundred foot: under the guiding</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101440">Of don Alonzo de Verdugo: then</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101450">From L●yre doth 〈◊〉 de Romero, bring</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101460">Five hundred foot; from Aelst two thousand more</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101470">Follow the conduct of Emanuel;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101480">The Duke of Alva likewise brings his power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101490">And for a better colour, to delude</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101500">These credulous inhabitants of Antwerp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101510">He causeth it be published he is dead,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101520">And that his soldiers guard his body hither,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101530">To have it shipped for Spain to be interred:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101540">Which well may serve to shadow his approach,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101550">The rest by night shall have their entrance;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101560">So that within two days I make account,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101570">We shall be gathered to a perfect head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101580">Of (At the least) six thousand Spaniards. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e101590" who="A06270-cornelius">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101600">I marry my lord, this soundeth somewhat like,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101610">Now dares Cornelius promise victory. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101620">But how intends your lordship to begin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101630">And give an entrance to this business? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101640">You know th' Antwerpians never yet took part,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101650">In any action 'gainst his majesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101660">But have remained as neutral, neither aiding</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101670">The prince of Orange nor offending you:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101680">How will you then enkindle flames of war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101690">And take occasion to commence your quarrel? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e101700" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101710">Why any way; it shall be thus Cornelius,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101720">I'll charge the master gunner of the castle,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101730">To make a shot or two upon the town;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101740"><pb facs="4"/> and when they come to know the cause of it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101750">I'll say it was, because they do not sink,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101760">The prince of Orange ships: but suffer them</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101770">To lie so near within the liver 〈◊〉,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101780">Which not withstanding, we precisely know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101790">Do hover there about, to no end else,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101800">But to safe conduct victuals to the town. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101810">Yet this excuse will serve to cloak our ha●e,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101820">And show some reason for what after follows. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e101830" who="A06270-cornelius">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101840">It cannot be but good my noble lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101850">And shortly (As their daily custom is)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101860">Changing the governor and other burghers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101870">Intend a solemn banquet at the statehouse. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101880">Even then, and at that place, give you direction,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101890">The gunner take his level, 'twill affright,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101900">And strike the greater terror to their souls. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e101910" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101920">Enough, I'll play them music to their meat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101930">And send such revellers into the room,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101940">As some of them shall have caroused their last,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101950">The most I crave, is that Cornelius</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101960">Will be as constant as he hath professed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e101970" who="A06270-cornelius">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101980">Once more my lord I gauge my hand with yours,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e101990">And as he is a soldier and a knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102000">Cornelius vows to be a friend to Spain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102010" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102020">I take thy word fair knight, and back again</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102030">Return the like to thee; both I and mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102040">For ever vow to love and honour thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102050">Now break we off our secret conference,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102060">And closely as we came unto this place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102070">So let us circumspectly make retreat. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102080">Walk thou into the town as if thou hadst</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102090">But only come abroad to take the air. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102100">I to the castle will withdraw myself</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102110">Down some back way, and ever as we need,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102120">Be this our meeting place, till Antwerp bleed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102130" who="A06270-cornelius">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102140">Farewell my lord, Cornelius is agreed. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e102150">Exeunt</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e102160"><pb facs="5"/>Enter Danila and the gunner. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102170" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102180">What ordinance have you laden on that part:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102190" who="A06270-gunner">
          <speaker>Gun.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102200">A falcon and two harguebuz of crock. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102210" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102220">What tellst thou me of harguebuz of crock? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102230">A pox upon your rascal squibs and crackers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102240">Have you been loading all this day till now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102250">And come you with your harguebuz of crock? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102260">A plague upon't. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102270" who="A06270-gunner">
          <speaker>Gun.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102280">My lord, blame your direction: nevertheless,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102290">Not full assured of your lordship's pleasure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102300">We have raised the cannons that came last from Harlam,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102310">And planted them this morning for the purpose. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102320" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102330">'Twas well advised; but gunner for what part? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102340" who="A06270-gunner">
          <speaker>Gun.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102350">That's as it please your honour to direct,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102360" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102370">That's for the statehouse gunner, where the Dutch</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102380">Sit swilling in the pride of their excess;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102390">Commend us to them, tell them we have sent</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102400">Music to make them merry at their feast:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102410">Go bid thy full-mouthed cannon ▪ much good do't them. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102420">Should we discharge some scurvy culvering,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102430">They'll think we are about some firework,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102440">To make them sport with. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102450">For sure they fall asleep upon full stomachs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102460">Shoot me their statehouse through both the sides,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102470">And tell them thou didst it for their health,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102480">To keepe them waking. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102490" who="A06270-gunner">
          <speaker>Gun.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102500">I warrant you my lord, I'll pierce her sides,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102510">Or never think me workman whilst I live. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e102520">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102530" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102540">I will not stir till I have heard the shot. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102550">Go light thy lintstock at some hellish brand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102560">To send black vengeance to that hated town;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102570">Let every corn of powder be a spirit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102580">Thy mortal aim as ominous as death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102590">And never a splinter that the bullet strikes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102600"><pb facs="5"/> but let it prove a very murdering piece,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102610">Amongst the burghers at their banqueting,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102620">To vomit horrid plagues upon them all. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e102630">The piece discharges.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102640">There be thou like the club of Hercules,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102650">Amongst the bousing Bacchanalian centures,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102660">To beat their Rhenish cans about their ears. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e102670">A great screek heard within.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102680">Good luck I hope hark how the sudden noise</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102690">In countering with the cannon's loud report,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102700">Stops his full mouth, with the reverberate sound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102710">And fills the circle of the empty air. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e102720">Enter two burghers running.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102730" who="A06270-burgher_1">
          <speaker>1 Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102740">The shot what from the castle questionless. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102750" who="A06270-burgher_2">
          <speaker>2 Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102760">The smoke and the report may tell you so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102770" who="A06270-burgher_1">
          <speaker>1 Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102780">And certainly intended at our lives. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102790" who="A06270-burgher_2">
          <speaker>2 Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102800">Call to the governor. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102810" who="A06270-burgher_1">
          <speaker>1 Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102820">He's walking here without the castle stay:,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102830">The citizens have sent me to demand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102840">On what occasion, or by whose commandment,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102850">You have discharged this shot upon the town? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102860" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102870">At my command sir, what is that to you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102880" who="A06270-1_burgher">
          <speaker>2 Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102890">Then thy command (I tell thee sancto Danila)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102900">Is devilish and unchristian;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102910">Which passing through the statehouse of the city,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102920">Hath slain three persons. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102930" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102940">Three frothy Rhenish fats that have drunk dead,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102950">Or in their cups have fallen to cutting throats,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102960">And fearing that it would be noised abroad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102970">To cover your foul bestial gourmandize,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e102980">Give it out to be a shot sent from the castle. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e102990" who="A06270-burgher_1">
          <speaker>1 Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103000">That men are slain we'll not expostulate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103010">But governor, was it by your commandment? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103020" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103030">Tell me you men of Antwerp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103040">If you do startle at a cannon's burst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103050"><pb facs="6"/> why suffer you the prince of Orange ships,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103060">To ride upon the river at their pleasure? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103070">And with their fleering tops to mock our fames,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103080">The whilst the sconces which do flank the river,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103090">Serve but for fishers to unload their nets;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103100">Whilst cankering rust, devours your empty cannons:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103110">And they lie hulling up and down the stream? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103120">Burghers of Antwerp answer me to this. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103130" who="A06270-1_burgher">
          <speaker>2 Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103140">They be of Zealand, and the prince of Orange</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103150">Hath ever been a friend unto the state. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103160" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103170">But enemy unto the King my master;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103180">Therefore they shall not ride upon the river;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103190">Which if your own security do suffer,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103200">We'll make our bandogs to awake your town. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103210" who="A06270-burgher_1">
          <speaker>1 Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103220">Is that the cause and reason of your shot? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103230" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103240">Burger it is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103250" who="A06270-2_burgher">
          <speaker>2. Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103260">You should have sent us word of your dislike:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103270" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103280">Why so we did, did we not send our post</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103290">Even now unto you? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103300">And wrapped our packet in a ball of lead? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103310">I think we sent a bold ambassador. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103320">That spoke our mind in thunder: did he not? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103330">You might before have known of our dislike,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103340">But that we did perceive you would not see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103350">'Twas well you heard of us. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e103360">A signet sounded, enter two with mourning pennons: a Drum sounding a dead march: Dalva carried upon a horse covered with black: soldiers after, trailing their pikes.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103370">No citizens of Antwerp, this the cause</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103380">That makes you careless and neglect our power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103390">The death of princely Dalva, had he lived,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103400">The fleet of Orange had not traded thus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103410">Nor braved our castle. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e103420"><pb facs="6"/>Enter two or three citizens running.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103430" who="A06270-1_citizen">
          <speaker>1 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103440">I pray God they mean not to assault the town. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103450" who="A06270-2_citizen">
          <speaker>2 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103460">'Tis Dalva's body brought unto the castle. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103470" who="A06270-3_citizen">
          <speaker>3 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103480">I would he had come thus, when he came first</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103490">Into these countries. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103500" who="A06270-1_citizen">
          <speaker>1 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103510">So would I, what's become of this damned fiend? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103520" who="A06270-2_citizen">
          <speaker>2 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103530">Let the devil look to that, for he has most right to him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103540" who="A06270-3_citizen">
          <speaker>3 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103550">I would the cow hide were off, we might see the four quarters. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103560" who="A06270-1_citizen">
          <speaker>1 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103570">A plague go with him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103580" who="A06270-2_citizen">
          <speaker>2 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103590">There will be old triumphing in hell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103600" who="A06270-3_citizen">
          <speaker>3 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103610">There will be old supping of boiling lead. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103620" who="A06270-1_citizen">
          <speaker>1 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103630">That Dalva was a bloody villain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103640" who="A06270-2_citizen">
          <speaker>2 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103650">He was worse than the Spanish inquisition. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103660" who="A06270-3_citizen">
          <speaker>3 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103670">Well, if ever man would have eaten up the cannibals, 'twas he. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103680" who="A06270-1_citizen">
          <speaker>1 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103690">I fear nothing but one. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103700" who="A06270-2_citizen">
          <speaker>2 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103710">What's that? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103720" who="A06270-1_citizen">
          <speaker>1 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103730">That the people will curse him out of's grave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103740" who="A06270-2_citizen">
          <speaker>2 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103750">I am glad they have cursed him into it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103760" who="A06270-3_citizen">
          <speaker>3 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103770">Well, it was never heard that Dalva was dead,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103780">But there was some notable villainy followed it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103790" who="A06270-1_citizen">
          <speaker>1 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103800">What dost thou think he will revive again? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103810" who="A06270-2_citizen">
          <speaker>2 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103820">If do, the devil's on't, I'll never trust death on's word for a half penny. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103830" who="A06270-3_citizen">
          <speaker>3 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103840">Come, we'll mourn in sack for him. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e103850">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103860" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103870">Come, let's retire ourselves into the statehouse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103880">'Tis Dalva's body brought into the castle. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e103890">Exeunt</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103900" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103910">March nearer to the castle with your hearse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103920">Before you set it down. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103930" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu. in the hearse.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103940">What are those villains gone that railed upon me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103950" who="A06270-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103960">They are my lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e103970" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e103980">Set down and let me light,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e103990">He comes from under the hearse.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104000"><pb facs="7"/>I would not hear myself again so railed on,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104010">Not for half Belgia. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104020">Zounds the dog's bark at me, a plague upon them all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104030">I think they do not hate the devil so;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104040">Dalva is never named but with a curse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104050">Think but these rogues, this is a time to die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104060">And hear these damned dogs revile me thus:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104070">Well I am dead, but Alva's spirit (Ere long)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104080">Shall haunt your ghosts, and with a fatal troop,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104090">Come in the dreadful night about your walls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104100">Grim death did ne'er affright the fearful martial,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104110">As I will fright these bousing Begians:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104120">Who's that above? Lord 〈◊〉 Danila? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104130" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104140">My lord of Alva; enter the castle. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e104150">Alva enters and his troop.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e104160">Enter Alonzo Verdugo, and his soldiers with a still march.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104170">O the lord Verdugo, and his regiment,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104180">From Mastricht? 'tis well. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e104190">Enter Julian Romero, and his power with a still march.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104200">Julian Romero and his regiment from Leyre? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104210">My lord Romero where is don Emanuel? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104220">To bring the power that we expect from Alst. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104230" who="A06270-romero">
          <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104240">Who's that? Lord sancto Danila? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104250">He's entered on the other side the castle,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104260">Withal his power. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104270" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104280">Not yet full ten, my mind presageth good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104290">Antwerp ere night, shall bathe herself in blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e104300">Exunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e104310">Enter Marquess d'hawrye, Egmount, champagne, van end and his page: English governor and one Burger.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104320" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104330">Monsieur champagne, great Antwerp's governor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104340">Will you refuse these fair and fresh supplies? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104350"><pb facs="7"/>Sent from the prince of Orange and the states,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104360">Under our conduct for your city's guard? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104370" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104380">Lord marquess Hawrye, we reject them not,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104390">Nor yet neglect the love of that great prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104400">And our kind friend the co-united states:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104410">But since we have no need of such a power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104420">Why should we pester Antwerp with such troops,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104430">To spend the victuals of the citizens,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104440">Which we can scarcely compass now for gilt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104450" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104460">The prince and states will furnish ye with store,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104470">To feed the army and relieve the town. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104480" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104490">It may be so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104500" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104510">And it may not be so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104520" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104530">Outwords and honours be engaged for it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104540" who="A06270-english_governor">
          <speaker>Eng. governor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104550">Under correction my lord governor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104560">The marks and count Egmont's noble words,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104570">(Although the prince of Orange and the states</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104580">Should be forgetful) were a pawn of worth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104590" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104600">What says the colonel of the Almains to it? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104610" who="A06270-van_end">
          <speaker>Van.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104620">This is van ends opinion my good lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104630">That the rich promise of such noble peers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104640">As marquess Hanurie and count Egmont are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104650">Is pawn enough for all the city's wealth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104660" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104670">The almain lies, wealth is worth more than words. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e104680">Standing aside.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104690" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104700">I way their promise with my sound belief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104710">And tie my thoughts to their assured trust,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104720">Yet are there many reasons of import,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104730">To bar your army's entrance to this town. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104740" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104750">The grand objection is decided. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104760" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104770">True. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104780" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104790">The lesser than are easily refelled. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104800" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104810">Suppose the prince and states do victual them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104820">Yet their disorder in our civil streets,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104830">May be pernicious, and breed mutiny. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104840" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104850">By this supposal you enfeeble us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104860"><pb facs="8"/> and tax our worth with indiscretion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104870">As though our skill and our authority,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104880">Stood upon bases of weak discipline. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104890" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104900">We said not so, and yet their ryotings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104910">May taint our wives and jeopardise our wealth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104920" who="A06270-van_end">
          <speaker>Van.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104930">In silence be it my lord, you need them not. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e104940">To cham aside.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104950" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104960">All riots shall be death by martial law,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104970">And all commanders, shall be vigilent</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e104980">Over their troops, that order may he kept. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e104990" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105000">My lords of Egmount and of Hauurye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105010">What are your numbers? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105020" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105030">Just 3000, foot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105040">One thousand horse, 800. at the least. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105050" who="A06270-english_governor">
          <speaker>Eng governor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105060">An honourable tender of true friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105070">To send such aid for safeguard of your city. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e105080">(Aside.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105090" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105100">'Twill will shake our bags too much to pay so many. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105110" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105120">At whose expense shall all this army rest? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105130" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105140">Some part yourselves, some part the prince will pay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105150" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105160">Six hundred Almains are our garrison,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105170">A guard sufficient to defend our walls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105180">And men enough, because we need no more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105190" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105200">And they too many to be paid by us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105210" who="A06270-van_end">
          <speaker>Van.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105220">O may these slaves refuse this succour sent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105230">Their misery shall bring their misery. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e105240">Aside.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105250" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105260">Count Egmont, surely Antwerp is bewitched,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105270">Security hath slain their providence,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e105280">Take Egm. aside</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105290">And riches makes them reckless of their friends;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105300">We must assume the charge upon ourselves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105310">And pray the prince and states to bear the pay;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105320">Or else their private avarice, will pull</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105330">Public destruction on this flower of towns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105340">To the disgrace of all the Netherlands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105350" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105360">I will make tender of so much to them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105370">Two months the prince of Orange and the states,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105380">And we ourselves, will pay four thousand men:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105390">If afterwards, our powers be not of use,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105400"><pb facs="8"/> we shall withdraw them to their provinces,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105410">May this content you curious citizens? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105420" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105430">The offer is so honourable now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105440">As modestly, we cannot challenge it:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105450">Captain Cornelius what's your counsel? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105460" who="A06270-van_end">
          <speaker>Van.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105470">This:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105480">Say, that you fear the Spaniards will conceive</l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e105490">Aside to Champ.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105500">Some high displeasure, if you take them in,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105510">My lords these fat pursed peasants are so proud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105520">Friends and defence, are less esteemed than pelf. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105530" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105540">Governor of Antwerp, how are you resolved? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105550" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105560">My lords, the prince of Orange and yourselves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105570">And all the states deserve our duteous love</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105580">And humble service: first, for sending power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105590">Then promising pay and victuals for that power:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105600">But with your pardon, yet there is a let,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105610">That makes us loath to take your army in. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105620" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105630">What let champagne? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105640" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Champ.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105650">The Spanish governor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105660">Danila, commander of the castle here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105670">If we receive your troops into our town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105680">Will judge we have some purpose of revolt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105690">And raising arms against the King of Spain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105700" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105710">What if he do? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105720" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105730">His fiery spirit inflamed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105740">Will send our bullets from the citadel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105750">And tear the sumptuous buildings of our town. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105760" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105770">As late he did when we were banqueting,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105780">And thought no harm, but drinking health to health,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105790">He shot, and slew some innocent poor souls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105800">And rent our statehouse and some buildings else. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105810" who="A06270-van_end">
          <speaker>Van.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105820">He'll rend you better if our purpose hold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105830" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105840">What was the cause? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105850" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105860">Because we did not sink,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105870">The prince of Orange ships, that lay to waft</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105880">Provision to our city up the river. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105890" who="A06270-english_governor">
          <pb facs="9"/>
          <speaker>Eng. Gover.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105900">Observe by that you discreet governors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105910">What love or faith the Spaniard holds with you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105920">That for his pride would have your city pine;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105930">Having destroyed the corn on Flanders side,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105940">And crossed a bridge of convoy to your town;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105950">Then that the river should not victual you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105960">He wished you sink that shipping in the skelt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e105970" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105980">Collect by this the Spaniards cruelty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e105990">Who though occasion should not come from you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106000">Would pick a quarrel for occasion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106010">To sack your city, and to suck your blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106020">To satisfy his pride and luxury:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106030">Let Harlem ▪ Mastricht, Alst example you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106040">And many city's models of his wrath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106050">Think on my father and the county horn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106060">Whose tragedy, if I recount with ruth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106070">May move the stones of Antwerp to relent ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106080">They served the Spaniard as his liegemen sworn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106090">Yet, for they did but wish their country good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106100">He picked a quarrel, and cut off their heads. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106110">Burghers the Spaniard waits to take your lives,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106120">That he may spoil your town, your wealth, your wives</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106130" who="A06270-english_governor">
          <speaker>Eng. governor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106140">Receive your friends, prevent his treachery,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106150">Lest unawares you taste his tyranny. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106160" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106170">What benefit (Good countrymen) gain we,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106180">That prostitute our fortunes and our blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106190">In your defence? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106200" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106210">Say, shall we let them in? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106220" who="A06270-van_end">
          <speaker>Van.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106230">In troth I think the Spaniard means no harm. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106240" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106250">Mean what he may, we'll not offend such friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106260">As these, the prince of Orange and the state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106270">Your army is at Kibdorpe port you say? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106280" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106290">There stay our forces. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106300" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106310">We will let them in,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106320">And quarter them with all convenient speed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106330">Van end draw up your Almains to one place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106340"><pb facs="9"/> and keep good rule for fear of civil braules,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106350">And now my lords I will attend on you. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e106360">Exeunt Champ. Marq. egm.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106370" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106380">I will attend to look and guard my doors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106390">And keep my wealth, my wife, and daughter safe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106400">For fear these hungry soldiers get a snatch. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e106410">Exit</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e106420">Manet Van and his boy.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106430" who="A06270-van_end">
          <speaker>Van.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106440">Younker come here, haste to the castle wall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106450">And call to speak with sancto Danila,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106460">Tell him from me, the flies begin to swarm ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106470">The sun grows hot, the herds do shake their horns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106480">The shepherds bring great flocks home to the fold;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106490">Say, if the butcher slaughter not in time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106500">The beasts will surfeit, and the soldiers pine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106510">Therefore begin before one glass be run,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106520">And we shall win ere setting of the sun:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106530">Remember this, be secret and away. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e106540">Exit boy.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106550">Now (Antwerp) comes the Spaniards holiday,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106560">With them join I, my share is in the gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106570">I run with the hare, and with the hound I hold;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106580">This Sunday shall be dismal to the town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106590">The burghers die, their gallant wiues gone down. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e106600">As he is going out stump encounters him.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e106610">Enter Burger, champagne, and their wives.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106620" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106630">Afore good wife, I fear that all's not well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106640">Monsieur champagne what's your opinion? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106650" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106660">Doubtless, the Spaniards do intend some hurt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106670">Hark how the tumult still increaseth? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106680" who="A06270-wife">
          <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106690">For shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106700">Be not so fearful, say that for some offence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106710">Either commenced, or but in conceit;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106720">The Spaniards were maliciously inclined:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106730">Have ye not soldiers to withstand their force? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106740">What should you need to be solicitous,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106750"><pb facs="10"/> keep ye 〈◊〉. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106760" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106770">Nay wife thou dost mistake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106780">If thou imagine we intend to fight;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106790">'Tis not 〈…〉 at the charge</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106800">To pay 〈…〉 should not they</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106810">Be at the care to see the city safe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106820" who="A06270-2_wife">
          <speaker>2 wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106830">The city's safe enough without their care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106840">Will you to dinner? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106850" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106860">Wherefore shoot they thus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106870">Unless there were some villainy abroach? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106880" who="A06270-2_wife">
          <speaker>2 wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106890">Wherefore shoot they but to try their pieces,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106900">I warrant you husband 'tis no otherwise. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e106910">Enter Marquess with his sword drawn.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106920" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106930">Here comes the marks he can tell the news. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106940" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106950">The cause my lord of this intestine uproar? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e106960" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106970">The cause is murder, misery and death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106980">You men of Antwerp, if with all the speed</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e106990">And expedition, that in men remains,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107000">You take not weapons to repulse the foe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107010">That like a swarm of deadly stinging hornets,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107020">Have all this while lay hid within their nest;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107030">But now do fly abroad with dreadful noise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107040">As if so many furies were awaked. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107050">To arms then all that love your country's peace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107060" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107070">How do ye mean my lord? or who are those</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107080">Your lordship shadows, underneath the name</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107090">Of swarming hornets? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107100" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107110">Are you so dull offence? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107120">And still so lulled in your security? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107130">Whom should I mean, but bloody Danila,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107140">And furious Alva his compeer in arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107150">That fill the castle yard with their battalions,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107160">And strive to take possession of your streets:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107170">To arms then straight, if you will keep them back. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e107180">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107190" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107200">Is't like that Alva is revived again? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107210" who="A06270-1_wife">
          <pb facs="10"/>
          <speaker>1 wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107220">As like as he intends to take the town. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107230" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107240">But I suspect there is some treachery. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107250" who="A06270-2_wife">
          <speaker>2 wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107260">Will you believe his words, he doth but jest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107270">To try how we will take it if 'twere so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107280" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Champ.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107290">Nay by his looks and by his sudden haste,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107300">It should appear the marks doth not jest. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e107310">Enter Egmont and Stump.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107320" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107330">To arms to arms, o where's the governor? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107340">Give order that your citizens prepare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107350">To stand upon their guard, defend themselves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107360">For whom you trusted, turns his weapons point</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107370">Upon your bosoms: all the Almaigne force,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107380">Is quite revolted, and the enemy</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107390">Entering your streets: van end that damned slave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107400">Gives aid to Spain, and with his traitorous hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107410">Draws in destruction, if you look not to it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107420" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107430">Where are the Switzers should supply the trenches? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107440" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107450">Drunk in their lodgings, and in reeling forth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107460">The Spaniards (Unresisted) murder them. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107470">For honour's sake, for wretched Antwerp's sake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107480">Stand not amazed, but with courageous hearts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107490">And forward hands, fight for your liberty. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e107500">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107510" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107520">Are yet your eyelids open, are you yet</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107530">Awaked out of the slumber you were in? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107540">Or will you still lie snorting in your sloth? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107550">Be still persuaded you are safe enough? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107560">Until the very instant, you do feel</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107570">Their naked swords glide through your weasond-pipes? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107580">Or do you think with belching puffs that fly</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107590">From your full paunches, you can blow them back? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107600">Or is the bottom of a deep carouse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107610">Able to drown them? will their fury melt</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107620">At the beholding of your dainty wives? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107630">Or can submission be a stickler</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107640">In these hot braules? I tell ye burghers no,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107650"><pb facs="11"/> fair words will be as oil to burning pitch;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107660">And gold as sulphur to enkindled; flames,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107670">Your daughter's chastity must quench their lust;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107680">And your dear wives, 〈◊〉 their lawless arms:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107690">I said as much but would not be believed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107700">Now tell me if I prophesied aright? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107710">Or that my zealous words deserved rebuke? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107720">Did I not say, the crocodile did weep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107730">But to obtain his prey? the sea look smooth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107740">But for a storm: would any thing be thought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107750">By the close confluence of the Spanish troops</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107760">Into the castle, but some massacre? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107770">Yet was I rated to object as much,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107780">Reviled and baffled for my loyalty:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107790" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107800">I 〈◊〉 soldier, lean thy bitter words,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107810">And help to fight for Antwerp's liberty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e107820" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stump.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107830">You have another groat to give me then,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107840">I know your liberal minds will scorn t'impose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107850">The sweat of bloody danger on the brow</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107860">Of any man, but you'll reward him for it:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107870">He shall at least (When he hath lost his limbs)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107880">Be sent for harbour to a spittle-house. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107890">How say ye, shall he not? Good reason then,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107900">But we should venture; yes, to laugh at you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107910">Whilst we behold the Spaniard cut your throats:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107920">An object base 〈◊〉 set a-work;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107930">A sweaty cobbler, whose best industry,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107940">Is but to clout a shoe, shall have his fee;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107950">But let a soldier, that hath spent his blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107960">Is lamed, 〈◊〉, or any way distressed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107970">Appeal for succour, than you look a sconce</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107980">As if you knew him not; respecting more</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e107990">An ostler, or some drudge that rakes your kennels,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108000">Than one that fighteth for the common wealth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108010" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108020">It is thy country that doth bind thee to it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108030">Not any imposition we exact. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108040" who="A06270-stump">
          <pb facs="11"/>
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108050">Binds me my country with no greater bonds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108060">Than for a groat to fight? Then for a groat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108070">To be enfeebled, or to lose a limb? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108080">Poor groatsworth of effection; well, I'll learn</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108090">To pay my debt and to measure my desert</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108100">According to the rate: a groat I had,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108110">And so much as a groat amounts unto you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108120">My sword shall pay ye in exchange of blows. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e108130">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e108140">Enter two citizens. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108150" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cham.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108160">Citizens how now? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108170" who="A06270-1_citizen">
          <speaker>1 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108180">O monsieur champagne,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108190">We are undone for want of discipline,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108200" who="A06270-2_citizen">
          <speaker>2 citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108210">The Spaniards hurry into every street,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108220">What shall we do for safeguard of our lives? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108230" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108240">What shall ye do? stand every man at's door,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108250">And take in's hand a Holbert or brown bill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108260">And study to defend him as he may. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108270" who="A06270-champaigne">
          <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108280">I hear them coming, let us shift away. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e108290">Exeunt</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e108300">In the alarum, Alva and Danila pursue Marquess hawrie, and count Egmont furiously.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108310" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108320">Marquess d' Hawrie stay, thou canst not scape. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108330" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108340">And stay count Egmont: Danila's conquering sword,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108350">Pursues thy life, therefore abide and yield it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108360" who="A06270-marquis">
          <speaker>Ma●</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108370">Insatiate Alva, that like sun-rise ground,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108380">Never sufficed with sweetest showers that fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108390">But with a thousand mouths gapes still for more. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108400">So thy desire of blood never satisfied,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108410">With the rich tribute of so many lives,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108420">Whose guiltless blood hath dyed poor Belgius' checks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108430">And changed her like a drunken bacchanal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108440">Still with a thousand quenchless appetites,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108450">Dost thirst for more, as if that epithet</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108460">Were the sole object of thy hearts best hopes</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108470"><pb facs="12"/> know tyrant, marquess Hawrie flies thee not,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108480">As fearing all the uttermost thou canst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108490">But the oppression of unequal power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108500">False treason, that betrayed our lives to thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108510">And the sharp scourge, that fond security,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108520">Hath justly thrown on Antwerp's wilfulness</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108530" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108540">These are the sluices that have brought on us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108550">The swelling pride and tyranny of Spain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108560">Which Antwerp careless off, although forewarned</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108570">By many bleeding instances about her,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108580">Could not; nay, would not be advised at all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108590">Tell me but this, Alva and Danila both,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108600">What state is there, be it ne'er so popular,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108610">Abounding in the height of fortune's gifts;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108620">And all felicities of worldly pomp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108630">That sees sad desolation sit in tears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108640">Upon her neighbour cities? wars keen edge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108650">Hath furrowed through their entrails, let them blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108660">In every artery that maintaineth life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108670">Yet will not dread her danger to be near? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108680">But warm her at their fires, sing at their sighs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108690">Revelling in her countless vanities,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108700">As a perpetual date were set thereon. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108710">Tell me I say, you that have seen all this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108720">And as devils, saints in the black calendar</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108730">Of wretchedst woe may truly be set down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108740">As authors of these sad confusions? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108750">Do not you deem that state well worth the ills,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108760">That this remissness brought upon the rest? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108770" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108780">They cannot but confess so much count Egmont. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108790" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Eg,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108800">If this be granted what's your glory then? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108810">An armed man to kill an naked soul:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108820">A thousand sickles thrust into a field,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108830">Of summer ripened and resistless corn:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108840">A mighty tide to overrun a land;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108850">Where no defence or bank to keep it back ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108860"><pb facs="12"/> this is your honour, this their misery,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108870">That are not conquered, but die wilfully. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108880" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108890">War taketh hold on all advantages. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108900" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108910">What need advantage, where is no resist? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108920" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108930">So much the better, this is our discipline,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108940">Therefore submit or die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108950" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108960">Not while I have a hand to lift my sword. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108970" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e108980">Nor you count Egmont? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e108990" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109000">Alva, nor I.</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109010">Egmont will with honour both live and die. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e109020">The alarum again, and champagne is pursued in by Romero, Verdugo and Van end, where he is slain: so is the Marquess hawrie, and all engirting count Egmont, Alva steps to defend him, and they strike at him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109030" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109040">Hold when I bid ye; strike ye all at me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109050" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109060">Why stands thou then to guard an enemy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109070" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109080">Because I will, honour incites me to it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109090">The honour of this worthy nobleman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109100">And his high spirit even in the face of death. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109110">Yield thee brave Egmont, Alva doth entreat thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109120">In pity of thy bold adventurous youth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109130">And hopeful fortunes shining in thine eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109140">Thou seest these slain, yet will save thy life:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109150">Thou seest me wounded to preserve thy life. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109160">I that was never pitiful before,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109170">Am forced to pity thee, what wouldst thou more? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109180" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109190">Such pity Alva, as thou show'dst my father,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109200">And noble horn, such thou intendest to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109210">Therefore proceed and never pity me. They offer at him again</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109220" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109230">Strike not I chargeve: come Egmont come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109240">Is wear that thou shalt yield; strike, spare me not,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109250">Alas thou art too faint; come, yield thee now,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e109260">Striving to g●t again his weapons</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109270">I'faith I will not hurt thee: so, have done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109280">Nay, no more weapons, thou art my prisoner. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109290"><pb facs="13"/>And I will use thee very honourably. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109300" who="A06270-egmont">
          <speaker>Egm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109310">Alva, let forth my life, and then thou honourst me</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109320" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109330">Not for the world, prisoner thou shalt to Spain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109340">And there be entertained to thy deserts. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109350">Now pity, pack from Alua's heart again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109360">Against my nature once I looked on thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109370">For this Count's sake: now to the deserts fly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109380">For havoc, spoil and murder now I cry. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e109390">Exeunt</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e109400">Champaigns wife hurried by two rascal solders.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109410" who="A06270-lady">
          <speaker>Lady</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109420">Have mercy on a woman I beseech you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109430">As you are men and soldiers:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109440">If you be Christians do not do me shame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109450" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 sold</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109460">Search her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109470" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109480">'Zounds turn her inside outward. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109490" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109500">Ransack her, every part of her. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e109510">Enter stump.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109520" who="A06270-lady">
          <speaker>Lady</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109530">For manhood spare me. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e109540">They stand to search her.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109550" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>St●m.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109560">How nimbly death bestirs him everywhere ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109570">And I that am a weary of my life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109580">And would fain die I cannot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109590">Death is so proud he will not look on me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109600">These muddy rogues that hoarded up their coin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109610">Now have their throats cut for the coin they have:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109620">They that for two pence would have seen me starve,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109630">And still my old rotten stump and I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109640">Trot up and down as long as we can wag. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e109650">They begin to strip her.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109660" who="A06270-lady">
          <speaker>Lady</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109670">As you are men ▪ be merciful to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109680" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109690">Cast lots who shall have her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109700" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109710">I'll give thee my share for thy part. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109720" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109730">I'll have my share in her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109740" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109750">Off with her jewels</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109760" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109770">How now, two soldiers ransacking a woman? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109780"><pb facs="13"/>O 'tis Champaigns wife that was the governor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109790">Here is she, that would not have been seen</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109800">With a moth upon her, for a thousand pound;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109810">That spent as much on monkeys, dogs and parrots,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109820">As would have kept ten soldiers all the year. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109830">Zblood I have seen her, where I have passed by her</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109840">In the streets, to stop her nose with her sweet gloves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109850">For fear my smell should have infected her;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109860">And now I live to see her lugged, and torn</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109870">By lousy tottered rogues: oh Antwerp, Antwerp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109880">Now madam Marchpane, minx, your blows</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109890">And you are one. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109900" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109910">Let's have her in the next corner. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109920" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109930">Draw her along,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109940" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109950">Take that she has it is sufficient,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109960">But go no further, it is inhuman to abuse a woman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109970" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e109980">What rogue art thou, dar'st speak unto a Spaniard? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e109990" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stumpe.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110000">No rogue sir, but a soldier as you are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110010">And have had one leg more than I have now. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e110020">Pointing to his leg.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110030">Sir, here's my passport, I have known the wars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110040">And have had the vantage of as fair a spoil as you have here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110050" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110060">Away you whoreson cripple rascal. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110070" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110080">You tottered shake-ragged rogues, what domineer you? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110090">If Dalva's self were here, he should not do it. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e110100">He draws his sword, kills one, and the other flies.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110110" who="A06270-lady">
          <speaker>Lady</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110120">Good soldier, here's one jewel that they have not</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110130">That I do value at a thousand crowns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110140">I pray thee take it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110150" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110160">What should I do with it, can you tell? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110170">To have my throat cut for it, ha:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110180">No, no your sister mince-pies groat</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110190">Will do me no pleasure now. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110200" who="A06270-lady">
          <speaker>Lady</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110210">For god's love, as you ever did respect a woman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110220">Help to convey me to some place of safety. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110230" who="A06270-stump">
          <pb facs="14"/>
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110240">Where is it? not in Antwerp. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110250">Your closet will not serve your turn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110260">You cannot walk to your garden-house. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110270" who="A06270-lady">
          <speaker>Lady</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110280">For god's sake help me as you are a man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110290" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stump.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110300">Well, follow me, I'll do the best I can. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e110310">A company of rascal soldiers came here pursuing the lady, he fights and bears her away from them all.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e110320">After a triumphant shout within, enter Alva, Danila, Romero, Verdugo, Van end, with their rapiers drawn, crying.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110330" who="A06270-all">
          <speaker>All.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110340">Victory, victory, Antwerp and victory. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110350" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110360">So valiant lords, this music likes me well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110370">Now may we boldly say the town is ours:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110380">Yet sheath not your victorious swords awhile,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110390">Till you have reaped the harvest of your pain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110400">In which pursuit, torture, exact and kill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110410">No less than in your fury you have done. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110420">If the proud antwerpers (That do survive)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110430">Lay not their treasure at your conquering feet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110440" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110450">Though no resistance anywhere appear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110460">Yet let not anger so decline with you</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110470">Be proud of victory, as well ye may,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110480">Knowing the worth of your attained prize. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110490">'Tis wealthy Antwerp you have won, and how? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110500">Not by a lingering siege, of months or years,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110510">But in a moment; entering at a leaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110520">By two o'clock her haughty pride is shrunk,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110530">And she in duty stoopeth to your will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110540" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110550">Can any here report the certain number,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110560">Of those that have been slain during the conflict? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110570" who="A06270-romero">
          <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110580">I had a note my lord, as I remember,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110590">The number of the dead, by us cut off,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110600"><pb facs="14"/> is seventeen thousand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110610" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110620">But of our men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110630">How many fell there in this short assault? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110640" who="A06270-romero">
          <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110650">Three hundred, or not many more my lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110660" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alua.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110670">For those three hundred, let ten thousand more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110680">Of this subiected city lose their lives,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110690">Chain them together in the market place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110700">By hundreds and two hundreds ▪ and with shot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110710">Ring them about until they all be slain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110720">Spare neither widow, matron, not young maid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110730">Gray-bearded fathers, nor the babe that sucks. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110740">One Spaniard's blood, I value better worth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110750">Than many hundreds of these drunken Dutch. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110760" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110770">First, if it please ye, quarter we the town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110780">That every one may know his privilege. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110790" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110800">Well thought upon Verdugo: thus it shall be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110810">The burse, the statehouse, and the market place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110820">Belongs to me: the castle and that side,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110830">To sancto Danila: on the other hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110840">The key, and water-port (Verdugo) is yours. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110850">Saint George's port, and Kibdop, we assign</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110860">To lord Romeso: and for you Van end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110870">The North part of the city, Venus' street,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110880">Remains the subject of desired spoil:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110890">So lords, if I have well divided, speak;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110900">If not, you shall be pleased before we part? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110910" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110920">Your lordship hath discreetly cast our lots,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110930">And for my part, I do accept of mine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110940" who="A06270-romero">
          <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110950">So doth Romero. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110960" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110970">And Verdugo too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e110980" who="A06270-van_end">
          <speaker>Van.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e110990">And I no less, than who is best content. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111000" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111010">About it then, be every one as quick,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111020">In rifling of these rich burghers, as he was</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111030">In the assault: the world may talk of us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111040">As well for valour as our quick dispatch. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111050" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Da.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111060">My soldiers and myself will straight begin. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e111070">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111080" who="A06270-romero">
          <pb facs="15"/>
          <speaker>Rom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111090">And mine shall follow. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e111100">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111110" who="A06270-cornelius">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111120">I'll not be behind. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e111130">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111140" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alua.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111150">What will Verdugo? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e111160">Enter English governor and Godfry. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111170" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111180">Not be idle long,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111190">But who are these so sawcily intrude? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111200" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alua.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111210">Who are ye? speak, that like unbidden guests,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111220">Dare tempt the patience of incensed Alva? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111230" who="A06270-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111240">We are of England (Castile's general) </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111250" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111260">Of England are ye● what although you be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111270">Back slaves unto the door from whence ye came,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111280">And on your knees solicit Alua's greatness:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111290">If you do look for mercy at his hands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111300" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111310">Back when he bids you; now down upon your knees,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111320">And crawl unto his presence to beg life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111330" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111340">Verdugo, drag him by the long tailed beard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111350">Alva doth scorn to wait upon their leisure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111360" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ve.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111370">Come forward with a pox; now speak your mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111380">And speak discreetly, lest you speak your last. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111390" who="A06270-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111400">This cruelty is more than we deserve,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111410">And more than we expected would be shown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111420" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111430">Tax ye me then with cruelty so soon? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111440">You shall have cause. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e111450">Offer to strike ▪</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111460" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111470">Nay hear them speak my lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111480" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Al.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111490">What can they say to shield themselves from death? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111500" who="A06270-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111510">Nothing my lord if in your angry spleen</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111520">You have already passed your sentence on us:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111530">But would the Duke of Alva cool his rage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111540">And mildly hear us: we would say my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111550">That England's league with Spain, King Phillip's word,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111560">Passed to our gracious mistress, were enough</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111570">To warrant all the lives of any such,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111580">As are her subjects in this wretched town:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111590">And not their lives alone, but safe protection</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111600">Both for their goods and money: but if now</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111610"><pb facs="15"/> your highness hath commission to break</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111620">The holy contract which your King hath made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111630">We must be patient and abide the worst. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111640" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Al.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111650">Why what art thou that standst upon the league? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111660" who="A06270-godfrey">
          <speaker>Go.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111670">Governor (My lord) of the English house. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111680" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Al.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111690">Sirrah, you challenge the virtue of the league,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111700">Yet understand not how the league is made. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111710">So long as you converse not with the foes</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111720">Of royal Philip, nor withstand his right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111730">You are exempt the rigour of his scourge;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111740">But being here, in this rebellious town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111750">You must partake the punishment they feel. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111760" who="A06270-godfrey">
          <speaker>Go.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111770">We are not here great lord, to join with them</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111780">In any bold confederacy of war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111790">But for the traffic, which all nations else,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111800">(As well as England) have within this place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111810" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111820">Why left ye not the city then, perceiving</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111830">We meant to call their duty to account? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111840" who="A06270-godfrey">
          <speaker>Go.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111850">We had no sign of any such intent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111860" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Al.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111870">You cannot so be quit nor so excused,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111880">Therefore provide before tomorrow night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111890">To bring unto us forty thousand crowns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111900">For ransom of your house; or if you fail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111910">Both goods and lives shall all be forfeited:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111920">So much we are content to yield unto,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111930">Because we will not seem to break the league. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111940" who="A06270-godfrey">
          <speaker>Go.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111950">Alas my lord, 'tis more than (At this time)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111960">Our goods and money will amount unto,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111970">Considering that our credit (By this trouble)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e111980">Is quite cut off, with any of the city. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e111990" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112000">Shift as you can, I vow to have no less,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112010">And at the appointed time. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e112020">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112030" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112040">Consider of it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112050">His favour's great in giving you such scope. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e112060">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112070" who="A06270-godfrey">
          <speaker>Go.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112080">So is the cat that dallieth with the mouse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112090">But in the end, her pastime is his death;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112100"><pb facs="16"/> we must provide, the Spaniards thirst is great,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112110">And better that we quench it with our gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112120">Than let them swallow and carouse our bloods:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112130">I prithee Godfrey try thy friends abroad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112140">And any money that thou hast bring forth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112150">That we may make the sum which he desires. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112160" who="A06270-godfrey">
          <speaker>God.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112170">I'll do the best I can, though hard it be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112180">To find a friend in this extremity. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e112190">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e112200">Enter Sancto Danila, an old citizen and soldiers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112210" who="A06270-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112220">Let not your rough entreaty so molest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112230">The soul of him whose spirit already stoops,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112240">Under the heavy burden of weak age;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112250">You have my treasure, what more can you crave? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112260" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112270">Thy 〈◊〉 so we please: there yet remains</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112280">A jewel of more worth than all thy wealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112290">Which (Like a 〈◊〉) thou didst hide from us.</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112300">Thou hast a daughter, whom till we enjoy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112310">All 〈…〉 proceeds from us, sits here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112320">〈…〉 point of my scimitar;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112330">〈…〉 speak? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112340">〈…〉 in this tumult. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112350">What 〈…〉 than her grave my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112360">Can be 〈◊〉 she hath? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112370" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112380">Torture the slave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112390">His guileful heart, that studies to conceal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112400">My dear heart's treasure, shall be forced in sighs</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112410">To publish, what his stubborn tongue denies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112420" who="A06270-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112430">Thou hearst old fellow, trifle then no longer,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112440">But show him where thy daughter doth abide. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112450" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112460">Why pause ye on my bidding let him die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112470">That doubles with a Spaniard in his will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112480" who="A06270-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112490">Hear ye my lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112500" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112510">Not any whispering noise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112520">Not any tittle, doth not bear the sound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112530"><pb facs="16"/> of beauty's sweet fruition to mine ears. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112540" who="A06270-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112550">My daughter lives, but not within the reach</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112560">Of my command: a nunnery in the arms</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112570">Of her religious peaceful privilege,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112580">Doth clip her silly frighted virgin's life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112590">From whence my lord she cannot be recalled. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112600" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112610">Bear art upon thy tongue, that may unlock</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112620">The gates of that in closed sanctuary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112630">And first entreat; but if entreaty fail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112640">Then use command; if neither will prevail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112650">Yet so thou shalt not cease, but in the cords</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112660">Of violent fury drag the damsel thence:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112670">My soldiers shall attend to see it done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112680">That if, thou shrink, their weapons naked points,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112690">May gorge thy sides, till thou bleed out thy life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112700" who="A06270-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112710">I would that sacrifice might end this strife. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112720" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Da.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112730">Away with him love faints through cold delay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112740">'Tis Danila speaks, and what he will he may. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e112750">Enter factor.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112760">Of whence are you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112770" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112780">Of England noble lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112790">A factor to a London merchant here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112800">Who having tried my friends, and strained my purse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112810">To make my ransom: am now carrying it</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112820">To mighty Alva, to redeem my life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112830" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112840">What value is it? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112850" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112860">Full five hundred dollars. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112870" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112880">Is this the utmost penny thou canst make? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112890" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112900">The length and depth of my ability. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112910" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112920">It will not serve to search thy chest for more</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112930">Or bide the torture we impose on such,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112940">As cunningly, withhold what we demand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112950" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112960">There is not in the world (That I may call</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112970">Rightly mine own) one stiver or one do●te,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e112980">More than is there comprised within th●● bag. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e112990" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113000">Give him the strappado; 〈…〉</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113010"><pb facs="17"/> out of your disjointed limbs other sums. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113020" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113030">The world doth know, my conscience and just heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113040">That there is all (At this time) I possess. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113050" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113060">Save what is thrown into some hollow vault,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113070">Or sunk into some well; or buried deep</l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e113080">Hoist him up and let him down again.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113090">Within the earth: so hoist the peasant up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113100">Now let him down; will ye confess as yet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113110">Where we may find the treasure you have hid? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113120" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113130">That which (My lord) is not, cannot be hid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113140">And to say that I know not, will but wrong</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113150">Your expectation, and deceive myself. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113160" who="A06270-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113170">Let him rest my lord, it seems the wretch</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113180">Argues the troth, and this is all he hath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113190" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113200">Hence greedy beggar, hark (Peeled sheep)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113210">Go hide thee in some bush, till waxing hours</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113220">Give thee another fleece to clothe thee with. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113230">Yonder ariseth the bright morning star. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e113240">Enter an old citizen with his daughter.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113250">Whose rich resplendour gilds my happy thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113260">And opens mines of treasure to my soul;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113270">Welcome fair sweet, mine arms shall be thy throne,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113280">Where seated once, mock death, and laugh to scorn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113290">The boisterous threats, of blood besprinkled war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113300">Who whilst he shows wild frisco's in the streets,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113310">And with his gambols, overthrows huge buildings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113320">Mingle their tottered ruins, with the limbs</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113330">And clotted blood of many thousand souls:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113340">Shall as an antic in thy sight appear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113350">Yielding no more occasion to be feared,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113360">Than painted shapes of lions on a wall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113370" who="A06270-unassigned">
          <speaker>Daug.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113380">Behold a virgin, whose distilling tears</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113390">Turn the dry dust to paste, where she doth kneel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113400">Behold the silver cognisance of age,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113410"><pb facs="17"/> soiled with dissolving drops of sorrows rage:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113420">If me you touch with a lascivious hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113430">As from his eyes descends a flood of tears;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113440">So will you draw a river from his heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113450">Of his life's blood; both ways you shall obscure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113460">The honour of your name: if virgin I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113470">Or aged he, misdo by tyranny. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113480" who="A06270-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113490">Let conquest satisfy, since in the strength</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113500">Of your successful power, our city vails,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113510">And lies in prostrate duty at your feet:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113520">Or if not conquest, be appeased with gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113530">Which in abundance pleads for our release,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113540">Only refrain, our conscience to wound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113550">With that, for which there is no physic found. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113560" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113570">I am impatient, she shall be my love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113580">Of all the spoils are reaped by painful war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113590">Blot beauty out, and what's our victory? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113600">But as a banquet without company. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e113610">Alarum.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e113620">Enter a soldier.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113630" who="A06270-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113640">Arm you my lord, and to the fight again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113650">A crew of straggling soldiers (Lately vanquished)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113660">Have gathered head, and in the heat of rage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113670">Give fresh assault: the leader to the rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113680">Is a lame fellow that doth want a leg,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113690">Who lays about him like a devil of hell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113700" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113710">A troop of musket's guard this damsel hence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113720">And to my lodging see her safely brought,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e113730">Alarum again</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113740">Why stir ye not? environ her with shot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113750">Whilst we extinguish (With a shower of blood)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113760">This late enkindled fire: be gone I say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113770" who="A06270-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113780">It is impossible to pass the streets,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113790">They are so pestered with this brainsick 〈◊〉:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113800">And hark my lord, except you mount be time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113810">(The clamorous tumult draws so near this place,)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113820"><pb facs="18"/> both you and we shall be surprised by them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113830" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Da.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113840">Is there no fortress near, nor house of strength,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113850">Where I may leave my love, till this black cloud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113860">Of swollen hostility be overblown? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113870" who="A06270-soldier">
          <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113880">Not any (Good my lord) lead on your troops. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113890" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113900">Then rather than another shall enjoy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113910">What Danila held esteemed in his eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113920">Here it began, and here my love shall die. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e113930">Shoots her with a pistol.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113940">Another stab her father, both combined,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e113950">By nature's laws, by nature's law shall end. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e113960">Exeunt</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e113970">Stab the old man.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e113980">Enter lieutenant Vaughan and captain.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e113990" who="A06270-vaughan">
          <speaker>Vaugh.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114000">Yet is not Antwerp quite bereft of life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114010">So long as we two breath, to stand for her,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114020">Nor shall her ransack pass, without some right</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114030">Of just revenge: witness this last assault,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114040">Wherein the scales of justice have been filled,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114050">With (At the least) a hundred Spaniards lives,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114060">That thought their victory to be secure. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114070">But who are these? A burger, and with him</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114080">His tender daughter, having both sustained</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114090">The heavy stroke of death? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114100" who="A06270-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114110">I knew them well. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114120">They were my neighbours, ne●re unto the burf. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114130" who="A06270-vaughan">
          <speaker>Vau.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114140">Had these grey hairs retained the reverent worth</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114150">Of grave experience, as they might have done;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114160">And had you been more rich in inward gifts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114170">And less magnificent in outward show,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114180">Then had you lived, to die a natural death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114190">And you to see some of his honoured years. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114200">But pride and luxury, have ever been,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114210">The gate of misery, and nurse of sin:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114220">Yet though you me contemned, I grieve your fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114230">And will in pity, give you burial. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e114240">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e114250"><pb facs="18"/>Enter Lenchy and Martin two little children running.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114260" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114270">Alas poor Lenchy, whether shall we go:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114280" who="A06270-lenchy">
          <speaker>Len.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114290">I cannot tell; come Martin let us hide us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114300" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114310">Where is my father? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114320" who="A06270-lenchy">
          <speaker>Len.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114330">He is in our house. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114340" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114350">Let us go thither? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114360" who="A06270-lenchy">
          <speaker>Len.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114370">All the street is full of Spaniards; they have killed</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114380">Little Maria, and Hans Vanderbrooke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114390" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114400">Ah whither shall we go? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114410" who="A06270-lenchy">
          <speaker>Len.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114420">Let's hide us here, no Spaniard will come hither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114430" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114440">Nay m. Hulder's orchard is hard by. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114450">We'll get in there, and hide's among the trees,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114460" who="A06270-lenchy">
          <speaker>Len.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114470">Come let us run. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e114480">A great noise as they are going.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114490" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114500">Alas the Spaniard's coming, what shall we do? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114510" who="A06270-lenchy">
          <speaker>Len.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114520">Alas poor Martin we shall both be killed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114530" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114540">Alas poor Lenchy, kiss me pretty sister,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114550">Now we must die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114560" who="A06270-lenchy">
          <speaker>Len.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114570">Let's sit down here, and mart. I will clip thee in</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114580">Mine arms, they shall not see thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114590" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114600">But they will kill thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114610">Alas where is my poor old father now, and my poor mother? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e114620">Enter two Spaniards running, with their swords drawn.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114630" who="A06270-spaniard">
          <speaker>1 Spa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114640">Kill, kill, kill. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114650" who="A06270-2_spaniard">
          <speaker>2 spa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114660">Tue, tue, tue, tue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114670" who="A06270-1_spaniard">
          <speaker>1 Spa,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114680">Fuora villiaco. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114690" who="A06270-2_spaniard">
          <speaker>2 spa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114700">Follow, follow, follow, follow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114710" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114720">I pray you m. Spaniard hurt us not,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114730">We are poor children, we have done no harm. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114740" who="A06270-lenchy">
          <speaker>Len.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114750">Good gaffer do not kill my little brother. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114760" who="A06270-spaniard">
          <speaker>1 Spa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114770">Fuora villiaco, sa, sa, sa, sa,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114780" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114790">Ah master Spaniard do not kill my sister,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114800">My father is a poor blind man, and he will die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114810"><pb facs="19"/> if you kill her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114820" who="A06270-2_spaniard">
          <speaker>2 spa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114830">Cut the bastard's throats. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e114840">The children gets fast hold, and hang upon the Spaniards.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114850" who="A06270-lenchy">
          <speaker>Len.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114860">O kill us not, we'll hang upon your arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114870">Sweet gaffer, stay and look me in the face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114880">Have you the heart to kill a pretty girl? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114890" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114900">Good master Spaniard do not kill us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114910">Take any thing we have, but save our lives. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114920" who="A06270-spaniard">
          <speaker>1 Spa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114930">How the young brats cling about our swords? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114940" who="A06270-2_spaniard">
          <speaker>2 spa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114950">Zounds, dash out their brains. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e114960">Enter old blind Harman and his wife.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e114970" who="A06270-harman">
          <speaker>Har.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114980">Where are my children? Martin, Lenchy speak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e114990">I heard you cry speak pretty souls, where are you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115000" who="A06270-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115010">Husband, Harman, whether will you go? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115020">Alas you fall into the enemy's hands</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115030">For lack of sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115040" who="A06270-harman">
          <speaker>Har.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115050">My children wife, my children, where are they? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115060" who="A06270-spaniard">
          <speaker>1 Spa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115070">Here you blind traitor, whether you shall go,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115080">To your throat-cutting. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115090" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115100">Here father, here, alas we shall be killed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115110" who="A06270-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115120">O my sweet children,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115130" who="A06270-2_spaniard">
          <speaker>2 Sp.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115140">Out you Brabant bitch, think you with whining</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115150">To preserve your whelps? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115160" who="A06270-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115170">O spare the infants ▪ and the aged blind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115180">These have not might, nor power to do you hurt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115190" who="A06270-spaniard">
          <speaker>1 Spa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115200">Cut all their throats. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115210" who="A06270-harman">
          <speaker>Har.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115220">Kill us, but let our little children live. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115230" who="A06270-lenchy">
          <speaker>Len.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115240">Help mother help, or else we shall be killed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115250" who="A06270-harman">
          <speaker>Har. weeping.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115260">Hard hearted soldiers, where have you been bred? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115270">Get honour on the proud resisting foe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115280">Myself have been a soldier as you are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115290">Now blind with age:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115300">Old men, weak women, and poor wretched infants,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115310">Should be respected in the heat of slaughter. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115320"><pb facs="19"/>O do not this foul injury to arms;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115330">Let my poor babies lead me to my grave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115340">Where are you my poor children? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115350" who="A06270-martin">
          <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115360">Father, here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115370" who="A06270-harman">
          <speaker>Har.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115380">Where art thou lenchy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115390" who="A06270-lenchy">
          <speaker>Len.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115400">Here poor father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115410" who="A06270-harman">
          <speaker>Har.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115420">Old as I am, and I have told this town;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115430">That you should sack it, I did prophesy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115440" who="A06270-2_spaniard">
          <speaker>2 spa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115450">Then prophet, didst thou prophesy of this? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e115460">Stabs the children.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115470" who="A06270-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115480">Ah bloody Spaniard, that hast slain my children. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115490" who="A06270-spaniard">
          <speaker>1 Spa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115500">Bitch, art thou railing? take thou this. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e115510">Stabs her.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115520" who="A06270-2_spaniard">
          <speaker>2 spa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115530">And this,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e115540">Stabs him.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115550">Get you together with your damned brats. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115560" who="A06270-harman">
          <speaker>Har.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115570">O cruel Spaniard that dost spare no age nor sex,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115580">Where art thou wife, and my poor little children? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e115590">Falls down.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115600" who="A06270-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115610">Their blessed souls in Abraham's bosom rests,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115620">Their bodies lie betwixt thyself and me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115630">By whom these pretty wretches were begotten,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115640">Oh let me join my freezing lips to thine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115650">Now farewell Antwerp, say not we did fly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115660">Where with thy fall, old, young, and all must die. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e115670">Enter Alva, English governor and soldiers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115680" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alua.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115690">Think ye to purchase freedom at this rate? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115700">Some thriftless prodigal bestows in wine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115710">Or spends in dalliance on his courtesan,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115720">Five thousand crowns: 〈◊〉 like your store affords</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115730">No greater plenty ▪ either from your chests,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115740">That swell with surfeit of your avarice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115750">Rain down a larger shower of fruitful gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115760">Or tender flowering pity, ne'er will spring. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115770" who="A06270-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115780">I do protest (My lord) beside our plate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115790">And household furniture, this is the sum,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115800"><pb facs="20"/> of all the wealth, at this time may be found</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115810">Within the english-house. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115820" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115830">And is not plate</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115840">Good boot for soldiers? have you that</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115850">And dare ye yet plead needy poverty? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115860">Go fetch it me, or presently I'll send</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115870">A crew of such sharp carvers to your gate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115880">As shall anatomize your panting hearts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115890">To fill their conquering hands with wished spoils. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115900" who="A06270-godfrey">
          <speaker>Go.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115910">The league with Engl. gave us better hope. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e115920">Exit</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e115930" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115940">Talk nor of league nor England, nothing sound</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115950">In our wars music, that can please the sense;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115960">Unless it have the cheerful sound of gold. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e115970">Enter factor.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115980">What's he? examine him: if he bring gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e115990">Free passage have he; but if empty be</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116000">The hollows of his hands; or cannot point</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116010">By demonstration, or express by speech,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116020">Where it is fled, in this tempestuous storm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116030">That we by hugging it, may banish fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116040">And burnish her pale cheeks with firmer red,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116050">Let him have that belongs, the torturing cord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116060" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116070">Excuse my want, that have already paid</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116080">To sancto Danila, five hundred dollars. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116090" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116100">Why not as much to me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116110" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116120">I have it not,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116130">Alas (My lord) consider of my state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116140">I am but factor for another man;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116150">Yet of those goods committed to my charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116160">Have I made bold (So much as I have said)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116170">To free my life from further prejudice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116180" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116190">How art thou free, when Alva is not fee'd? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116200" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116210">I hope (My lord) one ransom will suffice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116220">For one poor life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116230" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116240">That ransom let me see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116250" who="A06270-factor">
          <pb facs="20"/>
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116260">'Tis paid (My lord) to sancto Danila. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116270" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116280">That which he hath is his, and none of mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116290">Unless thou canst transform us, and of two</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116300">Make but one person: go to, trifle not,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116310">But show me how I may be satisfied,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116320">Or bide the peril that ensues thereon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116330" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116340">More satisfaction than I have (My lord)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116350">I cannot give, howe'er you torture me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116360" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116370">That will we try, if rope and gibbet hold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116380">Let him endure the punishment, he needs</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116390">Will wilfully impose upon himself. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116400" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116410">O that you would at once with ruthless steel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116420">Carve up my breast, and let my blood suffice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116430">To quench your thirst for that I cannot give. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116440" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116450">So, let him down, stand off and give him air,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116460">Speak now, and tell us where thy coin is hid? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116470" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116480">Will ye believe me if I speak the truth? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116490" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116500">So it be truth which thou intends to speak. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116510" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116520">As I do hope this troubled soul of mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116530">Which now is ready to forsake this flesh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116540">Shall find a resting place with my redeemer:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116550">The coin you seek, and all the coin I have,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116560">Lies in the coffers of proud Danila. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116570" who="A06270-alva">
          <speaker>Alu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116580">Lie there and pine then, for deluding me. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e116590">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e116600">Enter Verdugo.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116610" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116620">Here comes another; many strokes (At last)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116630">Cut down the strongest oak, much more, the tree</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116640">Hath but a few years growth, and that by storms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116650">And often whirlwinds shaken and decayed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116660" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116670">Hast thou been lately fallen into the hands</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116680">Of such as have had ryfling of thy purse? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116690" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116700">I have good sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116710" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116720">What art, a citizen? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116730" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116740">Even what ye will, a miserable man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116750" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116760">It seems, I come too late to profit by thee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116770" who="A06270-factor">
          <pb facs="21"/>
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116780">You may imagine by my sick faint speech,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116790">And by my faltring limbs distract and severed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116800">Whether I have been tortured, yea or no. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116810" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ve.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116820">Did they then torture thee for that thou hadst? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116830" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116840">They did and had it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116850" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116860">Nothing then remains? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116870" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116880">Nothing but this poor miserable life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116890">Which I would gladly were surrendered too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116900" who="A06270-verdugo">
          <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116910">They for that thou hadst, did torture thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116920">I see that thou hast not: here we'll put</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116930">A period to thy days. Hang him outright,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116940">And so speed all, whose naked indigence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116950">Have not to feed Verdugo for expense. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e116960">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e116970" who="A06270-factor">
          <speaker>Factor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116980">My destiny, was to die this shameful death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e116990">Which I accept with thanks to him that gives it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117000">And England now and London both farewell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117010">Let after times of Spanish rigour tell. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e117020">Hang him.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e117030">Enter van end and a burgher's wife.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117040" who="A06270-van_end">
          <speaker>Van.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117050">Thus will I feast myself with Antwerp's spoil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117060">And glut my pining soul with tragic acts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117070">Say pampered froe, where is thy treasure hid? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117080">Speak truth, or breathe thy last upon this steel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117090">The bloody tempered torment of this town. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117100">I'll batter down your pride from whence it came,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117110">And with your ornaments adorn vast hell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117120" who="A06270-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117130">Spare me van end I am a harmless woman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117140">Astonished unto death with frighting words,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117150">Refrain thy deeds, and let the stronger sort,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117160">Be miserable patients of thy wrath</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117170" who="A06270-van_end">
          <speaker>Van.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117180">Pity prevails not, treasure is the fee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117190">That bribes the terror of my threatening breast;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117200">And therefore speak, else hast thou spoke thy last. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117210" who="A06270-wife">
          <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117220">Within that vault lies all my wretched wealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117230">My gold my plate, my jewels all are there. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117240" who="A06270-van_end">
          <pb facs="21"/>
          <speaker>Van.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117250">Then, there that heap of glory lies for me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117260">Which is the way? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e117270">She pushes him down.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117280" who="A06270-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117290">That is the cursed way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117300">Go thou accursed into that shade of hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117310">The image of that everlasting night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117320">Where thy damned ghost must dwell exempt from light. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e117330">Enter stump.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117340" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117350">What stir is here? what discontented rumor</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117360">Sends second message to my dull struck days,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117370">Accustomed to the screeching yell of death? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117380">Lady, what grievance? what is there to do? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117390" who="A06270-wife">
          <speaker>Wife</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117400">O gentle soldier, heaven hath got me triumph,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117410">Over that hellborn fury, damned van end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117420">That sold the beauty of this famous town:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117430">And ravished Antwerp of her maiden joy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117440" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117450">For god's sake let me come plague the dog,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117460">I'll stone the Jew to death, and paint this vault</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117470">With the unhallowed blood of wicked treason:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117480">Here, wear this weighty jewel in thy hat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117490">The town hath sent it for a token slave;</l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e117500">Throw stones.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117510">I bought this with the goat you gave me sir;</l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e117520">Another sto.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117530">Soldier's must loathe despised ingratitude. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117540">This woman for her ransom sends you this;</l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e117550">Another.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117560">Give these two unto Charon for your passing. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e117570">Another.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117580">And with this last, present grim Belzebub. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e117590">Another.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117600">So sleep thy soul with princely Lucifer,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117610">And take such fare as treason will afford. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117620">Come lady, thus you see good friends must part,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117630">Lament not for his loss his time was come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117640">And friends from friends, must either go or run. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e117650">Enter three or four soldiers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117660" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117670">You see that all is lost, all spoiled and sacked,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117680"><pb facs="22"/> what think you the best course to get away? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117690" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117700">Is there no place of strength, nor hope of safety ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117710" who="A06270-3_soldier">
          <speaker>3 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117720">No hope but death for three days being passed</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117730">Since the first entered; now being in cold blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117740">The Spaniard is as hot in execution,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117750">As the first hour he entered on the town. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117760" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117770">Like maimed men let's pass out one by one,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117780">The safest way and with the least suspect. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117790" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117800">Dissevering of ourselves, and known for</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117810">Walloons, there's not a man of us shall pass the gates. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e117820">Enter stump and hearing them.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117830" who="A06270-3_soldier">
          <speaker>3 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117840">And if we troop thus as we do together,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117850">We shall be put to sword immediately. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117860" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117870">It were best to seek some low part of the wall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117880">On the moat side, and so escape by swimming. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117890" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117900">The courts of guard, and sentinels are kept,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e117910">And there's no hope of that. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117920" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stumpe.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e117930">Hark you hark you, whether will you fly? I would know that; 'sblood whither? whether? ha; where will you be relieved? there's not a town dare receive you: the Spaniard has all the country; you cannot straggle a foot out of the walls, but your throats are cut; what have you to carry with you, but your scurvy notched limbs? you damned rogues, whether will you go, to feed wolves? A you whoreson rascals; and though these villanos burghers have (By their own security been the destruction of the city, a pox on them: yet it will be laid to our charge, because we were in it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117940" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e117950">By the mass the old lieutenant says true, it will be so indeed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117960" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e117970">You are all Walloons, but in the miserablest case that ever poor slaves were in: for you see, that if any man hate a man, call him but Wallon, the Spaniards cut his throat, what countryman soe'er he be ▪</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e117980" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e117990">Nay it is very true, it is most sure:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118000" who="A06270-stump">
          <pb facs="22"/>
          <speaker>Stu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118010">The Dutch on the other side, they hate you worse than devils, because the Spaniards entered where you kept the trenches.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118020" who="A06270-3_soldier">
          <speaker>3 soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118030">Villains do questionless, nay it is certain.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118040" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118050">What will you do then? here is my poor stump and I have stumbled through a thousand shot, and yet we halt together; there was never one poor piece of timber has been so singed as it has been: 'sblood it has been four times a fire under me, and yet we scramble together trotting, trotting: you'll be starved every mothers son of ye, and worried with dogs, and yet you'll fly.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118060" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118070">Why lieutenant Vaughan, what would ye have us do?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118080" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118090">Die like men, what should we do, if there were any hope of safety but there is not, there is not.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118100" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118110">Lieutenant Vaughan, lead us, and we'll follow you to the death.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118120" who="A06270-3_soldier">
          <speaker>3 soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118130">We'll not forsake you to the last gasp.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118140" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118150">Yes, I'll halt before you, follow me as straight as you can ▪</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118160" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118170">Yes, and cut some of their throats before we die.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118180" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118190">They say the Spaniards and their whores are at dice upon the change: I'll lay my wooden leg afore them, cast at it who will; but who stands there?</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e118200">Enter the captain.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118210" who="A06270-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118220">It is lieutenant Vaughan as I take it, lieutenant what news?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118230" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>S●um.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118240">What news quoth our captain! where have you been?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118250" who="A06270-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118260">I took the friary to escape the Spaniards.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118270" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>S●um.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118280">Well, have seen the day captain, you 〈◊〉 rather been a cutting throats, then at a mass, 'twas not devotion<pb facs="23"/> drave you to the place: so captain, captain, the world is turned: do you remember the groat they offered me, when you came to train soldiers? ha, give him a groat? ha, ha, I have since that seen their mistress's 〈…〉 by a lousy lackey, as naked as a new shaved water-dog: and lord why went you to the friary? why to the friary?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118290" who="A06270-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118300">What should I do when the poor Walloons fighting at the trenches,</p>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118310">The Spaniards entering on the counterscarp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118320">Had not a soldier sent to second them. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118330">The great swollen bellied burghers get brown bills,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118340">As to drive rascal beggars from their doors;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118350">The madding people so amazed with fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118360">That turning head with every little noise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118370">Stopped up the entrance of the streets with throngs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118380">That when count Egmont, Hawry and the rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118390">Called to the burghers for supplies of men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118400">The uncertain murmur of the multitude,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118410">Increased but the confusion of the town:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118420">The villainous and dastard recreant Almains,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118430">Kneel to the Spaniards, casting down their arms. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118440" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A06270-e118450">A those Almains, those Almains, they cried live Spaniards: a vengeance take them, they were called high Almains, but they are low enough now; for a number of them are cut off by the waste: you may call them blanched Almains and you will, for their guts are blanched about their heels.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118460" who="A06270-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118470">By these disorders of witless townsmen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118480">Perceiving that the Spaniards would prevail;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118490">What should I do but shift to save my life? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118500" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118510">Captain. your life's in as great danger now as ere it was,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118520">The Spaniard is as cruel in cold blood as ere he was;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118530">Oh captain, captain, where is Antwerp now? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118540">It 〈◊〉 my native place, where should I then be free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118550">If made a slave, where I was freely born? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118560"><pb facs="23"/>There's not a town almost in Brabant now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118570">That gives a man the safety of a night:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118580">What should we then do living:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118590">Have you and I seen that, that we have seen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118600">And come to this? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118610">If you reserve the courage you were wont,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118620">Of a brave soldier and a gentleman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118630">Let's do something yet worthy the talking of,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118640">I have won a company of poor hurt soldiers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118650">Yet able to wield weapons and to fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118660" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118670">And we will follow you, live or die:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118680" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118690">Love life and love death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118700" who="A06270-3_soldier">
          <speaker>3 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118710">Through Alva's quarter. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118720" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118730">Why bravely spoke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118740">If you will take such part then as we do,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118750">Help me to lead these straggling companies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118760">And we'll amongst their quarters ere we die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118770" who="A06270-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118780">My hand and heart, and do engage my soul. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118790" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118800">Why then come lads; why this is resolved like men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118810">If we must go, we'll go together then. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e118820">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e118830">Enter two soldiers leading in the fat Burger in a Cord.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118840" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118850">Confess ye slave where thou hast hid thy money,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118860">Or we will hang thee on a gibbet straight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118870" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118880">That ever I was born; gentlemen believe me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118890">I have no more than what I told you of,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118900">Some thousand gilders in my counting house. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118910" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118920">You have no more than? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118930" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Burg.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118940">Not as I have faith</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118950">To God, and to the safety of my country. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118960" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118970">Then hang him presently. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e118980" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e118990">Nay courteous gentlemen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119000">As you are Spaniards famous for your acts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119010">Let me not die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119020" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119030">The rogue would flatter us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119040"><pb facs="24"/> S●●ra, imagine 'tis too weak a key,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119050">To tune our hearts to; when the cries of babes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119060">Screeks of distressed women and old men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119070">Have not prevailed to qualify our rage:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119080">Let us dispatch him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119090" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119100">Gentlemen, but hear me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119110" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119120">If thou canst tell us where thy treasure's hid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119130">Or else for ever let thy lips be dumb. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119140" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119150">Alas would ye have me lie? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119160" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119170">Stay fellow soldier,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119180">I have bethought me of a pretty trick,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119190">To sift this butterbox a better way:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119200">We will tie him by the thumbs unto this post,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119210">And tickle him until he do confess. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119220" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119230">Content i'faith, so at the least, suppose</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119240">We get no money yet we shall have sport. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119250" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119260">Nay gentlemen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119270" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119280">Sirrah, apply your wits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119290">Or with my sword I'll hack your filchers off. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119300" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119310">O that I were in'th bottom of my seller. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119320" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119330">Is thy money hidden there? speak? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119340" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119350">No truly sir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119360">But then I hope I should not hang byth' thumbs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119370" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119380">He dallies with us, tickle him a good. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119390" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119400">O God, God, what shall I do, sweet gentlemen. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e119410">They tickle him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119420" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119430">Confess then, sirrah. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119440" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119450">O lord I shall sound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119460">By these ten ends, I have nor plate nor coin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119470">Your general and countrymen have all. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e119480">Alarum, enter stump and captain, the Spaniards fly.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119490" who="A06270-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119500">What 〈◊〉 we here, a burger tied byth' thumbs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119510" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119520">It is the tallow-cake, the rammish fat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119530">That would not give a penny to a soldier,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119540"><pb facs="24"/> I know him well; now sir how feel yourself ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119550" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119560">O gentlemen never so much distressed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119570" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119580">Your greasy paunch will not defend you then? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119590" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119600">Not from these Spaniards, they 〈…〉 think,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119610">Nay far more covetous than devils of hell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119620" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119630">You cannot satisfy them with a groat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119640">But if I should requite thy vild contempt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119650">Here should I leave thee, that as thy treasure</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119660">Has been a prey to their devouring lust,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119670">So in this dunghill of thy carrion flesh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119680">Their ravenous swords might find a dirty feast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119690">For naught but draff art thou composed of. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119700">Nor fit for any thing but to feed worms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119710">Yet thou shalt find a difference twixt my thoughts</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119720">And the base temper of thy muddy mind:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119730">Go live, if thou canst scape their bloody hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119740">Till want and beggary cut short thy days. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119750" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119760">I thank you sir; I have (For all their threats)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119770">One bag of dollars cast into a well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119780">And that I'll give ye for this friendly succour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119790" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119800">Hence tumbril from my sight, when bounty might</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119810">Have calmed my sharp affliction than thy hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119820">Was fast closed up; but now it is too late,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119830">Thou wouldst seem prodigal, away base churl. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119840" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119850">Let me entreat you sir, to take that sum,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119860">My heart repents me much, for what is passed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119870" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119880">Guts, trouble me no more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119890" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119900">The lord preserve you sir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119910">Surely you seem an honest gentleman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119920" who="A06270-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119930">Wilt thou leave off thy prating and be gone? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119940" who="A06270-burgher">
          <speaker>Bur.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119950">With all my heart sir, and I thank you too. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A06270-e119960">Exit</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e119970" who="A06270-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119980">How like Leviathan, his clumsy limbs</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e119990">Walk not but tumble, that sad common wealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120000">Nurseth such drones to suck her honey up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120010">In time of need shall find as small supply,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120020">As he hath been to Antwerp's wretchedness:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120030"><pb facs="25"/> but valiant soldier, what is now to do? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e120040" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120050">What, but to hunt the footsteps of pale death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120060">Until we rouse him in his sooty cave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120070">There, will no prospect of our countries fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120080">Offend our eyesight; there no treachery</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120090">Of haughty Spaniards tread a bloody march;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120100">Nor any base objection of ingrate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120110">And thankless citizens sit in our doors:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120120">But we shall quietly enjoy the peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120130">For which we breathe; there shall we be secure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120140">There free from thought of this world's misery,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120150">And there indeed find true felicity:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120160">For there our travel shall be recompensed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120170">Our love requited, and our wounds repaid</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120180">With double merit. Haste then unto the place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120190">Upon the earth is nothing but disgrace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e120200" who="A06270-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120210">I fly with thee true honourable mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120220">And we together will that mansion find. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e120230">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e120240">Alarum and excursions, enter stump and captain, bloody and wounded.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e120250" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120260">See captain, now I have it on my breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120270">The honourable cognisance of death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120280">This purple river, from this weeping fount,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120290">More glads and quickens my decayed spirit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120300">Than ever Christ all spring in heat of summer:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120310">The weary traveller, his strength revives,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120320">To draw out tedious hours still on earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120330">But mine doth flourish to possess, anon</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120340">The blessed haven of eternity. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e120350" who="A06270-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120360">I trust I shall be there with as much speed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120370">My passport (I do think) the Spaniards</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120380">Has sealed as deeply, and my journey laid</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120390">With no less easy travel to be there. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120400">See, if thy bleeding wounds can speak to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120410"><pb facs="25"/> mine can as fast make answer unto thine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e120420" who="A06270-stump">
          <speaker>Stum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120430">Let me embrace this sweet affinity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120440">Like in our lives agreeing in our deaths:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120450">But what do I behold? thine eyelids faint,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120460">And the warm touch of thy desired cheek,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120470">Begins to freeze; wilt thou anticipate</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120480">Those joys before me? gentle captain slay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120490">There's but a minute that divides our hopes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120500">O he is dead, may his departing soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120510">Usher my spirit above those fleeting clouds:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120520">Death, why delayest thou? set thy lazy hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120530">To the divorcement of my loathed flesh. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120540">I am prepared, my penitent sad thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120550">Have long ago washed my contagious sin:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120560">The blood that I have spilt (The massacres</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120570">Procured and practised by this hand of mine)</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120580">Heaven lay not to my charge; for though my sword</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120590">Was never drawn but in a rightful cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120600">Yet much misprision hath attended it;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120610">That, and all else, this sigh craves pardon for,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120620">Mine eyes were near accustomed to tears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120630">Let it suffice, these wounds do weep for them:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120640">Antwerp farewell, if thou have done me wrong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120650">This latest gasp, sends pardon from my tongue. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e120660">Astorish.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e120670">Enter in triumph, with drum, colours and soldiers, Sancto Danila. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e120680" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120690">Now war hath wrapped his bloody colours up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120700">And sheathed his fatal sword with his, we ours,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120710">Prefixing truce to our laborious arms;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120720">This city late of christening the fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120730">For wealth and glory: now remains the map,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120740">〈◊〉 destruction and perpetual ruin;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120750">〈…〉 with slaughtered carcases,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120760">〈…〉 before were stuffed with pride,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120770">An left as 〈…〉:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120780"><pb facs="26"/> o in remorse of human clemency,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120790">My heart (Not thinks) could sigh, my eyes shed tears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120800">To call to mind and see their misery:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120810">But they were wanton and lascivious,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120820">Too much addicted to their private lust:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120830">And that concludes their martyrdom was just. </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120840">Hold, one of you, convey this serious letter</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120850">To warlike Alva, tell him as he willed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120860">After my forces lodged in garrison,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120870">I'll meet his grace at bridges, and from thence</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120880">Acquaint the court of Spain with our success;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120890">Pray God the tyranny expressed in Antwerp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120900">Like to the echoing clamour of a trumpet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120910">Speak not our deeds before our own approach. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e120920" who="A06270-soldier_1">
          <speaker>1 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120930">My lord, behold where lie the mangled bodies</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120940">Of those two fierce assailing Brabanters,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120950">That all this while kept us at such a bay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120960">And when we thought the town was won, procured</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120970">So great a deluge of Iberian blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e120980" who="A06270-soldier_2">
          <speaker>2 soldier</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e120990">Let's drag them at our horses tails my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121000">And as we pass through every town and village,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121010">Make them example to the world for pride? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e121020" who="A06270-danila">
          <speaker>Dan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121030">Who toucheth them but in disgrace, my sword</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121040">Shall lop his arm off ▪ were they proud sayst thou? </l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121050">Their pride was honourable, deserving love</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121060">Rather than hate; nay should we do them right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121070">Had they been strengthened with convenient aid</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121080">We had been beaten from the town again</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121090">And made exchange of conquest: which subdued</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121100">There never lived two 〈◊〉 heroieth spirits</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121110">That for their country have deserved as much</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121120">To be renowned; as ever 〈◊〉 was</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121130">Or Roman 〈◊〉 or the 〈…〉</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121140">They for their 〈◊〉 could but lose their lives</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121150">These have inequal service done as much</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121160">Take up their bodies; of ten thousand others</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121170"><pb facs="26"/> rest by our swords, and left unburied</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121180">These two will we in person see interred,</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121190">And do them right, the law of arms requires;</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121200">So march we hence, striking a mournful sound</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121210">Till we have said our honoured foes in ground</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e121220">Exeunt</stage>
      </div>
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="A06270-e121230">
        <head>Epilogus</head>
        <stage xml:id="A06270-e121240">Enter time</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A06270-e121250" who="A06270-time">
          <speaker>Time</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121260">Thus worldlings, time in his unwonted love</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121270">Hath stayed his course, to rub the memory</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121280">Of actions long since cast behind his back</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121290">His care is fruitful, and doth wish to see</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121300">No heavy or disastrous chance befall</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121310">The sons of men if they will warned be</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121320">But when they 〈◊〉 against my discipline</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121330">Wasting the treasure of my precious hour</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121340">No marvel then, like misery catch hold</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121350">On them, did fasten o this woeful town</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121360">Whose bleeding fortune, whose lamenting 〈◊〉</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121370">Whose streets besmeared with blood, whose blubbered eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121380">Whose tottered walls, whose buildings overthrown</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121390">Whose riches lost, and poverty made known:</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121400">May be a mean all cities to affright</l>
          <l xml:id="A06270-e121410">How they in sin and pleasure take delight</l>
        </sp>
        <trailer xml:id="A06270-e121420">Finis</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A06270"><item xml:id="A06270-danila" n="48">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-danila</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">48</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-alva" n="36">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-alva</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">36</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-stump" n="34">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-stump</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">34</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-burgher" n="31">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-burgher</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">31</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-martin" n="28">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-martin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">28</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-champaigne" n="25">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-champaigne</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">25</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-factor" n="21">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-factor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">21</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-soldier_1" n="20">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-soldier_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">20</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A06270-soldier_2" n="17">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-soldier_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">17</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-egmont" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-egmont</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-verdugo" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-verdugo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-captain" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-captain</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-van_end" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-van_end</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-lenchy" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-lenchy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-wife" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-wife</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-cornelius" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-cornelius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-1_citizen" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-1_citizen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-2_citizen" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-2_citizen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-2_spaniard" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-2_spaniard</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-godfrey" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-godfrey</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-harman" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-harman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-3_citizen" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-3_citizen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-lady" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-lady</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-soldier" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-soldier</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-spaniard" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-spaniard</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-burgher_1" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-burgher_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-citizen" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-citizen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-romero" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-romero</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-3_soldier" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-3_soldier</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-governor" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-governor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-gunner" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-gunner</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-english_governor" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-english_governor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-2_wife" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-2_wife</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-burgher_2" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-burgher_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-vaughan" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-vaughan</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-1_burgher" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-1_burgher</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-2_burgher" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-2_burgher</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-unassigned" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-all" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-1_wife" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-1_wife</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-1_spaniard" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-1_spaniard</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-time" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-time</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A06270-marquis" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A06270-marquis</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

