<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A69121">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Clyomon and Clamydes <date type="creation_date">1599</date></title>
        <author>Peele, George</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A69121.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The historie of the tvvo valiant knights, Syr Clyomon Knight of the Golden Sheeld, sonne to the King of Denmarke: and Clamydes the white Knight, sonne to the King of Suauia As it hath bene sundry times acted by her Maiesties Players.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2008 September (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">AUA7872</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 5450a</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 157</idno>
            <idno type="vid">10869</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69121</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The historie of the tvvo valiant knights, Syr Clyomon Knight of the Golden Sheeld, sonne to the King of Denmarke: and Clamydes the white Knight, sonne to the King of Suauia As it hath bene sundry times acted by her Maiesties Players.</title>
            <title type="alt">Historie of the two valiant knights, Syr Clyomon Knight of the Golden Sheeld, sonne to the King of Denmarke: and Clamydes the white Knight, sonne to the King of Suavia</title>
            <title type="alt">Historie of Clyomon Knight of the golden Sheeld.</title>
            <title type="alt">Sir Clyomon and Sir Clamydes.</title>
            <title type="alt">Historie of the two valiant knights, Syr Clyomon Knight of the Golden Sheeld, sonne to the King of Denmarke: and Clamydes the white Knight, sonne to the King of Suavia.</title>
            <author>Peele, George, 1556-1596,</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[68] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by Thomas Creede,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1599.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Erroneously attributed to George Peele.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-HÛp4Ûs IÛp2Ûs .</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: The historie of Clyomon Knight of the golden Sheeld.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Identified as STC 19538 on UMI microfilm reel 348.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproductions of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Appears at reel 348 ± and reel 1022 #5 (same copy filmed twice).</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A69121-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A69121-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A69121-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A69121-e100040">The history of the two valiant knights, sir Clyomon knight of the golden shield, son to the King of Denmark:</p>
        <p xml:id="A69121-e100050">And Clamydes the white knight, son to the King of Suavia. </p>
        <p xml:id="A69121-e100060">As it hath been sundry times acted by her majesty's players.</p>
        <p xml:id="A69121-e100070">
          <figure xml:id="A69121-e100080">
            <p xml:id="A69121-e100090">Viressit wlnere veritas</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="A69121-e100100">London printed by Thomas creed. 1599.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="A69121-e100110">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>The prologue.</head>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100120">As lately lifting up the leaves of worthy writers works,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100130">Wherein the noble acts and deeds of many hidden lurks,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100140">Our author he hath found the glass of glory shining bright,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100150">Wherein their lives are to be seen, which honour did delight,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100160">To be a lantern unto those which daily do desire,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100170">Apollo's garland by desert, in time for to aspire,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100180">Wherein the froward chances oft, of fortune you shall see,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100190">Wherein the cheerful countenance, of good successes be:</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100200">Wherein true lovers findeth joy, with hugy heaps of care,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100210">Wherein as well as famous facts 〈◊〉 placed are:</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100220">Wherein the just reward of both, is manifestly shown,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100230">That virtue from the root of vice, might openly be known. </l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100240">And doubting naught right courteous all, in your accustomed wont</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100250">And gentle ears, our author he, is pressed to bide the brunt</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100260">Of babblers tongues, to whom he thinks, as frustrate all his toil,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100270">As peerless taste to filthy swine, which in the mire doth moil. </l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100280">Well, what he hath done for your delight, he gave not me in charge,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e100290">The actors come, who shall express the same to you at large. </l>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A69121-e100300">
      <div type="text" xml:id="A69121-e100310">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>The history of sir clyomon knight of the golden shield, son to the King of Denmark: and Clamydes the white knight, son to the King of Swavia.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e100320">Enter Clamydes.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e100330" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100340">As to the weary wand'ring wights, whom waltering waves 〈◊〉,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100350">No greater joy of joys may be, then when from out the ocean</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100360">They may behold the altitude of billows to abate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100370">For to observe the longitude of seas in former rate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100380">And having then the latitude of sea-room for to pass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100390">Their joy is greater through the grief, then erst before it was. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100400">So likewise I Clamydes, prince of Swavia noble soil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100410">Bringing my bark to Denmark here, to bide the bitter broil:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100420">And beating blows of billows high, while raging storms did last,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100430">My griefs was greater than might be, but tempests overpast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100440">Such gentle calms ensued hath, as makes my joys more</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100450">Through terror of the former fear, than erst it was before. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100460">So that I sit in safety, as seaman under shrouds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100470">When he perceives the storms be passed, through vanquishing of clouds. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100480">For why, the doubtful care that drave me off, in danger to prevail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100490">Is dashed through bearing lesser brain, and keeping under sail:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100500">So that I have through travel long, at last possessed the place</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100510">Whereas my bark in harbour safe, doth pleasures great embrace:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100520">And hath such licence limited, as heart can seem to ask,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100530">To go and come, of custom free, or any other task. </l>
          <pb facs="3"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100540">I mean by Juliana she, that blaze of beauties breeding,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100550">And for her noble gifts of grace, all other dames exceeding:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100560">She hath from bondage set me free, and freed, yet still bound</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100570">To her, above all other dames that lives upon the ground:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100580">For had not she been merciful, my ship had rushed on rocks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100590">And so decayed amids the storms, through force of clubbish knocks:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100600">But when she saw the danger great, where subject I did stand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100610">In bringing of my silly bark, full fraught from out my land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100620">She like a meek and modest dame, what should I else say more? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100630">Did me permit with full consent, to land upon her shore:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100640">Upon true promise that I would, here faithful still remain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100650">And that perform which she had vowed, for those that should obtain</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100660">Her princely person to possess, which thing to know I stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100670">And then adventurously for her, to pass upon my way. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100680">Lo where she comes, ah peerless dame, my Juliana dear. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e100690">Enter Juliana with a white shield.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e100700" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Juliana.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100710">My Clamydes, of troth sir prince, to make you stay thus here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100720">I proffer too much injury, that's doubtless on my part,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100730">But let it no occasion give, to breed within your heart</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100740">Mistrust that I should forge or feign, with you my love in ought. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e100750" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100760">No lady, touching you, in me doth lodge no such a thought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100770">But thanks for your great courtesy that would so friendly here</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100780">In mids of misery receive, a foreign stranger mere:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100790">But lady say, what is your will, that it I may perstand? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e100800" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100810">Sir prince, upon a vow, who spouseth me, must needsly take in hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100820">The flying serpent for to slay, which in the forest is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100830">That of strange marvels beareth name, which serpent doth not miss</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100840">By daily use from every coast, that is adjacent there,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100850">To fetch a virgin maid or wife, or else some lady fair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100860">To feed his hungry paunch withal, if case he can them take,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100870">His nature lo it only is, of women spoil to make:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100880">Which thing no doubt, did daunt me much, and made me vow indeed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100890">Who should espouse me for his wife, should bring to me his head:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100900">Whereto my father willingly, did give his like consent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100910">Lo sir Clamydes, now you know what is my whole intent:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100920">And if you will as I have said, for me this travel take,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100930">That I am yours, with heart and mind, your full account do make. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e100940" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <pb facs="3"/>
          <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100950">Ah lady, if case these travels should surmount, the travels whereby came</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100960">Unto the worthies of the world, such noble brute and fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100970">Yea though the dangers should surpass stout Hercules his toil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100980">Who fearing naught the dogged fiend, stern Serbarus did foil. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e100990">Take here my hand, if life and limb the living gods do lend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101000">To purchase thee, the dearest drop of blood my heart shall spend. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101010">And therefore lady link with me, thy loyal heart for aye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101020">For I am thine till fates untwine, of vital life the stay:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101030">Protesting here if gods assist, the serpent for to kill. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101040" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Juli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101050">Then shalt thou of all women win, the heart and great good will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101060">And me possess for spouse wife, who in election am</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101070">To have the crown of Denmark here, as heir unto the same. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101080">For why, no children hath my fire besides me, but one other,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101090">And he indeed is heir before, for that he is my brother. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101100">And Clyomon so hight his name, but where he doth remain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101110">Unto my parents is unknown, for once he did obtain</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101120">Their good wills for to go abroad, a while to spend his days,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101130">In purchasing through active deeds, both honour, laud and praise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101140">Whereby he might deserve to have the order of a knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101150">But this omitting unto thee, Clamydes here I plight</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101160">My faith and troth, if what is said by me thou dost perform. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101170" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101180">If not, be sure oh lady with my life, I never will return. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101190" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Juli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101200">Then as thou seemest in thine attire, a virgin's knight to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101210">Take thou this shield likewise of white, and bear thy name by me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101220">The white knight of the silver shield, to elevate thy praise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101230" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101240">O lady as your pleasure is, I shall at all assays</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101250">Endeavour my good will to win, if Mars do send me might,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101260">Such honour as your grace with joy, shall welcome home your knight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101270" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Juli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101280">Then farewell my dear Clamydes, the gods direct thy way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101290">And grant that with the serpent's head, behold thy face I may. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e101300">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101310" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101320">You shall not need to doubt thereof, oh faithful dame so true,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101330">And humbly kissing here thy hand, I bid thy grace adieu. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101340">Ah happy time and blissful day, wherein by fate I find</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101350">Such friendly favours as is food, to feed both heart and mind:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101360">To Suavia soil I swiftly will prepare my footsteps right,</l>
          <pb facs="4"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101370">There of my father to receive the order of a knight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101380">And afterwards address myself in hope of honour's crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101390">Both tiger fell and monster fierce, by dint for to drive down. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101400">The flying serpent soon shall feel, how boldly I dare vaunt me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101410">And if that Hydra's head she had, yet dread should never daunt me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101420">If murdering minotaur, a man might count this ugly beast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101430">Yet for to win a lady such, I do account it lest</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101440">Of travels toil to take in hand, and therefore farewell care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101450">For hope of honour sends me forth, amongst warlike wights to share. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e101460">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e101470">Enter sir Clyomon knight of the golden shield, son to the King of Denmark, with subtle Shift the vice, booted.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101480" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101490">Come on good fellow follow me, that I may understand</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101500">Of whence thou art, thus travelling here in a foreign land:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101510">Come why dost thou not leave loitering there, and follow after me ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101520" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101530">Ah I am in an't shall please you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101540" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101550">In, why where art thou in? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101560" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101570">Faith in a dirty ditch with a woman, so berayed, as it's pity to see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101580" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101590">Well, I see thou art a merry cōpanion, I shall like better of thy company:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101600">But I pray thee come away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101610" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101620">If I get out one of my legs as fast as I may</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101630">Ha lo, a my buttock, the very foundation thereof doth break,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101640">Ha lo, once again, I am as fast, as though I had frozen here a week. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e101650">Here let him slip unto the stage backwards, as though he had pulled his leg out of the mire, one boot off, and rise up to run in again.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101660" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101670">Why how now, whither runnest thou, art thou foolish in thy mind</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101680" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shi.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101690">But to fetch one of my legs an't shall please, that I have left in the mire behind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101700" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101710">One of thy legs, why look man, both thy legs thou hast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101720">It is but one of thy boots thou hast lost, thy labour thou dost waste. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101730" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101740">But one of my boots, Jesu, I had such a wrench with the fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101750">That I assure, I did think one of my legs had gone withal. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101760" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101770">Well let that pass, and tell me what thou art, and what is thy name? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101780">And from whence thou cam'st, and whither thy journey thou dost frame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101790">That I have met thee by the way, thus travelling in this sort? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101800" who="A69121-shift">
          <pb facs="4"/>
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101810">What you have requested, an't shall please, I am able to report,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101820">What I am by my nature each wight shall perceive</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101830">That frequenteth my company, by the learning I have. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101840">I am the son of Apollo, and from his high seat I came,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101850">But whither I go, it skills not, for knowledge is my name:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101860">And who so hath knowledge, what needs he to care</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101870">Which way the wind blow, his way to prepare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101880" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Cly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101890">And art thou knowledge, of troth I am glad that I have met with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101900" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101910">I am knowledge, and have as good skill in a woman as any man whatsoever he be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101920">For this I am certain of let me but lie with her all night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101930">And I'll tell you in the morning, whither she is maid, wife, or spright:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101940">And as for other matters, speaking of languishes, or any other thing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101950">I am able to serve an't shall please, an't were great Alexander the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101960" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101970">Of troth, then for thy excellency ▪ I will thee gladly entertain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e101980">If in case that with me thou wilt promise to remain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e101990" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102000">Nay an't shall please ye, I am like to a woman, say nay and take it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102010">When a gentleman proffers entertainment, I were a fool to forsake it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e102020" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102030">Well knowledge, then sith thou art content my servant to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102040">And endued with noble qualities, thy personage I see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102050">Thou having perfect knowledge, how thyself to behave:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102060">I will send thee of mine arrant, but haste thither I crave:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102070">For here I will stay thy coming again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e102080" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102090">Declare your pleasure sir, and whither I shall go, and then the case is plain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e102100" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102110">Nay of no great importance, but being here in Suania</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102120">And near unto the court, I would have thee to take thy way</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102130">Thither with all speed, because I would hear</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102140">If any shows or triumphs be towards, else would I not come there,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102150">For only upon feats of arms, is all my delight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e102160" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102170">If I had known so much before, serve that serve will, I would have served no martial knight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102180">Well sir, to accomplish your will, to the court I will by,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102190">And what news is there stirring, bring word by and by. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e102200">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e102210" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102220">Do so good knowledge, and here in place thy coming I will stay:</l>
          <pb facs="5"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102230">For nothing doth delight me more ▪ then to hear of martial play,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102240">Can food unto the hungry corpse, because of greater joy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102250">Then for the haughty heart to hear, which doth itself employ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102260">Through martial exercises much to win the brute of fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102270">Where mates do meet which there unto their fancies seems to frames:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102280">Can music more the pensive heart or daunted mind delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102290">Can comfort more the careful corpse and over palled spright,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102300">Rejoice then sound of trumpet doth each warlike wight allure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102310">And drum and fife unto the fight doth noble hearts procure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102320">To see in sunder shivered, the lance that leads the way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102330">And worthy knights unbeaver, in field amid the fray,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102340">To hear the rattling cannons roar, and Hyles on helmets ring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102350">To see the soldier's swarm on heaps, where valiant hearts doth bring</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102360">The cowardly crew into the case of careful captives band,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102370">Where ancients brave displayed be, and won by force of hand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102380">What wight would not as well delight as this to hear and see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102390">Betake himself in like affairs a fellow mate to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102400">With Clyomon to Denmark King the only son and heir. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102410">Who of the golden shield as now, the knightly name doth bear</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102420">In every land since that I foiled the worthy knight of fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102430">Sir Samuel before the King, and prince of martial game. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102440">Alexander called the great, which when he did behold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102450">He gave to me in recompense, this shield of glittering gold:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102460">Requesting for to know my name, the which shall not be shown</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102470">To any kite, unless by force he make it to be known. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102480">For so I vowed to Denmark King, my father's grace when I</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102490">First got his leave, that I abroad my force and strength might try. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102500">And so I have myself behaved, in city, town and field,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102510">That never yet did fall reproach, to the knight of the golden shield. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e102520">Enter subtill Shift, running. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e102530" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102540">God's ames, where are you, where are you? and you be a man come away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e102550" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clya.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102560">Why what is the matter knowledge to tell thy errand stay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e102570" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102580">Stay, what talk you of staying, why then all the sight will be passed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102590">Clamides the King's son shall be dubbed knight in all haste. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e102600" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102610">Ah knowledge, then come indeed, and good pastime thou shalt see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102620">For I will take the honour from him, that dubbed I may be. </l>
          <pb facs="5"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102630">Upon a courageous stomach, come let us haste thither. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e102640">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e102650" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102660">Lead you the way and I'll follow, we'll be both made knights together,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102670">Ah sirrah, is my master so lusty, or dares he be so bold? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102680">It is no marvel then, if he bear a shield of gold. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102690">But by your patience if he continue in this business, farewell master than,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102700">For I promise you, I intend not very long to be his man:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102710">Although under the title of knowledge my name I do feign,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102720">Subtle shift I am called, that is most plain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102730">And as it is my name, so it is my nature also,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102740">To play the shifting knave wheresoever I go. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102750">Well, after him I will, but soft now, if my master chance to be lost</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102760">And any man examine me, in telling his name I am as wise as a post. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102770">What a villain was I, that ere he went, could not ask it? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102780">Well, it's no great matter, I am but half bound, I may serve whom I will yet. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e102790">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e102800">Enter the ring of Suauis with the herald before him: Clamydes, three lords.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e102810" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102820">Come Clamides thou our son, thy father's talk attend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102830">Since thou art pressed thy youthful days in prowess for to spend:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102840">And dost of us the order ask, of knighthood for to have,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102850">We know thy deeds deserves the same, and that which thou dost crave</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102860">Thou shalt possess: but first my son, know thou thy father's charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102870">And what to knighthood doth belong, thine honour to enlarge:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102880">Unto what end a knight is made, that likewise thou mayst know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102890">And bear the same in mind also, that honour thine may flow</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102900">Amongst the worthies of the world, to thy immortal fame:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102910">Know thou therefore Clamydes dear, to have a knightly name</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102920">Is first above all other things his god for to adore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102930">In truth according to the laws prescribe to him before. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102940">Secondly, that he be true unto his lord and King. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102950">Thirdly, that he keep his faith and troth in every thing. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102960">And then before all other things that else we can commend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102970">That he be always ready pressed, his country to defend:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102980">The widow poor, and fatherless, or innocent bearing blame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e102990">To see their cause redressed right, a faithful knight must frame:</l>
          <pb facs="6"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103000">In truth he always must be 〈…〉</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103010">That will receive a knightly name, his honour to enlarge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103020" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103030">O father this your gracious counsel given to me your only son,</l>
        </sp>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103040">Shall not be in oblivion cast 〈…〉 be run:</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103050">What way doth win dame honour's crown ▪ those paths any steps shall trace</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103060">And those that to reproach doth lead, which seeketh to deface</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103070">True honour in her regal seat ▪ I shall detest for aye,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103080">And be as utter enemy, to them both night and day ▪</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103090">By flying force of flickering fame ▪ 〈◊〉 grace shall understand ▪</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103100">Of my behaviour noble sire, in 〈…〉 lands</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103110">And if you hear by true report 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103120">Of wilfulness contrary this, your 〈…〉 charge:</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103130">Let ignomy to my reproach in steed of lady fame. </l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103140">Sound through the earth and azure skies the strained blast of shame. </l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103150">Whereby within oblivions tomb, my deeds shall be detained,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103160">Where otherwise of memory 〈◊〉 I might have gained. </l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103170">So that the den of darsomeness shall 〈…〉 my chest,</l>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103180">Where worthy deeds prefers each wight, with honour to be blessed. </l>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103190" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103200">Well 〈…〉 right,</l>
        </sp>
        <l xml:id="A69121-e103210">That here thou mayst receive of me the order of a knight. </l>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e103220">Here let 〈…〉 and us the King doth go about to lay the 〈…〉 Clyomon take the 〈…〉.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103230" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103240">Now prepare your self, or 〈…〉</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103250" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103260">Content thyself knowledge for i●● quickly 〈…〉. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103270" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103280">The noble orders of a knight, 〈…〉</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103290">We give through due 〈…〉 that thou be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103300">Both valiant, wise, and hardy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103310" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103320">Away now 〈…〉 be take ●ardie. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e103330">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103340" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103350">Ah stout attempt of 〈…〉 my son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103360">The knighthood 〈…〉</l>
          <pb facs="6"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103370">Ah Clamydes how art thou be rest of honour here? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103380">Was like presumption ever seen, that one a stranger mere,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103390">Should come in presence of a prince, and tempt as he hath done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103400">To take the knighthood thus away, from him who is his son? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103410" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103420">Ah father, how am I perplexed, till I revenged be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103430">Upon the wretch which here hath ta'en, the honour thus from me? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103440">Was ever any one deceived of knight hood so before? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103450" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103460">Well Clamydes, my lords return, stay till we do know more. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e103470">Enter Shift brought in by the two lords, who pursued Clyomon. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103480" who="A69121-1_lord">
          <speaker>1. Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103490">O King the knight is fled and gone, pursuit prevaileth naught,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103500">But here his slave we taken have, to tell why this he wrought. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103510" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103520">Ah cruel grudge that grieves my ghost, shall he escape me so ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103530">Shall he with honour from my son, without disturbance go? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103540">Ah caitiff thou, declare his name, and why he ventured here:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103550">Or death shall be thy 〈◊〉 sure, by all the gods I swear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103560" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103570">Ah 〈…〉 please you, I know neither 〈…〉 country nor name. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103580" who="A69121-2_lord">
          <speaker>2. Lord</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103590">What, what sir, are not you his servants will you deny the same ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103600" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103610">Nay then you are a dissembling knave, I know very well. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103620" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103630">An't shall please your grace, even the very troth I shall tell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103640">I should have been his servant when we met together;</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103650">Which was not full three hours before we came hither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103660" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103670">Well what is his name, and of what 〈…〉 ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103680" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103690">That cannot I tell 〈◊〉 shall please you, you never saw servant to such care:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103700">To know his master's name, neither in town nor field,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103710">And what he was he would tell, but the knight of the golden shield. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103720" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103730">Well Clamides mark my charge, what I to thee shall say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103740">Prepare thyself for to pursue that traitor on his way:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103750">Which hath thine honour reft from thee, and either by force of hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103760">Or love, his name and native soil, see that thou understand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103770">That I may know for what intent, he bore this grudge to thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103780">Else see thou never dost return again to visit me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103790">For this imports him for to be, of valiant heart and mind:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103800">And therefore do pursue thy foe, until thou dost him find. </l>
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103810">To know his name and what he is, or as I said before,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103820">Do never view thy father I, in presence any more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103830" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103840">Well father, sith it is your charge, and precept given to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103850">And more for mine own honour's sake, I frankly do agree</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103860">To undertake the enterprise, his name to understand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103870">Or never else to show my face again in Swavia land. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103880">Wherefore I humbly do desire, the order to receive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103890">Of knighthood, which my sole desire hath ever been to have:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103900">It is the name and mean, whereby true honour is achieved:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103910">Let me not then oh father dear, thereof be now deprived. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103920">Sith that mine honour cowardly was stolen by caitiff he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103930">And not by dinted dastards deed, oh father lost by me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103940" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103950">Well Clamydes, than kneel down, here in our nobles sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103960">We give to thee that art our son, the order of a knight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103970">But as thou wilt our favour win, accomplish my desire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e103980" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e103990">Else never to your royal court, oh father I'll retire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104000" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104010">Well, than adieu Clamides dear, the gods thine aider be:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104020">But come my lords, to have his hire, that caitiffe bring with me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104030" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104040">Alas not shall please you, I am knowledge, and no evil did pretend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104050">Set me at liberty, it was the knight that did offend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104060" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104070">O father, sith that he is knowledge, I beseech your grace set him free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104080">For in these affairs, he shall wait and tend on me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104090">If he will protest, to be true to me ever. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104100" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104110">Ah noble Clamydes, here's my hand, I'll deceive you never. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104120" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104130">Well then father, I beseech your grace grant that I may have him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104140" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104150">Well Clamydes, I am content, sith thou my son dost crave him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104160">Receive him therefore at my hands. My lords come let's depart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104170" who="A69121-all">
          <speaker>All.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104180">We ready are to wait on you oh King, with willing heart. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e104190">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104200" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104210">Well knowledge, do prepare thyself, for here I do protest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104220">My father's precepts to fulfil, no day nor night to rest</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104230">From toilsome travel, till I have revenged my cause aright,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104240">On him who of the golden shield, now beareth name of knight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104250">Who of mine honour hath me robbed, in such a cowardly sort,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104260">As for to be of noble heart, it doth him not import. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104270">But knowledge, to me thy service stall thou must with loyal heart profess. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104280" who="A69121-shift">
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104290">Use me that all other villains may take ensample by me, if I digress. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104300" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104310">Well then come follow speedily, that him pursue we may. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e104320">(Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104330" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104340">Keep you before an't shall please you, for I mind not to stay. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104350">Ah sirrah shift, thou wast driven to thy shifts now indeed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104360">I dreamt before, that untowardly I should speed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104370">And yet it is better luck than I looked to have:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104380">But as the proverb saith, good fortune ever happeneth to the veriest knave. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104390">And yet I could not escape with my master, do what I can,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104400">Well by this bargain he hath lost his new servingman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104410">But if Clamydes overtake him now, what buffets will there be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104420">Unless it be four miles off the fray, there will be no standing for me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104430">Well after him I will, but howsoever my master speed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104440">To shift for myself I am fully decreed. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e104450">(Exit.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e104460">Enter King Alexander the great, as valiantly set forth as may be, and as many soldiers as can.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104470" who="A69121-alexander">
          <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104480">After many invincible victories, and conquests great achieved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104490">I Alexander with sound of fame, in safety am arrived</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104500">Upon my borders long wished for, of Macedonia soil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104510">And all the world subject have, through force of warlike toil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104520">Oh Mars I laud thy sacred name, and for this safe return,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104530">To Pallas temple will I wend, and sacrifices burn</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104540">To thee, Bellona and the rest, that warlike wights do guide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104550">Who for King Alexander did, such good success provide. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104560">Who bows not now unto my beck, my force who doth not fear? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104570">Who doth not of my conquests great, throughout the world hear? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104580">What King as to his sovereign lord, doth now not bow his knee? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104590">What prince doth reign upon the earth, which yields not unto me</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104600">Due homage for his regal mace? What country is at liberty? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104610">What dukedom, island or province else, to me now are not tributary? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104620">What fort of force, or castle strong, have I not battered down? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104630">What prince is he, that now by me, his princely seat and crown</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104640">Doth not acknowledge for to hold, not one the world throughout,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104650">But of King Alexander's power they all do stand in doubt? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104660">They fear as fowls that hovering fly, from out the falcon's way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104670">As lamb the lion, so my power, the stoutest do obey. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104680">In field who hath not felt my force, where battering blows abound? </l>
          <pb facs="8"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104690">King or 〈◊〉, who hath not 〈◊〉 his knees to me on ground,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104700">And yet Alexander ▪ what art th●● thou art a mortal wight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104710">For all that ever thou hast got or won by force in fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104720" who="A69121-1_lord">
          <speaker>I. lo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104730">Acknowledging thy state o King, to be at thou hast said,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104740">The gods no doubt as they have been, will be thy shield and aid</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104750">In all attempts thou takest in hand, 〈◊〉 no glory vain</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104760">Thou seekest, but acknowledging thy victories and gain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104770">Through the providence of sacred gods to happen unto thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104780">For vain is trust, that in himself, man doth repose we see:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104790">And therefore least these victories which thou o King haste got,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104800">Should blind thine eyes with arrogancy thy, noble fame to blot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104810">Let that victorious prince his words, of Macedon thy fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104820">To acknowledge still thy state oh King, thy noble heart inspire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104830">Who after all his victories 〈…〉 obtained,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104840">Lest that the great felicity of that which she had gained,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104850">Should cause him to forget himself, 〈…〉 did provide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104860">Which came unto his chamber door, and every morning cried</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104870">Philip, thou art a mortal man, this practice of thy sire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104880">A midst all these thy victories, thy servant doth desire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104890">O Alexander that 〈…〉 print within thy mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104900">And then no doubt as father did, thou solace sweet shall find. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e104910" who="A69121-alexander">
          <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104920">My lords, your counsel doubtless I esteem, and with great thanks again ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104930">I do require 〈…〉 this is plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104940">All 〈…〉: and since the god's divine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104950">To us 〈…〉 this fortune doth assign,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104960">To have in our subjection the world for most part,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104970">We will at this 〈…〉, with fervent zeal of heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104980">In 〈…〉 gods, such sacrifices make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e104990">Of thankfulness for our success, as they in part shall take</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105000">The same, 〈…〉 from us sent:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105010">Come 〈…〉, to accomplish our intent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105020" who="A69121-omnes">
          <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105030">We 〈…〉 King, to follow thee with victory. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105040" who="A69121-alexander">
          <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105050">〈…〉 drums and trumpets both, that we may march triumphantly. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e105060">Exeunt.</stage>
        <pb facs="8"/>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e105070">Enter sir Clyomon, knight of G. S.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105080" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105090">Now Clyomon a knight thou art, though some perhaps may say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105100">Thou cowardly camest to Clamydes, and stole his right away:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105110">No, no, it was no cowardly part, to come in presence of a King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105120">And in the face of all his court, to do so worthy a thing. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105130">Amid the mates that martial be, and stern knights of his hall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105140">To take the knighthood from their prince, even mauger of them all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105150">It gives a guerdon of goodwill, to make my glory glance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105160">When warlike wights shall hear thereof, my fame they will advance:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105170">And where I was pretended late, to Denmark King my sire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105180">His royal grace to see, homeward to retire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105190">Now is my purpose altered by brute of late report. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105200">And where fame resteth to be had, thither Clyomon will resort:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105210">For as I understand by fame, that worthy prince of might,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105220">The conqueror of conquerors, who Alexander hight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105230">Returning is to Macedon, from many a bloody broil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105240">And there to keep his royal court, now after weary toil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105250">Which makes the mind of Clyomon, with joys to be clad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105260">For there I know of martial mates, is company to be had. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105270">Adieu therefore, both Denmark King and Suania prince beside,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105280">To Alexander's court I will, the gods my journey guide. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e105290">Enter Clamydes and Shift.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105300" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105310">Come knowledge here he is, nay stay thou cowardly knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105320">That like a dastard cam'st, to steal away my right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105330" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105340">What, what, you rail sir princocks prince, me coward for to call. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105350" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105360">An't shall please you he is a coward, he would have hired me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105370">Amid your father's hall. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105380">To have done it for him, being himself in such stay</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105390">That scarcely he durst, before your presence appear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105400" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105410">Why how now knowledge, what forsake thy master so soon? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105420" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105430">Nay master was, but not master is, with you I have done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105440" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105450">Well for what intent canst thou, my honour to steal away? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105460" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105470">That I took ought from thee, I utterly denay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105480" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105490">Didst not thou take the honour, which my father to me gave? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105500" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105510">Of that thou hadst not, I could thee not deprave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105520" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105530">Didst not thou take away my knighthood from me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105540" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105550">No, for I had it before it was given unto thee:</l>
          <pb facs="9"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105560">And having it before thee, what argument canst thou make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105570">That ever from thee the same I did take? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105580" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105590">That's true, he received the blow before at you it came,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105600">And therefore he took it not from you, because you had not the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105610" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105620">Well, what hight thy name, let me that understand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105630">And wherefore thou travailedst here in my father's land</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105640">So boldly to attempt in his court such a thing? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105650" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105660">The bolder the attempt is, more fame it doth bring:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105670">But what my name is desirest thou to know? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105680" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105690">Nay he hath stolen sheep I think, for he is ashamed his name for to show. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105700" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105710">What thy name is, I would gladly perstand:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105720" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105730">Nay that shall never none know, unless by force of hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105740">He vanquish me in fight, such a vow have I made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105750">And therefore to combat with me, thyself do persuade,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105760">If thou wilt know my name. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105770" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105780">Well, I accord to the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105790" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105800">Nay then God be with you, if you be at that point I am gone. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105810">If you be of the fighters disposition, I'll leave you alone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105820" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105830">Why stay knowledge, although I fight, thou shalt not be molested. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105840" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105850">An't shall please you, this fear hath made me bewray myself, with a proynstone that was not digested. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e105860" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105870">Well Clamydes stay thyself, and mark my sayings here:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105880">And do not think I speak this same, for that thy force I fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105890">But that more honour may redound, unto the victor's part,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105900">Wilt thou here give thy hand to me, withouten fraud of heart</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105910">Upon the faith which to a knight doth rightly appertain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105920">And by the loyalty of a knight, I'll swear to thee again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105930">For to observe my promise just, which is if thou agree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105940">The fifteenth day next following, to meet sir prince with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105950">Before King Alexander's grace, in Macedonia soil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105960">Who all the world subject hath, through force of warlike toil:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105970">For he is chief of chivalry, and King of martial mates,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105980">And to his royal court thou knowest, repair all estates. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e105990">Give me thy hand upon thy faith, of promise not to fail. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106000">And here is mine to thee again, if fortune's froward gale,</l>
          <pb facs="9"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106010">Resist me not, the day forespoke to meet sir prince with thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106020">Before that King to try our strengths, say if thou dost agree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106030">For triple honour will it be, to him that gets the victory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106040">Before so worthy a prince as he, and nobles all so publicly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106050">Where otherwise if in this place we should attempt the same,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106060">Of the honour that were got thereby, but small would be the fame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106070" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106080">Well sir knight, here is my hand, I'll meet in place forespoke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106090" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106100">And by the loyalty of a knight, I'll not my words revoke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106110" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106120">Till then adieu; I'll keep my day. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e106130">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106140" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106150">And I, if fates do not gainsay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106160" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106170">What is he gone, and did take no leave of me? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106180">Jesu so unmannerly a gentleman did any man see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106190">But now my lord which way will you travel declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106200" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106210">Sith I have fifteen days' respite myself to prepare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106220">My lady's charge for to fulfil, behold I do intend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106230" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106240">Your lady an't shall please you, why who is your lady, may a man be so bold as ask and not offend ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106250" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106260">Juliana daughter to the King of Denmark lo is she,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106270">Whose knight I am, and from her hands this shield was given to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106280">In sign and token of good will, whose noble grace to gain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106290">I have protested in her cause for to omit no pain</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106300">Nor travail, till I have subdued the flying serpent's force,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106310">Which in the forest of marvels is, who taketh no remorse</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106320">Of women kind, but doth devour all such as are a stray,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106330">So that no one dares go abroad, nor wander forth the way. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106340">And sith I have yet fifteen days, myself for to prepare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106350">To meet the knight of the golden shield, my heart is void of care. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106360">I will unto the forest wend, sith it is in my way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106370">And for my Juliana's sake, that cruel serpent slay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106380" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106390">What are you a mad man, will you wilfully be slain? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106400">If you go into that forest, you will never come out again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106410" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106420">Why so knowledge, dost thou think the serpent I fear? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106430" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106440">No, but do you not know of Bryan sance foy, the champion dwells there</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106450" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106460">A cowardly knight knowledge is he, and dares fight with no man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106470" who="A69121-shift">
          <pb facs="10"/>
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106480">Ah a noble match, couple him and me together than:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106490">Yea, but although he dares not fight, and enchanter he is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106500">And whosoever comes in that forest, to enchant he doth not miss. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106510" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106520">Tush, tush, I fear him not knowledge, and therefore come away. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e106530">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106540" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106550">Well seeing you are so wilful, go you before I'll not stay. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106560">Ah sirrah, now I know all my master's mind, the which I did not before,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106570">He adventureth for a lady, well I say no more:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106580">But to escape the enchantments of Bryan sans foy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106590">That's Bryan without faith, I have devised a noble toy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106600">For he and I am both of one consanguinity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106610">The veriest cowardly villain that ever was born, that's of a certainty. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106620">I'll fight with no man, no more will Bryan, that's plain:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106630">But by his enchantments, he putteth many to great pain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106640">And in a forest of strange marvels doth he keep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106650">Altogether by enchantments to bring men asleep ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106660">Till he have wrought his will of them, to Bryan straight will I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106670">And of my master's coming to the forest inform him privily,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106680">So shall I win his favour, and subtle shift in the end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106690">Thou shalt escape his enchantment, for he will be thy friend:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106700">Well unknown to my master, for mine own safeguard this will I do,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106710">And now like a subtle shifting knave, after him I'll go. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e106720">Exit:</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e106730">Enter Bryan sance foy.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e106740" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bry.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106750">Of Brian sance foi who hath not heard? not for his valiant acts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106760">But well I know throughout the world, doth ring his cowardly facts. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106770">What though I pray all are not born to be god Mars his men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106780">To toy with dainty dames in courts, should be no copesmates then. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106790">If all were given to chivalry, than Venus might go weep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106800">For any court in venery, that she were like to keep. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106810">But shall I frame then mine excuse, by serving Venus she,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106820">When I am known throughout the world, faint hearted for to be? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106830">No, no, alas, it will not serve, for many a knight in love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106840">Most valiant hearts no doubt they have, and knightly prowess prove,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106850">To get their ladies' loyal hearts, but I in Venus' yoke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106860">Am forced for want of valiancy, my freedom to provoke:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106870">Bearing the name and port of knight, enchantments for to use,</l>
          <pb facs="10"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106880">Wherewith full many a worthy wight, most cowardly I abuse:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106890">As witnesseth the number now, which in my castle lie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106900">Who if they were at liberty, in arms I durst not try. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106910">The feeblest there though he unarmed, so is my courage daunted,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106920">Whenas I see the glittering arms, whereby each knight is vaunted. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106930">But how I vanquish these same knights, is wonderful to see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106940">And knights that ventured for her love, whom I do love they be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106950">That's Juliana, daughter to the King of Denmark's grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106960">Whose beauty is the cause that I do haunt or keep this place. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106970">For that no wight may her possess, unless by vow decreed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106980">He bring and do present to her the flying serpent's head. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e106990">Which many hath attempt to do, but none yet could him slay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107000">Ne afterwards hence back again, for me could pass away:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107010">For that through my enchantments lo, which here this forest keep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107020">So soon as I did look on them, they straight were in a sleep. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107030">Then presently I them unarmed, and to my castle brought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107040">And there in prison they do lie, not knowing what was wrought. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107050">Lo thus I range the woods to see who doth the serpent slay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107060">That by enchantment I may take the head from him away:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107070">And it present unto the dame, as though I were her knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107080">Well here comes one, I'll shroud myself, for sure I will not fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e107090">Enter subtill Shift. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107100" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107110">Gog's blood where might I meet with that cowardly knave Bryan sance foy? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107120">I could tell him such a tale now as would make his heart leap for joy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107130">Well yonder I have espied one, whatsoever he be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107140" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107150">Nay gog's blood I'll be gone, he shall not fight with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107160">But by enchantment I'll be even with him by and by. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107170" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107180">A an't shall please you, I'll fight with no man, never come so nigh. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107190" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107200">Why what art thou declare? whither dost thou run? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107210" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107220">Even the cowardly cowardliest villain an't shall please you that lives under the sun. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107230" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107240">What of my fraternity, dost thou not know Bryan sance foy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107250" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107260">What master Bryan, Jesu how my heart doth leap for joy</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107270">That I have met with you, whoever had better luck? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107280" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107290">But touch me not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107300" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107310">Wherefore? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107320" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107330">A lest you inchant me into the likeness of a buck. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107340" who="A69121-shift">
          <pb facs="11"/>
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107350">Tush, tush, I warrant thee, but what art thou declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107360" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107370">Knowledge and it shall please you, who hither doth repair to tell you good news. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107380" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107390">Good news? what are they knowledge express? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107400" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107410">A knight hath slain the flying serpent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107420" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107430">Tush it is not so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107440" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107450">It is most true that I do confess. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107460" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107470">Ah what hight his name knowledge? let me that understand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107480">Clamydes the white knight, son to the King of Swavia land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107490">Who for Juliana, daughter to the King of Denmark's grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107500">Did take the attempt in hand, now you know the whole case. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107510" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107520">Ah happy news of gladsomeness unto my danted mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107530">Now for to win my lady's love, good fortune is assigned:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107540">For though she be Clamydes, right won worthily indeed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107550">Yet will I sure possess that dame, by giving of the head. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107560">But knowledge where about declare, doth that Clamydes rest? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107570" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107580">Even hard by in the forest here where he slew the beast</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107590">I left him, and to seek you did hie:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107600">But let us go further into the woods, you shall meet him by and by. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107610" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107620">Well knowledge for thy pains take this as some reward,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107630">And if thou wilt abide with me, be sure I'll thee regard</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107640">Above all others of my men, besides I'll give to thee</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107650">A thing, that from enchantments aye, preserved shalt thou be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107660" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107670">Then here is my hand, I'll be your servant ever:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107680" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107690">And seeing thou art a coward as well as I, I'll forsake thee never. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107700">But come let us go Clamydes to meet. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e107710">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107720" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107730">Keep on your way and I'll follow, I trust if he meet him, he'll take him to his feet. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107740">Gog's blood was ever seen such a jolt-headed villain as he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107750">To be so afraid of such a fainthart knave as I am to see? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107760">Of the fraternity quoth you? by’r lady it's a notable brood:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107770">Well shift these chinks doth thy heart some good:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107780">And I'll close with Bryan till I have gotten the thing</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107790">That he hath promised me, and then I'll be with him to bring. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107800">Well, such shifting knaves as I am, the ambodexter must play,</l>
          <pb facs="11"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107810">And for commodity serve every man, whatsoever the world say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107820">Well after Bryan I will, and close with him awhile,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107830">But as well as Clamydes, in the end I'll him beguile. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e107840">Enter Clamydes, with the head upon his sword.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e107850" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107860">Ah happy day my deadly foe submitted hath to death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107870">Lo here the hand, lo here the sword that stopped the vital breath:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107880">Lo here the head that shall possess my Juliana's dear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107890">The knight of the golden shield his force, what need I now to fear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107900">Since I by force subdued have this serpent fierce of might,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107910">Who vanquished hath as I have heard, full many a worthy knight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107920">Which for to win my lady's love, their lives have ventured here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107930">Besides that cowardly Bryan which the faithless shield doth bear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107940">A number keeps as I have heard, as captives in his hold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107950">Whom he hath by enchantment got, and not through courage bold. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107960">Shall such defamed dastards, dared by knights, thus bear their name? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107970">Shall such as are without all faith, live to impair our fame? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107980">Shall valiant hearts by cowardly charm, be kept in captives thrall? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e107990">Shall knights live subject to a wretch which hath no heart at all? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108000">Nay first Clamydes claim to thee fell Atrapos his stroke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108010">Ere thou dost see such worthy knights to bear the heavy yoke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108020">Of cowardly Bryan without faith, his charms let daunt not thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108030">And for his force thou needst not fear, the gods thy shield will be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108040">Well, to meet the knight of the golden shield, yet ten days' space I have,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108050">And to set free these worthy knights, but rest a while I crave. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108060">Here in this place near to this fort, for that I weary am</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108070">With travel, since from killing of the serpent late I came:</l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e108080">Here let him sit down and rest himself.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108090">Lo here a while I mind to rest, and Bryan then subdue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108100">And then to Alexander's court, to keep my promise true. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e108110">Enter Bryan sance foy, and Shift.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108120" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108130">Come knowledge, for here he lies laid weary on the ground:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108140" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108150">Nay, I'll not come in his sight, if you would give me a thousand pound. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108160">For he is the terriblest knight of any you have heard spoke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108170">He'll beat a hundreth such as you and I am down at one stroke. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108180" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108190">Tush, fear thou naught at all, I have charmed him, and he is fast asleep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108200">Lying near unto the castle here which I do keep. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108210">And ten days in this sleep I have charmed him to remain,</l>
          <pb facs="12"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108220">Before nature shall overcome it, that he might wake again. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108230">In the mean season, lo behold the serpent's head I'll take away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108240">His shield and his apparel, this done, then will I convey</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108250">His body into prison, with other his companions to lie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108260">Whose strengths, ah knowledge, I durst never attempt to try. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108270" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108280">Ah handle him softly, or else you will cause him to awake:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108290" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108300">Tush, tush, not if all the noise in the world I were able to make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108310">Till ten days be expired, the charm will not leave him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108320">And then I am sure he will marvel who did thus deceive him:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108330">So now he is stripped, stay thou here for a season,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108340">And I'll go fetch two of my servants to carry him into prison. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e108350">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108360" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108370">Well do so master Bryan, and for your coming I'll stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108380">Gog's blood what a villain am I my master to betray. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108390">Nay sure I'll awake him if it be possible ere they carry him to jail:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108400">Master, what master, awake man, what master, ah it will not prevail. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108410">Am not I worthy to be hanged, was ever seen such a deceitful knave? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108420">What villainy was in me, when unto Bryan understanding I gave</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108430">Of my masters being in this forest, but much I muse indeed</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108440">What he means to do with my master's apparel, his shield and the head? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108450">Well, seeing it is through my villainy, my master is at this drift,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108460">Yet when he is in prison, shift shall not be void of a shift</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108470">To get him away, but if it ever come to his ear</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108480">That I was the occasion of it, he'll hang me that's clear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108490">Well here comes Bryan, I'll cloak with him if I may,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108500">To have the keeping of my master in prison night and day. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e108510">Enter Bryan sance foy, two servants. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108520" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108530">Come sirs take up this body, and carry it into the appointed place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108540">And there let it lie, for as yet he shall sleep ten days' space. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108550" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108560">How say you master Bryan, shall I of him have the guard? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108570" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108580">By my troth policy, thy good will to reward</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108590">In hope of thy just service, content I agree</l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e108600">Carry him out.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108610">For to resign the keeping of this same knight unto thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108620">But give me thy hand that thou wilt deceive me never:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108630" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108640">Here's my hand, charm, inchant, make a spider catcher of me, if I be false to you ever. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108650" who="A69121-bryan">
          <pb facs="12"/>
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108660">Well then come follow after me, and the guard of him thou shall have. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e108670">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108680" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108690">A thousand thanks I give you, this is all the promotion I crave:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108700">Ah sirrah, little knows Bryan, that Clamydes my master is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108710">But to set him free from prison I intend not to miss:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108720">Yet still in my mind, I can do no other but muse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108730">What practise with my master's apparel and shell he will use:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108740">Well, seeing I have played the crafty knave with the one, I'll play it with the other:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108750">Subtle shift for advantage, will deceive his own brother. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e108760">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e108770">Here let them make a noise as though they were mariners. And after Clyomon knight of G. S. come in with one.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108780" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108790">Ah set me to shore sirs, in what country soever we be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108800" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shiftmai.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108810">Well hail out the cockboat, seeing so sick we do him see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108820">Strike sail, cast Ankers, till we have rigged our ship again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108830">For never were we in such storms before, that's plain. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e108840">Enter Clyomon, boateswaine.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108850" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108860">Ah boatswain, gramercies for thy setting me to shore. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108870" who="A69121-boatswain">
          <speaker>Boatswain.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108880">Truly gentlemen we were never in the like tempests before. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108890" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108900">What country is this wherein now we be? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108910" who="A69121-boatswain">
          <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108920">Sure the I'll of strange marshes, as our master told to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108930" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108940">How far is it from Macedonia, canst thou declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108950" who="A69121-boatswain">
          <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108960">More than twenty days sailing, and if the weather were fair. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e108970" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108980">Ah cruel hap of fortune's spite, which signed this luck to me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e108990">What palace boatswain is this same, canst thou declare, we see? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109000" who="A69121-boatswain">
          <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109010">There King Patranius keeps his court, so far as I do guess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109020">And by this train of ladies here, I sure can judge no less. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e109030">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109040" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109050">Well boatswain, there's for thy pains, and here upon the shore</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109060">I'll lie to rest my weary bones, of thee I crave no more. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e109070">Enter Neronis daughter to Patranius, King of the strange marshes, two lords, two ladies.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109080" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Neronis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109090">My lords, come will it please you walk abroad to take the pleasant air? </l>
          <pb facs="13"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109100">According to our wonted use, in fields both fresh and fair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109110">My ladies here I know right well, will not gainsay the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109120" who="A69121-1_lord">
          <speaker>1. Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109130">Nor we sure for to pleasure you, Neronis noble dame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109140" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109150">Yes yes, men they love entreaty much, before they will be won,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109160" who="A69121-2_lord">
          <speaker>2. Lord</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109170">No princes that hath women's natures been, since first the world begun. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109180" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109190">So you say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109200" who="A69121-1_lord">
          <speaker>1. Lord</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109210">We boldly may,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109220">Under correction of your grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109230" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109240">Well, will it please you forth to trace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109250">That when we have of fragrant fields, the dulcet fumes obtained,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109260">We may unto the sea side go, whereas is to be gained,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109270">More stranger sights among Neptune's waves, in seeing ships to sail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109280">Which pass here by my father's shore, with merry western gale. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109290" who="A69121-1_lord">
          <speaker>1. Lord</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109300">We shall your highness lead the way to fields erst spoke before. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109310" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109320">Do so, and as we do return we'll come hard by the shore. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e109330">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109340" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109350">What greater grief can grow to gripe, the heart of grieved wight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109360">Then thus to see fell fortune she, to hold his state in spite. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109370">Ah cruel chance, ah luckless lot, to me poor wretch assigned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109380">Was ever seen such contraries, by fraudulent goddess blind. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109390">To any one save only I, imparted for to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109400">To animate the mind of any man, did ever fortune she</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109410">Show forth herself so cruel bent, as thus to keep me back,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109420">From pointed place by weather driven, my sorrows more to sack,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109430">Ah fatal hap, herein alas, what further shall I say? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109440">Since I am forced for to break, mine oath and pointed day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109450">Before King Alexander's grace, Clamydes will be there:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109460">And I through fortune's cruel spite, oppressed with sickness here:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109470">For now within two days' it is that we should meet together,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109480">Woe worth the wind and raging storms, alas that brought me hither. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109490">Now will Clamides me accuse, a faithless knight to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109500">And eke report, that cowardliness did daunt the heart of me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109510">The worthy praise that I have won, through fame shall be defaced,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109520">The name of the knight of the golden shield, alas shall be defaced:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109530">Before that noble prince of might, whereas Clamydes he</l>
          <pb facs="13"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109540">Will show himself in combat wise, for to exclaim on me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109550">For breaking of my pointed day, and Clyomon to thy grief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109560">Now art thou in a country strange, clean void of all relief:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109570">Oppressed with sickness through the rage of stormy blasts and cold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109580">Ah death come with thy direful mace, for longer to unfold</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109590">My sorrows here it booteth not yet clyomon do stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109600">The ladies lo, comes towards thee, that walked the other way. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e109610">Enter Neronis, two lords, two ladies.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109620" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109630">Come fair dames, sith that we have in fragrant fields obtained,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109640">Of dulcet flowers the pleasant smell, and that these knights disdained</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109650">Not to bear us company, our walk more large to make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109660">Here by the sea of surging waves, our home return we'll make. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109670">My lords therefore do keep your way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109680" who="A69121-1_lord">
          <speaker>1. Lord</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109690">As it please your grace, we shall obey,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109700">But behold madam, what woeful wight, here in our way before,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109710">As seemeth very sick to me, doth lie upon the shore. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109720" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109730">My lords, let's know the cause of grief, whereof he is oppressed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109740">That if he be a knight, it may by some means be redressed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109750">Fair sir well met, why lie you here ▪ what is your cause of grief? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109760" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109770">O lady, sickness by the sea, hath me oppressed in brief. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109780" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109790">Of truth my lords, his countenance betrays him for to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109800">In health, of valiant heart and mind, and eke of high degree. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109810" who="A69121-2_lord">
          <speaker>2. Lord</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109820">It doth no less than so import, oh princes as you say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109830" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109840">Of whence are you? or what's your name? you wander forth this way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109850" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109860">Of small valour oh lady fair, alas my name it is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109870">And for not telling of the same, hath brought me unto this. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109880" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109890">Why, for what cause sir knight, should you not express your name? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109900" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109910">Because oh lady I have vowed, contrary to the same. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109920">But where I travel lady fair, in city, town or field,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109930">I am called, and do bear by name, the knight of the golden shield. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109940" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109950">Are you that knight of the golden shield, of whom such fame doth go? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109960" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109970">I am that self same knight fair dame, as here my shield doth sho. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e109980" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e109990">Ah worthy then of help indeed, my lords assist I pray,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110000">And to my lodging in the court, see that you him convey,</l>
          <pb facs="14"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110010">For certainly within my mind, his state is much deplored,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110020">But do despair in naught sir knight, for you shall be restored,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110030">If physic may your grief redress, for I Neronis lo,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110040">Daughter to Patranius King, for that which fame doth show,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110050">Upon your acts, will be your friend, as after you shall prove. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e110060" who="A69121-1_lord">
          <speaker>1. Lord</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110070">In doing so, you shall have need of mighty love above. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e110080" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110090">O princes, if I ever be to health restored again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110100">Your faithful servant day and night, I vow here to remain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e110110" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110120">Well my lords, come after me, do bring him I require:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e110130" who="A69121-ambo">
          <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110140">We shall oh princes willingly accomplish your desire. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e110150">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e110160">Enter Bryan sance foy, having Clamydes his apparel on his shield, and the serpent's head.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e110170" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bry.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110180">Ah sirrah, now is the ten days full expired, wherein Clamydes he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110190">Shall wake out of his charmed sleep, as shortly you shall see:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110200">But here I have what I desired, his shield, his coat and head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110210">To Denmark will I straight prepare, and there present with speed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110220">The same to Juliana's grace, as in Clamydes name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110230">Whereby I am assured I shall enjoy that noble dame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110240">For why Clamydes he is safe, for ever being free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110250">And unto knowledge is he left, here guarded for to be:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110260">But no man knows of my pretents, ne whither I am gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110270">For secretly from castle I, have stolen this night alone</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110280">In this order as you see, in the attire of a noble knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110290">But yet poor Bryan, still thy heart holds courage in despite. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110300">Well, yet the old proverb to disprove, I purpose to begin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110310">Which always say, that cowardly hearts, fair ladies never win. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110320">Shall I not Juliana's win, and who hath a cowardlier heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110330">Yet for to brag and boast it out, I'll will none take my part. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110340">For I can sooke both grim and fierce, as though I were of might,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110350">And yet three frogs out of a bush, my heart did so affright,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110360">That I fell dead almost therewith, well cowardly as I am,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110370">Farewell, forest for now I will in knight Clamydes name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110380">To Denmark to present this head, to Juliana bright,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110390">Who shall cowardly dastard wed, in steed of a worthy knight. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e110400">Exit.</stage>
          <pb facs="14"/>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e110410">Enter Shift with sword and target.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e110420" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110430">Be your leave I came up so early this morning that I cannot see my way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110440">I am sure it's scarce yet in the break of the day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110450">But you muse I am sure wherefore these weapons I bring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110460">Well, listen unto my tale, and you shall know every thing. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110470">Because I played the shifting knave, to save myself from harm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110480">And by my procurement, my master was brought in this charm. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110490">The ten days are expired, and this morning he shall awake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110500">And now like a crafty knave, to the prison my way will I take,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110510">With these same weapons, as though I would fight to set him free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110520">Which will give occasion that he shall mistrust, there was no deceit in me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110530">And having the charge of him, here under Bryan sance foy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110540">I'll open the prison doors, and make as though I did employ</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110550">To do it by force, through good will, and only for his sake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110560">Then shall Clamydes being at liberty, the weapons of me take,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110570">And set upon Bryan and all his men ▪ now that they are asleep ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110580">And so be revenged, for that he did him keep</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110590">By charm in this order, so shall they both deceived be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110600">And yet upon neither part mistrust towards me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110610">Well, near to the prison I'll draw, to see if he be awake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110620">Hark, hark, this same is he, that his lamentation doth make. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e110630" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamydes in prison.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110640">Ah fatal hap, where am I wretch, in what distressed case,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110650">Be reft of Tyro, head and shield, not knowing in what place</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110660">My body is, ah heavenly gods, was ere such strangeness seen:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110670">What do I dream? or am I still within the forest green? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110680">Dream? no, no, alas I dream not I, my senses all do fail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110690">The strangeness of this cruel hap, doth make my heart to quail. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110700">Clamydes ah by fortune she, what froward luck and fate</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110710">Most cruelly assigned is, unto thy noble state. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110720">Where should I be, or in what place hath destiny assigned</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110730">My silly corpse for want of food and comfort to be pinned. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110740">Ah farewell hope of purchasing my lady, since is lost,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110750">The serpent's head whereby I should possess that jewel most. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110760">Ah farewell hope of honour eke, now shall I break my day</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110770">Before King Alexander's grace, whereon my faith doth stay. </l>
          <pb facs="15"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110780">And shall I be found a faithless knight, fie on fell fortune she,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110790">Which hath her wheel of froward chance, thus whirled back on me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110800">Ah farewell King of Swavia land, ah farewell Denmark dame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110810">Farewell thou knight of the golden shield, to thee shall rest all fame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110820">To me this direful destiny, to thee I know renown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110830">To me the blast of ignomy, to thee dame honours crown. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110840">Ah hateful hap, what shall I say, I see the gods hath signed</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110850">Through cruelty my careful corpse, in prison to be pined. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110860">And naught alas amates me so, but that I know not where I am,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110870">Nor how into this doleful place my woeful body came. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e110880" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110890">Alas good Clamydes, in what an admiration is he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110900">Not knowing in what place his body should be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e110910" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110920">Who nameth poor Clamydes there? reply to him again,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e110930" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110940">An't shall please you I am your servant knowledge, which in a thousand woes for you remain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e110950" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110960">Ah knowledge where am I declare and be brief. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e110970" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110980">Where are you? faith even in the castle of that false thief</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e110990">Bryan sance foy, against whom to fight and set you free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111000">Look out at the window, behold I have brought tools with me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111010" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111020">Ah knowledge, then cowardly that caitiff did me charm. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111030" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111040">Yea, or else he could never have done you any harm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111050">But be of good cheer, for such a shift I have made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111060">That the keys of the prison I have got, yourself persuade:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111070">Wherewith this morning I am come to set you free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111080">And as they lie in their beds, you may murder Bryan and his men, and set all other at liberty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111090" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111100">Ah knowledge, this hath me bound to be thy friend for ever:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111110" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111120">A true servant you may see will deceive his master never. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111130">So the doors are open, now come and follow after me. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e111140">Enter out.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111150" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111160">Ah heavens, in what case myself do I see:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111170">But speak knowledge, canst thou tell how long have I been here? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111180" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111190">These ten days full, and sleeping still, this sentence is most clear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111200" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111210">Alas, than this same is the day the which appointed was</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111220">By the knight of the golden shield to me, that combat ours should pass</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111230">Before King Alexander's grace, and there I know he is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111240">Ah cruel fortune why shouldst thou thus wrest my chance amiss:</l>
          <pb facs="15"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111250">Knowing I do but honour seek, and thou dost me defame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111260">In that contrary mine expect, thou all things seeks to frame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111270">The faith and loyalty of a knight thou causest me to break,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111280">Ah hateful dame, why shouldst thou thus thy fury on me wreak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111290">Now will King Alexander judge the thing in me to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111300">The which since first I arms could bear, no wight did ever see. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111310">But knowledge give from thee to me, those weapons that I may</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111320">Upon that Bryan be revenged, which cowardly did betray</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111330">Me of my things, and here from thrall all other knights set free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111340">Whom he by charm did bring in bale, as erst he did by me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111350">Come, into his lodging will I go, and challenge him and his. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e111360">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111370" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111380">Do so, and to follow I will not miss. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111390">Ah sirrah, here was a shift according to my nature and condition,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111400">And a thousand shifts more I have, to put myself out of suspicion. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111410">But it doth me good to think how that cowardly knave Bryan sance foy</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111420">Shall be taken in the snare, my heart doth even leap for joy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111430">Hark, hark, my master is amongst them, but let him shift as he can,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111440">For not to deal with a dog, he shall have help of his man. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e111450">Exeunt.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e111460">Enter after a little fight within, Clamydes three knights.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111470" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111480">Come, come sir knights, for so unfortunate was never none as I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111490">That I should joy that is my joy, the heavens themselves deny. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111500">That cowardly wretch that kept you here, and did me so deceive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111510">Is fled away and hath the shield, the which my lady gave</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111520">To me in token of her love, the serpent's head like case,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111530">For which this mine adventure was, to win her noble grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111540" who="A69121-1_knight">
          <speaker>1 knight.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111550">And sure that same th'occasion was, why we adventured hither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111560" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111570">Well, sith I have you delivered, whenas you please together</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111580">Each one into his native soil his journey do prepare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111590">For though that I have broke my day as erst I did declare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111600">Through this most cowardly caitiffs charms, in meeting of the knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111610">Which of the golden shield bears name, to know else what he hight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111620">I will to Alexander's court, and if that thence he be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111630">Yet will I seek to find him out, lest he impute to me</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111640">Some cause of cowardliness to be, and therefore sir knights depart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111650">As to myself I wish to you with fervent zeal of heart:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111660">Yet if that any one of you do meet this knight by way</l>
          <pb facs="16"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111670">What was the cause of this my let, let him perstand I pray. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111680" who="A69121-omnes">
          <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111690">We shall not miss o noble knight, to accomplish this your will. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e111700">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111710" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111720">Well then adieu fit knights each one, the gods protect you still. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111730">What knowledge ho, where art thou man? come forth that hence we may. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111740" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift within.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111750">Where am I? faith breaking open of chests here within, for I'll have the spoil of all away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111760" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111770">Tush, tush, I pray thee come that hence we may, no riches thou shalt lack. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e111780">Shift with a bag as it were full of gold on his back.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111790">I come now with as much money as I am able to carry of my back. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111800">A there was never poor ass so laden, but how now, that cowardly Bryan have you slain? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111810">And your shield, the serpent's head, and coat, have you again? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111820" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111830">Ah no knowledge, the knights that here were captives kept, they are by me at liberty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111840">But that false Bryan this same night, is fled away for certainty. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111850">And hath all things he took from me, conveyed where none doth know. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111860" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111870">O the bones of me, how will you then do for the serpent's head to Juliana to show? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111880" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111890">I have no other hope alas, but only that her grace</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111900">Will credit give unto my words, whenas I show my case</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111910">How they were lost, but first ere I unto that dame return,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111920">He seek the knight of the golden shield, whereas he doth sojourn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111930">To accomplish what my father wild, and therefore come away. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e111940">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e111950" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111960">Well, keep on before, for I mind not to stay. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111970">A fura, the craftiest knave, the better luck, that's plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111980">I have such a deal of substance here, where Bryan's men are slain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e111990">That is passeth. O that I had while for to stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112000">I could load a hundreth cuts full of kitchen stuff away. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112010">Well, it's not best to carry too long behind, left my master overgo,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112020">And then some knave knowing of my money, a piece of cozenage sho. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e112030">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e112040">Enter Neronis.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e112050" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Neronis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112060">How cast that tree but withered be</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112070">That wanteth sap to moist the root? </l>
          <pb facs="16"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112080">How can that vine but waste and pine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112090">Whose plants are trodden under foot? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112100">How can that spray but soon decay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112110">That is with wild weeds overgrown? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112120">How can that wight in ought delight</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112130">Which shows, and hath no good will shown? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112140">Or else how can that heart alas,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112150">But die by whom each joy doth pass? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112160">Neronis, ah I am the tree, which wanteth sap to moist the root. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112170">Neronis, ah I am the vine, whose plants are trodden under foot. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112180">I am the spray which doth decay, and is with wild weeds overgrown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112190">I am the wight without delight, which shows, and hath no good will shown. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112200">Mine is the heart by whom alas, each pleasant joy doth pass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112210">Mine is the heart which vades away, as doth the flower or grass. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112220">In wanting sap to moist the root, is joys that made me glad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112230">And plants being trodden under foot, is pleasures that was had. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112240">I am the spray which doth decay, whom cares have overgrown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112250">But stay Neronis, thou sayest thou showest, and hath no good will shown:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112260">Why so I do, how can I tell, Neronis force no cruelty</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112270">Thou seest thy knight endued is, with all good gifts of courtesy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112280">And doth Neronis love indeed, to whom love doth she yield,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112290">Even to that noble brute of fame, the knight of the golden shield. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112300">Ah woeful dame, thou knowest not thou, of what degree he is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112310">Of noble blood his jester's show, I am assured of this. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112320">Why belike he is some runagate that will not show his name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112330">Ah why should I this allegate, he is of noble fame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112340">Why dost thou not express thy love, to him Neronis then? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112350">Because shamefastness and womanhood, bids us not seek to men. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112360">Ah careful dame lo thus I stand, as 'twere one in a trance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112370">And lacketh boldness for to speak, which should my words advance. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112380">The knight of the golden shield it is, to whom a thrall I am,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112390">Whom I to health restored have, since that to court he came. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112400">And now he is pressed to pass again, upon his weary way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112410">Unto the court of Alexander, yet hath he broke his day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112420">As he to me the whole expressed, ah sight that doth me grieve,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112430">Lo where he comes to pass away, of me to take his leave. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="17"/>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e112440">Enter Clyomon.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e112450" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112460">Who hath more cause to praise the gods, than I whose state deplored? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112470">Through physic and Neronis help, to health am now restored:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112480">Whose fervent thrall I am become, yet urgent causes doth</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112490">Constrain me for to keep it close, and not to put in proof</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112500">What I might do to win her love, as first my oath and vow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112510">In keeping of my name unknown, which she will not allow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112520">If I should seem to break my mind, being a Princess born,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112530">To yield her love to one unknown, I know she'll think it scorn? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112540">Besides here longer in this court, alas I may not stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112550">Although that with Clamydes he, I have not kept my day:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112560">Lest this he should suppose in me, for cowardliness of heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112570">To seek him out elsewhere, I will from out this land depart. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112580">Yet though unto Neronis she, I may not show my mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112590">A faithful heart when I am gone, with her I leave behind. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112600">Whose bounteousness I here have felt, but since I may not stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112610">I will to take my leave of her, before I pass away. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112620">Lo where she walks, oh Princess well met, why are you here so sad? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e112630" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112640">Good cause I have, since pleasures pass, the which should make me glad. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e112650" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112660">What you should mean, oh Princess dear, hereby I do not know. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e112670" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112680">Then listen to my talk a while, sir knight and I will show. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112690">If case you will reanswer me, my question to obsolue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112700">The which propound within my mind, doth oftentimes revolve. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e112710" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112720">I will oh princes answer you as aptly as I may. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e112730" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112740">Well then sir knight, apply your cares, and listen what I say:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112750">A ship that storms had tossed long, amid the mounting waves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112760">Where harbour none was to be had, fell fortune so depraves:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112770">Through ill success that ship of hope, that anchor's hold doth fail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112780">Yet at the last she's driven to land, with broken mast and sail:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112790">And through the force of furious wind, and billows bouncing blows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112800">She is a simple shipwreck made, in every point God knows. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112810">Now this same ship by chance being found, the finders take such pain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112820">That fit to sail upon the seas, they rig her up again. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112830">And where she was through storms sore shaked, they make her whole and sound</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112840">Now answer me directly here, upon this my propound. </l>
          <pb facs="17"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112850">If this same ship thus rent and torn, being brought in former rate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112860">Should not supply the finders true to profit his estate</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112870">In what she might. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e112880" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112890">Herein a right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112900">I will oh Princess as I may, directly answer you. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112910">This ship thus found, I put the case it hath an owner now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112920">Which owner shall sufficiently content the finders charge:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112930">And have again to serve his use, his ship, his boat or barge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112940">The ship then cannot serve the turn of finders, this is plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112950">If case the owner do content, or pay him for his pain:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112960">But otherwise if none lay claim, nor seem that ship to stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112970">Then is it requisite it should, the finders pains repay:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e112980">For such endeavour as it is to serve for his behoof. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e112990" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113000">What owner truly that it hath, I have no certain proof. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113010" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113020">Then can I not define thereof, but thus I wish it were,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113030">That you would me accept to be, that ship oh lady fair:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113040">And you the finder, than it should be needless for to move,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113050">If I the ship, of duty ought to serve at your behoof. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113060" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113070">Thou art the ship oh worthy knight, so shivered found by me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113080" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113090">And owner have I none dear dame, I yield me whole to thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113100">For as this ship I must confess, that was a shipwreck made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113110">Thou hast restored me unto health, whom sickness caused to vade,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113120">For which I yield oh Princess dear, at pleasure thine to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113130">If your grace, oh noble dame, will so accept of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113140" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113150">If case I will, what have you shown? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113160" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113170">Because I am to you unknown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113180" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113190">Your fame importeth what you be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113200" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113210">You may your pleasure say of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113220" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113230">What I have said due proof do show. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113240" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113250">Well lady dear, to thee I owe</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113260">More service then of duty I am able to profess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113270">For that thou didst preserve my life amid my deep distress:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113280">But at this time I may not stay, oh lady here with thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113290">Thou knowest the cause, but this I vow within three score days to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113300">If destiny restrain me not, at court with thee again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113310">Protesting whilst that life doth last, thine faithful to remain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113320" who="A69121-neronis">
          <pb facs="18"/>
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113330">And is there then no remedy, but needs you will depart? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113340" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113350">No Princess for a certainty, but here I leave my heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113360">In gage with thee till my return, which as I said shall be:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113370" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113380">Well, sith no persuasion may prevail, this jewel take of me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113390">And keep it always for my sake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113400" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113410">Of it a dear account I'll make, yet let us part dear dame with joy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113420">And to do the same I will myself employ. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113430" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113440">Well now adieu till thy return, the gods thy journey guide. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e113450">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113460" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113470">And happily in absence mine, for thee dear dame provide:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113480">Ah Clyomon let dolours die, drive daunts from out thy mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113490">Since in the sight of fortune now, such favour, thou dost find,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113500">As for to have the love of her whom thou didst sooner judge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113510">Would have denied thy loyalty, and 'gainst thy good will grudge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113520">But that I may here keep my day, you sacred gods provide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113530">Most happy fate unto my state, and thus my journey guide:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113540">The which I tempt to take in hand Clamydes for to meet:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113550">That the whole cause of my first let, to him I may repeat. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113560">So shall I seem for to excuse myself in way of right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113570">And not be counted of my foe, a false periured knight. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e113580">Exit.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e113590">Enter Thrasellus King of Norway two lords.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113600" who="A69121-thrasellus">
          <speaker>Thra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113610">Where deep desire hath taken root, my lords alas you see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113620">How that persuasion 〈◊〉 not, if contrary it be ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113630">Unto the first expected hope, where fancy hath take place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113640">And vain it is for to withdraw, by counsel in that case:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113650">The mind who with affection is, to one only thing affected,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113660">The which may not till dint of death, from them be sure rejected:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113670">You know my lords through fame, what force of love hath taken place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113680">Within my breast as touching now Neronis noble grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113690">Daughter to Patranius King, who doth the sceptre sway:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113700">And in the I'll of marshes eke, bear rule now at this day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113710">Through love of daughter his, nay sorrows daily grow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113720">And daily do loves do me daunt, for that alas I show</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113730">Such friendship whereas favour none, is to be found again:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113740">And yet from o●● my careful mind, naught may her love restrain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113750">I sent to crave her of the King he answered me with nay:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113760">But shall I not provide by force to fetch her thence away? </l>
          <pb facs="18"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113770">Yes, yes, my lords, and therefore let your aids be pressed with mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113780">For I will sure Neronis have, or else my days I'll pine. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113790">For King Patranius and his power, I hold of small account,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113800">To win his daughter to my spouse, amids his men I'll mount. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113810" who="A69121-1_lord">
          <speaker>1 lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113820">Most worthy prince, this rash attempt, I hold not for the best,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113830">For sure Patranius' power is great, and not to be suppressed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113840">For why, the I'll environed is, with sea on every side,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113850">And landing place lo is there none, whereas you may have tide</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113860">To set your men from ship to shore, but by one only way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113870">And in that place a garrison great, he keepeth at this day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113880">So that if you should bring your power, your travel were in vain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113890">That is not certainly the way, Neronis for to gain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113900">But this your grace may do indeed, and so I count it best,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113910">To be in all points with a ship, most like a merchant pressed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113920">And sail with such as you think best, all dressed in merchant's guise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113930">And for to get her to your ship, some secret mean device,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113940">By showing of strange merchandise, or other such like thing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113950">Lo this is best advice I can, Thrassellus lord and King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113960" who="A69121-2_lord">
          <speaker>2 lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113970">And certainly as you have said, my lord it is the way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e113980">Wherefore o King, do prosecute the same without delay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e113990" who="A69121-thrasellus">
          <speaker>Thrasell.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114000">Of truth my lords this your advice doth for our purpose frame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114010">Come therefore let us hence depart, to put in ure the same</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114020">With present speed, for merchant-wise myself will thither sail:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114030" who="A69121-1_lord">
          <speaker>1 lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114040">This is the way if any be, of purpose to prevail. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e114050">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e114060">Enter Clyomon with a knight, signifying one of those that Clamyde, had delivered.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114070" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114080">Sir knight, of truth this fortune was most luckily assigned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114090">That we should meet in travel thus, for thereby to my mind</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114100">You have a castle of comfort brought, in that you have me told,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114110">Clamydes our appointed day, no more than I did hold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114120" who="A69121-knight">
          <speaker>Knight.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114130">No certis sir he kept not day, the cause I have expressed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114140">Through that enchanter Bryan's charms, he came full sore distressed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114150">Yet fortune favoured so his state, that through his help all we</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114160">Which captives were through cowardly craft, from bondage were set free:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114170">And at our parting willed us, if any with you met,</l>
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114180">We should inform you with the truth what was his only let. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114190" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114200">Well, know you where he abideth now, sir knight I crave of courtesy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114210" who="A69121-knight">
          <speaker>Knight.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114220">No questionless I know not I, to say it of a certainty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114230" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114240">Well then adieu sir knight with thanks, I let you on your way:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114250" who="A69121-knight">
          <speaker>Knight.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114260">Unto the gods I you commit, naught else I have to say. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e114270">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114280" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114290">A sirrah, now the hugy heaps of cares that lodged in my mind</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114300">Is scaled from their nestling place, and pleasure's passage find. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114310">For that as well as Clyomon, Clamydes broke his day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114320">Upon which news my passage now in seeking him I'll stay:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114330">And to Neronis back again, my joyful journey make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114340">Lest that she should in absence mine, some cause of sorrow take. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114350">And now all dumps of deadly dole, that daunted knightly breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114360">A due, since salve of solace sweet, hath sorrows all suppressed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114370">For that Clamydes cannot brag, nor me accuse in ought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114380">Unto the gods of destinies, that thus our fates hath brought</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114390">In equal balance to be weighed, due praises shall I send,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114400">That thus to way each cause aright, their eyes to earth did bend. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114410">Well, to keep my day with lady now, I mind not to be slack,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114420">Wherefore unto Patranius' court, I'll dress my journey back. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114430">But stay, methinks I rumor hear throughout this land to ring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114440">I will attend his talk, to know what tidings he doth bring. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e114450">Enter rumor running.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114460">Ye rolling clouds give rumor room, both air and earth below,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114470">By sea and land, that every ear may understand and know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114480">What woeful hap is chanced now within the isle of late,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114490">Which of strange marshes beareth name, unto the noblest state. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114500">Neronis daughter to the King, by the King of Norway he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114510">Within a ship of merchandise, conveyed away is she. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114520">The King with sorrow for her sake, hath to death resigned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114530">And having left his Queen with child, to guide the realm behind. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114540">Mustantius brother to the King, from her the crown would take,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114550">But till she be delivered, the lords did order make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114560">That they before King Alexander, thither coming should appeal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114570">And he by whom they hold the crown, therein should rightly deal</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114580">For either part, lo this to tell, I rumor have in charge,</l>
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114590">And through all lands I do pretend, to publish it at large. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e114600">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114610" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114620">Ah woeful rumor ranging thus, what tidings do I hear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114630">Hath that false King of Norway stolen my love and lady dear? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114640">Ah heart, ah hand, ah head and mind, and every sense beside,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114650">To serve your master's turn in need, do every one provide. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114660">For till that I revenged be upon that wretched King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114670">And have again my lady dear, and her from Norway bring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114680">I vow this body takes no rest, ah fortune fickle dame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114690">That canst make glad and so soon sad, a knight of worthy fame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114700">But what should I delay the time, now that my dear is goned? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114710">Auaileth ought to ease my grief, to make this pensive moan?</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114720">No, no, wherefore come courage to my heart, and happy hands prepare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114730">For of that wretched King I will wreak all my sorrow and care. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114740">And maugre all the might he may, be able for to make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114750">By force of arms my lady I, from him and his will take. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e114760">Exit.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e114770">Enter Clamydes and Shift, with his bag of money still.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114780" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114790">Come knowledge, thou art much to blame, thus for to load thyself</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114800">To make thee on thy way diseased, with carrying of that pelf. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114810">But now take courage unto thee, for to that isle I will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114820">Which of strange marshes called is, for fame declareth still</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114830">The knight of the golden shield is there, and in the court abideth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114840">Thither will I him to meet, whatsoever me betideth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114850">And know his name, as thou canst tell my father charged me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114860">Or else no more his princely court nor person for to see. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114870">Come therefore, that unto that isle we may our journey take,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114880">And afterwards having met with him, our voyage for to make</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114890">To Denmark to my lady there, to show her all my case,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114900">And then to Swavia if her I have, unto my father's grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114910" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114920">Nay but an't shall please you, are you sure the knight of the golden shield in the isle of strange marshes is? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114930" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114940">I was informed credibly, I warrant thee we shall not miss. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e114950">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e114960" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114970">Then keep on your way, I'll follow as fast as I can,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114980">Faith he even means to make a martris of poor shift his man. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e114990">And I am so tied to this bag of gold I got at Bryan sance foyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115000">That I tell you where this is, there all my joy is:</l>
          <pb facs="20"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115010">But I am so weary, sometimes with riding, sometimes with running,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115020">And other times going a foot:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115030">That when I came to my lodging at night, to bring me a woman it is no boor. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115040">And such care I take for this pelf lest I should it lose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115050">That where I come, that it is gold, for my life I dare not disclose. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115060">Well after my master I must, here's nothing still but running and riding:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115070">But I'll give him the slip sure, if I once come where I may have quiet biding. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e115080">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e115090">Enter Neronis in the Forrest, in man's apparel.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e115100" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115110">As 〈◊〉 the hound, as lamb the wolf, as foul the falcons dint,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115120">So do I fly from tyrant he, whose heart more hard than flint</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115130">Hath sacked on me such hugy heaps of ceaseless sorrows here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115140">That sure it is intolerable, the torments that I bear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115150">Neronis, ah who knoweth thee, a Princess to be born,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115160">Since fatal gods so frowardly, thy fortune doth adorn:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115170">Neronis, ah who knoweth her, in painful pages show? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115180">But no good lady will me blame, which of my case doth know:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115190">But rather when they hear the truth, wherefore I am disguised,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115200">They'll say it is an honest shift, the which I have devised:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115210">Since I have given my faith and troth to such a brute of fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115220">As is the knight of the golden shield, and tyrants seeks to frame</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115230">Their engines to detract our vows, as the King of Norway hath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115240">Who of all princes living now, I find devoid of faith:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115250">For like a wolf in lambs skin clad, he cometh with his aid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115260">All merchant like to father's court, and ginneth to persuade</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115270">That he had precious jewels bought, which in his ship did lie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115280">Whereof he willed me take my choice, if case I would them buy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115290">Then I mistrusting no deceit, with handmaids one or two</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115300">With this deceitful merchant then unto the ship did go. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115310">No sooner were we under hatch, but up they hoist their sail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115320">And having then to serve their turn, a merry western gale:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115330">We were lashed out from the haven, lo a dozen leagues and more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115340">When still I thought the bark had been, at anchor by the shore:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115350">But being brought by Norway here, not long in court I was,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115360">But that to get from thence away, I brought this feat to pass:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115370">For making semblance unto him as though I did him love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115380">He gave me liberty, or ought that served for my behoof:</l>
          <pb facs="20"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115390">And having liberty, I wrought by such a secret slight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115400">That in this tire like to a page, I scaped away by night. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115410">But ah I fear that by pursuit, he will me overtake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115420">Well here entereth one, to whom some sure for service I will make. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e115430">Enter Corin a shepherd.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e115440" who="A69121-corin">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115450">Gos bone turn in that sheep there and you be good fellows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115460">Jesu how cham beraid●,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115470">Chave a cur here, an 'a were my vellow, cha must him consuade,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115480">And yet an cha should kiss, look you of the arse, cha must run myself, an Chil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115490">An cha should entreat him with my cap in my hand, ha wad stand still. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115500">But 'tis a world to zee what merry lives we shepherds lead,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115510">Why where gentlemen and we get once a thorn bush over our head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115520">We may sleep with our vaces against the zone, an were hog's</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115530">Bath ourselves, stretch out our legs an't were a cennell of dogs:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115540">And then at night when maids come to milkin, the games begin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115550">But I may zay to you my neighbour, hog's maid had a clap, well let them laugh that win. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115560">Chave but one daughter, but chould not vor vorty pence she were zo sped,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115570">Cha may zay to you, she looks every night to go to bed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115580">But 'tis no matter, the whores be so whiskish when there under a bush,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115590">That there never satisfied, till their bellies be flush. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115600">Well cha must abroad about my flocks, lest the fengeance wolves catch a lamb:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115610">Warrant by my cursen soul, thale steal an cha stand by, there not a verd of the dam ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e115620" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115630">Well to scape the pursuit of the King, of this same shepherd here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115640">Suspicion wholly to avoid, for service I'll inquire:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115650">Well met good father, for your use, a servant do you lack? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e115660" who="A69121-corin">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115670">What you will not flout an old man you courtnold Jack? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e115680" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115690">No truly father I flout you not, what I ask I would have. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e115700" who="A69121-corin">
          <speaker>Co.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115710">Gos bones they leest, serve a shepherd an be zo brave? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115720">You courtnoll crack-ropes, would be hanged, you do nothing now and then</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115730">But come up and down the country, thus to flout poor men. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115740">Go too goodman boy, chave no zervis vor no zuch flouting jacks as you be</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e115750" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115760">Father I think as I speak, upon my faith and troth believe me</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115770">I will willingly serve you, if in case you will take me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e115780" who="A69121-corin">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115790">Dost not inocke? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e115800" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115810">No truly father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e115820" who="A69121-corin">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115830">Then come with me, by Gos bones Chil never vorsake thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115840"><pb facs="21"/>Whow bones of my soul, though wilt thebravest shepherd's boy in our town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115850">Thous go to church in this coat, bevore Madge a Sunday in her grey gown. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115860">Good lord how our churchwardens will look upon thee, bones of god zeest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115870">There will be more looking at thee, than our sir John the parish priest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115880">Why everybody will ask whose boy thou'rt, an cha cātel the this by the way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115890">Thou shalt have all the varest wenches of our town in the veelds vor to play. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115900">There's neighbour Nychols daughter, a jolly smug whore with vat checks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115910">And neighbour Hodges maid, meddle not with her, she hath eaten set leeks. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115920">But there's Frumpton's wench in the freeze scake, it will do thee good to see</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115930">What canuosing is at the milking time, between her and me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115940">And those wenches will love thee bonhomably in every place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115950">But do not fall in with them in any kind of case. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e115960" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115970">Tush, you shall not need to fear me, I can be merry with measure as well as they:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e115980" who="A69121-coryn">
          <speaker>Coryn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e115990">Well then come follow after me, and home Chil lead thee the way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116000" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116010">Alas poor simple shepherd, by this princes may see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116020">That like man, like talk, in every degree. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e116030">Exeunt.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e116040">Enter Thrasellus King of Norway, and two lords.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116050" who="A69121-thrasellus">
          <speaker>Thras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116060">My lords pursue her speedely, she cannot far be gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116070">And lo himself to seek her out, your King he will be one. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116080">Ah fraudulent dame, how hath she glossed, from me to get away? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116090">With sugared words how hath she fed, my senses night and day? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116100">Professing love with outward shows, and inwardly her heart</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116110">To practise such a deep deceit, whereby she might depart</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116120">From out my court so suddenly, when I did wholly judge</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116130">She loved me most entirely, and not against me grudge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116140">She made such signs by outward shows, I blame not wit and policy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116150">But here I may exclaim and say, fie, fie, on women's subtlety. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116160">Well well my lords, no time delay, pursue her with all speed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116170">And I this forest will seek out myself, as is decreed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116180">With aid of such as are behind, and will come unto me:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116190" who="A69121-ambo">
          <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116200">We shall not slake what here in charge to us is given by thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e116210">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116220" who="A69121-thrasellus">
          <speaker>Thras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116230">Ah subtle Neronis, how hast thou me vexed? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116240">Through thy crafty dealings how am I perplexed? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116250">Did ever any win a dame, and lose her in such sort? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116260">The maladies are marvelous, the which I do support</l>
          <pb facs="21"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116270">Through her deceit, but forth I will my company to meet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116280">If ever she be caught again, I will her so entreat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116290">That others all shall warning take, by such a subtle dame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116300">How that a prince for to delude, such engines they do frame. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e116310">Enter Clyomon knight of the golden shield.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116320" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116330">Nay traitor stay, and take with thee that mortal blow or stroke</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116340">The which shall cause thy wretched corpse this life for to revoke. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116350">It joyeth me at the heart that I have met thee in this place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116360" who="A69121-thrasellus">
          <speaker>Thras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116370">What varlet darest thou be so bold, with words in such a case,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116380">For to upbraid thy lord and King? what art thou soon declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116390" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116400">My lord and King, I thee defy, and in despite I dare</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116410">Thee for to say thou art no prince, for thou a traitor art,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116420">And what reward is due therefore, to thee I shall impart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116430" who="A69121-thrasellus">
          <speaker>Thras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116440">Thou braggest all too boldly still, what hight thy name express? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116450" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116460">What hight my name thou shalt not know, ne will I it confess:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116470">But for that thou my lady stolest from father's court away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116480">I'll sure revenge that traitorous fact upon thy flesh this day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116490">Since I have met so luckily with thee here all alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116500">Although as I do understand, from thee she now is gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116510">Yet therefore do defend thyself, for here I thee assail,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116520" who="A69121-thrasellus">
          <speaker>Thras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116530">Alas poor boy, thinkest thou against me to prevail? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e116540">Here let them fight, the King fall down dead.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116550" who="A69121-thrasellus">
          <speaker>Thras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116560">Ah heavens, Thrasellus he is slain, ye gods his ghost receive,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116570" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116580">Now hast thou justice for thy fact, as thy desert doth crave:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116590">But ah alas poor Clyomon, though thou thy foe hast slain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116600">Such grievous wounds thou hast received, as doth increase thy pain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116610">Unless I have some speedy help, my life must needly waste,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116620">And then as well as traitor false, my corpse of death shall taste. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116630">Ah my Neronis where art thou? ah where art thou become? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116640">For thy sweet sake thy knight shall here receive his vital doom. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116650">Lo here all gored in blood thy faithful knight doth lie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116660">For thee, ah faithful dame, thy knight for lack of help shall die. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116670">For thee, ah here thy clyomon, his mortal stroke hath ta'en,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116680">For thee, ah these same hands of his, the Norway King hath slain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116690">Ah bleeding wounds from longer talk my faltering tongue doth stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116700">And if I have not speedy help, my life doth waste away. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="22"/>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e116710">Enter father Coryn the shepherd, and his dog.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116720" who="A69121-coryn">
          <speaker>Coryn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116730">A plague on thee for a cur, a ha, driven me sheep above from the flock:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116740">A thief, art not ashamed? I'll beat thee like a stock:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116750">And cha been azeeking here, above voure miles and more:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116760">But Chill tell you what, chave the bravest lad of Jack the courtnoll, that ever was zeene bevore. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116770">A, the whorcop is plagely well loved in our town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116780">An you had zeene go to church bevore Madge my wife in her holy day gown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116790">You would have blessed your zelves t'ave seen it, she went even cheek by jowl</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116800">With our head controms wife, brother to my neighbour Nycholl,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116810">You know ha dwells by master justice, over the water on the other side of the hill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116820">Cham zure you know it, between my neighbour filchers varme house, and the windmill. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116830">But an you did zee how Joan Jenkin, and Gilian Giffrey loves my boy Jack,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116840">Why it is marvelation to see, Joan did so baste Gillian's back,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116850">That by gos bones I laughed till cha be pissed my self, when cha zaw it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116860">All the maids in town valls out for my boy, but and the young men know it</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116870">Thale be zo ielisom over them, that cham in doubt</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116880">Ich shall not keep Jack my boy till seven years go about. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116890">Well, Cham never the near vor my sheep, chave sought it this voure mile,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116900">But chill home, and send Jack forth to seek it another while. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116910">But bones of God man stay, Jesu whither wilt? wha what meanst lie here? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116920" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116930">Ah good father help me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116940" who="A69121-coryn">
          <speaker>Coryn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116950">Nay who there, by your leave, Chill not come near. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116960">What another? bones of me, he is either killed or dead? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116970">Nay varewell vorty pence, year a knave, Gos death a doth bleed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e116980" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e116990">I bleed indeed father, so grievous my wounds be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117000">That if I have not speedy help, long life is not in me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117010" who="A69121-coryn">
          <speaker>Coryn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117020">Why what art thou? or how chanced thou camest in this case? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117030" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117040">Ah father, that dead corpse which thou seest there in place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117050">He was a knight, and mine enemy, whom here I have slain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117060">And I a gentleman, whom he hath wounded with marvelous pain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117070">Now thou knowest the truth, good father show some courtesy</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117080">To stop my bleeding wounds, that I may find some remedy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117090">My life to preserve, if possible I may ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117100" who="A69121-coryn">
          <pb facs="22"/>
          <speaker>Coryn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117110">Well he are you gentleman, chould have you know this by the way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117120">Cham but father Coryn the shepherd, Cham no surringer I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117130">But Chill do what cha can vor you, cha were loath to see you die. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117140">Lo how zay you by this, have cha done you any ease? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117150" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clya.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117160">Father thy willingness of a certainty, doth me much please:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117170">But good father lend me thy helping hand once again. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117180">To bury this same knight whom here I have slain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117190">Although he was to me a most deadly enemy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117200">Yet to leave his body unburied, were great cruelty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117210" who="A69121-coryn">
          <speaker>Coryn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117220">Bones of God man, our priest dwells too far away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117230" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117240">Well, then for want of a priest, the priest's part I will play:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117250">Therefore father, help me to lay his body aright:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117260">For I will bestow a hearse of him, because he was a knight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117270">If thou wilt go to a cottage hereby, and fetch such things as I lack. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117280" who="A69121-coryn">
          <speaker>Coryn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117290">That chill gentleman, and by and by return back. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e117300">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117310" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117320">But Clyomon pluck up thy heart, with courage once again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117330">And I will set over his dead corse in sign of victory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117340">My golden shield and sword, but with the point hanging down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117350">As one conquered and lost his renown. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117360">Writing likewise thereupon, that all passengers may see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117370">That the false King of Norway, here lieth slain by me. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e117380">Enter Coryn with a hearse.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117390" who="A69121-corin">
          <speaker>Co.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117400">Lo gentleman, Cha brought zuch things, as are requisite for the same:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117410" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117420">Then good father help me, the hearse for to frame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117430">Chat chall gentleman, in the best order that cha may:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117440">Oh that our parish priest were here, that you might hear him say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117450">Warrant by Gos bones, an there be any noise in the church, in the midst of his prayers he'll swear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117460">A he loves hunting a life, would to God you were acquainted with him a while,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117470">And as vor a woman, well Chill zay nothing, but cha know whom he did beguile. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117480" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117490">Well father Coryn let that pass, we have nothing to do withal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117500">And now that this is done, come reward thy pain I shall. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117510">There is part of a recompense, thy good will to requite. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117520" who="A69121-coryn">
          <pb facs="23"/>
          <speaker>Coryn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117530">By my troth cha thank you, Cham bound to pray vor you day and night. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117540">And now Chil even home, and send Jack my boy this sheep to seek out:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117550" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117560">Tell me father ere thou goest, didst thou not see a lady wand'ring here about? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117570" who="A69121-corin">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117580">A lady, no good vaith gentleman, Cha zaw none cha tell you plane:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117590" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117600">Well then farewell father, gramercies for thy pain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117610">Ah Neronis where thou art, or where thou dost abide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117620">Thy Clyomon to seek thee out shall rest no time nor tide:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117630">Thy foe here lieth slain on ground, and living is thy friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117640">Whose travel till he see thy face, shall never have an end. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117650">My ensign here I leave behind, these verses writ shall yield</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117660">A true report of traitor slain, by the knight of the golden shield. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117670">And as unknown to any wight, to travel I betake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117680">Until I may her find, whose sight my heart may joyful make. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e117690">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e117700">Enter Shift very brave.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e117710" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117720">Jesu what a gazing do you make at me, to see me in a gown? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117730">Do you not know after travel, men being in court or in town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117740">And specially such as is of any reputation, they must use this guise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117750">Which signifieth a fool to be sage, grave, and of counsel wise. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117760">But where are we think you now, that shift is so brave? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117770">Not running to seek the knight of the golden shield, another office I have:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117780">For coming here to the court, of strange marshes so named,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117790">Where King Alexander in his own person lies, that prince mightily famed</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117800">Between Mustantius brother to the late King deceased</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117810">And the Queen, through King Alexander, a strife was appeased:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117820">But how or which way I think you do not know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117830">Well then give ear to my tale, and the truth I will show:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117840">The old King being dead, through sorrow for Neronis,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117850">Whom we do hear, lover to the knight of the golden shield is. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117860">The Queen being with child, the sceptre asked to sway,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117870">But Mustantius the King's brother, he did it denay. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117880">Whereof great contention grew, amongst the nobles on either side,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117890">But being by them agreed the judgement to abide</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117900">Of King Alexander the great, who then was coming hither,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117910">At his arrival to the court, they all were called together. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117920">The matter being heard, this sentence was given,</l>
          <pb facs="23"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117930">That either party should have a champion to combat them between:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117940">That which champion were overcome, the other should sway,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117950">And to be fought after that time, the sixteen day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117960">Now my master Clamydes coming hither, for Mustantius will he be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117970">But upon the Queen's side, to venture none can we see:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117980">And yet she maketh proclamation through every land:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e117990">To give great gift; to any that will take the combat in hand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118000">Well within ten days is the time, and King Alexander he</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118010">Stayeth till the day appointed, the trial to see:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118020">And if none came at the day for the Queen to fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118030">Then without travel to my master, Mustantius hath his right. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118040">But to see all things in a readiness, against th'appointed day:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118050">Like a shifting knave for advantage, to court I'll take my way. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e118060">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e118070">Enter Neronis like a shepherd's boy.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e118080" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118090">The painful paths, the weary ways, the travels and ill fare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118100">That simple feet, to princes seem, in practice very rare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118110">As I poor dame, whose pensive heart, no pleasure can delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118120">Since that my state so cruelly, fell fortune holds in spite. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118130">Ah poor Neronis in thy hand, is this a seemly show,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118140">Who shouldst in court thy lute supply, where pleasures erst did flow? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118150">Is this an instrument for thee to guide a shepherd's flock? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118160">That art a Princess by thy birth, and born of noble stock. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118170">May mind from mourning more refrain, to think on former state? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118180">May heart from sighing eke abstain, to see this simple rate? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118190">May eyes from down distilling tears, when thus a love I am,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118200">Resistance make, but must they not, through ceaseless sorrows frame</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118210">A river of bedewed drops, for to distil my face? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118220">Ah heavens when you are revenged enough, then look upon my case:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118230">For till I hear some news alas upon my loving knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118240">I dare not leave this loathsome life, for fear of greater spite:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118250">And now as did my master will, as sheep that is a stray</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118260">I must go seek her out again, by wild and weary way. </l>
          <pb facs="24"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118270">Ah woeful sight; what is alas, with these mine eyes beheld,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118280">That to my loving knight belonged, I view the golden shield:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118290">Ah heavens, this hearse doth signify my, knight is slain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118300">Ah death no longer do delay, but rid the lives of twain:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118310">Heart, hand, and every sense prepare, unto the hearse, draw nigh:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118320">And thereupon submit yourselves, disdain not for to die</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118330">With him that was your mistress joy, her life and death like case,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118340">And well I know in seeking me, he did his end embrace. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118350">That cruel wretch that Norway King this cursed deed hath done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118360">But now to cut that linger thread, that Lachis long hath spun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118370">The sword of this my loving knight, behold I here do take,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118380">Of this my woeful corpse alas, a final end to make:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118390">Yet ere I strike that deadly stroke that shall my life deprave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118400">Ye muses aid me to the gods, for mercy first to crave. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e118410">Sing here.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118420">Well now you heavens receive my ghost, my corpse I leave behind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118430">To be enclosed with his in earth, by those that shall it find. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e118440">Descend providence.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e118450" who="A69121-provi">
          <speaker>Proui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118460">Stay, stay thy stroke, thou woeful dame, what wilt thou thus despair? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118470">Behold to let this wilful fact, I providence prepare</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118480">To thee, from seat of mighty love, look hereupon again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118490">Read, that if case thou canst it read, and see if he be slain</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118500">Whom thou dost love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e118510" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nere.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118520">Ah heavens above. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118530">All land and praise and ho honour due to you I here do render,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118540">That would vouchsafe your handmaid here, in woeful state to tender ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118550">But by these same verses do I find, my faithful knight doth live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118560">Whose hand unto my deadly foe, the mortal stroke did give:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118570">Whose cursed carcass lo it is, which here on ground doth lie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118580">Ah honour due for this I yield, to mighty Jove on high. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e118590" who="A69121-provi">
          <speaker>Proui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118600">Well, let desperation die in thee, I may not here remain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118610">But be assured, that thou shalt ere long thy knight attain. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e118620">Ascend.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e118630" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118640">And for their providence divine, the gods above I'll praise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118650">And show their works so wonderful, unto their laud always. </l>
          <pb facs="24"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118660">Well, sith that the gods by providence hath signed unto me</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118670">Such comfort sweet in my distress, my knight again to see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118680">Farewell all feeding shepherds flocks, unseemly for my state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118690">To seek my love I will set forth, in hope of friendly fate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118700">But first to shepherd's house I will, my pages tire to take,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118710">And afterwards depart from thence, my journey for to make. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e118720">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e118730">Enter sir Clyomon. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e118740" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118750">Long have I sought but all in vain, for neither far nor near</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118760">Of my Neronis woeful dame, by no means can I hear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118770">Did ever fortune violate two lovers in such sort? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118780">The griefs ah are intolerable, the which I do support</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118790">For want of her, but hope somewhat revives my pensive heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118800">And doth to me some sudden cause of comfort now impart</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118810">Through news I hear, as I abroad in weary travel went,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118820">How that the Queen her mother hath her proclamations sent</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118830">Through every land, to get a knight to combat on her side,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118840">Against Mustantius, Duke and lord, to have a matter tried:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118850">And now the day is very nigh, as I do understand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118860">In hope to meet my lady there I will into that land:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118870">And for her mother undertake the combat for to try,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118880">Yea though the other Hector were, I would him not deny</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118890">Whatsoever he be, but ere I go, a golden shield I'll have,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118900">Although unknown, I will come in, as doth my knighthood crave:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118910">But covered will I keep my shield, because I'll not be known,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118920">If case my lady be in place, till I have prowess shown. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118930">Well, to have my shield in readiness, I will no time delay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118940">And then to combat for the Queen, I straight will take my way. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e118950">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e118960">Enter Neronis like the page.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e118970" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118980">Ah weary paces that I walk, with steps unsteady still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e118990">Of all the gripes of grisly griefs, Neronis hath her fill. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119000">And yet amids these miseries, which were my first mishaps,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119010">By brute I hear such news alas, as more and more enwraps</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119020">My wretched corpse with thousand woes, more than I may support,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119030">So that I am to be compared unto the scaled fort,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119040">Which doth so long as men and might, and sustenance prevail,</l>
          <pb facs="25"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119050">Give to the enemy's repulse, that cometh to assails</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119060">But when assistance begins to fail, and strength of foes increase,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119070">They forced are through battering blows, the same for to release. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119080">So likewise I so long as hope, my comfort did remain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119090">The griefly griefs that me assailed, I did repulse again:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119100">But now that hope begins to fail, and griefs anew do rise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119110">I must of force yield up the fort, I can no way devise</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119120">To keep the same, the fort I mean, it is the weary corpse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119130">Which sorrows daily do assail, and siege without remorse:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119140">And now to make my griefs the more, report alas hath told,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119150">How that my father's aged bones, is shrined up in mould,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119160">Since Norway King did me betray, and that my mother she,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119170">Through Duke Mustantius, uncle mine, in great distress to be:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119180">For swaying of the sceptre there, what should I herein say? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119190">Now that I cannot find my knight, I would at combat day</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119200">Be gladly there, if case I could with some good master meet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119210">That as his page in these affairs, would seem me to entreat:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119220">And in good time, here cometh one, he seems a knight to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119230">I'll proffer service, if in case, he will accept of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e119240">Enter Clyomon with his shield covered, strangely disguised.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e119250" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119260">Well, now as one unknown, I will go combat for the Queen:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119270">Who can bewray me, since my shield is not for to be seen? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119280">But stay, who do I here espy? of truth a proper boy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119290">If case he do a master lack, he shall sustain no noy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119300">For why in these affairs, he may stand me in passing steed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e119310" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119320">Well, I see to pass upon my way, this gentleman's decreed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119330">To him I will submit myself, in service for to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119340">If case he can his fancy frame, to like so well on me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119350">Well met sir knight upon your way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e119360" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119370">My boy gramercies, but to me say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119380">Into what country is thy journey dight? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e119390" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119400">Towards the strange marsh, of truth sir knight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e119410" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119420">And thither am I going, high Jove be my guide. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e119430" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119440">Would God's I were worthy to be your page by your side. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e119450" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119460">My page my boy, why what is thy name? that let me hear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e119470" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119480">Sir knight, by name I am called cur Daceer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e119490" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <pb facs="25"/>
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119500">Cur Daceer, what heart of steel, now certis my boy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119510">I am a gentleman, and do entertain thee with joy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119520">And to the strange marshes am I going, the Queen to defend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119530">Come therefore, for without more saying, with me thou shalt wend. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e119540">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e119550" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119560">As diligent to do my duty as any in this land:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119570">Ah fortune, how favourably my friend doth she stand:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119580">For thus no man knowing mine estate nor degree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119590">May I pass safely, a page as you see. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e119600">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e119610">Enter Bryan sance foy with the head.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e119620" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bry.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119630">Even as the owl that hides her head, in hollow tree till night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119640">And dares not while sir Phoebus shines, attempt abroad in flight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119650">So likewise I as buzzard bold, while cheerful day is seen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119660">Am forced with owl to hide myself, amongst the ivy green:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119670">And dares not with the silly snail, from cabin show my head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119680">Till Vesper I behold aloft, in skies begin to spread:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119690">And then as owl that flies abroad when other fowls do rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119700">I creep out of my drowsy den, when summons hath suppressed</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119710">The head of every valiant heart, lo thus I shroud the day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119720">And travel as the owl by night upon my wished way:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119730">The which hath made more tedious my journey, by half part,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119740">But blame not Bryan, blame alas, his cowardly caitiffs heart:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119750">Which dares not show itself by day, for fear of worthy wights,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119760">For none can travel openly, to escape the venturous knights,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119770">Unless he have a noble mind, and eke a valiant heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119780">The which I will not brag upon, I assure you for my part:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119790">For if the courage were in me, the which in other is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119800">I doubtless had enjoyed the wight whom I do love ere this. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119810">Well, I have not long to travel now, to Denmark I draw nigh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119820">Bearing knight Clamydes name, yet Bryan sance foy am I. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119830">But though I do usurp his name, his shield or ensign here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119840">Yet can I not usurp his heart, still Bryan's heart I bear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119850">Well, I force not that, he is safe enough, and Bryan as I am,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119860">I will unto the court, whereas I shall enjoy that dame. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e119870">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="26"/>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e119880">Enter Shift like a waffler.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e119890" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119900">Room there for a reckoning, see I beseech you if thale stand out of the way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119910">Jesu, Jesu, why do you not know that this is the day</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119920">That the combat must pass for Mustantius and the Queen? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119930">But to fight upon her side as yet no champion is seen. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119940">And Duke Mustantius he smiles in his sleeve, because he doth see</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119950">That neither for love nor rewards, any one her champion will be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119960">An't were not but that my master the other champion is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119970">To fight for the Queen myself, I surely would not miss. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119980">Alas good lady, she and her child is like to lose all the land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e119990">Because none will come in, in her defence for to stand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120000">For where she was in election, if any champion had come</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120010">To rule till she was delivered, and have the prince's room:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120020">Now shall Duke Mustantius be sure the sceptre to sway,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120030">If that none do come in to fight in her cause this day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120040">And King Alexander all this while hath he stayed the trial to see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120050">Well here they come, room there for the King, here's such thrusting of women as it grieveth me. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e120060">Enter King Alexander, the Queen, Mustantius, two lords, and Clamydes like a champion.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120070" who="A69121-mustantius">
          <speaker>Mustan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120080">O Alexander lo behold, before thy royal grace</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120090">My champion here at pointed day I do present in place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120100" who="A69121-alexander">
          <speaker>Alexand.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120110">Well sir Duke in your defence is he content to be? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120120" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120130">Yea worthy prince, not fearing who encounter shall with me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120140">Although he were with Hercules of equal power and might,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120150">Yet in the cause of this same Duke, I challenge him the fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120160" who="A69121-alexander">
          <speaker>Alexa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120170">I like your courage well sir knight: what shall we call your name? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120180" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120190">Clamydes, son to the Swavian King, oh prince so hight the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120200" who="A69121-alexander">
          <speaker>Alexa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120210">Now certainly I am right glad Clamydes for to see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120220">Such valiant courage to remain within the mind of thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120230">Well lady, according to the order ta'en herein, what do you say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120240">Have you your champion in like case, now ready at the day? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120250" who="A69121-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120260">No sure o King no champion I, have for to aid my cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120270">Unless 'twill please your noble grace on further day to pause. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120280">For I have sent throughout this I'll, and every foreign land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120290">But none as yet hath proffered, to take the same in hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120300" who="A69121-alexander">
          <pb facs="26"/>
          <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120310">No, I am more sorry certainly, your chance to see so ill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120320">But day deferred cannot be, unless Mustantius will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120330">For that his champion ready here, in place he doth present,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120340">And who so missed at this day, should lose by full consent</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120350">Of either part, the title right, and sway of regal mace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120360">To this was your consentment given, as well as his in place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120370">And therefore without his assent, we cannot refer the day? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120380" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120390">An't shall please your grace, herein try Mustantius what he will say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120400" who="A69121-alexander">
          <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120410">How say you Mustantius, are you content the day to defer? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120420" who="A69121-mustantius">
          <speaker>Mustan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120430">Your grace will not will me I trust, for then from law you err:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120440">And having not her champion here, according to decree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120450">There resteth naught for her to lose, the crown belongs to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120460" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120470">Nay an't shall please your grace, rather than she shall it lose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120480">I myself will be her champion for half a dozen blows. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120490" who="A69121-mustantius">
          <speaker>Mustan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120500">Wilt thou? then by full congo to the challenger there stands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120510" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120520">Nay soft, of sufferance cometh ease, though I cannot rule my tongue, I'll rule my hands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120530" who="A69121-mustantius">
          <speaker>Mustan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120540">Well noble Alexander, sith that she wants her champion as you see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120550">By greement of your royal grace, the crown belongs to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120560" who="A69121-alexander">
          <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120570">Nay Mustantius, she shall have law, wherefore to sound begin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120580">To see if that in three hours space no champion will come in. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e120590">Sound here once.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120600">Of truth madam I sorry am, none will thy cause maintain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120610">Well, according to the law of arms, yet trumpet sound again. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e120620">Sound second time.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120630">What, and is there none will take in hand, to combat for the Queen? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120640" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120650">Faith I think it must be I must do the deed, for none yet is seen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120660" who="A69121-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120670">O King let pity plead for me, here in your gracious sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120680">And for so slender cause as this deprive me not of right:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120690">Consider once I had to spouse a prince of worthy fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120700">Though now blind fortune spurn at me, her spite I needs must blame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120710">And though I am bereft oh King, both of my child and mate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120720">Your grace some greement may procure, consider of my state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120730">And suffer not a widow Queen with wrong oppressed so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120740">But pity the young infant's case, wherewith oh King I go:</l>
          <pb facs="27"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120750">And though I suffer wrong, let that find favour in your sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120760" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120770">Why lady I respect you both, and sure would if I might</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120780">Entreat Mustantius there unto, some such good order frame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120790">Your strife should cease, and yet each one well pleased with the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120800" who="A69121-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120810">I know your grace may him persuade, as reason wills no less. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120820" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120830">Well, sir Mustantius, than your mind to me in brief express,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120840">Will you unto such order stand here limited by me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120850">Without deferring longer time, say on if you agree? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120860" who="A69121-mustantius">
          <speaker>Mustan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120870">In hope your grace my state will way, I give my glad consent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120880" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120890">And for to end all discord say, madam, are you content? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120900" who="A69121-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120910">Yea noble King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e120920" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120930">Well then before my nobles all, give ear unto the King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120940">For swaying of the sword and mace all discord to beat down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120950">The child when it is born, we elect to wear the crown. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120960">And till that time Mustantius, you of lands and living here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120970">Like equal part in every point, with this the Queen shall share:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120980">But to the child when it is born, if gods grant it to live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e120990">The kingdom whole in every part, as title we do give. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121000">But yet Mustantius, we will yield this recompense to you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121010">You shall receive five thousand crowns for yearly pension due,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121020">To maintain your estate, while you here live and do remain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121030">And after let the whole belong unto the crown again. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121040">Now say your minds if you agree? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121050" who="A69121-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121060">I would the like choice were put to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121070" who="A69121-mustantius">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121080">I for my part oh noble King therewith am well content:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121090">Well better half than naught at all, I likewise give consent. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e121100">Enter Clyomon, as to combat.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121110" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121120">Renowned King and most of fame, before thy royal grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121130">The Queen to aid, I do present my person here in place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121140" who="A69121-mustantius">
          <speaker>Mustan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121150">You come too late in faith sir knight, the hour and time is past. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121160" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121170">Your hour I am not to respect, I entered with the blast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121180" who="A69121-unassigned">
          <speaker>Cl●my.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121190">What princox is it you, are come to combat for the Queen? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121200">Good fortune now, I hope ere long your courage shall be seen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121210" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121220">And sure I count my hap as good, to meet with you sir knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121230">Come according to your promise made, prepare yourself to fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121240" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <pb facs="27"/>
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121250">I knew you well enough sir, although your shield were hid from me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121260" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121270">Now you shall feel me as well as know me, if hand and heart agree. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121280" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121290">Stay, stay sir knights, I charge you not in combat to proceed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121300">For why the quarrel ended is, and the parties are agreed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121310">And therefore we discharge you both, the combat to refrain:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121320" who="A69121-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121330">The heavens therefore oh noble King, thy happy shield remain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121340" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121350">O King although we be discharged for this contention now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121360">Betwixt us twain there resteth yet a combat made by vow:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121370">Which should be fought before your grace: and since we here be met,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121380">To judge twixt us for victory, let me your grace entreat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121390" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121400">For what occasion is your strifes sir knights, first let me know? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121410" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamid.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121420">The truth thereof renowned King thy servant he shall show:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121430">What time oh King, as I should take of Suavia King my sire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121440">The noble orders of a knight, which long I did desire:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121450">This knight a stranger comes to court, and at that present day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121460">In cowardly wise he comes by stealth, and takes from me away</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121470">The honour that I should have had, for which my father he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121480">Did of his blessing give in charge, oh noble King to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121490">That I should know his name, that thus bereft me of my right</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121500">The which he will not show, unless he be subdued in fight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121510">Whereto we either plighted faith, that I should know his name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121520">If that before thy grace oh King, my force in fight could frame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121530">To vanquish him, now having met thus happily together,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121540">Though they are 'greed, our combat rest, decreed ere we came hither. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121550">Are you that knight that did subdue sir Samuel in field,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121560">For which you had in recompense of us, that golden shield? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121570" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121580">I am that knight renowned prince, whose name is yet unknown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121590">And since I foiled sir Samuel, some prowess I have shown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121600" who="A69121-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121610">Then as I guess, you are that knight by that same shield you bear</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121620">Which sometime was restored to health within our palace here? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121630">By Neronis our daughter she betrayed by Norway King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121640" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121650">I am that knight indeed oh Queen, whom she to health did bring ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121660">Whose servant ever I am bound wheresoever that she be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121670">Whose enemy oh Queen is slain pursuing her, by me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121680" who="A69121-queen">
          <pb facs="28"/>
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121690">Know you not where she abides, sir knight to us declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121700" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121710">No certis would to gods I did, she should not live in care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121720">But escaped from the Norway King, I am assured she is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121730" who="A69121-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121740">Well her absence was her father's death, which turned to bale my (Bliss. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121750" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121760">And till I find her out again, my toil no end shall have</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121770" who="A69121-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121780">Alas he is nigh enough to her, small toil the space doth crave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121790" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121800">Well sir knights, since that you have declared before me here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121810">The cause of this the grudge which you to each other bear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121820">I wish you both a while to pause, and to my words attend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121830">If reason rest with you, be sure knights, this quarrel I will end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121840">Without the shedding any blood betwixt you here in sight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121850">Clamydes, weigh you are nobly born, and will you then sir knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121860">Go hazard life so desperately ▪ I charge you both refrain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121870">Since for so small a cause, the strife doth grow betwixt you twain:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121880">And let him know your name sir knight, and so your malice end:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121890" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121900">I have vowed to the contrary, which vow I must defend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121910" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121920">Well though so it be that you have vowed, your name shall not be known:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121930">Yet not detracting this your vow, your country may be shown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121940">And of what stock by birth you be:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121950" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121960">But lady he is dashed now I see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e121970" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121980">Indeed this hath astounded me much, I cannot but confess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e121990">My country and my birth, my state, which plainly will express</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122000">My name, for that unto them all my state is not known,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122010" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122020">Sir knight, of our demand from you again, what answer shall be shown ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122030" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122040">Of Denmark noble prince I am, and son unto the King:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122050" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122060">Why then sir Cliomon hight your name, as rare report doth ring? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122070" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122080">It doth indeed so hight my name, oh prince of high renown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122090">I am the prince of Denmark's son, and heir unto the crown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122100" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122110">And are you son to Denmark King? then do embrace your friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122120">Within whose heart here towards you, all malice makes an end:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122130">Who with your sister linked is, in love with loyal heart:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122140" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122150">And for her sake, and for thine own, like friendship I impart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122160" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122170">Well sir knights, since friendship rests, where rancour did remain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122180">And that you are such friends become, I certain am right fain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122190">In hope you will continue still, you shall to court repair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122200">And remain if that you please awhile, to rest you there</l>
          <pb facs="28"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122210">Till time you have decreed which way your journey you will frame ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122220" who="A69121-both">
          <speaker>Both.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122230">We yield you thanks, beseeching Jove still to augment your fame. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e122240">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122250" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamydes.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122260">Well, come my Clyomon let us pass, and as we journey by way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122270">My most misfortunes unto thee I wholly will bewray</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122280">What happened in my last affairs, and for thy sister's sake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122290" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122300">Well then coeur d'acer come and wait, your journey you shall take,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122310">And seeing thou art prepared, and haste all things in readiness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122320">Hast thee before to Denmark with speediness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122330">And tell the King and the Queen that Clyomon their son</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122340">In health and happy state to their court doth return,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122350">But in no wise to Juliana say any thing of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122360" who="A69121-unassigned">
          <speaker>Curdaser.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122370">I will not show one word amiss contrary your decree. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122380" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamydes.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122390">Well then my Clyomon, to take our leave to court let us repair:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122400" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122410">As your friend and companion Clamydes everywhere . </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e122420">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122430" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Neronis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122440">O heavens! is this my loving knight whom I have served so long ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122450">Now have I tried his faithful heart, o so my joys doth throng,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122460">To think how fortune favoureth me, Nerones now be glad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122470">And praise the gods, thy journey now, such good success hath had. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122480">To Denmark will I haste with joy my message to declare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122490">And tell the King how that his son doth homeward now repair. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122500">And more to make my joys abound, fortune could never frame</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122510">A finer mean to serve my turn, than this, for by the same</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122520">I may unto the Queen declare my state in secret wise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122530">As by the way I will recount how best I can devise. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122540">Now pack Nerones like a page, haste hence lest thou be spied,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122550">And tell thy master's message there, the gods my journey guide. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e122560">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e122570">Enter King of Denmark, the Queen, Juliana, two lords.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122580" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122590">Come lady Queen, and daughter eke, my Juliana dear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122600">We muse that of your knight as yet no news again you hear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122610">Which did adventure for your love the serpent to subdue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122620" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122630">O father, the sending of that worthy knight my woeful heart doth rue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122640">For that alas the furious force of his outrageous might,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122650">As I have heard subdued hath full many a worthy knight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122660">And this last night oh father past, my mind was troubled sore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122670">Methought in dream I saw a knight not known to me before,</l>
          <pb facs="29"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122680">Which did present to me the head of that same monster slain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122690">But my Clamydes still in voice methought I heard complain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122700">As one bereft of all his joy, now what this dream doth signify,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122710">My simple skill will not suffice the truth thereof to specify. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122720">But sore I fear to contraries, the expect thereof will hap,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122730">Which will in huge calamities my woeful corpse bewrap:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122740">For sending of so worthy a prince, as was Clamydes he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122750">To sup his dire destruction there, for wretched love of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122760" who="A69121-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122770">Tush daughter these but fancies be, which run within your mind:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122780" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122790">Let them for to suppress your joys, no place of harbour find. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122800" who="A69121-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122810">O princes let no dollars daunt, behold your knight in place:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122820" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122830">Ah happy sight, do I behold my knight Clamydes face? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e122840">Enter Bryan sans foy with the head on his sword.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122850" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122860">Well, I have at last through travel long, achieved my journey's end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122870">Though Bryan, yet Clamydes name, I stoutly must defend. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122880">Ah happy sight, the King and Queen with daughter in like case</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122890">I do behold, to them I will present myself in place:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122900">The mighty god's renowned King, thy princely state maintain:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122910" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122920">Sir Clamydes, most welcome sure you are to court again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122930" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122940">O princes lo my promise here performed thou mayst see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122950">The serpent's head by me subdued I do present to thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122960">Before thy father's royal grace:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e122970" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122980">My Clamydes do embrace. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e122990">Thy Juliana, whose heart thou hast till vital race be run▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123000">Sith for her sake so venturously this deed by thee was done. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123010">Ah welcome home my faithful knight:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123020" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123030">Gramerces' noble lady bright. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123040" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123050">Well Juliana in our court your lover cause to stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123060">For all our nobles we will send, against your nuptial day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123070">Go carry him to take his rest:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123080" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Iulian.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123090">I shall obey your grace's hest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123100">Come my Clamydes go with me, in court your rest to take:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123110" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123120">I thank you lady, now I see account of me you make. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e123130">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123140" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123150">Well my Queen, sith daughter ours hath chosen such a make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123160">The terror of whose valiant heart may cause our foes to quake,</l>
          <pb facs="29"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123170">Come let us presently depart, and as we did decree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123180">For all our nobles will we send, their nuptials for to see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123190" who="A69121-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123200">As pleaseth thee, thy lady Queen oh King is well agreed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123210" who="A69121-lord">
          <speaker>Lord</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123220">May it please your graces to arrest, for lo with posting speed</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123230">A messenger doth enter place:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123240" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123250">Then will we stay to know the case. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e123260">Enter Neronis.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123270" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123280">The mighty powers renowned prince preserve your state for ay,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123290" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123300">Messenger thou art welcome, what hast thou to say? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123310" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123320">Sir Clyomon your noble son, knight of the golden shield,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123330">Who for his valiant victories in town and eke in field</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123340">Is famed through the world, to your court doth now return,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123350">And hath sent me before to court, your grace for to inform. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123360" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123370">Ah messenger declare, is this of truth the which that thou hast told ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123380" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123390">It is most true oh noble King, you may thereof be bold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123400" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123410">Ah joy of joys surpassing all, what joy is this to me? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123420">My Clyomon in court to have, the nuptial for to see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123430">Of Juliana sister his, o so I joy in mind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123440" who="A69121-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123450">My boy where is thy master speak, what is he far behind:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123460">Declare with speed, for these my eyes do long his face to view:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123470" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123480">O Queen this day he will be here, 'tis truth I tell to you. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123490">But noble Queen let pardon here my bold attempt excuse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123500">And for to hear a simple boy in secret not refuse. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123510">Who hath strange tidings from your son to tell unto your grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e123520">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123530" who="A69121-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123540">Behold my lord where as I guess, some strangers enter place:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123550" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123560">I hope my Clyomon be not far, o joy, I see his face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123570" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123580">Come knowledge, come forward, why art thou always slack? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123590">Get you to court, brush up our apparel, untruss your pack:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123600">Go seek out my page, bid him come to me with all speed you can:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123610" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123620">Go seek out, fetch, bring here, gog's 'ounds, what am I, a dog or a man ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123630">I were better be a hangman, and live so like a drudge:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123640">Since your new man came to you, I must pack, I must trudge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123650" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123660">How stands thou knave? why gets thou not away? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123670" who="A69121-shift">
          <speaker>Shift.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123680">Now, now sir, you are so hasty now, I know not what to say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123690" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123700">O noble prince, the gods above preserve thy royal grace:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123710" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123720">How joyful is my heart dear son, to view again thy face? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123730" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <pb facs="30"/>
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123740">And I as joyful in the view of parents happy plight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123750">Whom sacred gods long time maintain in honour day and night. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123760">But this my friend oh father dear, even as myself entreat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123770">Whose nobleness when time shall serve to you he shall repeat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123780" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123790">If case my son he be thy friend, with heart I thee embrace:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123800" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123810">With loyal heart in humble wise, I thank your noble grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123820" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123830">My Clyomon declare my son in thine adventures late,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123840">What hath been wrought by fortune most to advance thy noble state? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123850" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123860">O father, the greatest joy of all the joys which was to one assigned</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123870">Since first I left your noble court by cruel fortune blind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123880">Is now bereft from me away, through her accursed fate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123890">So that I rather find she doth envy my noble state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123900">Then seek for to advance the same, so that I boldly may</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123910">Express she never gave so much, but more she took away. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123920">And that which I have lost by her, and her accursed ire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123930">From travel will I never cease, until I may aspire</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123940">Unto the view thereof o King, wherein is all my joy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123950" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123960">Why how hath fortune wrought to thee this care and great annoy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e123970" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123980">O father unto me the heavenly powers assigned a noble dame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e123990">With whom to live in happy life, my heart did wholly frame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124000">But not long did that glazing star, give light unto mine eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124010">But this fell fortune begins to frown, which every state despise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124020">And takes away through cankered have that happy light from me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124030">In which I fixed had my hope, a blessed state to see:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124040">And daughter to the King she was, which of strange marshes hight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124050">Bearing brute each where, to be dame beauties darling bright:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124060">Right heir unto dame virtue's grace, dame nature's pattern true,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124070">Dame prudence scholar for her wit, dame Venus for her hue. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124080">Diana for her dainty life, Susanna being sad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124090">Sage Saba for her soberness, mild Marpha being glad. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124100">And if I should re-enter make, amongst the Muses nine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124110">My lady lacked no kind of art, which man may well define</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124120">Amongst those dainty dames to be, then let all judge that hear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124130">If that my cause it be not just, for which this pensive cheer</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124140">Fell fortune forceth me to make. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124150" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124160">Yet Clyomon good counsel take. </l>
          <pb facs="30"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124170">Let not the loss of the lady thine so pinch thy heart with grief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124180">That nothing may unto thy mind give comfort or relief:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124190">What man there ladies are enough, although that she be gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124200">Then leave to wail the want of her, cease off to make this moan. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124210" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124220">No father, never seem for to persuade, for as is said before,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124230">What travel I have had for her, it shall be triple more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124240">Until I meet with her again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124250" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124260">Well Clyomon, a while refrain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124270">And let me here my woes recount before your father's grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124280">But let me crave, your sister may be sent for into place. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124290">O King vouchsafe I may demand a simple bound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124300">Although a stranger, yet I hope such favour may be found,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124310">The thing is this, that you will send for Juliana hither,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124320">Your daughter fair, that we may talk a word or twain together. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124330" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124340">For what, let me know sir knight, do you her fight desire? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124350" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124360">The cause pretends no harm my liege, why he doth this require. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124370" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124380">My lord go bid our daughter come and speak with me straight way. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124390" who="A69121-lord">
          <speaker>Lord</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124400">I shall my liege in every point, your mind herein obey. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A69121-e124410">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124420" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124430">O father this is Clamydes, and son to Swavia King. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124440">Who for my sister ventured life, the serpent's head to bring:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124450">With whom I met in travel mine, but more whad did befall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124460">To work his woe whenas she comes, your grace shall know it all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124470" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124480">My son you are deceived much, I you assure in this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124490">The person whom you term him for, in court already is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124500" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124510">No father I am not deceived, this is Clamydes sure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124520" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124530">Well my son do cease a while such talk to put in ure:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124540">For lo thy sister entereth place, which soon the doubt shall end. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124550" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124560">Then for to show my name to her, I surely do pretend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124570">My Juliana noble dame, Clamydes do embrace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124580">Who many a bitter brunt hath bided, since that he saw thy face. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e124590">Enter Juliana.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124600">Avant dissembling wretch, what credit canst thou yield? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124610">Where's the serpent's head thou brought, where is my glittering shield? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124620">Tush, tush sir knight, you counterfeit, you would Clamydes be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124630">But want of these bewrays you quite, and shows you are not he,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124640" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124650">O princes do not me disdain, I certain am your knight:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124660" who="A69121-juliana">
          <pb facs="31"/>
          <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124670">What art thou frantic foolish man ▪ avaunt from out my sight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124680">If thou art he, then show my shield, and bring the serpent's head:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124690" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124700">O Princess hear me show my case, by fortune fell decreed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124710">I am your knight and when I had subdued the monster fell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124720">Through weary fight and travel great as knowledge here can tell:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124730">I laid me down to rest a space within the forest, where</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124740">One Bryan then sans foy height, who with cowardly usage there,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124750">By chanting charm, brought me a sleep, then did he take from me</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124760">The serpent's head, my coat and shield, the which you gave to me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124770">And left me in his prison lo still sleeping as I was. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124780">Lo lady thus I lost those things the which to me you gave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124790">But certainly I am your knight, and he who did deprave</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124800">The flying serpent of his life according as you willed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124810">That who so won your love by him, the same should be fulfilled. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124820" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Juli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124830">Alas poor knight, how simply have you framed this excuse ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124840">The name of such a noble knight to usurp and eke abuse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124850" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124860">No sister you are deceived, this is Clamydes sure:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124870" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124880">No brother, than you are deceived, such tales to put in ure:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124890">For my Clamydes is in court, who did present to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124900">In white attire the serpent's head and shield, as yet to see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124910" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124920">That shall I quickly understand, oh King permit I may</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124930">Have conference a while with him, whom as your grace doth say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124940">Presents Clamydes, for to be before your royal grace:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124950" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Juli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124960">Behold no whit agast to show himself, where he doth enter place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124970" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e124980">Ah traitor, art thou he that doth my name and state abuse? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e124990" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Juli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125000">Sir knight you are too bold in presence here, such talk against him for to use. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125010" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bry.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125020">Wherefore dost thou upbraid me thus, thou varlet do declare? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125030" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clio.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125040">No varlet he, to call him so, sit knight you are too blame:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125050" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125060">Wouldst thou perstand for what intent such talk I here do frame? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125070">Because I know thou dost usurp my state and noble name. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125080" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bry.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125090">Who art thou, or what's thy name? can swear quickly make:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125100" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125110">I am Clamydes, whose name to bear, thou here dost undertake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125120" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bry.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125130">Art thou Clamydes? vaunt thou false usurper of my state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125140">Avoid this place, or death shall be thy most accursed fate. </l>
          <pb facs="31"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125150">How darest thou enterprise to take my name thus unto thee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125160" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125170">Nay rather, how darest thou attempt to usurp the name of me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125180" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125190">You lie sir knight, he doth not so, 'gainst him you have it done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125200" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125210">Sister you are deceived, my friend here is Clamydes prince, the King of Suavia's son. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125220" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125230">Nay brother, neither you nor he can me deceive herein. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125240" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125250">O King bow down thy princely ears, and listen what I say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125260">To prove myself the wight I am before your royal grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125270">And to disprove this faithless knight which here I find in place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125280">For to usurp my name so much, the combat will I try:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125290">For before I will mine honour lose, I rather choose to die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125300" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125310">I like well your determined mind, but how say you sir knight? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125320" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125330">Nay by his 'ounds I'll gauge my gown he dares not fight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125340">By gog's blood I shall be slain now, if the combat I deny,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125350">And not for the ears of my head with him I dare try. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125360" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125370">Sir knight why do you not reanswer make in trial of your name? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125380" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bry.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125390">I will oh King, if case he dare in combat try the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125400" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125410">Well then go to prepare yourselves, each one his weapons take:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125420" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125430">Good father let it not be so, restrain them for my sake. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125440">I may not here behold my knight in danger for to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125450">With such a one who doth usurp his name to purchase me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125460">I speak not this for that I fear his force or strength in fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125470">But that I will not have him deal with such a desperate wight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125480" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125490">Nay sure, there is no better way than that which is decreed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125500">And therefore for to end their strife the combat shall proceed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125510">Sir knights prepare yourselves, the truth thereof to try. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125520" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125530">I ready am, no cowardly heart shall cause me to deny. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125540" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bry.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125550">Nay I'll never stand the trial of it, my heart to fight doth faint:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125560">Therefore I'll take me to my legs, seeing my honour I must attaint. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125570" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125580">Why whither runs Clamydes? Sir knight seem to stay him:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125590" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125600">Nay it is Clamydes o King that doth fray him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125610" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125620">Nay come sir come, for the combat we will try:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125630" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bry.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125640">Ah no my heart is done, to be Clamydes I deny. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125650" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125660">Why how now Clamydes, how chance you do the combat here thus shun? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125670" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bry.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125680">O King grant pardon unto me, the thing I have begun</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125690">I must deny, for I am not Clamides, this is plain:</l>
          <pb facs="32"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125700">Though greatly to my shame, I must my words revoke again:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125710">I am no other than the knight, whom they sans foy call,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125720">This is Clamydes, the fear of whom, my danted mind doth pall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125730" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Iulian.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125740">Is this Clamydes? ah worthy knight, then do forgive thy dear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125750">And welcome eke ten thousand times unto thy lady here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125760" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125770">Ah my Juliana bright, what's past I do forgive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125780">For well I see thou constant art, and whilst that I do live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125790">For this, my firmed faith in thee for ever I'll repose. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125800" who="A69121-juliana">
          <speaker>Iulian.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125810">O father now I do deny that wretch, and do amongst my foes</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125820">Recount him for this treason wrought. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125830" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125840">Well knowledge, take him unto thee, and for the small regard</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125850">The which he had to valiant knights, this shall be his reward,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125860">Sith he by charms, his cruelty in cowardly manner wrought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125870">On knights, who as Clamydes did, the crown of honour fought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125880">And traitorously did them betray, in prison for to keep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125890">The fruits of such like cruelty, himself by us shall reap:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125900">By due desert therefore I charge to prison him convey,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125910">There for to lie perpetually unto his dying day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125920" who="A69121-bryan">
          <speaker>Bryan.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125930">O King be merciful, and show some favour in this case:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125940" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125950">Nay, never think that at my hands thou shalt find any grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125960" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamydes,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125970">Ah most welcome thou, our daughter to enjoy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e125980">The heavens be praised that this hath wrought, to foil all future noy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e125990" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamydes.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126000">I thank your grace, that you thus so well esteem of me. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e126010">Enter knowledge.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126020">What is all things finished, and every man eased? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126030">Is the pageant packed up, and all parties pleased? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126040">Hath each lord his lady, and each lady her love? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126050" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126060">Why knowledge, what meanst thou those motions to move? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126070" who="A69121-knowledge">
          <speaker>Knowledge.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126080">You were best stay a while, and than you shall know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126090">For the Queen herself comes, the motion to show. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126100">You sent me if you remember, to seek out your page,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126110">But I cannot find him, I went whistling and calling through the court in such a rage:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126120">At the last very scarcely in at a chamber I did pry,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126130">Where the Queen with other ladies very busy I did spy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126140">Decking up a strange lady very gallant and gay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126150">To bring her here in presence, as in court I heard say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126160" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126170">A strange lady knowledge of whence is she canst thou tell me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126180" who="A69121-knowledge">
          <speaker>Knowledge.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126190">Not I an't shall please you, but anon you shall see. </l>
          <pb facs="32"/>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126200">For lo where the lady with your mother doth come:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126210" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126220">Then straightway my duty to her grace shall be done. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126230">The mighty gods preserve your state, oh Queen, and mother dear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126240">Hoping your blessing I have had, though absent many a year. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A69121-e126250">Enter Queen.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126260">My Clyomon, thy sight my son doth make thy aged mother glad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126270">Whose absence long and many a year, hath made thy pensive parents sad. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126280">And more to let thee know my son, that I do love and tender thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126290">I have here for thy welcome home, a present which I'll give to thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126300">This lady though she be unknown, refuse her not, for sure her state</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126310">Deserves a prince's son to wed, and therefore take her for thy more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126320" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126330">O noble Queen and mother dear, I thank you for your great good will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126340">But I am otherwise bestowed, and sure I must my oath fulfil. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126350">And so I mind if gods to fore on such decree I mean to pause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126360">For sure I must of force deny, my noble father knows the cause. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126370" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126380">Indeed my Queen this much he told, he loved a lady since he went,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126390">Who hath his heart and ever shall, and none but her to love he's bent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126400" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126410">So did I say, and so I will, no beauties blaze, no glistering wight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126420">Can cause me to forget her love, to whom my faith I first did plight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126430" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nerones.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126440">Why are you so straight laced sir knight, to cast a lady off so coy? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126450">Turn once again and look on me, perhaps my sight may bring you joy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126460" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126470">Bring joy to me? alas which way? no lady's looks can make me glad:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126480" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126490">Then were my recompense but small, to quit my pain for you I had. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126500">Wherefore sir knight do weigh my words, set not so light the love I show,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126510">But when you have bethought yourself, you will recant and turn I know. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126520" who="A69121-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126530">My Clyomon refuse her not, she is and must thy lady be:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126540" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126550">If otherwise my mind be bent, I trust your grace will pardon me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126560" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126570">Well then I see 'tis time to speak, sir knight let me one question crave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126580">Say on your mind. Where is that lady now become, to whom your plighted faith you gave? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126590" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126600">Nay if I could absolve that doubt, then were my mind at ease:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126610" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126620">Were you not brought to health by her, when you came sick once of theseas? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126630" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Cly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126640">Yea sure I must confess a truth, she did restore my health to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126650">For which good deed I rest her own, in hope one day her face to see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126660" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126670">But did you not promise her to return, to see her at a certain day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126680">And ere you came that to perform, the Norway King stole her away? </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126690">And so your lady there you lost:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126700" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyomon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126710">All this I grant, but to his cost. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126720">For stealing her against her will, this hand of mine bereft his life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126730" who="A69121-neronis">
          <pb facs="33"/>
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126740">Now sure sir knight you served him well, to reach him know another 〈◊〉 wife:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126750">But yet once more sir knight reply, the truth I crave to understand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126760">In forest once, who gave you drink, whereas you stood with sword in hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126770">Fearing lest some had you pursued for slaying of your enemy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126780" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Cly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126790">That did a silly shepherd's boy, which there I took my page to be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126800" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126810">And what is of that page become, remains he with you, yea or no? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126820" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126830">I sent him hither ere I came, because the King and Queen should know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126840">That I in health returned was, but since, I never saw him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126850" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126860">And sure he stands not far from hence, though now you do not know him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126870" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126880">〈…〉 from hence, where might he be? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e126890" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126900">Of troth sir knight, myself am he:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126910">I bought your message the King, as here the Queen can testify:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126920">I gave you drink in forest sure, when you with drought were like to die. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126930">I found you once upon the shore full sick, whenas you came from seas,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126940">I bought you home to father's court, I sought all means your mind to pleas,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126950">And 〈◊〉 was that all this while have weighted like a page on thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126960">〈◊〉 hoping for to 〈…〉 might discover me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126970">And so by hap at last I did, I thank your mother's noble grace:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126980">〈…〉 me courteously, when I had told her all my case. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e126990">And now let this suffice my dear, I am Neronis whom you see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127000">Who 〈…〉 gone, before and since I met with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e127010" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127020">〈…〉 fight, oh words more worth than gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127030">〈◊〉, oh my 〈…〉 arms I here unfold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127040">To clasp thy comely corpse withal, twice welcome to thy knight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e127050" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127060">And I enjoyful am no doubt, my Clyomon of thy happy sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e127070" who="A69121-clyomon">
          <speaker>Clyo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127080">〈◊〉 my assured friend, lo how dame fortune favoureth me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127090">This is 〈◊〉 my dear love, whose face so long I wished to see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e127100" who="A69121-clamydes">
          <speaker>Clamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127110">My Clyomon, I am as glad as you yourself to see this day:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e127120" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127130">Well daughter though a stranger yet, welcome to court as I may say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e127140" who="A69121-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127150">And lady as welcome unto me, as if thou wert mine only child. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e127160" who="A69121-neronis">
          <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127170">For this your gracious courtesy, I thank you noble princes mild. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e127180" who="A69121-unassigned">
          <speaker>〈◊〉.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127190">Though strange and unacquainted yet, do make account you welcome are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127200">Your nuptial day as well as mine, I know my father will prepare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e127210" who="A69121-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127220">Yes we are pressed your nuptial day with daughter ours to see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127230">As well as Clyomon's our son, with this his lady fair:</l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127240">Come therefore to our court, that we the same may soon prepare. </l>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127250">For we are pressed throughout our land, for all our peers to send:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A69121-e127260" who="A69121-omnes">
          <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A69121-e127270">Thy pleasure most renowned King, thy servants shall attend. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer xml:id="A69121-e127280">Finis.</trailer>
        <pb facs="33"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A69121"><item xml:id="A69121-clyomon" n="117">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-clyomon</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">117</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-shift" n="75">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-shift</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">75</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-clamydes" n="71">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-clamydes</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">71</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-neronis" n="57">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-neronis</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">57</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-king" n="53">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-king</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">53</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-bryan" n="33">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-bryan</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">33</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-juliana" n="19">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-juliana</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">19</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-queen" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-queen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-1_lord" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-1_lord</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-alexander" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-alexander</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-thrasellus" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-thrasellus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-coryn" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-coryn</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-corin" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-corin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-mustantius" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-mustantius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-2_lord" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-2_lord</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-boatswain" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-boatswain</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-lord" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-lord</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-knight" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-knight</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-omnes" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-omnes</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-unassigned" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-ambo" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-ambo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-page" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-page</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-provi" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-provi</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-knowledge" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-knowledge</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-1_knight" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-1_knight</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-both" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-both</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A69121-all" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A69121-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

