<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1 Love's Adventures<date type="creation_date">1662</date></title>
        <author>Cavendish, Margaret</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nayoon Ahn</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A53060_01.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>356 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">11861873</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing N868.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">50022</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53060</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
            <author>Newcastle, William Cavendish, 1592-1676.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[24], 679 [i.e. 675], [4] p. : ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by A. Warren, for John Martyn, James Allestry, and Tho. Dicas ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1662.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>First edition.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Errata: p. [4] at end.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A53060_01-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A53060_01-e100020">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A53060_01-e100030">
        <pb facs="13"/>
        <pb facs="13" n="1"/>
        <div type="introduction" xml:id="A53060_01-e100040">
          <head>An introduction.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e100050">Enter 3. Gentlemen. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100060" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100070">Come Tom will you go to a play?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100080" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100090">No</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100100" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100110">Why?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100120" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100130">Because there is so many words, and so little wit, as the words tire me more than the wit delights me; and most commonly there is but one good part or humour, and all the rest are forced in for to interline that part, or humour;</p>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100140">Likewise not above one or two good actors, the rest are as ill actors as the parts they act, besides their best and principle part or humour is so tedious, that I hate at last what I liked at first, for many times a part is very good to the third act, but continued to the fifth is stark naught.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100150" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100160">The truth is, that in some plays the poets runs so long in one humour, as he runs himself out of breath.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100170" who="A53060_01-yyyy_3">
            <speaker>3. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100180">Not only the poet but the humour he writes of seems to be as broken-winded.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100190" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100200">I have heard of a broken-winded horse, but never heard of a broken-winded poet, nor of a broken-winded play before.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100210" who="A53060_01-yyyy_3">
            <speaker>3. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100220">I wonder why poets will bind themselves, so as to make every humour they write, or present, to run quite through their play.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100230" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100240">Bind say you? they rather give themselves line and liberty, nay they are so far from binding, as for the most part they stretch the line of a humour into pieces.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100250" who="A53060_01-yyyy_3">
            <speaker>3. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100260">Let me tell you, that if any man should write a play wherein he should present an humour in one act, and should not continue it to the end: although it must be stretched, as you say, to make it hold out, he would be condemned, and not only accounted an ill poet, but no poet, for it would be accounted as ill as wanting a rhyme in a copy of verses, or a word too short, or too much in a number, for which a poet is condemned, and for a word that is not spelled right, he is damned for ever.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100270" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100280">Nay, he is only damned if he doth not write strictly to the orthography.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100290" who="A53060_01-yyyy_3">
            <speaker>3. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100300">Scholars only damn writers and poets for orthography, but for the others, they are damned by the generality: that is, not only all readers, but all that are but hearers of the works.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100310" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100320">The generality for the most part is not foolishly strict, or rigid as particulars are.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100330" who="A53060_01-yyyy_3">
            <speaker>3. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100340">Yes faith, they are led by one bell-wether like a company of silly sheep.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100350" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <pb facs="14" n="2"/>
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100360">Well, if I were to write a play, I would write the length of a humour according to the strength of the humour and breadth of my wit. Let them judge me and condemn as they would; for though some of the past, and present ages be erroneously or maliciously foolish in such cases; yet the future ages may be more wise, and better natured as to applaud what the others have condemned.</p>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100370">But prithee Tom let us go.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100380" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100390">No, I will not go for the reasons before mentioned, which is, they tire me with their empty words, dull speeches, long parts, tedious acts, ill actors; and the truth is, there's not enough variety in an old play to please me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100400" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100410">There is variety of that which is bad, as you have divided it, but it seems you love youth and variety in plays, as you do in mistresses.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100420" who="A53060_01-yyyy_3">
            <speaker>3. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100430">Plays delights amorous men as much as a mistress doth.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100440" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100450">Nay, faith more, for a man and his mistress is soon out of breath in their discourse, and then they know not what to say, and when they are at a nonplus, they would be glad to be quit of each other, yet are ashamed to part so soon, and are weary to stay with each other long, when a play entertains them with love, and requires not their answers, nor forceth their brains, nor pumps their wits; for a play doth rather fill them than empty them.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100460" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100470">Faith most plays doth rather fill the spectators with wind, than with substance, with noise, than with news;</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100480" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100490">This play that I would have you go to, is a new play.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100500" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100510">But is there news in the play, that is (Is there new wit, fancies, or new scenes) and not taken our of old stories, or old plays newly translated.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100520" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100530">I know not that, but this play was writ by a lady, who on my conscience hath neither language, nor learning, but what is native and natural.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100540" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100550">A woman write a play!</p>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100560">Out upon it; out upon it, for it cannot be good, besides you say she is a lady, which is the likelier to make the play worse, a woman and a lady to write a play; fie, fie.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100570" who="A53060_01-yyyy_3">
            <speaker>3. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100580">Why may not a lady write a good play?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100590" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100600">No, for a woman's wit is too weak and too conceived to write a play.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100610" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100620">But if a woman hath wit, or can write a good play, what will you say then.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100630" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100640">Why, I will say nobody will believe it, for if it be good, they will think she did not write it, or at least say she did not, besides the very being a woman condemns it, were it never so excellent and care, for men will not allow women to have wit, or we men to have reason, for if we allow them wit, we shall lose our pre-eminence.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100650" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100660">If you will not go Tom, farewell; for I will go set this play, let it be good, or bad.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100670" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100680">Nay stay, I will go with thee, for I am contented to cast away so much time for the sake of the sex. Although I have no saith of the authoress's wit.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e100690" who="A53060_01-yyyy_3">
            <speaker>3. Gentleman. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e100700">Many a reprobate hath been converted and brought to repentance by hearing a good sermon, and who knows but that you may be converted from your erroneous opinion; by seeing this play, and brought to confess that a lady may have wit.</p>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A53060_01-e100710">
          <pb facs="14" n="3"/>
          <head>Love's adventures. Play.</head>
          <list xml:id="A53060_01-e100720">
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100730">The lord fatherly. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100740">The lord singularity. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100750">His son. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100760">Sir serious Dumbe. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100770">Sir Timothy compliment. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100780">Sir Humphrey bold. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100790">Sir Roger exception. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100800">Sir peaceable studious. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100810">Foster trusty. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100820">The lady orphan. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100830">The lady ignorant wife to sir peaceable studious. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100840">The lady bashful. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100850">The lady wagtail. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100860">The lady amorous. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100870">Mrs. acquaintance. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100880">Nurse Hondly foster trusties wise.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100890">Lady orphan's nurse.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100900">Mrs. reformers woman to the lady bashful. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_01-e100910">Two chambermaids.</item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div type="prologue" xml:id="A53060_01-e100920">
          <head>Prologue.</head>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e100930">Noble spectators, you are come to see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e100940">A play, if good, perchance may clapped be;</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e100950">And yet our authoress says that she hath heard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e100960">Some plays, though good, hath not been so preferred;</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e100970">As to be mounted up on high raised praise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e100980">And to be crowned with garlands of fresh hayes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e100990">But the contrary have been hissed off,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101000">Out from our stage with many a censuring scoff;</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101010">But afterwards there understanding cleared,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101020">They gave the praise, what they before had jeered. </l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101030">The same she says may to her play befall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101040">And your erroneous censures may recall:</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101050">But all such plays as take not at first sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101060">But afterwards the viewers takes delight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101070">It seems there is more wit in such a play,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101080">Than can be understood in one whole day:</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101090">If for, she is well content for her wit's sake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101100">From ignorance repulses for to take;</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101110">For she had rather want those understanding brains,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_01-e101120">Than that her play should want wits flowing veins. </l>
        </div>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A53060_01-e101130">
          <pb facs="15" n="4"/>
          <head>Act i.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e101140">
            <head>Scene 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e101150">Enter the lord fatherly, and the lord singularity his son.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101160" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101170">Pray, sir, do not force me to marry a child, before you know whether she will prove virtuous, or discreet; when for the want of that knowledge, you may endanger the honour of your line and posterity, with cuckoldry and bastardy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101180" who="A53060_01-fatherly">
              <speaker>Lord fatherly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101190">Son, you must leave that to fortune.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101200" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101210">A wise man, sir, is to be the maker or spoiler of his own fortune.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101220" who="A53060_01-fatherly">
              <speaker>Lord fatherly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101230">Let me tell you son, the wisest man that is, or ever was, may be deceived in the choosing a wife, for a woman is more obscure than nature herself, therefore you must trust to chance, for marriage is a lottery, if you get a prize, you may live quietly and happily.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101240" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101250">But if I light of a blank, as a hundred to one, nay a thousand to one but I shall, which is on a fool or a whore, her follies or adulteries, instead of a praise, will found out my disgrace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101260" who="A53060_01-fatherly">
              <speaker>Lord fatherly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101270">Come, come, she is rich, she is rich.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101280" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101290">Why sir, guilded I horns are most visible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101300" who="A53060_01-fatherly">
              <speaker>Lord fatherly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101310">'Tis better, son, to have a rich whore than a poor whore, but I hope heaven hath made her chaste, and her father being an honourable, honest, and wise man, will breed her virtuously, and I make no question but you will be happy with her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101320" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101330">But sir, pray consider the inequality of our ages, she being but a child, and I at man's estate; by that time she is ready for the marriage bed: I shall be ready for the grave, and youths sharp appetites, will never relish age, wherefore she will seek to please her palate else where.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101340" who="A53060_01-fatherly">
              <speaker>Lord fatherly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101350">Let me tell you, son, should you marry a woman that were as many years older, than she is younger than you; it were a greater hazard, for first old women are more intemperate than young: and being older than the husband, they are apt to be jealous, and being jealous, they grow malicious, and malice seeks revenge, and revenge disgrace, therefore she would cuckold you merely to disgrace you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101360" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101370">On the other side, those women that are married young, cuckolds there husband's fames dishonouring them by their ignorant follies, and childish indiscretions, as much as with adultery. And I should as soon choose to be a cuckold, as to be thought to be one: for my honour will suffer as much by the one as the other, if not more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101380" who="A53060_01-fatherly">
              <speaker>Lord fatherly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101390">Heaven bless thee, son, from jealousy, for thou art horrible afraid of being a cuckold.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101400" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101410">Can you blame me, sir, since to be a cuckold is to be despised, scorned, laughed, and pointed at, as a monster worse than nature ever made, and all the honour that my birth gave me and my education endued me,<pb facs="15" n="5"/> my virtue gained me, my industry got me; fortune bestowed on me, and fame enthroned me for: may not only be lost by my wife's adultery, but as I said by her indiscretion, which makes me wonder, how any man that hath a noble soul, dares marry since all his honour lies or lives in the light heels of his wife, which every little passion is apt to kick away, wherefore good sir, let me live a single life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101420" who="A53060_01-fatherly">
              <speaker>Lord fatherly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101430">How son, would you have me consent to extinguish the light of my name, and to pull out the root of my posterity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101440" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101450">Why sir, it were better to lie in dark oblivion, than to have a false light to divulge your disgrace; and you had better pull out the root, than to have a branch of dishonour ingrafted therein:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101460" who="A53060_01-fatherly">
              <speaker>Lord fatherly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101470">All these arguments against marriage is because you would enjoy your mistresses with freedom; fearing you should be disturbed by a wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101480" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101490">That needs not, for I observe, married men takes as much liberty, if not more than bachelors; for bachelors are afraid they should challenge a promise of marriage, and married men are out of that danger.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101500" who="A53060_01-fatherly">
              <speaker>Lord father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101510">Then that is the reason that bachelors court married wives, and married men courts maids; but howsoever son, if all men should be of your mind, there would be no marring nor giving in marriage; but all must be in common.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101520" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101530">That were best sir, for then there could be no adultery committed, or cuckolds made.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101540" who="A53060_01-fatherly">
              <speaker>Lord fatherly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101550">For shame take courage, and be not afraid of a woman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101560" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101570">By heaven sir, I would sooner yield up my life to death, thou venture my honour to a woman's management.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101580" who="A53060_01-fatherly">
              <speaker>Lord father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101590">Well son, I shall not force you with threats or commands to marry against your will and good liking; but I hope heaven will turn your mind towards marriage, and sent thee a loving, virtuous and discreet wife.</p>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e101600">
            <head>Scene 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e101610">Enter the lady Wagtaile, the lady amorous, sir Timothy compliment, sir Humphrey bold, and sir Roger exception.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101620" who="A53060_01-timothy_compliment">
              <speaker>Sir Timothy compliment.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101630">Bright beauty, may I be servant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101640" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101650">If I have any beauty, it was begotten in your eyes. And takes light from your commendations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101660" who="A53060_01-timothy_compliment">
              <speaker>Sir Timothy compliment.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101670">You are lady, the star of your sex.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101680" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101690">No truly, I am but a meteor that soon goeth out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101700" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101710">Prithee sir Timothy compliment, and lady amorous, do not stand prating here, but let us go a broad to some place to devert the time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101720" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101730">Dear wagtail, whether shall we go?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101740" who="A53060_01-timothy_compliment">
              <speaker>Sir Timothy compliment.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101750">Faith let us go to a play.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101760" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101770">Let's go to a tavern.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101780" who="A53060_01-roger_exception">
              <speaker>Sir Roger exception.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101790">What with ladies!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101800" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101810">Why, ladies have been in taverns before now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101820" who="A53060_01-roger_exception">
              <pb facs="16" n="6"/>
              <speaker>Sir Roger exception.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101830">It were as good to carry them to a bawdy-house.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101840" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101850">As good say you, faith now I think of it, better; it were the only place to pass a way idle time. Come ladies shall we go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101860" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101870">Whether?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101880" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101890">To a bawdy-house.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101900" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101910">O sue! sue! Sir Humphrey bold; how wantonly you talk?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101920" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101930">But would you carry us in good earnest to a bawdy-house?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101940" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101950">Why, do you question it, when every house is a secret bawdy-house. Nam! Let me tell you, there be many right worshipful, nay, right honourable, and most noble palaces made bawdy-houses.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101960" who="A53060_01-roger_exception">
              <speaker>Sir Roger exception.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101970">Some perchance that are old and ruinous, and the right owners out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e101980" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e101990">No, some that are new, large, and finely furnished; and the owners stately, proud, scornful, and jeering, living therein.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102000" who="A53060_01-roger_exception">
              <speaker>Sir Roger exception.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102010">They should take heed of jeering, lest they be jeered, and of being scornful, lest they be scorned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102020" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102030">What say you ladies, are you resolved.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102040" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102050">No, no, we will not go with you to such places now; but I will carry you to a young lady whose father is newly dead, and hath left her all his estate; and she is become a great heir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102060" who="A53060_01-roger_exception">
              <speaker>Sir Roger exception.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102070">Perchance lady she will not receive our visit, if her father be newly dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102080" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102090">I perceive you are ignorant of funeral customs, for widows, heirs, and heiresses receives visits whilst the corpses lies above ground: and they will keep them so much the longer, to have so many more visitants: nay, sometimes they will keep them so long, as there dissembling is perceived, or so long as they stink above ground; for if they bury not the corpses and set empty coffins for want of embalming, their miserableness will stench up the nostrils of their vanity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102100" who="A53060_01-roger_vanity">
              <speaker>Sir Roger Vanity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102110">Nay by your savour lady, there are some that are buried whilst they are steaming hot.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102120" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102130">Those are only such whose executors, widows, or widowers, sears they may revive again, and rather than that they should do so, they will bury them alive.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102140" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102150">You say rightly true, sir Humphrey bold. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102160" who="A53060_01-timothy_compliment">
              <speaker>Sir Timothy compliment.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102170">Sweet beauties, let us go to see this rich heiress.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102180" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102190">Content.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102200" who="A53060_01-roger_exception">
              <speaker>Sir Roger exception.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102210">But ladies are you acquainted with her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102220" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102230">O no! but you may know that all women rather than want visits, they will go to those they never saw, nor spoke to: but only hears of them; and where they live, and I can direct the coachman to this lady's lodging, wherefore let us go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102240" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102250">I shall not deny to visit a rich heiress.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102260" who="A53060_01-roger_exception">
              <speaker>Sir Roger exception.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102270">I shall wait upon you ladies, but —</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102280" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102290">Nay, never make butts, but let's go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102300" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102310">Pray let us call sir serious dumb, to go along with us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102320" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102330">Faith amorous you love his company, because he can tell no tales.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102340" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102350">Pray call him not, but let him alone: for I dare swear he is inventing of some useless and foolish art.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102360" who="A53060_01-timothy_compliment">
              <speaker>Sir Timothy compliment.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102370">Is he so inventive say you, but if his inventions is useless, he invents in vain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102380" who="A53060_01-roger_exception">
              <pb facs="16" n="7"/>
              <speaker>Sir Roger exception.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102390">Why may not a dumb man's inventions be as good as a blind, for the most usefullest arts were invented, as the learned saith, by one born blind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102400" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102410"> methinks a dumb man should not have much wit, for by my troth one that is dumb seems to me like a fool; nay, one that speaks but little: I cannot for my life but condemn him, or her for an ass.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102420" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102430">He may be a fool, although he may chance to light on some inventions; for arts are oftener produced from chance than wit, but let us go and leave him.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e102440">Lady Wagtaile whispers to sir H. bold. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102450" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102460">Faith sir Humphrey bold, we must call him, or otherwise my friend amorous will be out of humour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102470" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102480">Doth she love silence so well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102490" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102500">No, no, it is that she loves secrecy so well.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e102510">Exit.</stage>
              <lg type="chorus" xml:id="A53060_01-e102520">
                <head>Chorus.</head>
                <l xml:id="A53060_01-e102530">In a minute's time is flown</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_01-e102540">From a child, to woman grown;</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_01-e102550">Some will smile, or laughing say;</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_01-e102560">This is but a foolish play;</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_01-e102570">By reason a comedy, should of one days' action be,</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_01-e102580">Let them laugh and so will I</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_01-e102590">At there great simplicity;</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_01-e102600">I as other poets brings</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_01-e102610">Several nations, subjects, Kings</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_01-e102620">All to act upon one stage,</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_01-e102630">So several times in one age. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e102640">
            <head>Scene 3.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e102650">Enter the lady orphan, and mrs. Acquaintance.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102660" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Mistriss acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102670">How do you know the lord singularity is such a gallant man? For he hath been out of the kingdom this 7. years; wherefore, you could have no acquaintance, you being yet very young.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102680" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102690">Although I have no acquaintance by sight, or experienced knowledge; yet by report I have: for I remembered I heard my father say, he was the honour of the age, the glory of our nation; and a pattern for all mankind to take a sample from, and that his person was answerable to his merits, for he said he was a very handsome man, of a masculine presence, a courtly garb, and affable and courteous behaviour; and that his wit was answerable ●● his merits, person, and behaviour, as that he had a quick wit, a solid judgement, a ready tongue and a smooth speech.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102700" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102710">And did your father proffer you to be his wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102720" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102730">Yes, and I remember my father sighing said, he should have died in peace, and his soul would have rested in quiet, if he had been pleased to have accepted of me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102740" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <pb facs="17" n="8"/>
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102750">When did your father proffer you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102760" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102770">When I was but a child:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102780" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102790">He is not married, and therefore he may chance to accept of you now, if you were proffered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102800" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102810">That were but to be refused again, for I hear he is resolved never to marry, and it will be a greater disgrace to be refused now I am grown to woman's estate, than when I was but a child, besides my father is dead, and my marring can give him no content in the grave; unless his soul could view the world and the several actions therein.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102820" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102830">So, is his father dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102840" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102850">Yes, and I hear that is the cause he cares not to return into his native country.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102860" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102870">I have a friend that hath his picture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102880" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102890">Is it a he or a she friend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102900" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Lady acquaintance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102910">A she friend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102920" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102930">Pray be so much my friend, as to get your friends consent to show me the picture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102940" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102950">Perchance I may get it to view it myself, but I shall never persuade her to lend it you, jealousy will forbid her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102960" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102970">She hath no cause to fear me, for I am not one to make an amorous Mrs. and I have heard he will never marry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e102980" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e102990">That is all one; woman hath hopes as much as fears, or doubts whatever men doth vow for, or against.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103000" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103010">Pray send to her to lend it you, and than you may show it me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103020" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103030">I will try if she will trust me with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103040">Exit.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103050" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan solus.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103060">O heaven, grant that the praise my father gave this lord whilst in the world he lived, prove not as curses to me his child, so grieve his soul with my unhappy life.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103070">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e103080">
            <head>Scene 4.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103090">Enter the lady bashfull, and mrs. Reformer her woman; she being in years. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103100" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Mistriss reformer. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103110">Madam, now you are become a Mrs. of a family, you must learn to entertain visitants, and not be so bashful as you were wont to be, insomuch as you had not confidence to look a stranger in the face, were they never so mean persons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103120" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103130">Alas reformer, it is neither their birth, breeding, wealth, or title, that puts me out of countenance; for a poor cobbler will put me as much out of countenance as a prince; or a poor seamstress, as much as a great lady.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103140" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Mrs. reformer. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103150">What is it then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103160" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103170">Why there are unacustomated faces, and unacquainted humours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103180" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <pb facs="17" n="9"/>
              <speaker>Mrs. reformer. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103190">By this reason, you may be as much out of countenance as an unaccustomed dog, or cat, that you never saw before; or any other beast.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103200" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103210">O no, for mankind is worse natured than boasts, and beasts better natured than men; besides beasts looks not with censuring eyes, nor hears, or listens with inquisitive cares, nor speaks with detracting tongues, nor gives false judgement, or spiteful censures, or slandering reproaches, nor jeers, nor laughs at innocent or harmless errors, nor makes every little mistake a crime.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103220">Enter the lady Bashful's page.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103230" who="A53060_01-page">
              <speaker>Page.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103240">Madam, there is a coachful of gallants alighted at the gate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103250" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103260">For heaven's sake, say I have no desire to be seen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103270" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103280">No, say my lady is full of grief and is not fit to receive visits.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103290">Enter the ladies and gentlemen.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103300">Whereat the lady bashfull stands trembling and shaking, and her eyes being cast to the ground, and her face as pale as death. They speak to reformer. </stage>
            <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103310">Where is the lady bashful, pray gentlewoman tell her we are come to kiss her hands.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103320">Reformer offers to go forth. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103330" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103340">Will you do us the favour old gentlewoman, as to let the lady know we are here.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103350" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103360">If I am not so old as to be insensible, this is she.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103370" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103380">Is this she, alas good lady, she is not well, for surely she hath a fit of an ague upon her, she doth so shake; you should give her a carduus-possit and put her to bed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103390" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103400">Lady, are you sick.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103410">She answers not.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103420" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103430">She is sick indeed, if she be speechless.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103440" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103450">Madam, pray pull up your spirits, and entertain this honourable company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103460" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103470">Why is the defect in her spirits.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103480" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103490">She is young and bashful. —</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103500">They all laugh, except sir Roger exception, and sir serious Dumb.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103510">Ha! ha! she is out of countenance.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103520" who="A53060_01-roger_exception">
              <speaker>Sir Roger exception.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103530">No she is angry, because we are strangers unknown unto her; and she takes it for a rudeness that we are come to visit her, therefore let us be gone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103540" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103550">Let me tell you, it is mere shamefacedness.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103560" who="A53060_01-roger_exception">
              <speaker>Sir Roger exception.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103570">I say no, for those that are angry will shake extremely, and turn as pale as death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103580" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103590">Lady, take courage, and look upon us with a confident brow.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103600"><pb facs="18" n="10"/>All the while sir serious dumb looks on the lady bashfull with sixth eyes. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103610">The lady bashfull offers to speak to the company, but cannot for stuttering; they all laugh again at her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103620" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103630">Lord, madam I will you make yourself ridiculous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103640" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103650">I cannot help it, for my thoughts are consumed in the fiery flame of my blushes; and my words are smothered in the smoke of shame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103660" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103670">O! she speaks, she speaks a little.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103680" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103690">Pray madam leave her at this time, and if you honour her with your company again, she may chance to entertain you with some confidence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103700" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103710">Pray let me and sir Humphrey bold come and visit her once a day, if it be but half an hour at a time, and we shall cure her I warrant thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103720" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103730">I wish she were cured of this imperfection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103740" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphry bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103750">She must marry, she must marry, for there is no cure like a husband, for husbands beget confidence, and their wives are brought a-bed with impudence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103760" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103770">By your favour sir Humphrey bold, marriage must give way or place to courtship, for there are some wives as simply bashful as virgins; but when did you ever see, or know, or hear of courtly lovers, or amorous courtships, to be bashful: their eyes are as piercing as light, and twinkles as stars, and their countenance as confident as day; and the discourses is freer than wind.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103780">He embraces her.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103790" who="A53060_01-humphry_bold">
              <speaker>Sir Humphry bold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103800">And your embraces are wondrous kind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103810" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103820">In troth we women love you men but too well, that is the truth of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103830" who="A53060_01-roger_exception">
              <speaker>Sir Roger exception.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103840">Pray madam let us go, and not stay to anger this young lady as we do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103850" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103860">Farewell friend, sir Humphrey bold and I will visit your lady tomorrow.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103870">As they were all going away, the lady Wagtaile turns back again. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103880" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103890">Pray what may I call your name.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103900" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103910">My name is reformer. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103920" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103930">Good Mrs. reformer, I am heartily glad to see you well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103940" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e103950">I thank you ladyship.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103960">All goeth away but sir serious dumb, and he stays a little time to look upon the lady bashfull, and then goeth out. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103970">Ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e103980">The lady bashfull sola, and after they were all gone she stretches up herself. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e103990" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104000">O in what a torment I have been in; hell is not like it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e104010">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e104020">
            <pb facs="18" n="11"/>
            <head>Scene 5.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e104030">Enter the lady orphan, and mrs. Acquaintance.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104040" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104050">Have you got the picture?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104060" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104070">Yes, but I have seen handsomer men in my opinion than this picture doth represent.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e104080">The lady orphan takes the picture and views it with a steadfast eye. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104090" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104100">I perceive you have no judgement in the original, nor skill in the copy; for this picture is most naturally penciled, the painter hath drawn it so lively. That one may perceive his noble soul to appear through his lovely, and lively countenance; do but observe it well, and you will see as much as I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104110" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104120">That is impossible, unless I had your heart, for though my skill of the copy, or shadow, may be as much as yours, yet my affections to the original is less; which makes my eyes not partial.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104130" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104140">What will the owner take for that picture?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104150" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104160">She will not sell it at any rate:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104170" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104180">I wish she would, for I would buy it at any price.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104190" who="A53060_01-acquaintance">
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104200">She prizes it as highly as you, loving him as much; or well (As you do.)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104210" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104220">How know you that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104230" who="A53060_01-UNASSIGNED">
              <speaker>Mrs. acquaintance. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104240">Because I know she hath given him proofs of her love, which I believe you never did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104250" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104260">You mistake lust for love, ambition, for merit, I love not for the body's sake, but for the soul's pure spirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e104270">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A53060_01-e104280">
          <head>Act ii.</head>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e104290">
            <head>Scene 6.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e104300">Enter two merchants.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104310" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104320">I hear the lord singularity hath given the Turks a great defeat, he is both a wise, prudent, and valiant man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104330" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104340">Methinks our nation should not suffer such a person as he, to hazard his life in the service of other countries.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104350" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104360">O it is an honour to our nation, to let the world know what gallant men it breeds, besides our nation is in peace with all the world; and he being active, hates to live idly, and dully at home, although he have a great estate, and is well beloved in his country.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104370" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104380">What command doth the Venetians give him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104390" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <pb facs="19" n="12"/>
              <speaker>1. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104400">He is a general, for he commands a great army.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104410" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104420">Is he married?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104430" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104440">No, and it is reported he never will marry, but he loves mistresses well, which all soldiers doth for the most part.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104450" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104460">Then Italy is the best country in the world for a soldier, there being the greatest store and most variety of courtesans, for many of the Italians are, as many are in other nations, rather carpet-knights, then fighting soldiers, they have more skill in setting musical notes, than pitching a battle; in kissing a mistress's hand with a good grace, than shooting of a cannon bullet with a great courage; they can take better aim at a window, than of an enemy. And though they often receive wounds, yet they are from fair Venus, not from cruel Mars. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104470" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104480">But Mars soldiers when they skirmish in love's dvels, receives wounds as often from fair Venus, as other men, and Italy hath as many gallant valiant men, bred and born in her, as any other nation; and there are as many carpet-knights in other nations, as in Italy; and if valiant, and gallant men be endued with virtue, they are not the less to be esteemed; and as for courtesans, all nations is stored as much as Italy, but they do not so openly profess it, as those in Italy doth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104490" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104500">For my part, I cannot think they are so good soldiers as they were in Caesar's time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104510" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104520">That may be, for there is no such soldiers as Caesar's soldiers were, no not in the world; that is, there are no men so patient, obedient, careful, industrious, laborious, daring, adventurous, resolute, and active, in these wars, in this age, as the Romans were in Caesar's time; and of all the soldiers, Caesar's soldiers were the best, and of all commanders Caesar himself, yet those warriors was not less courtly to the feminine sex, than these of this age; and if you did talk with an understanding soldier, he would tell you that amours gave an edge to courage, and that it is a mark of a gallant man, and a brave soldier to be an Amarato; and as for the courtesans of Italy, if there can be an honest act in a dishonest life, it is that the courtesans in Italy professes what they are; so that men are, not deceived by them, nor betrayed into marriage; wherein other nations men are cozened with counterfeit modesty, and drawn into marriage by pretended chastity, and then dishonoured by soul adultery, or shamed by marrying a private courtesan, not knowing she was so.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104530" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104540">I perceive by thee, that merchants loves a mistress as well as a soldier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104550" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104560">Surely by thy talk thou art ignorant of thy own profession, which is to trade, and traffic into all nations, and with all sorts; but yet, merchants may be soldiers if they will, and soldiers may be merchants if they please; but the truth is all men in the world are merchants.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104570" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104580">No, beggars are not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104590" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104600">But they are, for they traffic with prayers and praises for alms.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104610" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104620">The best merchants I know are priests, for they trade into heaven; and traffic with Jove. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104630" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Merchant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104640">That makes them so poor, for heaven's commodity are not saleable on earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e104650">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e104660">
            <pb facs="19" n="13"/>
            <head>Scene 7.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e104670">Enter the lady orphan, nurse Fondly, Foster Trusty.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104680" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104690">Dear nurse and foster father, grant to my desires and assist my designs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104700" who="A53060_01-fondly">
              <speaker>Nurse fondly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104710">What to let you wander about the world like a vagabond, besides it is against the modesty of your sex.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104720" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104730">Are holy pilgrims vagabonds, or is it immodest for the bodies of devout souls to travel to the sacred tomb to offer penitential tears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104740" who="A53060_01-fondly">
              <speaker>Nurse fondly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104750">Why, you are no pilgrim, nor is your journey to a godly end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104760" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104770">My journey will be to an honest end, for though I am love's pilgrim, yet I shall travel to an honest heart; there to offer my pure affections.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104780" who="A53060_01-fondly">
              <speaker>Nurse fondly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104790">To a deboist man, there to offer your virginity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104800" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104810">Mistake me not, for though I love beyond a common rate, even to an extreme degree, yet I am chastely honest, and so shall ever be; my grave shall witness my constancy.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e104820">The lady orphan weeping. Ex. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104830" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104840">Beshrew your tongue wife for speaking so sharply to our young lady, she was left to our trust, care, and tender usage, and not to be snapped and quarrelled with.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104850" who="A53060_01-fondly">
              <speaker>Nurse fondly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104860">Yes, and you would betray your trust to her childish folly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104870" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104880">No that I would not, neither would I venture or yield up her life to love's melancholy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104890" who="A53060_01-fondly">
              <speaker>Nurse fondly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104900">Come, come husband, you humour her too much, and that will spoil her I am sure.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e104910">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="8" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e104920">
            <head>Scene 8.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e104930">Enter sir peaceable studious with a book in his hand; a table being set out, whereon is Pen, ink and paper. After he hath walked a turn or two, with his eyes fixed upon the ground, he sits down to the table, and begins to write. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e104940">Enter the lady ignorant his wife. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104950" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104960">Lord husband! I can never have your company, for you are at all times writing, or reading, or turning your globes, or peaking through your prospective glass, or repeating verses, or speaking speeches to yourself.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104970" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <pb facs="20" n="14"/>
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e104980">Why wife, you may have my company at any time, nay, never to be from me if you please, for I am always at home.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e104990" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorant,</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105000">'Tis true, your person is always at home, and fixed to one place, your closet as a dull dead statue to the side of a wall, but your mind and thoughts are always abroad.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105010" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. studious</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105020">The truth is, my mind sometimes sends out my thoughts like coy ducks, to bring more understanding in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105030" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorant,</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105040">You mistake husband, for your thoughts are like vain, or rather like false scouts that deceives your understanding, imprisons your senses, and betrays your life to a dull solitariness.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105050" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105060">'Tis better to live a quiet solitary life, than a troublesome and an uneasy life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105070" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105080">What is a man born for, but to serve his country, side with his friends, and to please the effeminate sex.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105090" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105100">You say right wife, and to serve his country, is to find out such inventions as is useful either in peace or war; and to form, order and settle commonwealths by devizing laws, which none but studious brains e'er did, or can do. 'tis true, practice doth polish beauty and adorn, but neither lays the foundation, nor brings the materials, nor builds the walls thereof; and to side with friends, is to defend right and truth with sound arguments and strong proofs, from the tyrannical usurpation of false opinions, vain phantasines, malicious satires, and flattering oratory, and to please the effeminate sex, is to praise their beauty, wit, virtue and good graces in soft numbers, and smooth language, building up pyramids of poetical praises, printing their fame thereon, by which they live to after-ages.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105110" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105120">Prithee husband mistake us not, for women cares not for wide mouthed fame; and we take more delight to speak ourselves whilst we live, than to be talked of when we are dead, and to take our present pleasures, than to abstain ourselves for after-ages.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105130" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studeous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105140">Well wife, what would you have me do?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105150" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105160">Why, I would have you so sociable, as to sit and discourse with our friends and acquaintance, and play the good fellow amongst them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105170" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105180">What need we to have any other friends than ourselves; our studies, books and thoughts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105190" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105200">Your studies, books and thoughts, are but dull acquaintance, melancholy companions, and weak friends.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105210" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105220">You do not wife consider their worth; for books are conversable, yet silent acquaintance, and study, is a wise counsellor; and kind friends, and poetical thoughts are witty companions, wherein other societies and companies are great inconveniences, and oft-times produces evil effects, as jealousy, adultery, quarrels, duels, and death, besides slanders, backbitings and the like.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105230" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105240">Truly husband, you are strangely mistaken; for those societies as I would have you frequent, doth sing, dance, rally, make balls masks, plays, feasts, and the like, and also makes frolics or rubices, or plays, at questions and commands, purposes or riddles, and twenty such like pastimes and fine sports they have.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105250" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105260">But surely wife you would not like this kind of life, nor I neither; especially if we were in one and the same company; for perchance you may hear wanton songs sung, and see amorous glances, or rude or immodest actions, and when you dance, have a secret nip, and gentle gripe of<pb facs="20" n="15"/> the band silently to declare their amorous affections; and when you are at questions or commands, you will be commanded to kiss the men, or they you, which I shall not like, neither should you; or if they are commanded to pull of your garter, which no chaste and modest woman will suffer, nor no gallant man, or honourable husband will endure to stand by to see, and if you refuse, you disturb the rest of the company, and then the women falls out with you in their own defence, and the men takes it as an affront, and disgrace, by reason none refuses but you; this causes quarrels with strangers, or quarrels betwixt ourselves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105270" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorant,</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105280">'Tis true, if the company were not persons of quality which were civilly bred; but there is no rude actions, or immodest behaviours offered or seen amongst them; besides, if you do not like those sports, you may play at cards or dice to pass away the time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105290" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105300">But wife, let me examine you, have or do you frequent these societies that you speak so knowingly, learnedly and affectionately of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105310" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105320">No otherwise husband, but as I have heard, which reports makes me desire to be acquainted with them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105330" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105340">Well, you shall, and I will bear you company, to be an eye-witness how well you behave yourself, and how you profit thereby.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105350" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105360">Pray husband do, for it will divert you from your too serious studies, and deep thoughts, which feeds upon the health of your body, which will shorten your life; and I love you so well, as I would not have you die, for this I persuade you to, is for your good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105370" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105380">We will try how good it is.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e105390">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="9" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e105400">
            <head>Scene 9.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e105410">Enter nurse Fondley, and Foster Trusty her husband. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105420" who="A53060_01-fondly">
              <speaker>Nurse fondly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105430">How shall I keep your journey secret, but that everybody will know of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105440" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105450">We will give out that such a deep melancholy have seized on her, since her father's death, as she hath made a vow not to see any creature besides yourself for two years; as for me, that I have lived so solitary a life with my solitary master, this lady's father, that I have few or no acquaintance; besides, I will pretend some business into some other parts of the kingdom, and I having but a little estate, few will inquire after me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105460" who="A53060_01-fondly">
              <speaker>Nurse fondly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105470">So in the mean time I must live solitary, all alone, without, my husband, or nurse-child, which child, heaven knows, I love better, than if I had one living of my own.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105480" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105490">I am as fond of her, as you are, and heaven knows, would most willingly sacrifice my old life, could it do her any service.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105500" who="A53060_01-fondly">
              <pb facs="21" n="16"/>
              <speaker>Nurse fondly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105510">But we endanger her life, by the consenting to this journey, for she that hath been bred with tenderness and delicateness, can never endure the colds and heats, the dirt and dust that travellers are subject to; besides, to be disturbed and broken of her sleep, and to have ill lodging, or perhaps none at all, and then to travel a foot like a pilgrim: her tender feet will never endure the hard ground, nor her young legs never able to bear her body so long a journey.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105520" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105530">'Tis true, this journey may very much incommode her, yet if she doth not go to satisfy her mind, I cannot perceive any hopes of life, but do foresee her certain death; for her mind is so restless, and her thoughts works so much upon her body, as it begins to waste, for she is become lean and pale.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105540" who="A53060_01-fondly">
              <speaker>Nurse fondly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105550">Well! heaven bless you both, and prosper your journey, but pray let me hear often from you, for I shall be in great frights and fears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105560" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105570">If we should write, it may chance to discover us, if our letters should be opened, wherefore you must have patience.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e105580">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="10" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e105590">
            <head>Scene 10.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e105600">Enter the lady bashfull, and reformer her woman. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105610" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105620">Reformer, I am little beholding to you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105630" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105640">Why madam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105650" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105660">Why, you might have told a lie for me once in your life, for if you had not spoke the truth by saying I was the lady, they came to see; they would never have guest I had been she, for they expected me to have been a free bold entertainer, as they were visitors, which is, as I do perceive, to be rudely familiar at first sight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105670" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105680">But to have told a lie, had been to commit a sin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105690" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady, bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105700">In my conscience to please the effeminate sex, is to praise their beauty, wit, virtue and goa most pious and charitable act in helping the distressed; besides, you had not only helped a present distress, but released a whole life out of misery; for as long as I live my thoughts will torment me: o! they wound my very soul already, they will hinder my pious devotions; for when I pray, I shall think more of my bashful behaviour, and the disgrace I have received thereby, than of heaven; besides, they will starve me, not suffering the meat to go down my throat, or else to choke me, causing it to go awry, or else they will cause a fever; for in my conscience I shall blush even in my sleep, if I can sleep; for certainly I shall dream of my disgrace, which will be as bad as a waking memory: o! that I had opium, I would take it, that I might forget all things; for as long as I have memory, I shall remember my simple behaviour, and as for my page, he shall go, I am resolved to turn him away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105710" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105720">Why madam?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105730" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105740">Because he let them come in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105750" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105760">He could not help it, for they followed him at the heels, they<pb facs="21" n="17"/> they never stayed for an answer from you, or to know whether you were within or no, and there were a great many of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105770" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105780">I think there was a legion of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105790" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105800">You speak as if they were a legion of angels.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105810" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105820">Nay, they proved a legion of devils to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105830" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105840">There was one that seemed to be a fine gentleman, but he spoke not a word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105850" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105860">They may be all what you will make them, or describe them, for I could make no distinction whether they were men or women, or beasts nor herd no articulated sound, only a humming noise.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105870" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105880">They spoke loud enough to have pierced your ears, if strength of noise could have done it, but the gentleman that did not speak, looked so earnestly at you, as if he would have looked you through.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105890" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful,</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105900">O that his eyes had that piercing faculty, for then perchance he might have seen; I am not so simple as my behaviour made me appear.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e105910">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="11" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e105920">
            <head>Scene 11.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e105930">Enter sir peaceable studious, and the lady ignorance his wife. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105940" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir peaceable studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105950">I have lost 500. pounds since you went in with the ladies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105960" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105970">500. Pounds in so short a time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e105980" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e105990">'Tis well I lost no more: but yet, that 500. pounds would have bought you a new coach, or bed, or silver plate, or cabinets, or gowns, or fine flanders-laces, and now it's gone, and we have no pleasure nor credit for it, but it is no matter, I have health for it, therefore I will call to my stewards to bring me some more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106000" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106010">No, do not so, for after the rate you have lost, you will lose all your estate in short time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106020" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106030">Faith let it go, 'tis but begging or starving after it is gone, for I have no trade to live by, unless you have a way to get a living, have you any.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106040" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106050">No truly husband, I am a shiftless creature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106060" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106070">Yes, but you may play the whore, and I the shark, so live by cozening and cheating.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106080" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106090">Heaven defend husband.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106100" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106110">Or perchance some will be so charitable to give us sucked bones from stinking breathes, and rotten teeth, or greasy scraps from fowl hands; but go wife, prithee bid my steward send me 500. pounds more, or let it alone, I will run on the score, and pay my losings at a lump.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106120" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106130">No dear husband, play no more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106140" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106150">How! not play any more say you, shall I break good company with sitting out; besides, it is a question whether I have power to leave off, now I have once begun; for play is witchcraft, it enchants temperance, prudence, patience, reason and judgement, and it kicks away time, and bids him<pb facs="22" n="18"/> go as an old bald-pated fellow as he is, also it chains the life with fears, cares and griefs of losing to a pair of cards and set of dice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106160" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106170">For heaven's sake pity me! If you consider not yourself.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106180" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious:</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106190">Can you think a husband considers his wife, when he forgets, or regards not himself, when all love is self-love, for a man would have his wife to be loving and chaste for his honour's sake, to be thrifty for his profit's sake, to be patient for quiet sake, to be cleanly, witty and beautiful for his pleasure's sake, and being thus, he loves her; for if she be false, unkind, prodigal, froward sluttish, foolish, and ill-favoured, he hates her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106200" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106210">But if a husband loves his wife, he will be careful to please her, prudent for her, subsistence, industrious for her convenience, valiant to protect her, and conversable to entertain her, and wise to direct and guide her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106220" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106230">To rule and govern her, you mean wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106240" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106250">Yes, but a husband's follies will be but corrupt tutors, and ill examples for a wife to follow; wherefore dear husband, play no more, but come amongst the effeminate society, you will find more pleasure at less charges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106260" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106270">Well wife, you shall persuade me for this time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106280" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106290">I thank you husband.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e106300">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="12" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e106310">
            <head>Scene 12.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e106320">Enter the lady orphan, and Foster Trusty, as two pilgrims.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106330" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106340">My child, you were best sit and rest yourself, you cannot choose but be very weary, for we have travelled a great journey today.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106350" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106360">Truly I am as fresh, and my spirits are as lively, as if I had not trod a step today.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106370" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106380">I perceive love can work miracles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106390" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106400">Are not you father a weary?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106410" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106420">It were a shame for me to be weary, when you are not; but my child, we must change these pilgrims weeds, when we are out of our own country; as when we are in Italy, otherwise we cannot pretend to stay in the Venetian army, but must travel as pilgrims do to Jerusalem: but it were best we put ourselves into beggars garments until we come into the army, for fear we should be striped by thieves; for I have heard, thieves will strip travellers, if their clothes be not all rags.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106430" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106440">'Tis true, and thieves as I have heard, will rob pilgrims soonest, finding many good pillage, wherefore we will accoutre ourselves like to ragged beggars.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e106450">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A53060_01-e106460">
          <pb facs="22" n="19"/>
          <head>Act iii.</head>
          <div n="13" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e106470">
            <head>Scene 13.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e106480">Enter the lady bashfull, as in a melancholy humour, and reformer her woman. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106490" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106500">Lord madam! I hope you are not seriously troubled for being out of countenance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106510" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106520">Yes truly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106530" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106540">What? as to make you melancholy!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106550" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106560">Yes, very melancholy, when I think I have made myself a scorn, and hath endangered my reputation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106570" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106580">Your reputation! Heaven bless you, but your life is so innocent, harmless, chaste, pure and sweet, and your actions so just and honest, as all the devils in hell cannot endanger your reputation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106590" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106600">But spiteful tongues, which are worse than devils, may hurt my reputation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106610" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106620">But spite cannot have any thing to say.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106630" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106640">Spite will lie, rather than not speak, for envy is the mother to spite, and slander is the midwife.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106650" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106660">Why, what can they say?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106670" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106680">They will say I am guilty of some immodest act, or at least thoughts, or else of some heinous and horrid crime, otherwise I could not be ashamed, or out of countenance, if I were innocent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106690" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106700">They cannot say ill, or think ill, but if they could, and did, what are you the worse, as long as you are innocent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106710" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106720">Yes truly, for I desire to live in a pure esteem, and an honourable respect in every breast, and to have a good report spoke on me, since I deserve no other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106730" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106740">There is an old saying, that opinion travels without a passport, and they that would have every ones good opinion, must live in every man's age: but I am very confident, there is none lives or dies without censures, or detraction; even the gods themselves, that made man, hath given man power and free will to speak, at least to think what they will; that makes so many atheists in thought, and so many several factions by disputation, and since the gods cannot, or will not be free from censures, why should you trouble yourself with what others say, wherefore pray put off this indiscreet and troublesome humour, for if you would not regard censure, you would be more confident.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106750" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106760">I will do what I can to mend.</p>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="14" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e106770">
            <pb facs="23" n="20"/>
            <head>Scene 14.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e106780">Enter the lady orphan, and Foster Trusty, like two poor beggars. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106790" who="A53060_01-foster">
              <speaker>Foster.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106800">Child, you must beg of every one that comes by, otherwise we shall not seem right beggars.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106810" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106820">If our necessities were according to our outward appearance, we were but in a sad condition; for I shall never get any thing by begging, for I have neither learned the tone, nor the beggar's phrase to more pity or charity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106830" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106840">Few beggars move pity, they get more by importunity, than by their oratory, or the giver's charity.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e106850">Enter 2. Gentlemen. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e106860">She goeth to them and begs.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106870" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106880">Noble gentlemen, pity the shiftless youth, and infirm old age that hath no means to live, but what compassionate charity will bestow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106890" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106900">You are a young boy, and may get your living by learning to work.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106910" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106920">But my father being very old, is past working, and I am so young, as I have not arrived to a learning degree of age, and by that time I have learned to get my living, my father may be starved for want of food.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106930" who="A53060_01-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2. Gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106940">Why, your father may beg for himself whilst you learn to work.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106950" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106960">My father's feeble legs can never run after the flying speed of pitiless hearts, nor can he stand so long to wait for conscience aims, nor knock so hard to make devotion hear.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106970" who="A53060_01-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1. Gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e106980">I perceive you have learned to beg well, though not to work, and because you shall know my devotion is not deaf, there is something for your father and you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e106990" who="A53060_01-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2. Gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107000">Nay, faith boy, thou shalt have some of the scraps of my charity to, there is for thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107010" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107020">Heaven bless you; and grant to you, all your good desires.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e107030">Gentlemen ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e107040">Enter a lady and servants.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107050" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107060">Honourable lady, let the mouth of necessity suck the breast of your charity to feed the hungry beggars.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107070" who="A53060_01-lady">
              <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107080">Away you rogue, a young boy and beg! You should be striped, whipped, and set to work.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107090" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107100">Alas madam, naked poverty is always under the lash of misery, which forceth us to work in the quarries of stony hearts, but we find the mineral so hard, as we cannot get out enough to build up a livelihood.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107110" who="A53060_01-lady">
              <pb facs="23" n="21"/>
              <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107120">Employ yourselves upon some other work then.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e107130">Lady ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e107140">Enter a mean tradesman.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107150" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107160">Good sir relieve a poor beggar.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107170" who="A53060_01-trades-man">
              <speaker>Tradesman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107180">Faith boy, I am so poor, as I want relief myself; yet of what I have, thou shalt share with me; there is a penny of my two pence, which is all I have, and heaven do thee good with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e107190">Tradesman exit.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107200" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107210">I perceive poverty pities poverty, as feeling the like misery, where riches is cruel, and hard-hearted, not knowing what want is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107220" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107230">I perceive wit can work upon every thing, and can form itself into what shape it please, and thy wit plays the beggar so well, as we needed not to have stored ourselves from our own stocks, but have lived upon the stocks of others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107240" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107250">But if all stocks were as insipid as the ladies, we should have starved, if we had not brought sap from our own home; but father, I am weighed down with the penny the poor tradesman gave me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107260" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107270">Why, it is not so heavy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107280" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107290">It is so heavy, as it burdens my conscience, and I shall never be at ease, not be able to travel any farther, until I have restored the penny to the giver again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107300" who="A53060_01-foster_nurse">
              <speaker>Foster nurse.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107310">How should we do that, for it is as hard and difficult to find out that man, as to find out the first cause of effects.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107320" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107330">Well, I will play the philosopher, and search for him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107340" who="A53060_01-foster_nurse">
              <speaker>Foster nurse.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107350">But if you should meet him, perchance you will not know he was he.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107360" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107370">O yes, for his extraordinary charity made me take particular notice of him.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e107380">Enter the tradesman as returning back.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107390" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107400">Most charitable and —</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107410" who="A53060_01-trades-man">
              <speaker>Tradesman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107420">What boy, wouldst thou have the other penny,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107430" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107440">Most noble sir, I have received from a bountiful hand, a sum of money, and since you were so charitable to divide the half of your store to me, so I desire I may do the like to you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107450" who="A53060_01-trades-man">
              <speaker>Tradesman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107460">No boy, keep it for thyself, and thy old father; I have a trade, and shall get more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107470" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107480">Pray take it for luck-sake, otherwise I shall never thrive.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107490" who="A53060_01-trades-man">
              <speaker>Tradesman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107500">Faith I find boy, thou art not as most of the world are; the more riches they get, the more covetous they grow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107510" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107520">Sir, pray take this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107530" who="A53060_01-trades-man">
              <speaker>Tradesman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107540">What do you give me here, a piece of gold?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107550" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107560">Yes sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107570" who="A53060_01-trades-man">
              <speaker>Tradesman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107580">That were extortion, to take a pound for a penny.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107590" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107600">No, it is not extortion, since I can better space this pound now, than you could your penny, when you gave it me; wherefore it is but justice,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107610" who="A53060_01-trades-man">
              <speaker>Tradesman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107620">Well, I will keep it for thee, and when you want it, come to<pb facs="24" n="22"/> me again, and you shall have it: I live in the next street, at the sign of the Holy-lamb. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107630" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107640">Pray make use of it, for I may chance never to see you more.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e107650">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="15" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e107660">
            <head>Scene 15.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e107670">Enter sir studious and the lady ignorance his wife. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107680" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107690">Faith wife, with sipping of your gossiping-cups, I am half drunk.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107700" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107710">Lord husband! There were some of the ladies that drank twice as much as you did, and were not drunk, and to prove they were not drunk, was that they talked as much before they drunk, as after; for there was such a confusion of words, as they could not understand each other, and they did no more, when they had drunk a great quantity of wine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107720" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107730">That was a sign they were drunk, that they talked less, but how chance that you drank so little.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107740" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107750">Truly, wine is so nauseous to my taste, and so hateful to my nostrils, as I was sick when the cup was brought to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107760" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107770">I know not what it was to you, but to me it was pleasant, for your ladies were so gamesome, merry and kind, as they have fired me with amorous love ever since.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e107780">Enter the lady Ignoranc's maid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107790" who="A53060_01-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107800">Madam, the lady wagtail, and other ladies, have sent to know if your ladyship were within, that they might come and wait upon you.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e107810">Sir peaceable studious chucks the maid under the chin, and kisses her.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107820" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. studious</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107830">Faith Nan, thou art a pretty wench.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107840" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107850">What husband? Do you kiss my maid before my face.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107860" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107870">Why not wife, as well as one of your sociable ladies in a frolic, as you kiss me, I kiss Nan. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107880" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107890">So, and when Nan kisses your barber, he must kiss me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107900" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107910">Right, this is the kissing frolic, and then comes the striking frolic, for you strike Nan, Nan gently strikes me, and I justly beat you, and end the frolics with a —</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e107920">Enter the lady Wagtail, and other ladies of the society, with the lady amorous.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107930" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107940">What? A man and his wife dully alone together! Fie for shame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107950" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107960">Lawful love is the dullest and drowsiest companion that is, for wives are never thought fair, nor husbands witty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107970" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <pb facs="24" n="23"/>
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e107980">Your ladyship is learned in love's societies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e107990" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108000">Yes that I am, for I have observed, that if there be a matched company, every man having a woman, their conversation is dull, every man's tongue whispering in his mistress ear, whilst the women are mute, listening to that which is whispered unto them; but let there be but one man amongst a company of women, and then their tongues runs races, striving with each other, which shall catch that one man, as the only prize, when the weaker wits runs themselves straight out of breath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108010" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108020">And must not one man run against them all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108030" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108040">O yes? and many times his wit beats them all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108050" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108060">Faith lady? They must not be such strong winded wits as yours is, which is able to beat a dozen masculine wits out of the field.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108070" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108080">You are pleased to give me a compliment.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e108090">The lady ignorance seems melancholy.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108100" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108110">The merry God have mercy on you? What makes you so melancholy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108120" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108130">I am not well today.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108140" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108150">If you are troubled with melancholy vapours, arising from crude humours, you must take as soon as you wake after your first sleep, a draught of wormwood-wine, then lie to sleep again, and then half an hour before you rise, drink a draught of jelly-broth, and after you have been up an hour and half, eat a white-wine-caudle, than a little before a dinner, take a toast and sack, and at your meals, two or three good glasses of claret-wine; as for your meats, you must eat those of light digestion, as pheasant, partridges, cocks, snipes, chickens, young turkeys, pea-chickens and the like; and in the afternoon, about four or five o'clock , you must take naples-biscuit dipped in hippocrase, which helps digestion much, and revives the spirits, and makes one full of discourse, and not only to discourse, but to discourse wittily, and makes one such good company, as invites acquaintance, and ties friendship.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e108160">The whilst the lady Wagtail talks to the lady ignorance, the eyes her husband, who seems to court the lady amorous.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108170" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108180">Faith I will tell your wife what you say.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108190" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108200">That is fowl play, and not done like one of the society, especially when my lady is not well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108210" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108220">What? Is she sick! I lay my life she hath eat too much bran sturgeon, or salmon without muskadine or sack, or neats-tongues, bacon and anchoves, caviar, or lobsters, without rhenish-wines, or oysters, or sausages without claret-wine, or hath she eaten potatoe-pies without dates, ringo-roots, marrow and chestnuts, have you not? I saith confess.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108230" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108240">No indeed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108250" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108260">Why? I hope you have not taken a surfeit of white-meats, those childish meats, or with water-gruel, pomado, barley-gruel, those hodge-podgely meats.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108270" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108280">Neither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108290" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108300">Why, than you have overheated yourself with dancing<pb facs="25" n="24"/> or fretting and vexing yourself at your ill fortune at cards; or your tailor hath spoilt some gown, or your coachman was out of the way when you would go abroad; is it not so.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108310" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108320">No.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108330" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108340">Why? Then your husband hath crossed some design, or hath angered you some other way.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e108350">The lady ignorance blushes. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e108360">They all laugh, and speak at one time; she blushes, she blushes.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108370" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108380">Faith amorous, thou hast found it out! Sir peaceable studious you are to be chidden to anger your wife; wherefore tell us how you did anger her, when you did anger her, and for what you did anger her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108390" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108400">Dear, sweet, fine, fair ladies! be not so cruel to me, as to lay my wife's indisposition to my charge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108410" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108420">But we will, and we will draw up an accusation against you, unless you confess, and ask pardon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108430" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108440">Will you accuse me without a witness?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108450" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108460">Yes, and condemn you too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108470" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108480">That were unjust! if ladies could be unjust.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108490" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108500">O madam! we have a witness? her blushing is a sufficient witness to accuse him; besides, her melancholy silence will help to condemn him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108510" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108520">Pardon me ladies, for when any of our sex are offended, or angered, whether they have cause or not, they will rail louder than Jove's thunder.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108530" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108540">So will you in time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108550" who="A53060_01-wagtail">
              <speaker>Lady wagtail.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108560">Let us jumble her abroad; come madam! we will put you out of your dull humour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108570" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108580">No madam? Pray excuse me today; in truth I am not well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108590" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108600">No, let us let my lady alone, but let us take her husband, and tutor him</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108610" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108620">Ladies, give me leave to praise myself, and let myself, and let me tell you? I am as apt a scholar, as ever you met with, and as willing to learn.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108630" who="A53060_01-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108640">Farewell madam, we will order sir P. Studious, and try what disposition he is of, and how apt to be instructed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108650" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108660">Pray do madam, he promiseth well.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e108670">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="16" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e108680">
            <head>Scene 16:</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e108690">Enter Foster Trusty, and the lady orphan.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108700" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108710">Now we are come into the army, how shall we demean ourselves like poor beggars.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108720" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108730">By no means, for though you beg well, yet you will never get<pb facs="25" n="25"/> what you come for with begging, for there is an old saying, that although all charity is love, yet all love is not charity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108740" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108750">It were the greatest charity in the world, for him to love me; for without his love, I shall be more miserable than poverty can make me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108760" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108770">But poverty is so scorned and hated, that no person is accepted which she presents; nay, poverty is shunned more than the plague.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108780" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108790">Why? it is not infectious.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108800" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108810">Yes faith, for the relieving of necessity, is the way to be impoverished.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108820" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108830">But their rewards are the greater in heaven.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108840" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108850">'Tis true, but their estates are less on earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108860" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108870">But blessings are more to be desired than wealth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108880" who="A53060_01-foster_nurse">
              <speaker>Foster trusty,</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108890">Well? Heaven bless us, and send us such fortune, that our long journey may prove successful, and not profitless, and because heaven never gives blessings, unless we use a prudent industry; you shall put yourself into good clothes, and I will mix myself with his followers and servants, and tell them, as I may truly, that you are my son, for no man's son but mine you are, was so importunate, as you would never let me rest, until I brought you to see the lord singularity, and they will tell him, to let him know his fame is such, as even young children adore him, taking a pilgrimage to see him, and he out of a vainglory will desire to see you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108900" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108910">But what advantage shall I get by that.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e108920">Enter the lord singularity, and many commanders attending him. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108930" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108940">Peace! here is the general.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108950" who="A53060_01-commander">
              <speaker>Commander.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108960">The enemy is so beaten, as now they will give us some time to breathe ourselves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108970" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e108980">They are more out of breath than we are, but the states are generous enemies, if they give them leave to fetch their wind, and gather strength again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e108990" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109000">Father, stand you by, and let me speak.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e109010">She goeth to the general, and speaks to him.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e109020">Heaven bless your excellency.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109030" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>Lord general.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109040">From whence comest thou boy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109050" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lord Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109060">From your native country.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109070" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109080">Camest thou lately?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109090" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109100">I am newly arrived.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109110" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109120">Pray how is my country, and countrymen, live they still in happy peace, and flourishing with plenty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109130" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109140">There is no noise of war, or fear of famine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109150" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109160">Pray Jove continue it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109170" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109180">It is likely so to continue, unless their pride and luxury be gets a factious child, that is born with war, and fed with ruin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109190" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109200">Do you know what faction is?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109210" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109220">There is no man that lives, and feels it not, the very thoughts are factious in the mind, and in rebellious passions arises warring against the soul.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109230" who="A53060_01-general">
              <pb facs="26" n="26"/>
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109240">Thou canst not speak thus by experience boy, thou art too young, not yet a man's estate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109250" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady orphan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109260">But children have thoughts, and said to have a rational soul, as much as those that are grown up to men; but if souls grow as bodies doth, and thoughts increases with their years, then may the wars within the mind be like to schoolboys' quarrels, that falls out for a toy, and for a roy are friends.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109270" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109280">Thou speakest like a tutor, what boyish thoughts soever thou hast; but tell me boy? what madest thee travel so great a journey.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109290" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109300">For to see you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109310" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109320">To see me boy!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109330" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109340">Yes, to see you sir; for the trumpet of your praise did sound so loud, it struck my ears, broke open my heart, and let desire forth, which restless grew until I travelled hither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109350" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109360">I wish I had merits to equal thy weary steps, or means for to reward them:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109370" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109380">Your presence hath sufficiently rewarded me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109390" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109400">Could I do thee my service boy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109410" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109420">A bounteous favour you might do me sir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109430" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109440">What is that boy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109450" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109460">To let me serve you, sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109470" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109480">I should be ingrateful to refuse thee, choose thy place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109490" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109500">Your page, sir, if you please.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109510" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109520">I accept of thee most willingly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109530" who="A53060_01-captain">
              <speaker>Captain.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109540">But sir? may not this boy be a lying, cozening, flattering dissembling, treacherous boy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109550" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109560">Why captain, there is no man that keeps many servants, but some are liars, and some treacherous, and all flatterers; and a master receives as much injury from each particular, as if they were joined in one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109570" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109580">I can bring none that will witness for my truth, or be bound for my honesty, but my own words.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109590" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109600">I desire none, boy, for thy tongue sounds so sweetly, and thy face looks so honestly, as I cannot but take, and trust thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109610" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109620">Heaven bless your excellence, and fortune prosper you, for your bounty hath been above my hopes, and equal to my wishes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109630" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109640">What is thy name?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109650" who="A53060_01-orphant">
              <speaker>Lady Orph.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109660">Affectionata my noble lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109670" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109680">Then follow me Affectionata. </p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e109690">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A53060_01-e109700">
          <pb facs="26" n="27"/>
          <head>Act iv.</head>
          <div n="17" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e109710">
            <head>Scene 17.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e109720">Enter the lady bashfull, and reformer her woman. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e109730">Enter page.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109740" who="A53060_01-page">
              <speaker>Page.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109750">Madam, there was a gentleman gave me this letter, to deliver to your ladyship's hands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109760" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109770">A letter I pray reformer open it, and read it, for I will not receive letters privately.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e109780">Page exit.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109790" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109800">The superscription is for the right honourable, the lady bashful; these present.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e109810">The letter.</stage>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:id="A53060_01-e109820">
              <body xml:id="A53060_01-e109830">
                <opener xml:id="A53060_01-e109840">
                  <salute xml:id="A53060_01-e109850">Madam,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109860">Since I have had the honour to see you, I have had the unhappiness to think myself miserable, by reason I am deprived of speech, that should plead my suit, but if an affectionate soul, chaste thoughts, lawful desires, and a fervent heart can plead without speech, let me beg your favour to accept of me for your servant; and what I want in language, my industrious observance, and diligent service shall supply; I am a gentleman, my breeding hath been according to my birth, and my estate is sufficient to maintain me according to both; as for your estate, I consider it not, for were you so poor of fortune's goods, as you had nothing to maintain you, but what your merit might challenge out of every purse; yet if you were mine, I should esteem you richer than the whole world, and I should love you, as saints love heaven, and adore you equal to a deity; for I saw so much sweetness of nature, nobleness of soul, purity of thoughts, and innocency of life, through your bashful countenance, as my soul is wedded thereunto, and my mind so restless; therefore, that unless I may have hopes to enjoy you for my wife; I shall die,</p>
                <closer xml:id="A53060_01-e109870">
                  <signed xml:id="A53060_01-e109880">Your distracted servant, serious dumb. </signed>
                </closer>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109890" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109900">Now reformer, what say you to this letter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109910" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109920">I say it is a good honest, hearty affectionate letter, and upon my life, it is the gentleman I commended so; he that looked so seriously on you; and your ladyship may remember, I said he viewed you, as if he would have looked you through, and you made answer, that you wished he could, that he might see you were not so simple, as your behaviour made you appear, and now your wish is absolved.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109930" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <pb facs="27" n="28"/>
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109940">What counsel will you give me in this cause?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109950" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109960">Why? write him a civil answer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109970" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e109980">Why should I hold correspondence with any man, either by letter, or any other way, since I do not intend to marry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e109990" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110000">Not marry?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110010" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110020">No, not marry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110030" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110040">Why so?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110050" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110060">Because I am now mistress of myself, and fortunes, and have a free liberty; and who that is free, if they be wise, will make themselves slaves, subjecting themselves to another's humour, unless they were fools, or mad, and knew not how to choose the best and happiest life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110070" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110080">You will change this opinion, and marry, I dare swear.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110090" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110100">Indeed I will not swear, but I think I shall not, for I love an easy, peaceable and solitary life, which none enjoys but single persons; for in marriage, the life is disturbed with noise and company, troublesome employments, vexed with crosses, and restless with cares; besides, I could not endure to have partners to share of him, whom my affections had set a price upon, or my merit, or beauty, or wealth, or virtue had bought.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110110" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110120">So, I perceive you would be jealous, if you were married.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110130" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110140">Perchance I might have reason, but to prevent all inconveniences, and discontents, I will live a single life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110150" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110160">Do what likes you best, for I dare not persuade you any way, for fear my advice should not prove to the best.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e110170">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="18" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e110180">
            <head>Scene 18.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e110190">Enter Affectionata, and Foster Trusty. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110200" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110210">Now you are placed according to your desire, what will you command me to do?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110220" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110230">Dear foster father, although I am loath to part from you, yet by reason I shall suffer in my estate, I must entreat you to return home, for my nurse your wife, hath not skill to manage that fortune my father left me; for she knows not how to let leases, to set lands, to receive rends, to repair ruins, to disbursed charges, and to order those affairs as they should be ordered, which your knowledge, industry and wisdom will dispose and order for my advantage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110240" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110250">But how if you be discovered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110260" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110270">Why, if I should, as I hope I shall not, yet the lord singularity is so noble a person, as he will neither use me uncivilly, not cruelly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110280" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110290">All that I fear is, if you should be discovered, he should use you too civilly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110300" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110310">That were to use me rudely, which I am confident he will not do, and I am confident that you do believe I will receive no more civility (If you call it so) than what honour will allow and approve of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110320" who="A53060_01-foster_trusty">
              <speaker>Foster trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110330">But jealousy will creep into the most confident breasts sometimes, yet I dare trust you, though I fear him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110340" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <pb facs="27" n="29"/>
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110350">I hope there is no cause to fear him, or doubt me, wherefore dear father, let us go and settle our affairs here, that you may return home to order those there.</p>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="19" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e110360">
            <head>Scene 19.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e110370">Enter sir peaceable studious, and the lady ignorance his wife, she being undressed, her mantle about her, as being not well. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110380" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110390">In truth wife, it is a great misfortune you should be sick this termtime, when the society is so much increased, as it is become a little commonwealth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110400" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110410">If there be so many, they may the better spare me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110420" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110430">'Tis true, they can spare your company, but how can you want their companies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110440" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110450">You shall be my intelligencer of their pastimes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110460" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110470">That I will wife, but it will be but a dull recreation, only to hear a bare relation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110480" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110490">As long as you partake of their present pleasures, and pleasant actions, what need you take care for me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110500" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110510">Yes, but I must in justice, for since you have cured me of a studious lethargy, I ought to do my endeavour to divert your melancholy; and there is no such remedy as the society; wherefore dear wife, fling off this melancholy sickness, or sick melancholy, and go amongst them; for surely your sickness is in your mind, not in your body.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e110520">She cries.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110530" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110540">What, do you cry wife, who hath angered you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110550" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110560">Why you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110570" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110580">Who, I angered you I why I would not anger a woman, no, not my wife for the whole world, if I could possible avoid it, which I fear cannot be avoided, for if I should please out of your sex, I should be sure to displease another: — but that is my comfort, it is not my fault; but dear wife, how have I offended you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110590" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110600">Why did you kiss my maid before my face.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110610" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110620">Why did you persuade me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110630" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110640">Did I persuade you to kiss my maid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110650" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110660">No, but you did persuade me to be one of the society and there is kissing, and I thought it was as well to kiss your maid before your face, as a sociable lady before your face.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110670" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110680">And why do you make love to the ladies, since I suffer none to make love to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110690" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110700">No, for if you did, I would fling you to death, to be embraced in his cold arms; besides, those actions that are allowable and seemly, as manly in men, are condemned in women, as immodest, and unbecoming, and dishonourable; but talking to you, I shall miss of the pleasant sports, and therefore, if you will go, come, the coach is ready.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110710" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <pb facs="28" n="30"/>
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110720">No, I will not go 〈…〉 u..</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110730" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110740">Then I will go without you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110750" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110760">No, pray husband go no more thither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110770" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110780">How! not to go? nor to go no more, would you desire me from that which you persuaded me to; nay, so much as I could never be quiet, disturbing my harmless studies, and happy mind, crossing my pleasing thoughts with complaining words, but I perceive you grow jealous, and now you are acquainted, you have no more use of me, but would be glad to quit my company, that you may be more free abroad.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110790" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110800">No husband, truly I will never go abroad, but will enanchor myself in my own house, so you will stay at home, and be as you were before, for I see my own follies, and am ashamed of myself, that you should prove me such a fool.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110810" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110820">Do you think me so wise and temperate a man, as I can on a sudden quit vain pleasures, and lawful follies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110830" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110840">Yes, or else you have studied to little purpose.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110850" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110860">Well, for this day I will stay at home, and for the future time I will consider.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e110870">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="20" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e110880">
            <head>Scene 20.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e110890">Enter two servants of the generals.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110900" who="A53060_01-servant_1">
              <speaker>I. servant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110910">This boy that came but the other day, hath got more of my lords affection, than we that have served him this many years.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110920" who="A53060_01-servant_2">
              <speaker>2. Servant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110930">Newcomers are always more favoured than old waiters; for masters regards old servants no more, than the imagery in an old suit of hanging, which are grown threadbare with time, and out of fashion with change; besides, new servants are more industrious and diligent than old; but when he hath been here a little while, he will be as lazy as the rest, and then he will be as we are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110940" who="A53060_01-servant_1">
              <speaker>I. servant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110950">I perceive my lord delights to hear him talk, for he will listen very a tentively to him, but when we offer to speak, he bids us to be silent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110960" who="A53060_01-servant_2">
              <speaker>2. Servant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e110970">I wonder he should, for when we speak, it is with gravity, and our discourse is sententious, but his is mere squibs.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e110980">Enter Affectionata.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e110990" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111000">Gentlemen, my lord would have one of you to come to him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111010" who="A53060_01-servant_1">
              <speaker>I. servant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111020">Why, I thought you could supply all our places, for when you are with him, he seems to have no use of us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111030" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111040">It shall not be for want of will, but ability, if I do not serve him in every honest office.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111050" who="A53060_01-servant_1">
              <speaker>I. servant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111060">So you will make some of us knaves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111070" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111080">I cannot make you knaves, unless you be willing to be knaves yourselves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111090" who="A53060_01-servant_2">
              <speaker>2. Servant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111100">What, do you call me knave?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111110" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <pb facs="28" n="31"/>
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111120">I do not call you so.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111130">Ex.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111140" who="A53060_01-servant_2">
              <speaker>2. Servant. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111150">Well, I will be revenged, if I live.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111160">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="21" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e111170">
            <head>Scene 21.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111180">Enter the lady bashfull, and reformer her woman. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111190" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111200">Madam, I have inquired what this sir serious dumb is, and 'tis said he is one of the finest gentlemen in this kingdom, and that his valour hath been proved in the wars, and that he is one that is very active and dexterous in all manly exercises, as riding, fencing, vaulting, swimming, and the like, also that he is full of inventions, and a rare poet, and that he hath a great estate, only that he is dumb, and hath been so this twelve years and upwards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111210" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111220">Reformer. What makes you so industrious to inquire after him, surely thou art in love within.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111230" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111240">In my conscience I liked him very well, when he was to see you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111250" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111260">The truth is, he cannot weary you with words, nor anger you in his discourse, but prey do not inquire after him, nor speak of him; for people will think I have some design of marriage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111270" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111280">I shall obey you, madam.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111290">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="22" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e111300">
            <head>Scene. 22.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111310">Enter the lord singularity, and Affectionata.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111320">He strokes Affectionata's head. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111330" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111340">Affectionata, thou art one of the diligentest boys that had.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111350" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111360">How can I be otherwise, sir, since you are the governor of my soul, that commands the fort of my passion, and the castle of my imaginations, which are the heart, and the head.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111370" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111380">Do you love me so much?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111390" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111400">So well my lord, as you are the architector of my mind, the foundation of my thoughts, and the gates of my memories, for your will is the form, your happiness the level, and your actions the treasury.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111410" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111420">Thy wit delights me more, than thy flattery persuades: for I cannot believe a boy can love so much; besides, you have not served me so long, as to beget love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111430" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111440">I have loved you from my infancy, for as I sucked life from my nurse's breast, so did I love from fames, drawing your praises forth, as I did milk, which nourished my affections.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111450" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111460">I shall strive; boy, to require thy love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111470" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <pb facs="29" n="32"/>
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111480">To requite, is to return love for love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111490" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111500">By heaven? I love thee, as a father loves a son.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111510" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111520">Then I am blessed,</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111530">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="23" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e111540">
            <head>Scene 23.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111550">Enter two soldiers.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111560" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Souldier. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111570">What is this boy that our general is so taken with.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111580" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Soldier,</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111590">A poor beggar-boy!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111600" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Soldier. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111610">Can a poor beggar-boy merit his affections?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111620" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Soldier. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111630">He is a pretty boy, and waits very diligently.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111640" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Soldier. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111650">So doth other boys, as well as he, but I believe he is a young pimp, and carries, and conveys love-letters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111660" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Soldier. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111670">Like enough to, for boys are strangely crafty in those employments, and so industrious, as they will let no times nor opportunities slip them, but they will find ways to deliver their letters and messages.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111680">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="24" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e111690">
            <head>Scene 24.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111700">Enter the lady Bashful's page, and sir serious dumb, who gives a note to the page to read. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111710" who="A53060_01-page">
              <speaker>Page.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111720">Sir, I dare not direct you to my lady, as you desire me in this note, and if I should tell her, here is a gentleman that desired to visit her, she would refuse your visit.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111730">Dumb gives the young page four or five pieces of gold. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111740" who="A53060_01-page">
              <speaker>Page.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111750">I will direct you to the room wherein my lady is, but I must not be seen, nor confess I showed you the way.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111760">Page, and sir serious dumb exeunt</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="25" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e111770">
            <head>Scene 25.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e111780">Enter the lord singularity, and Affectionata.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111790" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111800">Come Affectionata, sit down and entertain me with thy sweet discourse, which makes all other company troublesome, and tedious to me, thine only doth delight me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111810" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111820">My noble lord? I wish the platform of my brain were a garden of wit, and then perchance my tongue might present your excellencies with a posy of flowery rhetoric, but my poor brain is barren, wanting</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111830" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <pb facs="29" n="33"/>
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111840">Thou hast an eloquent tongue, (And a gentle soul.)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111850" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111860">My noble lord, I have hardly learned my native words, much less the eloquence of language, and as for the souls of all mankind, they are like commonwealths, where the several virtues, and good graces are the citizens therein, and the natural subjects thereof; but vices and follies, as the thievish borderers, and neighbour-enemies, which makes inroads, factions, mutinies, intrudes and usurps authority, and if the follies be more than the good graces, and the vices too strong for the virtues, the monarchy of a good life falls to ruin, also it is endangered by civil-wars amongst the passions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111870" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111880">What passions endangers it most?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111890" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111900">Anger, malice, and despair.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111910" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111920">Were you never angry?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111930" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111940">I am of too melancholy a nature, to be very angry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111950" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111960">Why? are melancholy persons never angry?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111970" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e111980">Very seldom, my lord, for those that are naturally melancholy, doth rather grieve, than fret, they sooner wast into sighs, than fly about with fury; more tears flows through their eyes, than words pass through their lips.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e111990" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112000">Why should you be melancholy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112010" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112020">Alas, nature hath made me so; besides, I find there is not much reason to joy, for what we love, perchance it loves not us, and if it doth, we cannot keep it long, for pleasures passeth like a dream; when pains doth stay, as if eternal were.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112030" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112040">Thou art composed with such harmony, as thy discourse is as delightful music, wherein the soul takes pleasure.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112050">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="26" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e112060">
            <head>Scene 26.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112070">Enter the lady bashfull, sir serious dumb following her, where reformer her woman meets them. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112080" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112090">Madam, now the gentleman is here, you must use him civilly, and not strive to run away from him, wherefore pray turn, and entertain him.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112100">The lady bashfull turns to him, but is so out of countenance, and trembles so much, as she cannot speak, but stands still and mute; all the while he fixes his eyes upon her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112110" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112120">Pray speak to him, madam, and not stand trembling, as if you were like to fall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112130" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112140">My spirits is seized on by my bashful and innocent fears, insomuch, as they have not strength to support my body without trembling.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112150" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112160">Sweet madam, try not speak to him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112170" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112180">Honourable sir? give me leave to tell you, that my bashfulness<pb facs="30" n="34"/> doth smother the senses and reason in my brain, and chokes the words in my throat I should utter, but prey do not think it proceeds from crimes, but an imperfection of nature, which I have strove against, but cannot as yet rectify</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112190">Sir serious dumb Civily bows to her, and then gives reformer his table-book to read. </stage>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112200">She reads.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112210">Madam,</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112220">He hath writ here, that had his tongue liberty to speak, all that he could say, would be so far below, and inferior to what might be said in your praise, as he should not adventure to presume to speak. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112230" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112240">I will presume to break my brain, but I will invent some ways to be rid of his company.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112250">He follows her, exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A53060_01-e112260">
          <head>Act. v.</head>
          <div n="27" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e112270">
            <head>Scene 27.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112280">Enter the general, and sits in a melancholy posture. Enters Affectionata, and stands with a sad countenance. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112290">The general sees him.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112300" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112310">What makes thee look so sad, my boy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112320" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112330">To see you sit so melancholy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112340" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112350">Clear up thy countenance, for it's not a deadly melancholy, though it is a troublesome one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112360" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112370">May I be so bold to ask the cause of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112380" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112390">The cause is, a cruel mistress.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112400" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112410">Have you a mistress, and can she be cruel?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112420" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112430">O! women are tyrants, they daw us on to love, and then denies our suits.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112440" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112450">Will not you think me rude, if I should question you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112460" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112470">No, for thy questions delights me more, than my mistress denials grieves me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112480" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112490">Then give me leave to ask you, whether your suit be just?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112500" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112510">Just, to a lover's desires.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112520" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112530">What is your desire?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112540" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112550">To lie with her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112560" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <pb facs="30" n="35"/>
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112570">After you have married her?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112580" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112590">Marry her sayest thou, I had rather be banished from that sex for ever, than marry one, and yet I love them well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112600" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112610">Why have you such an adversion to marriage, being lawful and honest.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112620" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112630">Because I am afraid to be a cuckold!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112640" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112650">Do you think there is no chaste women?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112660" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112670">Faith boy, I believe very few, and those that are men, knows not where to find them out, for all that are not married, professes chastity, speaks soberly, and looks modestly, but when they are married, they are more wild than bachalins, far worse than satires, making their husbands horns far greater than a stag's, having more branches sprouts thereon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112680" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112690">And doth he never cast those horns?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112700" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112710">Yes, if he be a widower, he casts his horns, only the marks remains, otherwise he bears them to his grave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112720" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112730">But put the case you did know a woman that was chaste; would not you marry her?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112740" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112750">That is a question not to be resolved, for no man can be resolved, whether a woman can be chaste or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112760">Affectionata fetches a greater sigh.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112770" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112780">Why do you sigh, my boy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112790" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112800">Because all women are false, or thought to be so, that wise men dares not trust them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112810" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112820">But they are fools, that will not try, and make use of them, if they can have them; wherefore I will go, and try my mistress once again.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112830">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="28" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e112840">
            <head>Scene. 28.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112850">Enter the lady ignorance, and her maid. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112860">She hears a noise.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112870" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112880">What a noise they make below, they will disturb my husband's study; go and tell those of my servants, that I will turn them away for their carelessness, as that they cannot place, set, or hold things sure, but let them fall to maké such a noise.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112890" who="A53060_01-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112900">I shall.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112910">Maid ex.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112920" who="A53060_01-ignorance">
              <speaker>Lady ignorance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112930">It shall be my study how to order my house without noise, wherefore all my servants shall be dumb, although not deaf, and I will take none, but such as have corns on their feet, that they may tread gently, and all my household-vessel shall be of wood, for wood makes not such a noise when it chance to fall, or is hit against a wall, as metal doth, which rings like bells, when it is but touched, neither will I have household-vessels of earth, for earthen-pots, pans and the like; when they fall and break, sounds as if a stonewall fell.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112940">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="29" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e112950">
            <pb facs="31" n="36"/>
            <head>Scene 29.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e112960">Enter the general, and three or four commanders. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112970" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e112980">On my soul gentlemen, the boy is an honest boy, and no ways guilty of this you tax him for.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e112990" who="A53060_01-commander">
              <speaker>Commanders.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113000">Pardon us, my lord, for giving your excellence notice that the states are jealous of him for a spy, but we do not any ways accuse him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113010" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113020">Will the states examine him, say you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113030" who="A53060_01-commander">
              <speaker>Commanders.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113040">So we hear, my lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113050" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113060">Well gentlemen, pray leave me for this time, and I will take care the boy shall be forthcoming, whensoever the state shall require him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113070" who="A53060_01-commander">
              <speaker>Commanders.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113080">Your lordship's humble servants —</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e113090">Commanders ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e113100">The general solus.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113110" who="A53060_01-general">
              <speaker>General.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113120">A spy, it cannot be, for he is neither covetous, nor malicious, revengeful, nor irreligious, but I will try him.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e113130">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="30" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e113140">
            <head>Scene 30.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e113150">Enter the lady Bashful's chambermaid, and Mrs. reformer her gentlewoman. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113160" who="A53060_01-chamber-maid">
              <speaker>Chambermaid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113170">Mrs. reformer, pray tell me who that handsome gentleman is, which follows my lady about?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113180" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113190">He is one that is noble, and rich, and is in love with my lady.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113200" who="A53060_01-chamber-maid">
              <speaker>Chambermaid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113210">Truly it is the strangest way of wooing, that ever was, for my lady goeth blushing out of one room into another, and he follows her at the heels: in my conscience my lady is ashamed to sit down, or to bid him leave her company, and surely they must needs be both very weary of walking, but sure he will leave her, when it is time to go to bed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113220" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113230">It is to be hoped he will.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e113240">Enter the lady bashfull, and sir serious dumb following her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113250" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113260">Madam, you will tire yourself and the gentleman, with walking about your house, wherefore pray sit down.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113270" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113280">What! to have him gaze upon my face.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113290" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113300">Why, your face is a handsome face, and the owner of it is honest, wherefore you need not be ashamed, but pray rest yourself. —</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113310" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <pb facs="31" n="37"/>
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113320">Pray persuade him to leave me, and then I will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113330" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113340">Sir, my lady entreats you to leave her to herself.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e113350">Sir serious dumb writes then, and gives reformer his table-book to read. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113360" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113370">He writes he cannot leave you, for if his body should depart, his soul will remain still with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113380" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113390">That will not put me out of countenance, because I shall not be sensible of its presence, wherefore I am content he should leave his soul, so that he will take his body away.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e113400">He writes, and gives reformer the book. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113410" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer reads.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113420">He writes, that if you will give him leave once a day to see you, that he will depart, and that he will not disturb your thoughts, he will only wait upon your person for the time he lives, he cannot keep himself long from you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113430" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113440">But I would be alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113450" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113460">But if he will follow you, you must endure that with patience, you cannot avoid.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e113470">Sir serious dumb goeth to the lady bashfull, and kisseth her hand, and ex. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113480" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113490">You see he is so civil, as he is unwilling to displease you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113500" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113510">Rather than I will be troubled thus; I will go to some other parts of the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113520" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113530">In my conscience, madam, he will follow you, wheresoever you go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113540" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113550">But I will have him shut out of my house.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113560" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113570">Then he will lie at your gates, and so all the town will take notice of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113580" who="A53060_01-bashfull">
              <speaker>Lady bashful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113590">Why so, they will howsoever, by his often visits.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113600" who="A53060_01-reformer">
              <speaker>Reformer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113610">But not so public.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e113620">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="31" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e113630">
            <head>Scene 31.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e113640">Enter the general, and Affectionata.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113650" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113660">Affectionata. Thou must carry a letter from me, to my mistress.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113670" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113680">You will not marry her, you say.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113690" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113700">No.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113710" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113720">Then pardon me, my lord, for though I would assist your honest love by any service I can do, yet I shall never be so base an instrument, as to produce a crime.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113730" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113740">Come, come, thou shalt carry it, and I will give thee 500. pounds for thy service.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113750" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <pb facs="32" n="38"/>
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113760">Excuse me, my lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113770" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113780">I will give thee a thousand pounds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113790" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113800">I shall not take it, my lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113810" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113820">I will give thee five thousand, nay ten thousand pounds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113830" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113840">I am not covetous, my lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113850" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113860">I will make thee master of my whole estate, for without the assistance, I cannot enjoy my mistress, by reason she will trust none with our loves, but thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113870" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113880">Could you make me master of the whole world, it could not tempt me to do an action base, for though I am poor, I am honest, and so honest, as I cannot be corrupted, or bribed therefrom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113890" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113900">You said you loved me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113910" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113920">Heaven knows I do above my life, and would do you any service that honour did allow of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113930" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113940">You are more scrupulous than wise.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e113950" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e113960">There is an old saying, my lord, that to be wise, is to be honest.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e113970">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="32" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e113980">
            <head>Scene 32.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e113990">Enter sir peaceable studious, and meets his lady's maid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114000" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114010">Where is your lady?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114020" who="A53060_01-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114030">In her chamber, sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114040" who="A53060_01-peaceable_studious">
              <speaker>Sir P. Studious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114050">Pray her to come to me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114060" who="A53060_01-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114070">Yes sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e114080">Sir P. Studious, exit.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e114090">Enter another maid to the first.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114100" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114110">Lord, lord! What a creature my master is become; since he fell into his musing again, he looks like a melancholy ghost, that walks in the shades of moonshine, or if there be no ghost, such as we fancy, just such a one seems her, when a week since, he was as fine a gentleman as one should see amongst a thousand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114120" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114130">That was because he kissed you, Nan. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114140" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114150">Faith it was but a dull clownish part, to meet a maid that is not ill-favoured, and not make much of her, who perchance have watched to meet him, for which he might have clapped her on the cheek, or have chucked her under the chin, or have kissed her, but to do or say nothing, but bid me call my lady, was such a churlish part? Besides, it seemed neither manly, gallantly, nor civilly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114160" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114170">But it showed him temperate and wise, not minding such frivolous and troublesome creatures as women are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114180" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114190">Prithee, it shows him to be a miserable, proud, dull fool.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114200" who="A53060_01-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114210">Peace, somebody will hear you, and than you will be turned away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114220" who="A53060_01-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114230">I care not, for it they will not turn me away, I will turn myself away, and seek another service, for I hate to live in the house with a Stoic.</p>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="33" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_01-e114240">
            <pb facs="32" n="39"/>
            <head>Scene 33.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e114250">Enter the general, and Affectionata.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114260" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114270">By your face, sir, there seems a trouble in your mind, and I am restless until I know your griefs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114280" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114290">It is a secret I dare not trust the air with!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114300" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114310">I shall be more secret than the air, for the air is apt to divulge by retorting echoes back, but I shall be as silent as the grave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114320" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114330">But you may be tortured to confess the truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114340" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114350">But I will not confess the truth, if the confession may any ways hurt, or disadvantage you; for though I will not belie truth by speaking falsely, yet I will conceal a truth, rather than betray a friend. Especially, my lord and master: but howsoever, since your trouble is of such concern, I shall not with to know it, for though I dare trust myself, yet perchance you dare not trust me, but if my honest fidelity can serve you any ways, you may employ it, and if it be to keep a secret, all the torment that nature hath made, or art invented, shall never draw it from me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114360" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114370">Then let me tell thee, that to conceal it, would damn thy soul.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114380" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114390">Heaven bless me! But sure, my lord, you cannot be guilty of such sins, that those that doth but barely hear, or know them, shall be damned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114400" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul,</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114410">But to conceal them, is to be an actor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114420" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114430">For heaven's sake then keep them close from me, if either they be base or wicked, for though love prompt me to inquire, hoping to give you ease in bearing part of the burden, yet heaven knows, I thought my love so honourable placed on such a worthy person, and guiltless soul, as I might love and serve without a scandal, or a deadly sin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114440" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114450">Come, you shall know it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114460" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114470">I'll rather stop my ears with death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114480" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114490">Go, thou art a false boy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114500" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114510">How false a boy howsoever you think me, I have an honest soul and heart that is ready to serve you in any honest way, but since I am deceived, and cozened into love by false reports, finding the best of mankind basely wicked, and all the world so bad, that praise nothing good, and strives to poison virtue, I will enanchor myself, and live on antidotes of prayers, for fear of the infection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114520" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord Singul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114530">And I will not you pray for me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114540" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114550">I cannot choose, my lord, for gratitude enforces me; first, because I have loved you, next, because I have served you; and give me leave to kiss your hand, and then there drop some tears at my departure.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e114560">Weeping kneels down, and kisses her hand.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114570" who="A53060_01-singularity">
              <speaker>Lord singularity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114580">Rise, you must not go away until you have cleared yourself from being a spy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_01-e114590" who="A53060_01-affectionata">
              <speaker>Affectionata.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_01-e114600">I fear no accusations,</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_01-e114610">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A53060_01-e114620">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A53060_01"><item xml:id="A53060_01-orphant" n="65">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-orphant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">65</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-singularity" n="53">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-singularity</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">53</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-reformer" n="52">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-reformer</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">52</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-peaceable_studious" n="48">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-peaceable_studious</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">48</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-affectionata" n="48">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-affectionata</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">48</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-ignorance" n="44">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-ignorance</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">44</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-bashfull" n="41">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-bashfull</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">41</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-wagtail" n="30">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-wagtail</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">30</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-yyyy_1" n="30">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">30</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-yyyy_2" n="24">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-yyyy_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">24</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-amorous" n="22">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-amorous</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">22</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-general" n="22">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-general</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">22</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-foster_trusty" n="21">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-foster_trusty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">21</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-humphry_bold" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-humphry_bold</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-acquaintance" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-acquaintance</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-roger_exception" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-roger_exception</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-fatherly" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-fatherly</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A53060_01-fondly" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-fondly</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-yyyy_3" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-yyyy_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-trades-man" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-trades-man</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-timothy_compliment" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-timothy_compliment</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-servant_1" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-servant_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-commander" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-commander</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-page" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-page</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-maid" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-maid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-servant_2" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-servant_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-foster_nurse" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-foster_nurse</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-lady" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-lady</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-gentleman_2" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-gentleman_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-chamber-maid" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-chamber-maid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-gentleman_1" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-gentleman_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-foster" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-foster</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-UNASSIGNED" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-UNASSIGNED</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-roger_vanity" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-roger_vanity</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_01-captain" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_01-captain</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

