<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>2 The Lady<date type="creation_date">1662</date></title>
        <author>Cavendish, Margaret</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A53060_07.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>356 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">11861873</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing N868.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">50022</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53060</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
            <author>Newcastle, William Cavendish, 1592-1676.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[24], 679 [i.e. 675], [4] p. : ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by A. Warren, for John Martyn, James Allestry, and Tho. Dicas ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1662.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>First edition.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Errata: p. [4] at end.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A53060_07-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A53060_07-e100020">
      <div n="2" type="play" xml:id="A53060_07-e100030">
        <pb facs="118" n="212"/>
        <head>The second part of the lady contemplation. </head>
        <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A53060_07-e100040">
          <list xml:id="A53060_07-e100050">
            <head>The actors names.</head>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100060">Lord title. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100070">Lord courtship. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100080">Sir Fancy poet. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100090">Sir experienced traveller. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100100">Sir Humphrey interruption. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100110">Sir golden riches. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100120">Sir effeminate lovely. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100130">Sir John argument. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100140">Sir vain compliment. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100150">Master Inquirer. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100160">Doctor practice. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100170">Old humanity. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100180">Roger farmer. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100190">Thom. Purveyor. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100200">2. Beadles, gentlemen and others.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100210">Lady amorous. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100220">Lady ward. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100230">Lady Contemplation. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100240">Lady conversation. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100250">Lady visitant. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100260">Poor virtue. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100270">Mistress troublesome. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100280">Mistress gossip. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100290">Mistress messenger, lady Amorous's woman.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100300">Nurse careful. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100310">Maudlin housewife, Roger farmer's wife.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100320">Mall mean-bred, their daughter.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100330">Mistress Troublesomes maid.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_07-e100340">Servants and others.</item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A53060_07-e100350">
          <pb facs="118" n="213"/>
          <head>The second part of the lady contemplation,</head>
          <head type="sub">Act i.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e100360">
            <head>Scene. 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e100370">Enter sir effeminate lovely, and poor virtue.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100380" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effeminate lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100390">Sweetheart, you are a most heavenly creature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100400" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100410">Beauty is created and placed oftener in the fancy, than in the face.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100420" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100430">'Tis said there is a sympathy in likeness; if so, you and I should love each other, for we are both beautiful.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100440" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100450">But 'tis a question whether our souls be answerable to our persons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100460" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100470">There is no question or doubt to be made, but that loving souls live in beautiful persons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100480" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100490">And do those loving souls die, when their beauties are decayed and withered?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100500" who="A53060_07-effeminate">
              <speaker>Effem.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100510">The subject pleads itself, without the help of rhetoric, for love and beauty lives and dies together.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100520" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100530">'Tis amorous love that dies when beauty is gone, not virtuous love; for as amorous love is bred, born, lives, and dies with the appetite: so virtuous love is created, and shall live with the soul forever.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100540" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100550">You may call it what love you please.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100560" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100570">It is no love, but a disease.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e100580">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e100590">
            <head>Scene 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e100600">Enter the lord courtship, and the lady Ward.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100610" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courtship.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100620">Why did you leave the lady amorous company so uncivilly, as to go out of the room, leaving her all alone?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100630" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100640">I heard your lordship was coming, than I thought it was fit for me to withdraw; for I have heard lovers desire to be alone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100650" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courtship.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100660">Do you desire to be alone with a man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100670" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100680">I am no such lover, for I am too young as yet, but I know not what I shall or may be wrought or brought to, but time and good example may instruct and lead me into the way of amorous love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100690" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courtship.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100700">May it so?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100710" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100720">Why not? for I am docible, and youth is apt to learn.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100730" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <pb facs="119" n="214"/>
              <speaker>Lord courtship</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100740">But before I marry you, I would have you learn to know how to be an obedient wife, as to be content, and not murmur at my actions, also to please my humour, but not to imitate my practice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100750" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100760">If I might advise your lordship, I would advise you to take such a portion out of my estate, as you shall think just or fit, and then quit me, and choose such a one as you shall like, for I shall never please you; for though I may be apt to learn what will please myself, yet I am dull and intractable to learn obedience to another's will, nor can I flatter their delights.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100770" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courtship</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100780">I find you have learned, and now begin to practise how to talk; for now your sober silence seems as dead and buried in the rubbish of foolish words; but let me tell you, a talking wife will never please me; wherefore practice patience, and keep silence, if you would enjoy the happiness of peace.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e100790">The lord courtship goes out. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e100800">Lady Ward alone.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100810" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100820">There can be no peace, when the mind is discontented.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e100830">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e100840">
            <head>Scene. 3.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e100850">Enter lord title, and poor virtue.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100860" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100870">Why do you follow me so much, as never to let me rest in peace and quiet alone? Is it that you think I have beauty? and is it that you are in love with? why, to cure your disease, I will deform it; or do you think I have wit to cure that imagination? I will put my tongue to silence. I am sure it cannot be my virtue that inflames you to an intemperance; for virtue is an antidote against it: but had you all the beauty in nature squeezed into your form, and all the wit in nature pressed into your brain, and all the prosperities of good fortune at your command, and all the power of fate and destiny at your disposal, you could not persuade me to yield to your unlawful desires; for know, I am honest without self-ends; my virtue, like to time, still running forward, my chastity fixed as eternity, without circumferent lines; besides, it is built on the foundation of morality, and roofed and ceiled with the faith of religion, and the materials thereof are honour, which no subtle arguments can shake the one, nor no false doctrine can corrupt or rot the other; neither is the building subject to the fire of unlawful love, nor the tempestuous storms of torments, nor the deluge of poverty, nor the earthquakes of fear, nor the ruins of death; for so long as my soul hath a being, my chastity will live. But were you as poor as I, even to move pity, or so lowly and meanly born, at might bring contempt and scorn from the proud, yet if your mind and soul were endued with noble qualities, and heroical virtues, I should sooner embrace your love, than to be mistress of the whole world; for my affection to merit hath been ingrafted into the root of my infancy, which hath grown up with my years, so that the longer I live, the more it increases.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100880" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100890">You cannot think I would marry you, although I would lie with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100900" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <pb facs="119" n="215"/>
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100910">I cannot but think it more possible that you should marry me, than I to be dishonest.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100920" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100930">Thou art a mean poor wench, and I nobly descended.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100940" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100950">What though I am poor, yet I am honest, and poverty is no crime; nor have my ancestors left marks of infamy to shame me to the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100960" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100970">Thy ancestors? what were they but poor peasants? wherefore thou wilt dignify thy race, by yielding to my love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e100980" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e100990">Heaven keep them from that dignity that must be gained by my dishonesty: no, my chastity shall raise a monumental tomb over their cold dead ashes.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101000">Poor virtue goes out. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101010">Lord title alone.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101020" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101030">What pity it is nature should put so noble a soul into a mean-born body.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101040">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e101050">
            <head>Scene 4.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101060">Enter the lord courtship, and the lady Ward.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101070" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101080">Pray go visit the lady amorous, and if her husband be absent, deliver her this letter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101090" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101100">Excuse me my lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101110" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101120">Wherefore?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101130" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101140">I am no carrier of love-letters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101150" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101160">But you shall carry this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101170" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101180">But I will not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101190" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101200">Will you not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101210" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101220">No, I will rather endure all the torments that can be invented.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101230" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101240">And you shall; for I will torture you if you do not; for I will have you drawn up high by the two thumbs, which is a pain will force you to submit.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101250">The lady Ward falls into a passion. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101260" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101270">Do so if you will; nay screw me up into the middle-region, there will I take a thunderbolt, and strike you dead, and with such strength I'll fling it on you, as it shall press your soul down to the everlasting shades of death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101280" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101290">Sure you will be more merciful.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101300" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101310">No more than devils are to sinful souls; there will I be your bawd, to procure you variety of torments; for I had rather be one in Pluto's black court, caused by my own revenge, than to be a bawd on earth, which is a humane devil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101320" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101330">You are mad.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101340" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101350">Might every word I speak prove like a mad dogs bite, not only to transform your shape, and turn your speech to barks and howlings, but that your soul may be no other than the souls of beasts are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101360" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101370">You are transformed from a silent young maid to a raging fury.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101380" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101390">May all the furies that hell inhabits, and those that live<pb facs="120" n="216"/> on earth, torment your mind, as racks do torture bodies, and may the venom of all malice, spleen, and spite, be squeezed into your soul, and poison all content, your thoughts flame like burning oil, and never quench, but be eternally a fiery animal; and may the fire feed only on yourself, and as it burns, your torments may increase.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101400">The lady Ward goes out. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101410">Lord courtship alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101420" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101430">She is mad, very mad, and I have only been the cause.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101440">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e101450">
            <head>Scene 5.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101460">Enter the lord title, and poor virtue,</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101470" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101480">Fairest, will not you speak?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101490" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101500">My words have betrayed my heart, as discovering the secrets therein: wherefore I will banish them, and shut the doors of my lips against them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101510" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101520">What, for saying you love me. Sweet, why do you weep?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101530">Poor virtue weeps. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101540" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101550">Tears are the best cordials for a heart oppressed with grief.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101560" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101570">I should hate myself, if I could think I were the cause. But pray forbear to weep.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101580" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101590">Pray give my grief a liberty, my tears are no disturbance, they shower down without a rattling noise, and silent fall without a murmuring voice; but you disturb me: wherefore for pity-sake leave me, and I will pray you may enjoy as much prosperity as good fortune can present you with, and as much health as nature can give you, and as much tranquillity as heaven can infuse into a mortal creature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101600" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101610">Neither fortune, nature, nor heaven can please me, or make me happy in this world without you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101620" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101630">O you torment me.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101640">Exit, the lord follows her.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e101650">
            <head>Scene 6.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101660">Enter sir Humphry interruption to the lady contemplation.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101670" who="A53060_07-humphrey_inter">
              <speaker>Sir Humphry inter.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101680">Surely lady contemplation your thoughts must needs be very excellent, that they take no delight but with themselves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101690" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101700">My thoughts, although they are not material, as being profitable, yet they are innocent, as being harmless.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101710" who="A53060_07-humphrey_inter">
              <speaker>Sir Humphry inter.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101720">Yet your thoughts do the world an injury, in burying your words in the grave of silence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101730" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101740">Let me inform you, that sometimes they creep out of<pb facs="120" n="217"/> their graves as ghosts do, and as ghosts walk in solitary places, so I speak to my solitary self, which words offend no ears, because I speak to no ears but my own; and as they have no flatterers to applaud them, so they have no censurers to condemn them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101750" who="A53060_07-humphrey_inter">
              <speaker>Sir Humphrey inter.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101760">But you bury your life, whilst you live retired from company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101770" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101780">O no, for otherwise my life would be buried in company; for my life never enjoys itself, but when it is alone; and for the most part, all public societies are like a discord in music, every one playing several contrary parts in their actions, speaking in several contrary notes, striking on several contrary subjects, which makes a confusion; and a confused noise is like a disordered multitude, only the one offends the ear, as the other offends the eyes; and there can be no pleasure but in harmony, which harmony is quantity, quality, symmetry, and unity; and though quality, quantity, and symmetry are brought by the senses, yet unity is made in the mind. Thus harmony lives in the mind; for without the mind, the senses could take no delight.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101790">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A53060_07-e101800">
          <head>Act ii.</head>
          <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e101810">
            <head>Scene. 7.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e101820">Enter the lady Ward, and doctor practice.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101830" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101840">How do you lady?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101850" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101860">Why very well doctor, how do you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101870" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor Prac.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101880">Why I was sent, as being believed you are mad.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101890" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101900">Troth doctor that's no wonder; for all the world is mad, more or less.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101910" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor Prac.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101920">Do you find any distemper in your head?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101930" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101940">My head will ache sometimes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101950" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practice</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101960">I mean a distemper in your mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101970" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e101980">My mind is troubled sometimes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e101990" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practice</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102000">That is not well: let me feel your pulse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102010" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102020">Why doctor, can you know the temper of my mind, by the feeling of my pulse?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102030" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practice</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102040">There is a great sympathy between the mind and the body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102050" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102060">But I doubt, doctor, your learned skill is many times deceived by the pulse; you will sooner find a mad distemper in the tongue or actions, than in the wrists.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102070" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practice</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102080">In troth lady, you speak reason, which those that are mad do not do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102090" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102100">O yes, doctor, but they do, as you cure diseases, by chance.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e102110">Exeunt</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="8" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e102120">
            <pb facs="121" n="218"/>
            <head>Scene 8.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e102130">Enter the lord title alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102140" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102150">O love, dissembling love, that seemest to be the best of passions, and yet torments the soul!</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e102160">He walks in a melancholy muse.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e102170">Enter master Inquirer.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102180" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master Inquirer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102190">What makes your lordship so melancholy, as to shun all your friends, to walk alone?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102200" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102210">I am in love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102220" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102230">There are many remedies for love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102240" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102250">I would you could tell me one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102260" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102270">May I know the lady you are in love with?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102280" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102290">The lady say you? she is a poor lady.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102300" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102310">Your lordship is so rich, as you may marry without a portion,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102320" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102330">O I could curse my fate, and rail at my destiny.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102340" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102350">For what?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102360" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102370">To make me fall in love with one I am ashamed to make her known.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102380" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102390">Is she so mean, and yet so beautiful?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102400" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102410">O she hath all the beauties and graces that can attract a soul to love; for surely nature sat in council to make her body, and the gods sat in council to compose her mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102420" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102430">May not I see her?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102440" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102450">Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102460" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102470">Where may I find her?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102480" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102490">Upon the next plain, under a bush that bends much like a bower, there she most commonly sits to watch her sheep; but I will go with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102500" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102510">Your lordship is not jealous?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102520" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102530">All lovers think their beloved is never secure enough.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e102540">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="9" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e102550">
            <head>Scene 9.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e102560">Enter nurse careful, as in a fright, unto the lady Ward.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102570" who="A53060_07-careful">
              <speaker>Nurse careful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102580">O my child, I am told that on a sudden you turned mad!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102590" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102600">Surely nurse your fear, or what else it may be, you seem to me to be more mad than I can find in myself to be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102610" who="A53060_07-careful">
              <speaker>Nurse Caref.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102620">That shows you are mad.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102630" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102640">If I am mad, I sucked the madness from your breast.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102650" who="A53060_07-careful">
              <pb facs="121" n="219"/>
              <speaker>Nurse Caref.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102660">I do confess, child, I have not had those mad vagaries since I gave suck, as I had before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102670" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102680">'Tis a sign you are grown old, nurse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102690" who="A53060_07-careful">
              <speaker>Nurse Caref.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102700">I confess, youth is oftener mad than age; but dear child tell me, art thou mad?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102710" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102720">Prithee nurse, lest thou shouldst become mad, go sleep to settle thy thoughts, and quiet thy mind, for I remember a witty poet, one doctor don, saith,</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e102730">Sleep is pains easy salve, and doth fulfil</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e102740">All offices, unless it be to kill. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e102750">Nurse careful cries out, as in a great fright. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102760" who="A53060_07-careful">
              <speaker>Nurse Caref.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102770">O heaven, what shall I do, what shall I do!</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e102780">Enter doctor practice.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102790" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practice</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102800">What is the matter nurse, what is the matter you shriek out so?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102810" who="A53060_07-careful">
              <speaker>Nurse Caref.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102820">O doctor, my child is mad, my child is mad; for she repeats verses.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102830" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practice</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102840">That's an ill sign indeed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102850" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102860">Doctor, did you never repeat Latin sentences when you have read lectures, nor Latin verses, when you did dispute in schools?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102870" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practice</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102880">Yes, sweet lady, a hundred times.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102890" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102900">Lord, doctor, have you been mad a hundred times, and recovered so often!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102910" who="A53060_07-careful">
              <speaker>Nurse Caref.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102920">Those were Latin verses, those were Latin verses child.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102930" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practice</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102940">Faith lady you pose me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102950" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102960">Then doctor go to school again, or at least return again to the university and study again, and then practise not to be posed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102970" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practice</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e102980">Nurse, she is not well, she must be put to a diet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e102990" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103000">But why, doctor, should you think me mad? I have done no outrageous action; and if all those that speak extravagantly should be put to a diet, as being thought mad, many a fat waste would shrink in the doublet, and many a poetical vein would be dried up, and the flame quenched out for want of radical oil to prolong it; thus wit would be starved, for want of vapour to feed it; the truth is, a spare diet may make room in a scholar's head for old dead authors to lie in; for the emptyer their heads are of wit, the fuller they may be filled with learning; for I do imagine, old dead authors lie in a scholar's head, as they say souls do, none knows where, for a million of souls to lie in as small a compass as the point of a needle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103010" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practice</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103020">Her brain is hotly distempered, and moves with an extraordinary quick motion, as may be perceived by her strange fancy: wherefore nurse you had best get her to bed; if you can, and I will prescribe some medicine and rules for her.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103030">Exit doctor.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103040" who="A53060_07-careful">
              <speaker>Nurse Caref.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103050">Come sweet child, let me put thee to bed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103060" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady Ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103070">I will go to bed, if you would have me, but good nurse believe me, I am not mad; it's true, the force of my passion hath made my reason to err; and though my reason hath gone astray, yet it is not lost: but consider well nurse, and tell me what noble mind can suffer a base servitude without rebellious passions? But howsoever, since they are of this opinion, I am content to cherish it, if you approve of it; for if I seem mad,<pb facs="122" n="220"/> the next of my kindred will beg the keeping of me for the sake of my estate; and I had rather lose my estate, and be thought mad, than lose my honour in base offices, and my freeborn liberty to be enslaved to whores; and though I do not fear my honest youth can be corrupted by ill example, yet I will not have my youth a witness to wicked and base vice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103080" who="A53060_07-careful">
              <speaker>Nurse Caref.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103090">By no means, I do not approve of these strange ways; besides, you are a ward to a gallant man, and may be marriage will alter his humour; for most commonly those back-holders that are the greatest libertines, make the best husbands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103100" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103110">'Tis true, he is of a noble nature, valiant and generous, prudent, and just, and temperate in all delights, and free from all other vices but incontinency, civil and obliging to all the world, but to me, and I could love him better than life, could he be constant, and only love me as he ought to do a wife; otherwise, death were more pleasing to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103120">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="10" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e103130">
            <head>Scene 10.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103140">Enter the lady contemplation musing, and the lady visitant comes to her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103150" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103160">You were born to do me a mischief.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103170" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady Visit.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103180">Why how?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103190" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103200">Why you have routed an army.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103210" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady Visit.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103220">Which way?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103230" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103240">I did imagine myself married, my husband being a general of an army, who had fought many battles, and had won many victories, conquered many nations, at last an unfortunate day of battle being fought, my husband being too active and venturous, making lanes of slain bodies as he went, and his horse riding thorough rivers of blood, those rivers rising so high, as his horse was forced to swim; but the blood growing thick to a jelly, obstructed his way, which made his horse furious, which fury added to his strength, forced a passage over a hill, or heap of slain bodies; but the horses spirits being spent with fury and labour, fell strengthless to the ground, with my husband upon his back; and being in the midst of his enemy's army, his enemies seeing him fall, ran about him in great numbers, and so took him prisoner: whereupon his soldiers soon missing him, thought he was killed; upon which belief, their courages grew cold, their limbs unactive, and their spirits so benumbed, as they all seemed like to a number of stone-statues; which unactive dulness gave their enemies the day without any after-blows. I being in the camp, hearing of my husband's misfortunes, ran with a distracted fear towards the enemy's camp; I being espied by some of my husband's scattered troops, was stopped in the way, and so brought back to my tent again; where, when I was there, some of my husband's officers of the army told me, that though the day was lost, yet there was a considerable body left; which I no sooner heard, but my spirits took new life, and then excusing my fear, told those commanders it was not through fear that made me run out of my tent; for I did<pb facs="122" n="212"/> not fly from my enemies, but to them, and that I sought death, and not life; and to express my courage, I told them, that if they would give me leave, I would take my husband's office, and lead the army: they told me, that if the rest of the commanders would agree to it, they were well contented: so when all the commanders met together, I spoke thus unto them.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103250">Noble friends, and valiant soldiers, you may think it a vain ambition for me to desire to lead your army, especially against so potent an enemy, and being a woman, which female sex are usually unexperienced in martial affairs, as also by nature fearful, which fears may ruin an army, by giving wrong direction, causing a confusion through distraction; and truly an army were not to be trusted unto a woman; management and ordering, if that records had not given us precedents, which is, that woman have led armies, have fought valiantly themselves, and have had good success, and not so much by fortune's favour, as by their own wise conduct: and to show that Pallas is a friend unto her own sex, is, that in all history, there are very few women then can be found, that have lost battles in the field of wars, but many that have won battles; and in all public affairs it is to be observed, the gods do generally assist our sex, whereby to show their own power, and to abate the haughty pride of men. But to induce you more; for men trust not so much unto the gods, as to their own strength, is, that you are present in all counsels and actions, to assist and direct me; besides, I am wife unto your general, who was and is an expert soldier, and a valiant man, although he now had ill fortune; but ill fortune neither lessens valour nor experience, but rather increases them. This gallant and wise man, my husband and your general, his discourses have been my tutors, and his example hath and shall be my guide; and if you dare trust me, I dare venture; otherwise I shall stay in my tent, and pray for your good success. After I had left off speaking, an old commander which had served long in the wars, and was much esteemed, answered me as thus.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103260">Noble lady, although your youth doth dissuade us, yet your beauty and wit doth encourage us; for what man, although he were possessed with fear itself, can run away when a fair lady sights? for beauty triumphs in all hearts, and commands the whole world: wherefore that man that shall or will deny to follow your command, is of a bastard-kind, although a lawful issue. With that all the rest of the commanders cried or called out, that none was so fit to lead and command them as I. Thus being chosen, I called a general muster of my soldiers, and then gave order that some of the broken regiments should be mended and made up with other broken regiments, also I made new officers in the room of those that were slain or taken prisoners, and after, I surveyed my artillery and ammunition; which done, I drew my army into a body, and after I had given order and directions for the soldiers to march towards the enemy's camp, which when the enemy heard of a new army coming towards them, they drew out the body of their army in battle array: but I shunned to fight so soon as appeared, by reason my army was tired with marching; wherefore I gave order to entrench: besides, I thought it might give my soldiers more courage, when accustomed to the fight and neighbourhood of the enemies: but withal, I made some of them give intelligence to the enemy that a woman led the army, by which they might despise us, and so become<pb facs="123" n="222"/> more negligent, by which negligence we might have an advantage: in the mean time I sent to treat of a peace, and to have my husband set at liberty; but the enemy was so averse to a peace, as they returned me both jesting and scornful answers: so when I saw no peace could be made, I drew out my army into battle array; which when the enemy perceived, they did the like; but it will be too tedious at this time to tell the form and figures I put my army into, as also what commanders led, or who commanded the horse, or who commanded the foot that day; only let me tell you, I led the van myself, and was accoutred after this manner: I had a masculine suit, and over that a cloth of silver coat, made close to my waste, which reached to the ankles of my legs; and those arms I wore being all gilt, were back, breast, gorget, pot and gauntlet, all being made light according as my strength would bear: in my hand I carried my sword; for being not accustomed, I could not wear a sword by my side, as men do, but whensoever rested, I tied it to my saddlebow, and on my head-piece I wore a great plume of feathers: as for my horse, he was coal-black, only a white star on his forehead, and three white feet; my saddle was crimson velvet, but so embroidered with silver and gold, as the ground could not be seen: but when I was mounted, I spoke as following unto the common soldiers.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103270">Worthy friends, and laborous, and valiant soldiers, you may justly wonder to see a woman thus accoutred like a man, and being one of the tender female sex to be armed as a soldier, and in a posture to fight a battle: also you may fear the success of my command, by reason I am young, and unexperienced, as also unpractised in the wars: but fear not, the gods are with me, and will assist me, and have promised to give you victory by my conduct; for they will conduct me: but the gods suffered the other battle to be lost, because many victories had made you proud, and conceited of yourselves, and your own valours, trusting more to your own strength, than to their favours or powers, whereupon the gods destroyed many of you; but since they have taken pity of you, drawn to it by your humility: whereupon the gods have commanded me to lead and conduct you; and they have also commanded me to tell you, that if you trust in them, and fight courageously, that you shall have victory, and rich spoils; for I heard the common people, of which common soldiers were of, were apt to be superstitious, and to believe in any new reports, as also to believe in miracles, prophecies, and the like, and withal, very covetous; all which, made me feign myself to be commanded immediately from the gods, and to be sent as from the gods to command them, and to declare such promises to them; for all the common soldier's sight for spoils, not for honour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103280" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady visitant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103290">O but it is not good to dissemble.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103300" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103310">Pardon me; for without policy (Which is deceit) there can be neither government in peace or war: wherefore it is a virtue in a statesman, or a commander, to be a dissembler, although it be a vice in any other man; but you have put me out as you always do, and therefore I will tell you no more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103320" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady visitant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103330">Nay, pray make an end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103340" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103350">I will not; but I could have told you how I killed the general of the enemy with my own hand, and how I released my husband, and of such gallant acts as you never heard the like of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103360" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady visitant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103370">O pray tell me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103380" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <pb facs="123" n="223"/>
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103390">Which if I do, let me never contemplate more, which would be worse than death to me, by reason it is the only pleasure of my life.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103400">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A53060_07-e103410">
          <head>Act iii.</head>
          <div n="11" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e103420">
            <head>Scene. 11.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103430">Enter poor virtue alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103440" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103450">O love, though thou art bred within the soul, yet by the senses thou art begotten, or else by some opinions; for virtue is but the tutor, or guide, for to instruct or lead thee in a perfect way but though I lead love right, yet may it meet opposers.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103460">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="12" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e103470">
            <head>Scene 12.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103480">Enter the lord courtship, and doctor practice.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103490" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103500">How do you find my ward?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103510" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practice</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103520">Truly she is somewhat distempered; for her wit is very quick.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103530" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103540">That's it; for she being naturally of a dull disposition, and of a mild humour, and her brain slow of conceits, as also unpractised in speaking, should of a sudden fall into high raptures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103550" who="A53060_07-practice">
              <speaker>Doctor practice</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103560">You say true, my lord; and it is to be feared this distemper will increase.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103570" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103580">Pray doctor have a regard and care to her distemper; for I would not willingly have a wife that is more mad than natural women are.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103590">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="13" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e103600">
            <head>Scene 13.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103610">Enter lord title, and master Inquirer.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103620" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103630">She is not here.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103640">Enter poor virtue, with a sheephook in her hand. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103650" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103660">O yonder she comes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103670" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103680">She hath a garb not like a farmer's maid, but rather one<pb facs="124" n="224"/> that's nobly born, and her garments, though mean, sit nearly on her body.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103690">Master adviser goeth to her. </stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103700">Fair shepherdess, it is a melancholy life you lead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103710" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103720">It is a course of life suits best to my condition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103730" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103740">You may change this condition if you please.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103750" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103760">I had rather lie honoured in death, than by dishonour raised to glorious state of life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103770" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103780">But here you live like a creature not produced by mankind, amongst beasts, having no conversation by discourse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103790" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor Vir.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103800">Want of speech makes not beasts beasts, but want of reason, and want of reason makes a man a beast; and speech rather disturbs than benefits the life, when silence and pure thoughts make men like angels, whereas speech sometimes expresses men like devils, blaspheming heaven and God, fomenting factions amongst their kind, betraying trust and friendship, cozening innocency, flattering vice, reproaching virtue, and with distractions strives to pull down honour from its feat; where silence refines the thoughts, elevates the fancy, quickens wit, strengthens judgement, allays anger, sweetens melancholy, and collects the reason.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103810" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103820">Thou art a wonder, and for this one speech I do adores thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103830" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103840">I should be sorry so worthy a person, and so noble a gentleman as you seem to be, should adore my speech, when it might be chance that did produce it, and not wit or judgement.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103850" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103860">Thy speech is like to Orpheus' harp, it charms all ears that hear it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103870" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103880">I wish my speech were like a loadstone, to draw the iron hearts of men to pity and compassion, to charity and devotion.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103890">Poor virtue offers to be gone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103900" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103910">Pray stay and choose me for your love, and let me go along with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103920" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103930">An amorous lovers, as I believe your lordship is, never walks in sober pace, nor hath a constant and assured mind; for amorous lovers run with might and main, as if desires were catched with haste.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103940">Poor virtue goes out, lord title follows her. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103950">Master Inquirer alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103960" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e103970">I perceive farmers breed pretty maids, and honest, as well as lambs and doves, and witty and well-behaved maids, as well as courts and cities do. O that I were unmarried, that I might wed this sweet, fair country-maid!</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e103980">Enter Mall Mean-bred, with a pail in her hand. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e103990" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104000">But stay, here comes another by my troth, a very pretty lass, but yet her garments sit not so neat, nor becoming, nor is her behaviour so graceful as the other maids was. Sweet mistress!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104010" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104020">Pray keep your jeers to yourself, I am no mistress.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104030" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104040">You may be my mistress, if you please, and I will be your servant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104050" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104060">What to do?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104070" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <pb facs="124" n="225"/>
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104080">What you please.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104090" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104100">I am seldom pleased, and an idle fellow will anger me more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104110" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104120">I will be very industrious, if you please to set me to work.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e104130">Enter Maudlin housewife her mother, she falls a beating her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104140" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104150">You idle slut, do you stand loitering here, when it is more than time the cows were milked?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e104160">[Mall Mean-bred flings away her milking-pail.]</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104170" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104180">Go milk them yourself with a murrain, since you are so light-fingered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104190" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104200">I will milk your sides first.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e104210">The mother goeth to beat her again, Mall Mean-bred her daughter runs away from her mother, she follows her, running to catch her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104220" who="A53060_07-inquirer">
              <speaker>Master inqui.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104230">I marry sir, this is right as a farmer's daughter should be; but in my conscience the other maid that was here before her is a bastard, begotten by some gentleman.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e104240">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="14" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e104250">
            <head>Scene 14.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e104260">Enter sir John argument, and the lady conversation.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104270" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversa.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104280">Let me tell you, sir John argument, love delivers up the whole soul to the thing beloved; and the truth is, none but one soul can love another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104290" who="A53060_07-argument">
              <speaker>Argum.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104300">But justice, madam, must be the rule of love; wherefore those souls which love must give the bodies leave to join.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104310" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104320">O no; pure souls may converse without gross bodies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104330" who="A53060_07-argument">
              <speaker>Argument.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104340">Were it not for the senses, madam, souls could have no acquaintance, and without an acquaintance, there can be no reciprocal affection; and will you make the senses, which are the souls chief confidence, to be strangers or enemies?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104350" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104360">I would have them converse, but not interrupt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104370" who="A53060_07-argument">
              <speaker>Argum.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104380">The bodies must have mutual friendship and correspondency with each other, or otherwise they may dissemble, or betray the souls; or abuse the trust, loose appetites or wandering senses or contrary humours; and what can interrupt love more than the disagreement of bodies?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104390" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104400">The senses and appetites of the body, are but as subject to the soul.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104410" who="A53060_07-argument">
              <speaker>Argument.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104420">But 'tis impossible for foreign princes, as I will compare two loving souls unto, can live in peace and mutual amity, if their subjects disagree.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e104430"><pb facs="125" n="226"/>Enter mistress troublesome.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104440" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104450">O mistress troublesome, you are welcome; for you shall end the dispute between sir John argument and I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104460" who="A53060_07-troublesome">
              <speaker>Troublesome.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104470">If you cannot decide the dispute yourselves, I shall never do it. But what is the dispute madam?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104480" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104490">Whether there can be a perfect friendship of souls without a reciprocal and mutual conversation and conjunctions of bodies?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104500" who="A53060_07-troublesome">
              <speaker>Troublesome.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104510">Faith, madam, I think it would be a very faint friendship betwixt the souls, without the bodies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104520" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104530">I perceive sir John argument and you would never make Platonic lovers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104540" who="A53060_07-troublesome">
              <speaker>Troublesome.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104550">Faith, madam, I think Platonic is a word without sense.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104560" who="A53060_07-argument">
              <speaker>Argument.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104570">You say right, mistress troublesome, it is an insensible love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104580" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104590">It is the soul of love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104600" who="A53060_07-troublesome">
              <speaker>Troublesome.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104610">What's that, madam, a ghost, or spirit?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104620" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104630">Indeed it hath no material body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104640" who="A53060_07-argument">
              <speaker>Argument.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104650">No, for it is an incorporal thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104660" who="A53060_07-troublesome">
              <speaker>Troublesome.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104670">What is an incorporal thing, sir John?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104680" who="A53060_07-argument">
              <speaker>Argument.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104690">Why, nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104700" who="A53060_07-troublesome">
              <speaker>Troublesome.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104710">Pray leave this discourse, or else you will talk nonsense.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104720" who="A53060_07-argument">
              <speaker>Argument.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104730">That's usual in conversation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104740" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104750">Setting aside this discourse at mistress Troublesomes request, pray tell me how the lady contemplation doth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104760" who="A53060_07-troublesome">
              <speaker>Troublesome.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104770">Faith madam, by the course of her life one might think she were an incorporal thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104780" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104790">Why?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104800" who="A53060_07-troublesome">
              <speaker>Troublesome.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104810">Because she makes but little use of her body, living always within her mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104820" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104830">Then her body stands but as a cypher amongst the figures of her thoughts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104840" who="A53060_07-troublesome">
              <speaker>Troublesome.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104850">Just so, by my troth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104860" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104870">Pray bring me acquainted with the lady contemplation. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104880" who="A53060_07-troublesome">
              <speaker>Troublesome.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104890">If it be possible, I will; but the lady visitant can do it better than I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104900" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104910">I am resolved I will visit her.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e104920">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="15" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e104930">
            <head>Scene 15.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e104940">Enter the lord courtship, and the lady Ward.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104950" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courtship.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104960">What, is your passion over?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e104970" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e104980">My passion will strive to maintain my honour, and you may take my life; but as long as I live, my passion will fight in the quarrel. But what man of honour will make a bawd of her he intends to make his wife? and what man of honour will be cruel to those that are weak, helpless, and shiftless? and what man of honour will be uncivil to the meanest of our sex? It is more noble to flatter us, than to quarrel with us;<pb facs="125" n="227"/> but that I have heard you are valiant, I should think you were a base coward, and such a one that would quarrel in a brothel-house, rather than fight in a battle: but I perceive you are one that loves pleasure more than honour, and life more than fame; and I hate to be in that man's company, or to make a husband, whose courage lies in voluptousness, and his life in infamy: I will sooner marry death, than such a man.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e104990">The lady Ward goes out. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e105000">Lord courtship alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105010" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105020">Her words have shot through my soul, and have made a sensible wound therein. How wisely she did speak! how beautiful appeared! Her mind is full of honour, and the actions of her life are built upon noble principles; so young, so wise, so fair, so chaste, and I to use her so basely as I have done! O how I hate myself for doing so unworthily!</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e105030">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="16" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e105040">
            <head>Scene 16.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e105050">Enter sir effeminate lovely, and poor virtue.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105060" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effemin. Lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105070">The more ground is trodden on, the easier the path to walk in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105080" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105090">It seems so, that you visit me so often.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105100" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105110">Why, thou art such sweet company, and behavest thyself so prettily, as I cannot choose but visit thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105120" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105130">I would, if I could, behave myself so to the world, as my indiscretion might not defame me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105140" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105150">Why do you think of a fame?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105160" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105170">Why not? since fame many times arises from poor cottages, as well as from great palaces; witness the country labouring-man, that was taken from the plough, and made an emperor, as being thought sittest to rule, both for justice and wisdom, and he was more famous than those that were born of an heroic line, and were of royal dignity; and David a shepherd, became a King. 'tis merit that deserves a fame, not birth; and sometimes merit hath its desert, though but seldom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105180" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105190">Thy discourse would tempt any man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105200" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105210">Mistake not my discourse, it hath no such devilish design; for to tempt, is to pervert: 'tis true, my nature takes delight to delight and please others, and not to cross or displease any, yet not to tempt, or to delude with counterfeit demeanours, or fair insinuating words, smooth speech, or oiled tongue, to draw from virtue's side, but to persuade and plead in virtue's cause.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105220" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105230">Thy very looks would gain a cause, before thy tongue could plead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105240" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105250">Alas! man's countenance is like the sea, which ebbs and flows as passion moves the mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105260" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105270">I am sure love moves my mind, and makes it in a fiery heat.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105280" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <pb facs="126" n="228"/>
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105290">If it be noble love, it is like the sun, which runs about to give both light and heat to all the world, that else would sit in darkness, and be both cold and sterile; so doth a noble mind run with industry to help those in distress, his bounty heats, his counsel and advice gives light.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105300" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105310">I love you so much, sweetheart, that since you will not be my mistress, you shall be my wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105320" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105330">Indeed I will not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105340" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105350">Will you refuse me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105360" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105370">Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105380" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105390">Wherefore?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105400" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105410">Because I know, though you may use me well at first, after a time you'll be divorced.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105420" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105430">I will never part from thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105440" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105450">O yes but you will, for youth and beauty most commonly are inconstant; for vain ambition, and flattering praises, corrupt that mind that lives therein, and is pleased therewith.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e105460">Poor virtue goes out. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e105470">Effeminate lovely alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105480" who="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely">
              <speaker>Effem. lovely.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105490">Well, I will become a new man, and cast off all vanity, and study moral philosophy, to gain this maid; for then perchance she will love me.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e105500">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="17" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e105510">
            <head>Scene 17.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e105520">Enter lady conversation, and sir vain compliment.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105530" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105540">Compliments are the worst sort of conversation, for they are not sociable; besides, truth holds no intelligence nor correspondence with them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105550" who="A53060_07-vain_compliment">
              <speaker>Sir vain compl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105560">Truth is no compliment as flattery, and I speak nothing but what truth hath dictated to my tongue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105570" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105580">Those praises you gave me were writ by speech, in so fine a style of eloquence, with such flourishing letters of words, as I cannot believe but that custom of self-conceited wit or passion, hath given the scribe, which is the tongue, a bribe to flatter me.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e105590">Enter the lady contemplation, and mistress troublesome, to the lady conversation, and sir vain compliment.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105600" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105610">This is a wonder to see you, lady Contemplation, abroad, I doubt it doth prognosticate some change of fortune, pray Jove it be good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105620" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105630">All the ill will fall on me, madam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105640" who="A53060_07-troubles">
              <speaker>Mistress troubles.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105650">Nay, faith madam, she accounts company a worse fortune than the ruin of a kingdom, and you cannot conceive with what difficulty I have got her abroad; for at first I did persuade her with all the<pb facs="126" n="229"/> rhetoric I had, and pleaded with as powerful arguments as I could find, any promised more than I was able to perform, and nothing of this could get her forth, until I told her I would bring your ladyship to visit her, and that forced her out; for she said, she would rather trouble you, than you should trouble her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105660" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105670">Faith, contemplation, thou art only sit to keep beasts company; for what difference is there betwixt beasts and men, but conversation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105680" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105690">Indeed beasts want that folly of idle conversation, and the error of speaking, as much as the vanity of dressing, and the custom of dissembling; for they spend their time more prudently, quietly, easily, honestly, so more happily; and if it were for no other reason than speaking, I had rather be a beast, than of mankind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105700" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105710">O fie, oh fie, you are a beastly lady.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105720" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105730">No, madam, beasts have no false titles of honour, their honour lives in their natures, not in their names.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105740" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105750">Who that may choose, or have their liberty, would spend their time in idle thoughts?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105760" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105770">All that are wise, and would be happy; for should not we think that man were mad, that leaves a peaceful habitation, and thrusts himself in foreign broils? or should not we think a King were most unjust, that makes his peaceful and obedient subjects slaves to strange princes? The mind's a commonwealth, and the thoughts are the citizens therein, and reason rules as King, or ought to do: but there is no reason we should vex our thoughts with outward things, or make them slaves unto the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105780" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105790">But thoughts would want employment, were it not for the world, and idleness were worse than slavish toils.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105800" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105810">The thoughts, without the world's materials, can create millions of worlds, only with the help of imagination.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105820" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105830">Then your mind and the world are mere strangers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105840" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105850">I say not so; for though the world draws not my mind to wander up and down, yet my mind draws the world to it, than pencils out each several part and piece, and hangs that landscape in my brain, on which my thoughts do view with judgements eyes. Thus the world is in my mind; although my mind is not in the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105860" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105870">Then you inchant the world?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105880" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105890">I had rather inchant the world, than the world should inchant me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105900" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105910">If the mind be a commonwealth, as you said even now it was, pray tell me of what degree the passions are of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105920" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105930">They are the nobles thereof, and magistrates therein; each several passion still governs in its turn and office.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105940" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105950">And what are the appetites?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105960" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e105970">The appetites are none of the mind's citizens, but they are an unruly rout that dwell in the senses, which are the suburbs of the body: indeed the appetites are the outlawries, and do oft-times much hurt with their disorders, insomuch as they, many times, disturb the mind's tranquillity, and peace. But, madam, lest the appetite of talking should disturb the mind, I shall kiss your ladyship's hand, and leave you to those that are more delightful and pleasanter company than I am.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e105980">Exit.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e105990" who="A53060_07-troubles">
              <pb facs="127" n="230"/>
              <speaker>Mistress trouble.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106000">Lady conversation, I perceive you and sir vain compliment are grown dull with the lady contemplation's company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106010" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106020">Mercury defend me from her; for I would not keep her company for Jove's mansion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106030" who="A53060_07-vain_compliment">
              <speaker>Vain Compl.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106040">And Cupid defend me from her; for I would not be bound to court her for the favours Venus gives to Mars. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106050" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106060">Lord what a dull piece of gravity she is!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106070" who="A53060_07-vain_compliment">
              <speaker>Vain Compl.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106080">She looks as if she conversed with none but ghosts and spirits, walking in moonshine, and solitary and dismal places.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106090" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106100">Let us talk of her no more; for I am so far from keeping her acquaintance, as I hate to hear her named.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e106110">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="18" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e106120">
            <head>Scene 18.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e106130">Enter the lord courtship, and the lady Ward.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106140" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courtship.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106150">My sweet, fair maid, I cannot hope thy pardon, for my crimes are not only great, but many; for I have not only used you unkindly, uncivilly, ungentlemanly, which are vices and crimes that cankerfret the fame of honour, and bury all noble qualities; but I have used you barbarously, cruelly, and inhumanly, which are sins sufficient to annihilate all the masculine race; and surely, if there be that we call justice in nature, it will, unless thy virtue redeem them, and save them with thy pity: wherefore, for the sake of the generality, though not for my particular, pardon me. Thus will you become a deity to your whole sex and ours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106160" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106170">I am sure your lordship is a particular punishment to me, which heaven send me quit of.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e106180">She goes out, he follows her.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A53060_07-e106190">
          <head>Act iv.</head>
          <div n="19" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e106200">
            <head>Scene. 19.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e106210">Enter sir fancy poet, and the lady contemplation.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106220" who="A53060_07-fancy_poet">
              <speaker>Sir Fan. poet.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106230">Lady, you smother your thoughts, and stifle your conception in the close closet of study.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106240" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106250">No sir, I only keep them warm, being tender and weak.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106260" who="A53060_07-fancy_poet">
              <speaker>Sir Fan. poet.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106270">They will grow stronger in the air of conversation; but when continually kept close in the chamber of contemplation, they will be apt to fall into many several diseases, as melancholy opinions, and extravagant fancies, which may overheat the mind, and sire the thoughts: wherefore lady let me give you counsel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106280" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106290">What counsel would you give me? as a lawyer, or Physician?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106300" who="A53060_07-fancy_poet">
              <pb facs="127" n="231"/>
              <speaker>Sir Fan. poet.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106310">As a physician.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106320" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106330">For the body, or the mind?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106340" who="A53060_07-fancy_poet">
              <speaker>Sir Fan. poet.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106350">For the mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106360" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106370">The physicians for the mind are divine:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106380" who="A53060_07-fancy_poet">
              <speaker>Sir Fan. poet.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106390">No, the best physicians for the mind are poets.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106400" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106410">How will you prove that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106420" who="A53060_07-fancy_poet">
              <speaker>Sir Fan. poet.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106430">By example and skill; for when the mind is raging mad; poets, with gentle persuasions, in smooth numbers, and soft music, cure it; and when the mind is despairing, poets draw hopes into numbers, which beats out the doubtful foe: and for example.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106440">David with his poetical inspirations, and harpsical harmonious music, allayed the ill spirit, and raging passion of Saul; for poets take from the sweet spring of nature, an oil of love, and from heaven, the balsam of mercy, and pour them through golden numbers, and pipes of wit, into the festered wounds of despair, when oft-times divines, in stead of suppling oil, pour in corroding vitriol, and in stead of healing balsams, pour in burning sulphur, which are terrifying threats, and fearful menaces: wherefore lady, let me advise you as a poetical physician, to keep your mind cool, and your thoughts in equal temper; wherefore in order thereto, when the mind is wrapped in the mantle of imagination, if it finds itself very hot therewith, let it lay that mantle by, and bathe itself in the fresh, clear, pure rivers of discourse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106450" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106460">By your favour, sir, for the most part, the mind becomes hotter with the motion of the tongue, than the mantle of imagination; for when the tongue hath liberty, it runs wildly about, and drags the mind after it; and rather than I will have my minded dragged and hurried about by my unruly tongue, which will neither endure the bit of reason, nor the bridle of discretion, but runs beyond all sense, I will tie up my tongue with the cords of silence, in the stable of the mouth, and pull down the portcullis of the teeth before it, and shut the doors of my lips upon it. Thus shall it be treble locked, and kept with the key of judgement, and the authority of prudence.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e106470">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="20" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e106480">
            <head>Scene 20.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e106490">Enter the lady conversation, and a grave matron. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106500" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106510">Did you hear him say he had lain with me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106520" who="A53060_07-matron">
              <speaker>Matron.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106530">Yes, madam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106540" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106550">O the wicked, base vainglory of men, to bely the pure chastity of a woman! But surely he did not plainly express so much in clear words, as by nods, winks, shrugs, dark sentences, or broken discourses?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106560" who="A53060_07-matron">
              <speaker>Matron.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106570">He said plainly, he had lain with you in an unlawful manner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106580" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106590">Fates assist me in revenge; for it is no dishonour to be revenged of a base person, that hath maliciously slandered me, or vaingloriously injured me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106600" who="A53060_07-matron">
              <speaker>Matron.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106610">Revenge is against the laws of honour, madam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106620" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106630">It may be against the tenets of some particular religion,<pb facs="128" n="232"/> or religious opinions. But a noble revenge is the ground or foundation of heroic honour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106640" who="A53060_07-matron">
              <speaker>Matron.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106650">But what do you call a noble revenge?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106660" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106670">First, to be an open enemy, as to declare the enmity; next, to declare their endeavour to prosecute to the utmost of their power, either their enemies estate, liberty, and life; whereas a base revenger is to dissemble, in professing they have forgotten and forgiven their injury, and pardoned their enemy, yet underhand and disguisedly endeavour to do their enemy a mischief. Not but an honourable revenger may choose their time for executing their revenge; but they must declare they will be revenged before they execute their revenge, and let their enemies stand upon their guard.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106680" who="A53060_07-matron">
              <speaker>Matron.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106690">But a revengeful woman is not good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106700" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106710">Why not, as well as a revengeful man? For why may not a woman revenge her scandalised honour as well as a man? Is there any reason why it should be a dishonour for a man to pass by a disgrace, and for a woman to revenge her disgrace? Is it not as great a blemish to the honour of a woman, to be said to be unchaste, as for a man to be said to be a coward? And shall a woman only sit and weep over her lost honour, whilst a man fights to regain his? And shall it be thought no dishonour for a man to pistol, or at least bastonade another man for an injury, or an affront received, and a fault for a woman to do, or cause to be done the like? Must women only sit down with foolish patience, and endure wrong, when men may execute revenge with fury? These were both injustice, and an unjust act of education to our sex; as also it would be an unjust sentence, not only from men, but from the gods, since neither gods nor men will suffer injury, wrong, or dishonour, without revenge: but if gods, men, and education should be so unjust to our sex, yet there is no reason in nature we should be so unjust to ourselves: but for my part, as I am constant to an honest friend, and can easily forgive an honourable enemy, so I can never forgive a malicious foe, nor forget a vainglorious bragging fool, or false slandering knave, but will persecute them to the utmost of my power, and the weight of my revenge should be according to the pressure of my injury, or dishonour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106720" who="A53060_07-matron">
              <speaker>Matron.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106730">But let me tell you, madam, those that brag are seldom believed, and there is none that believe these vain bragging ranters; for it's well known, that all ranters are idle deboyst persons, and do usually belie the most honourable and chaste ladies, for which all worthy persons hate them, and account them so base, as they will shun their companies; no man of honour will come near them, unless it be to beat them. But if you appear to the world as concerned, you may raise those doubts which would never have been raised, had you took no notice thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106740" who="A53060_07-conversation">
              <speaker>Lady conversation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106750">Indeed disputes raise doubts; wherefore I will not bring it into a dispute, but take your counsel, and take no notice of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106760" who="A53060_07-matron">
              <speaker>Matron.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106770">You will do wisely, lady.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e106780">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="21" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e106790">
            <pb facs="128" n="233"/>
            <head>Scene 21.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e106800">Enter sir golden riches to poor virtue.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106810" who="A53060_07-golden_riches">
              <speaker>Sir gold. Rich.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106820">I wish my tongue as smooth as oil, to make my words as soft as air, that they may spread about your heart, there intermixed with your affection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106830" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106840">Words cannot win my love, no more than wealth, nor is my heart subject to those infections.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106850" who="A53060_07-golden_riches">
              <speaker>Sir gold. Rich.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106860">I will build thee palaces of burnished gold, where thou shalt be worshipped whilst thou livest, and when thou diest, I will erect a monument more famous than Mausolus' was.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106870" who="A53060_07-poor_virtue">
              <speaker>Poor virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106880">My virtue shall build me a monument far richer, and more lasting; for the materials with which it shall be built, shall be tried chastity, as pure gold, and innocency, as marble white, and constancy, as undissolving diamonds, and modesty, as rubies red, love shall the altar be, and piety, as incense sweet, ascend to heaven, truth, as the oil, shall feed the lamp of memory, whereby the flame of fame shall never go out.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e106890">Exit.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e106900">Sir golden riches alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106910" who="A53060_07-golden_riches">
              <speaker>Sir gold. Rich.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106920">And is she gone? are riches of no force? Then I will bury myself within the bowels of the earth, so deep, that men shall never reach me, nor light shall find me out.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e106930">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="22" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e106940">
            <head>Scene 22.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e106950">Enter mistress messenger, and the lady Amorous's woman, and lord courtship.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106960" who="A53060_07-messenger">
              <speaker>Mistress messenger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106970">My lord, my lady, the lady amorous, remembers her service to you, and sent me to tell you her husband is gone out of town, and she desires to have the happiness of your company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e106980" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courtship.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e106990">Pray present my service in the humblest manner to your lady, and pray her to excuse me; for though I cannot say I am sick, yet I am far from being well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107000" who="A53060_07-messenger">
              <speaker>Mistress Messen.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107010">I shall, my lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e107020">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="23" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e107030">
            <pb facs="129" n="234"/>
            <head>Scene 23.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e107040">Enter the lord title, and then enters a servant to him. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107050" who="A53060_07-servant">
              <speaker>Servant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107060">My lord, there is an old man without desires to speak with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107070" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107080">Direct him hither.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e107090">Servant goes out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e107100">Enter old humanity.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107110" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107120">Old man, what have you to say to me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107130" who="A53060_07-old_humanity">
              <speaker>Old humanity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107140">I am come to desire your lordship not to persecute a poor young maid, one that is friendless, and your lordship is powerful, and therefore dangerous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107150" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107160">What poor maid do you mean?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107170" who="A53060_07-old_humanity">
              <speaker>Old human</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107180">A maid called poor virtue. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107190" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107200">Do you know her?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107210" who="A53060_07-old_humanity">
              <speaker>Old human</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107220">Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107230" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107240">Are you her father?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107250" who="A53060_07-old_humanity">
              <speaker>Old human</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107260">No, I am her servant, and have been maintained by her noble family these threescore years, and upwards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107270" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107280">Ha, her noble family! what, or who is she?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107290" who="A53060_07-old_humanity">
              <speaker>Old humanity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107300">She is a lady, born from a noble stock, and hath been choicely bred, but ruined by misfortunes, which makes her poorly serve.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107310" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107320">Alas he weeps! Who were her parents?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107330" who="A53060_07-old_humanity">
              <speaker>Old human</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107340">The lord morality, and the lady piety. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107350" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107360">Sure it cannot be: but why should I doubt? her beauty, wit, and sweet demeanour, declares her noble pedigree: the lord morality was a famous man, and was a great commander, and wise in making laws, and prudent for the common good: he was a staff and prop unto the commonwealth, till civil wars did throw it down, where he fell under it. But honest friend, how shall I know this for a truth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107370" who="A53060_07-old_humanity">
              <speaker>Old human</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107380">Did not your lordship hear he had a child?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107390" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107400">Yes that I did, an only daughter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107410" who="A53060_07-old_humanity">
              <speaker>Old human</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107420">This is she I mention, and if times mend, will have her father's estate, as being her father's heir; but to prove it, and her birth, I will bring all those servants that lived with her, and with her father, and all his tenants, that will witness the truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107430" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107440">When I consider, and bring her and her actions to my mind, I cannot doubt the truth, and for the news, thou shalt be my adopted father, and my bosom-friend; I'll be a staff for thy old age to lean upon, my shoulders shall give strength unto thy feeble limbs, and on my neck shalt lay thy restless head,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107450" who="A53060_07-old_humanity">
              <speaker>Old human</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107460">Heaven bless you, and I shall serve you as my old age will give me leave.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e107470">Exit lord title, leading him forth. </stage>
          </div>
          <div n="24" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e107480">
            <pb facs="129" n="235"/>
            <head>Scene 24.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e107490">Enter lord courtship, and the lady Ward.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107500" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107510">Thou celestial creature, do not believe that I am so presumptuous to ask thy love, I only beg thy pardon, that when my body lies in the silent grave, you give my restless soul a pass, and leave to walk amongst sad lovers in dark and gloomy shades; and though I cannot weep to show my penitence, yet I can bleed.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e107520">He offers her a dagger.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107530">Here, take this instrument of death, for only by your hands I wish to die.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e107540">Give me as many wounds as pores in skin,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e107550">That I may bleed sufficient for my sin. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107560" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady Ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107570">It seems strange to me, that you, a wise man, or at least accounted so, should fall into such extremes, as one while to hate me to death, and now to profess to love me beyond life!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107580" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107590">My debaucheries blinded my judgement, nor did I know thy worth, or my own error, until thy wise wit gave the light to my dark understanding, and you have drawn my bad life, and all my unworthy actions therein, so naturally in your discourse, as now I view them, I do hate myself as much as you have cause to hate me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107600" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady Ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107610">I only hate your crimes, but for those excellent qualities, and true virtues that dwell in your soul, I love and honour; and if you think me worthy to make me your wife, and will love me according as my honest life will deserve your affections, I shall be proud of the honour, and thank fortune or heaven for the gift.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107620" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107630">Sure you cannot love me, and the world would condemn you if you should, and all your sex will hate you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107640" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady Ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107650">The world many times condemns even justice herself, and women, for the most part, hate that they should love and honour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107660" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107670">But can you love me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107680" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady Ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107690">I can, and do love you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107700" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107710">How happy am I, to enjoy a world of beauty, wit, virtue, and sweet graces.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e107720">Leads her forth.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e107730">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="25" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e107740">
            <pb facs="130" n="236"/>
            <head>Scen. 25.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e107750">Enter the lord title, and Roger farmer, and Maudlin housewife his wife. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107760" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107770">Honest Roger and Maudlin,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A53060_07-e107780">this scene was written by the lord marquess of Newcastle.</note> I present you with a kind good-morrow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107790" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107800">Present me? Bless your lordship, I should present you with a couple of capons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107810" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107820">'Tis a salutation when you salute; but how do you then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107830" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107840">Very well, I thank your honour: how do you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107850" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107860">Well, enough of compliments, I am come with a petition to you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107870" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107880">What is that, is't please your honour?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107890" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107900">A suit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107910" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107920">Byrlakin I have need of one, for I have but poor and bare clothing on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107930" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107940">No, Roger, it is a request and desire I have you should grant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107950" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107960">Grant, or to farm let, no sir, I will not part with my lease.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107970" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e107980">Roger, you understand me not, therefore let me speak with Maudlin your wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e107990" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108000">There she is sir, spare her not, for she is good metal I'll warrant your honour; wipe your lips maudlin, and answer him every time that he moves thee, and give him as good as he brings: Maudlin, were he twenty lords, hold up your head, Maudlin, be not hollow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108010" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108020">I'll warrant you husband, I'll satisfy him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108030" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108040">Honest Maudlin. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108050" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108060">That's more than your lordship knows.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108070" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108080">Why then maudlin. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108090" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108100">That's my name indeed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108110" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108120">You have a maid here in your house.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108130" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108140">I hope so forsooth; but I will not answer for no virgin in this wicked world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108150" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108160">Well said Maudlin; nay your honour will get nothing of my Maudlin, I'll warrant you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108170" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108180">Well, this supposed maid is poor virtue, that's her name, I desire you will let her live with me, this poor virtue. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108190" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108200">God bless you honour from her, it is not fit for a lord, and a great nobleman to meddle with virtue, your honour should not foul your fingers with her: besides, she will never stay in a great man's house, neither is it fit she should; and your honour's servants will hate her like the devil, for she will please nobody as she should do, a very peevish, ill-natured girl forsooth she is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108210" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108220">Why how doth she agree then with you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108230" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108240">Alas forsooth, if it please your honour, virtue may live in a cottage, when she will be whipped out of a court, or a great lords palace; they may talk of her, but they will never give her leave to live and board with them: it may be they give their chaplain leave to talk of her a Sundays, or so forsooth, but talks but talk, for they forget her the six days after,<pb facs="130" n="237"/> and never mind her; for indeed she is a very peevish girl, and not fit for gentlefolks company, that's the truth of it, hardly for poor folks.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108250" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108260">Why you agree well with her?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108270" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108280">Nay by the faith of my body do I not; for I can hardly go to market, and be merry, as I use to be, and all long of her peevishness: nay I cannot go to order one of our busy thrashers, but she troubles me; or to speak with the carter, but she whip, in presently, or discourse with the ploughman about his ploughshare, how he should order it for my advantage, but she troubles me; or about our husbandman, how and where he should sow his seed, but she vexes me still: such a life, the gods help me, as I am e'en weary of myself. Speak Roger, is it not true?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108290" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108300">True Maudlin as steel, I never was merry since she was in my house, the maypole is down since she came.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108310" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108320">I Roger that 'tis, the more the pity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108330" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108340">And the towns green is a meadow, and the poor big-pipers cheeks are fallen into a consumption, hardly wind to speak withal; the morris-dancers bells are silenced, and their cross garters held superstitious, idolatrous, and profane; the may-lord and his lady deposed, and the hobby-horse is forgotten; nay the whitson-lord and lady are banished, merry wakes abolished, and the poor alewives beggared,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108350" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108360">Ay, ay, and all since this melancholy girl virtue came into our house.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e108370">She cries.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108380">I cannot choose but cry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108390" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108400">Thou art true Maudlin then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108410" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108420">Yes, with small beer, that's the calamity of it; therefore bless every good subject from so melancholy a thing as this girl virtue is: but we have a daughter, and it please your honour's worship, that will give you good content, and please most of your household; for she is a lusty wench, though I say't that should not say't: did you but see her swim like a tench on our town-green, encircling the maypole, and at the end of a hornpipe, when she is to be kissed, how modestly the wries her head away, but so as to be civil; nay she hath been well educated, my own natural daughter, for indeed Roger, I was with child with her before you married me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108430" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108440">Peace Maudlin, all truths are not to be spoken of; for should that be, many a worshipful person would be very angry; but our vicar made all well betwixt thee and me, Maudlin: but I beseech your honour take my daughter, for you will find her another manner of woman than virtue is, for she is not like her i'faith, nor any thing that belongs to her, she is better blessed than so.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108450" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108460">No, I will have poor virtue, or none.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108470" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108480">Faith if you have virtue, you are sure to have her poor, for I never knew any of her family rich, the gods do not bless them, I think, in this world; but if you will have her, take her, shall he not, Maudlin?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108490" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108500">Yes, husband, and the house is well rid of her, and let us bless ourselves for it; for now we shall be like our neighbours again, we will not abate them an hair, the best in the parish shall not live merrier than we will now for all sports: why, vanity and sin, husband, is the liberty of the subject, and the seven deadly sins are the fundamental laws of the kingdom, from the greatest to the least, if poor folks might have their right. Well, your honour shall have her, but you will be as weary of her as we have been, the gods bless your honour, but alas you do not know what this<pb facs="131" n="238"/> girl virtue is, lords have no guess at her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108510" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108520">Well Maudlin, let me have her, I desire no more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108530" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108540">Nor we neither, if it pleases your honour, and so the gods give you good of her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108550" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108560">Let me speak to his honour, Maudlin. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108570" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108580">Do so Roger. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108590" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108600">I give your lordship many thanks.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108610" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108620">For what?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108630" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108640">For ridding our house of this troublesome girl.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108650" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title,</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108660">And I thank you for it too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108670" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108680">When thanks on all sides happen, we are eased. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108690" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108700">And I with your poor virtue am well pleased. </p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e108710">The lord goes out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e108720">As they were going forth, Maudlin speaks. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108730" who="A53060_07-maudlin">
              <speaker>Maudlin.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108740">Mark the end of it, Roger. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108750" who="A53060_07-roger">
              <speaker>Roger.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108760">Yes Maudlin, the end crowns the work.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e108770">Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e108780">Here ends my lord marquess's scene.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A53060_07-e108790">
          <head>Act iv.</head>
          <div n="26" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e108800">
            <head>Scene. 26.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e108810">Enter the lady visitant to the lady contemplation, who was musing to herself. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108820" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady Visit.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108830">What always musing? Shall I never find thee in a sociable humour?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108840" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108850">I would you had come sooner, or stayed longer away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108860" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady Visit.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108870">Why prithee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108880" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108890">I will tell you: a while since, there came the muses to visit me, being all either mad, or drunk, for they tossed and tumbled me, and rumbled me about, from one to the other, as I thought they would a divided me amongst them: at last came in the sciences to visit me, with sober faces, grave countenances, stayed and formal behaviours, and after they had saluted me, they began to talk very seriously to me, their discourse being rational, probable, wise, learned, and experienced; but all the while the muses would not let me alone, one pulled me to dance, another to sing, another to play on music, others to recite verses, speak speeches, and act parts of plays, and the like. Whereupon I gravely turned the incorporal head of my rational soul, nodding it to them to be quiet, and let me alone, but still they played with me: at last my thoughts, which are the language of the soul, spoke to them, and prayed them to forbear, until such time as the sciences were gone; but they would not be quiet, nor silent, do<pb facs="131" n="239"/> what I could, but would interrupt the sciences in the midst of their discourse, with their idle rhymes, light fancies, and odd numbers, insomuch as the sciences departed: whereupon the muses did rejoice, and skip, and run about, as if they had been wild: and in this jocund humour, in came the arts, even a whole commonwealth; for there were not only politic arts, civil and combining arts, profitable and necessary arts, military arts, and ceremonious arts; but there were superstitious arts, idolatrous arts, false, factious, and mischievous arts, destructive and wicked arts, base and mean art, foolish, childish, vain, superfluous and unprofitable arts: upon all these arts the Muses made good sport; for at some they flung jests, scorns, and scoffs, and some they stripped naked, but to others they were cruel, for some they stayed their skins off, and others they made very skeletons of, dissecting them to the very bones; and the truth is, they spared not the best of them, but they had one saying or other to them: but when all the arts departed, they took me, and carried to the well of Helicon, and there they threw me in over head and cares, and said they would souse me in the liquor of poetry; but when I was in the well, I thought verily I should have been drowned, for all my outward senses were smothered and choked, for the water did blind my eyes, stopped my ears and nostrils, and filled my mouth so full, as I had not so much space as to spout it forth; besides all my body was so numb, as I had no feeling, insomuch, as when they took me out of this well of Helicon, into which they had flung me, I seemed as dead, being quite senseless: whereupon they all agreed to take and carry me up on Parnassas hill, and to lay me on the  thereof, that the poetical flame, or heat therein, might dry and warm me; after which agreement they took me up, every one bearing a part of me, or was industrious about me, for some carried my head, others my legs, some held my hands, others embraced my waste, another oiled my tongue, and others poured spirits into my mouth, but the worst-natured muse pinched me, to try if I was sensible, or not, and the sweetest and tenderest natured muse wept over me, and another was so kind as to kiss me; but when they had brought me up to the top of the hill, and laid me thereupon, I felt such a heat, as if they had laid me on Aetna; but after I had lain some time, I felt it not so hot, and so less and less, until I felt it like as my natural heat; just like those that go into a hot bath, at first cry out it is insufferable and scalding hot, yet with a little use will find it cool enough: but whilst I lay on Parnassus hill, I began to make a lyric verse, as thus.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e108900">Bright, sparkling hot poetic sire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e108910">My duller muse inspire</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e108920">Unto thy sweeter lyre:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e108930">My fancies like as notes all sit</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e108940">To play a tune of wit</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e108950">On well-strung numbers fit. </l>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108960">But your unfortunate visit hath pulled me so hastily down from the hill, that the force of the speed hath cracked my imaginary fiddle, broke the strings of my wit, blotted the notes of numbers, so spoiled my song.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108970" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady Visit.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e108980">Prithee, there is none that would have taken the pains to have sung thy song, unless some blind fiddler in an alehouse, and then not any one would have listened unto it, for the fume of the drink would stop the<pb facs="132" n="240"/> sense of their ears: besides, drunkards love not, nor delight in nothing but beastly nonsense; but howsoever I had done thee a friendly part, to fetch thee down from off that monstrous high hill, whereby the vastness of the height might have made you so dizzy, as you might have fallen therefrom on the sharp stones of spite, or at least, on the hard ground of censure, which might have bruised, if not wounded the reputatio of thy wit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e108990" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109000">Let me tell you, you had done me a courtesy to have let me remained there some time; for if you had let me alone, I might there have improved the stature of my wit, perfected the health of my judgement, and had nourished the life of my muse.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109010">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="27" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e109020">
            <head>Scene 27.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109030">Enter the lord title, and the lady virtue, clothed like herself. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109040" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109050">Still I fear my fault is beyond a pacification, yet the gods are pacified with submissive actions, as bent knees, repentant tear, imploring words, sorrowful sighs, and dejected countenances, all which I gave to thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109060" who="A53060_07-virtue">
              <speaker>Lady virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109070">Though there is always in my mind an obedient respect to merit, yet a scorn is a sufficient cause to make a rebelling of thoughts, words, and actions; for though I am poor, yet I am virtuous, and virtue is to be preferred before wealth or birth, were I meanly born. But howsoever, true love, like a great and powerful monarch, soon disperses those rebellious passions, and quiets those factious thoughts, and all murmuring speeches, or words, are put to silence, banishing all frowning countenance, returning humble looks into the eyes again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109080" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109090">Then you have pardoned me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109100" who="A53060_07-virtue">
              <speaker>Lady virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109110">Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109120" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109130">And do you love me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109140" who="A53060_07-virtue">
              <speaker>Lady virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109150">As saints do heaven.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109160">Lord title kisses lady virtues hands</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109170" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109180">Your favours have raised my spirits from the grave of melancholy, and your pure love hath given me a new life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109190" who="A53060_07-virtue">
              <speaker>Lady virtue.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109200">So truly I love you, as nothing but death can destroy it; my, I am of that belief, that were I dead, and turned to ashes, my dust, like firm and lasting steel, would fly unto you, as to the loadstone, if you were at such distance as nothing might oppose.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109210" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109220">Thus souls, as well as bodies, love.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109230">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="28" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e109240">
            <pb facs="132" n="241"/>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109250">Enter the lord courtship, and the lady amorous.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109260" who="A53060_07-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109270">Since I cannot have the happiness of your lordship's company at my house, I am come to wait upon you at your house.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109280" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109290">Your ladyship doth me too great an honour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109300" who="A53060_07-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109310">Your lordship is grown very courtly. Pray how comes our familiar friendship so estranged, and set at distance with compliments?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109320" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109330">Madam, my wild manners have been so rude to your fair sex, as I am become a scorn and shame unto myself.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109340" who="A53060_07-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109350">I hate civility and manners in a man, it makes him appear sneakingly, poorly, and effeminate, and not a cavalier: bold and free actions become your sex.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109360" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109370">It doth so in a camp amongst rude and rough soldiers, whose breeding never knew civility, nor will obey gentle commands, submitting only to rigorous authority: but to the fair, tender, effeminate sex, men should offer their service by their admiring looks, civil discourses, and humble actions, bowing as to a deity; and when they are pleased to favour their servants, those favours to be accounted beyond the gifts of Jove. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109380" who="A53060_07-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109390">Have I cuckolded my husband, dishonoured my family, defamed myself for your sake, and am I thus rewarded and thrown aside with civil compliments? O basest of men!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109400" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109410">I am sorry I have wronged your husband, but more sorry I have dishonoured you, and what satisfaction a true repentance can make, I offer upon the altar of a reformed life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109420" who="A53060_07-amorous">
              <speaker>Lady amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109430">Do you repent? O false man! May you be cursed of all your sex, and die the death of Orpheus. </p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109440">Lady amorous goes out. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109450">Lord courtship alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109460" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109470">It is beyond the power of Jove to please the various humours of womankind.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109480">Exit</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="29" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e109490">
            <head>Scene 29.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109500">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109510" who="A53060_07-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109520">There was never so many noble persons married in one day, in one city, I think, before those that are to marry tomorrow .</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109530" who="A53060_07-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109540">Who are they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109550" who="A53060_07-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109560">Why, do you not hear?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109570" who="A53060_07-yyyy_2">
              <pb facs="133" n="240"/>
              <speaker>2 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109580">No.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109590" who="A53060_07-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109600">Surely you have been either dead or deaf.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109610" who="A53060_07-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109620">I have been in the country.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109630" who="A53060_07-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109640">That is some reason indeed; but the news of the city uses to travel in letters on post-horses into the country.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109650" who="A53060_07-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109660">No faith, for the most part they come in slow waggons; but tell me who those are that are to be married tomorrow?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109670" who="A53060_07-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109680">Why first there is the lord title and the lady virtue. Secondly, the lord courtship and the lady Ward. Thirdly, there is sir Famit poet and the lady contemplation. Fourthly, the lady conversation and sir experienced traveller. And fifthly, the lady visitant and sir Humphrey interruption. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109690" who="A53060_07-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109700">I will do my endeavour to see them all; for I will go to each bridal house.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109710" who="A53060_07-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109720">How will you do so, being all married on a day?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109730" who="A53060_07-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109740">Why I will bid good-morrow to the one, and I will go to church with another, and dine with the third, and dance the afternoon with the fourth, and see the fifth a-bed .</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109750" who="A53060_07-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109760">That you may do.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109770">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="30" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e109780">
            <head>Scene 30.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109790">Enter mistress troublesome, and her maid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109800" who="A53060_07-troubles">
              <speaker>Mistress troubles.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109810">Lord there are so many weddings to be tomorrow, as I know not which to go to! Besides, I shall displease those I go not to, being invited to them all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109820" who="A53060_07-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109830">If you would displease neither of them, you must feign yourself sick, and go to none of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109840" who="A53060_07-troubles">
              <speaker>Mistress troubles.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109850">None of them, say you? that would be a cause to make me die; for I would not but be a guest to one of them for any thing could be given me: but I am resolved to go to the lady conversation and sir experienced traveller's wedding, for there there will be the most company, and it is company that I love better than the wedding-cheer; for much company is a feast to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109860" who="A53060_07-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109870">Truly mistress, I wonder you should delight in company, you being in years.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109880" who="A53060_07-troubles">
              <speaker>Mistress troubles.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109890">Out you naughty wench, do you say I am old?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109900" who="A53060_07-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109910">No indeed, I did not name old.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109920" who="A53060_07-troubles">
              <speaker>Mistress troubles.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109930">Then let me tell you, that those women that are in years, seek company to divulge their wit, as youth to divulge their beauty; and we aged wits may chance to catch a lover from a young beauty: but I should applaud my own wit, if it could contrive to bring each bride and bridegroom into one assembly, making Hymen's monarchy a republic, where all should be in common.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109940" who="A53060_07-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109950">So mistress you would prove a traitor to Hymen, which is a bawd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e109960" who="A53060_07-troubles">
              <speaker>Mistress troubles.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e109970">Faith I will turn you away for your boldness.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109980"><pb facs="133" n="241"/>Enter mistress gossip.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e109990">O mistress gossip you are welcome, what news!</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110000" who="A53060_07-gossip">
              <speaker>Mistress gossip.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110010">I am come to tell you, that the five bridals meet with their guests and good cheer at the city-hall, and make their several companies joining as one, as one body, and there will be such revelling, as the like was never before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110020" who="A53060_07-troubles">
              <speaker>Mistress troubles.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110030">Juno be thanked, and Venus be praised for it; for I was much perplexed concerning their divisions, till you came and brought me this good news of their corporation.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110040">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="31" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e110050">
            <head>Scene 31.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110060">Enter the lord title, and the lady virtue as his bride, both of them richly attired, and old humanity following them. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110070" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110080">Come old humanity, and be our father, to join and give us in the church; and then when we are married, we will live a country-life, I as a shepherd, and this lady as my fair shepherdess.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110090">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="32" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e110100">
            <head>Scene 32.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110110">Enter the lady Ward as a bride, and her nurse nurse careful.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110120" who="A53060_07-careful">
              <speaker>Nurse careful.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110130">My dear child, you appear as a sweet budding rose this morning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110140" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110150">Roses are beset with thorns, nurse, I hope I am not so.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110160" who="A53060_07-careful">
              <speaker>Nurse Caref.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110170">By'r lady your husband may prove a thorn, if he be not a good man, and a kind husband; but o my heart doth ache.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110180" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110190">Wherefore doth it ache?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110200">Enter lord courtship as a bridegroom. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110210" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110220">Come sweet, are you ready? for it is time to go to church, it is almost twelve o'clock .</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110230" who="A53060_07-ward">
              <speaker>Lady ward.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110240">I am ready, but my nurse doth affright me, by telling me her heart doth ache, as if she did foreknow by her experienced age some ill fortune towards me, or that I shall be unhappy in my marriage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110250" who="A53060_07-courtship">
              <speaker>Lord courts.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110260">Her heart doth not ache for you, but for herself, because she cannot be a young fair bride, as you are, as being passed her youth; so that her heart doth ache out of a sad remembrance of herself, not for a present, or a future cause for you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110270" who="A53060_07-careful">
              <speaker>Nurse Caref.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110280">Well, well, I was young indeed, and a comely bride when I was married, though I say it, and had a loving bridegroom, heaven rest his soul.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110290">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="33" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e110300">
            <pb facs="134" n="244"/>
            <head>Scene 33.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110310">Enter the lady visitant as a bride, to the lady conplation, another bride. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110320" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady Visit.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110330">Come, I have brought all my bridal guests hither to join with yours, for we will go to church together: wherefore prithee come away, our bridegrooms and our guests stay for you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110340" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110350">I will go to them by and by.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110360" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady Visit.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110370">Why, I hope you do not stay to muse upon phantasms, saith marriage will banish them out of your head, you must now employ your time with realities.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110380" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110390">If I thought marriage would destroy or disturb my contemplations, I would not marry, although my wedding-guests were come, and my wedding-dinner ready dressed, and my wedding-clothes on; nay, were I at the holy altar, I would return back.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110400" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady Visit.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110410">That would be such an action, as all the kingdom would say you were mad.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110420" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contemplation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110430">I had rather all the world should not only say I were mad, but think me so, rather than myself to be unhappy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110440" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady Visit.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110450">Can want of contemplation make you unhappy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110460" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contemplation</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110470">Yes, as unhappy as a body can be without a soul; for contemplation is the life of the soul, and who can be happy that hath a dead soul?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110480" who="A53060_07-visitant">
              <speaker>Lady Visit.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110490">By my troth I had rather be dead, than have such a dull life.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110500">Enter maid.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110510" who="A53060_07-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110520">Madam, the bridegroom is coming hither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110530" who="A53060_07-contemplation">
              <speaker>Lady contempl</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110540">I will prevent him, and meet him.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110550">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="34" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e110560">
            <head>Scene 34.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110570">Enter the two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110580" who="A53060_07-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentlem. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110590">Come away, come away, they'll be all married before we shall get to church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110600" who="A53060_07-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110610">There will be enough witnesses, we may well be spared; but so I share of the feast, I care not whether they be married or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110620" who="A53060_07-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110630">The truth is, the benefit to us will be only in eating of their meat, and drinking of their wine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110640" who="A53060_07-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110650">And I mean to be drunk, but not for joy of their marriages, but for pleasure of my gusto.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110660">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="35" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_07-e110670">
            <pb facs="134" n="245"/>
            <head>Scene 35.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110680">Enter the five couples, and all the bridal guests: the bridegrooms and the bride's dance, and the while the bridal torches are held in their hands: then a ` poet speaks thus to them.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110690" who="A53060_07-speaker">
              <speaker>Speaker.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e110700">What lines of light do from those torches spin,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e110710">Which winds about those ladies' whiter skin? </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e110720">But from their eyes more splend'rous beams do run,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e110730">As bright as those that issue from the sun. </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e110740">Wherein the lesser lights wax dull and dim,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_07-e110750">Or like as minnows in an ocean swim. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110760">Enter Mall Mean-bred.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110770" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110780">By your good leave gentlefolks,<stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110790">The lord marquess writ this scene</stage>I am come here to complain of this hog-rubber sir golden riches, who did tempt me with gold till he had his desire, you know all what it is, and I like an honest woman, as it were, kept my word, and performed truly as any woman could do: speak, canst thou detect me either in word or deed? and like a false and covetous wretch as thou art, performed nothing with me as thou shouldst have done, I am sure of that: is't not a truth? speak coverous wretch, speak.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110800" who="A53060_07-golden_riches">
              <speaker>Sir gold. Rich.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110810">Why, what did I promise you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110820" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110830">Why thou didst promise me an hundred pounds in gold, showed it me, and then took it away again; nay further, thou saidst I should be a lady, and have a great parimanus coach gilt, with neighing horses, and a coachman, with a postilion to ride afore: nay, nay, I remember well enough what you said, you talked of Gessimond, pomatum, and Roman gunpowder for my hair, and fine gowns and stockings, and fine laced silk garters, and roses shining like stars, God bless us!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110840" who="A53060_07-golden_riches">
              <speaker>Sir gold. Rich.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110850">Did I, did I?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110860" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110870">Yes, that you did, you know what you did, and how you did, and so do I; and gentlefolks as I am a true woman, which he knows I am, I never had more than this white fustian waistcoat, and three pence to buy me three pennyworth of pins, for he would allow me no incle to tie it withal, and this old flannel petticoat, that was his great grandmothers in eighty eight, I am no two-legged creature else.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110880" who="A53060_07-golden_riches">
              <speaker>Sir gold. Rich.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110890">But I bought you velvet to guard it withal.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110900" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110910">Yes, that's true, an old black velvet jerkin without sleeves, that had belonged to one of Queen Elizabeth her learned counsel in the law of blessed memory, primo of her reign, and you bought it of an old broker at Nottingham; and as I am a true Christian woman, if our neighbour butcher could almost few it on, it was so mortified.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110920" who="A53060_07-golden_riches">
              <speaker>Sir gold. Rich.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110930">I bought you shoes, and ribbons to tie them withal.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e110940">She shows her shoes.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110950" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110960">Look gentlefolks, a pair of wet-leather shoes, that have given me a cold, and two leather points that he calls ribbons, like a lying false man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110970" who="A53060_07-golden_riches">
              <pb facs="135" n="246"/>
              <speaker>Sir gold Rich.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e110980">I am sure I bought you stockings and garters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e110990" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e111000">Old doncaster-stockins, that I was fain to wash myself with a little borrowed soap, and they were footed with yellow fustian too, and the garters he talks of were lists of cloth, which a tailor gave me for my new-years-gift, and I cannot choose but grieve to see his unkindness; I gave you satisfaction often, but you never satisfied me, I will take it upon my death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e111010" who="A53060_07-golden_riches">
              <speaker>Sir gold. Rich.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e111020">Go Gill Flirt, pack away hence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e111030" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e111040">Nay that puts me in mind of the pedlars pack you promised me, and I never had so much bought as that I might whistle for them; but I will follow thee to hell, but I will have something more out of thee than I have had, or else I will make all the town ring of me.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e111050">Enter two beadles.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e111060" who="A53060_07-golden_riches">
              <speaker>Sir gold. Rich.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e111070">Here beadles, take her to the correction-house, Bridewell, and let her be punished.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e111080" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e111090">Is it so, thou miscreant? well, I thought to be thy bride, and not Bridewell, I never thought it in my conscience.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e111100">Here ends my lords writing.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e111110" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title,</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e111120">Pray stay.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e111130">Enter Thom. Purveyor.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e111140">The lord title whispers to Thom. Purveyor, then turns to Mall Mean-bred.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e111150" who="A53060_07-title">
              <speaker>Lord title.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e111160">Mall, although you deceived me, and broke your promise, you I will not only save you from the punishment you were to suffer at the correction-house, but I will give thee a husband here, lusty Thom. Purveyor, to whom, for taking thee to wife, I will give him a lease of fifty pounds a year. Here Tom, take her and go marry her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e111170" who="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred">
              <speaker>Mall mean-bred.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e111180">Heaven bless your honour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_07-e111190" who="A53060_07-tom">
              <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_07-e111200">Come Mall, let us go wed, for fifty pounds a year is better than thy maidenhead.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_07-e111210">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A53060_07-e111220">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A53060_07"><item xml:id="A53060_07-title" n="58">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-title</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">58</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-ward" n="39">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-ward</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">39</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-conversation" n="35">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-conversation</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">35</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-courtship" n="33">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-courtship</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">33</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-poor_virtue" n="32">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-poor_virtue</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">32</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-contemplation" n="32">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-contemplation</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">32</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-inquirer" n="20">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-inquirer</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">20</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-roger" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-roger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-maudlin" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-maudlin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-practice" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-practice</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-effeminate_lovely" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-effeminate_lovely</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-mall_mean-bred" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-mall_mean-bred</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-visitant" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-visitant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-careful" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-careful</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-golden_riches" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-golden_riches</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-troublesome" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-troublesome</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-yyyy_1" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-old_humanity" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-old_humanity</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-argument" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-argument</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-troubles" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-troubles</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-yyyy_2" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-yyyy_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-matron" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-matron</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-fancy_poet" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-fancy_poet</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-maid" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-maid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-amorous" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-amorous</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-virtue" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-virtue</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-vain_compliment" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-vain_compliment</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-humphrey_inter" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-humphrey_inter</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-messenger" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A53060_07-gossip" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-gossip</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-effeminate" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-effeminate</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-tom" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-tom</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-servant" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-servant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_07-speaker" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_07-speaker</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

