<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A01253">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Imperiale <date type="creation_date">1639</date></title>
        <author>Freeman, Ralph</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Madeline Burg</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A01253.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Imperiale a tragedie.</title>
            <author>Freeman, Ralph, Sir, fl. 1610-1655.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>32 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2008 September (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99852506</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 11369.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 560(a).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">17831</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01253</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Imperiale a tragedie.</title>
            <author>Freeman, Ralph, Sir, fl. 1610-1655.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[64] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>M.DC.XXXIX. [1639]</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Anonymous. By Sir Ralph Freeman.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-H4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>First leaf blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>English drama -- 17th century -- Early works to 1800.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A01253-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A01253-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A01253-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A01253-e100040">Imperiale. A tragedy. </p>
        <bibl xml:id="A01253-e100050">Ovid. 2. Trist. ad Caes, August. </bibl>
        <quote xml:id="A01253-e100060">Omne genus scripti gravitate tragoedia vincit.</quote>
        <p xml:id="A01253-e100070">London, ¶ Printed by Thomas harper. M.dc.xxxix.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="argument" xml:id="A01253-e100080">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>The argument.</head>
        <p xml:id="A01253-e100090">Imperiale and Spinola noblemen of Genua having been ancient enemies, and lately reconciled by the mediation of Justiniano's, a friend to both; Spinola endeavoured to marry his son Francisco to Angelica daughter of imperial; but finding his son rejected, and Doria entertained, by that conceived affront, accompanied with other jealousies, suspects the old enmity not fully eradicated from the breast of imperial, and moved with indignation, hireth a brave to kill him in a crowd at a festival: this being accidentally discovered by Sango the slave of Spinola, he reveals it to Molosso the slave of imperial, as acceptable news to him, who had waited an opportunity to be revenged on his patron for severe and unusual punishment, inflicted upon him. Molosso to ingratiate himself with his lord, thereby to work a greater mischief, not only reveals the plot to him, but diverts the same upon Spinola's own son, at which unexpected encounter Spinola through rage falls into a strange kind of frenzy, but at length being an eyewitness of the misery which through the cruelty of the slaves befell imperial, his wife Honoria, Angelica, and Doria, he recovers his senses and turns his fury into compassion.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="epigraph" xml:id="A01253-e100100">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <bibl xml:id="A01253-e100110">Plutarchus de gloria atheniensium.</bibl>
        <quote xml:id="A01253-e100120">
          <p xml:id="A01253-e100130"><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01253-e100140">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>, etc.</p>
          <p xml:id="A01253-e100150"><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01253-e100160">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>.</p>
        </quote>
        <p xml:id="A01253-e100170">Tragedy flourished and was in high esteem , the hearing and sight whereof did wonderfully delight the men of those times.</p>
        <p xml:id="A01253-e100180">For if the accounts be made of the charge the Athenians were at in adorning their dramatic poems, it will appear that the Bacchae, Phaenissae, oedipi, Antigona, the cruelties of Medea and Electra, consumed more treasure, than their wars undertaken against barbarians for liberty and empire.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="epigraph" xml:id="A01253-e100190">
        <bibl xml:id="A01253-e100200">idem de vita x. Orat.</bibl>
        <quote xml:id="A01253-e100210">
          <p xml:id="A01253-e100220"><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01253-e100230">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>.</p>
        </quote>
        <p xml:id="A01253-e100240">Lycurgus ordained that statues of brass should be erected to the memory of the poets, Aeschylus, Sophocles, and Euripides, and that their tragedies should be carefully preserved, and often publicly read by the notary of the city, when stage-players were not admitted to act them.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="epigraph" xml:id="A01253-e100250">
        <bibl xml:id="A01253-e100260">Delrius in praefatione ad senecae tragedias.</bibl>
        <quote xml:id="A01253-e100270">
          <p xml:id="A01253-e100280">Non marcum varronem, non dvos julios caesares, non augustum Octavium, non scaurum, non thraseam, quibus nihil 〈◊〉 vidit orbis Romanus, huic scriptioni subsecivas horas 〈◊〉.</p>
        </quote>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A01253-e100290">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <head>Dramatis personae.</head>
        <list xml:id="A01253-e100300">
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100310">
            <table xml:id="A01253-e100320">
              <row role="data" xml:id="A01253-e100330">
                <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Sango</cell>
                <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="2">2 slaves.</cell>
              </row>
              <row role="data" xml:id="A01253-e100340">
                <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Molosso</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
          </item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100350">Imperial, a senator of Genua.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100360">Spinola, a noble man of Genua, and a soldier.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100370">Justiniano's a noble man of Genua, and a scholar.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100380">Verdugo a Bra●●</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100390">Doria a prince 〈◊〉 Genua.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100400">Francisco, Spinola his son.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100410">Judge.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100420">Doctor.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100430">Witnesses 2. </item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100440">
            <table xml:id="A01253-e100450">
              <row role="data" xml:id="A01253-e100460">
                <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Evagrio,</cell>
                <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="2">Kinsmen of Spinola.</cell>
              </row>
              <row role="data" xml:id="A01253-e100470">
                <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Fidele,</cell>
              </row>
            </table>
          </item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100480">Officers.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100490">Friends 2. </item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100500">Honoria, imperial his wife.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100510">Angelica, her daughter.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100520">Nugella, the waiting woman.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100530">Cooke.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100540">Cater.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100550">Porter.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01253-e100560">Chorus.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A01253-e100570">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A01253-e100580">
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A01253-e100590">
          <pb facs="4"/>
          <head>Actus primus.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e100600">
            <head>Scaena prima.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e100610">Sango, Molosso.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e100620" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>Sang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100630">'Tis true Molosso, fortune hath prepared</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100640">A full revenge for thee, without thy hazard,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100650">And ere the rising sun shall yet decline</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100660">Imperial thy proud lord shall fall</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100670">As low as hell; one unexpected blow</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100680">Shall recompense those many he gave thee;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100690">When imitating foreign cruelty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100700">He bound thee fast, and made thy feet an anvil. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e100710" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Molos.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100720">Sango, if thou contemplating our friendship,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100730">Begotten first by consanguinity,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100740">And since confirmed by our joint sufferings here,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100750">Hast undertaken some bold stratagem</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100760">Against my patron to revenge my wrongs,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100770">Thy great affection may but ruin me;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100780">Delay not then to make me understand</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100790">Thy full intent: believe it will be vain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100800">Our sword once drawn, to think to sheath again. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e100810" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>Sang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100820">Then know, the plot is more securely laid,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100830">Than my weak means (Although my will be strong)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100840">Could ever reach, without my certain death;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100850">And by strange chance I did discover it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100860">Without the actor's knowledge; thou hast heard</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100870">Of the old deadly feud between our lords,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100880">Which wound although it were in show healed up,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100890">Is broken out afresh; 't was not well searched;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100900">For the last night, at setting of the sun,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100910">A household business called me to the garden,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100920">Where in the thicket, near the arbour, lying</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100930">By myself, I quickly fell asleep. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100940"><pb facs="5"/>Into which arbour in the mean time came</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100950">My patron, with a brave accompanied,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100960">A fellow expert in that mystery:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100970">At their first entrance to the place I waked,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100980">But durst not stir, for had I, death had seized me;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e100990">There was I privy to their whole discourse,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101000">Which was in brief but this, that for the sum</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101010">Of fifteen hundred crowns, thy patron's life</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101020">Is sold, and must ere noon be snatched away. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e101030" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101040">Sure thou didst dream, thou wert not thoroughly awake,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101050">For though our lords were lately reconciled,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101060">Mine keeps a careful watch, and never stirs</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101070">Out of the city, where he knows he's safe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e101080" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>Sang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101090">He'll be deceived, the rareness of the plot</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101100">Did please beyond the dear and longed for act;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101110">Here's the design, this being a solemn day</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101120">Annually observed by the state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101130">In memory of a public benefit</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101140">Received by the private care of one</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101150">Of thy lords ancestors, will draw all sorts</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101160">Of people to the temple, where the 〈◊〉</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101170">Clothed like a silly peasant, is resolved</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101180">To watch imperial, and keep near him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101190">And when the usual ceremonies are done,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101200">In the confused crowd his cunning hand</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101210">Shall guide a poisoned dagger to his heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101220">And in an instant, letting fall his cloak,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101230">Which shall be large to hide his rustic habit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101240">He, with the rest, will stand about the body</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101250">And wring his hands at th'horror of the fact,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101260">And thus the brave shall thy part bravely act,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101270">What? silent? not affected with a joy</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101280">Should ravish thee? and swell thy veins with pleasure,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101290">Like to the ostrich in the act of lust? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e101300" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101310">Light joys are easily vented; such as this</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101320">Is entertained with an ecstasy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101330">And by degrees expressed: but as the full</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101340">Fruition of a thing we most delight in</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101350"><pb facs="5"/> is checked with daily fear of losing it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101360">So find I now my rising heart kept down</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101370">With doubt of such a wished happiness,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e101380" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>Sang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101390">Hadst thou, as I beheld the actors looks</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101400">When he declared his resolution,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101410">To my attentive patron, thou wouldst rest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101420">Assured of the event, and swear he needed</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101430">No other weapon to destroy a man;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101440">His eyes would have outstared a basilisk,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101450">They were two comets that are surely fatal. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e101460" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101470">May they portend more mischief to this house,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101480">Than those that blasted ours and our whole country;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101490">But in this strong desire of a revenge</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101500">Discretion must direct our passion;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101510">And therefore let it be thy chiefest care</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101520">Neither in word, nor gesture, to disclose</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101530">Thy fortunate discovery, till the end</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101540">Shall crown the work, and banish all our fears;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101550">My task shall be to make it profitable</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101560">No less than pleasant, by his foreknown fall</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101570">We'll raise ourselves to wealth and liberty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101580">The great allurements of those bold attempts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101590">Wherein the vassal dares affront his lord,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101600">And quite shake off the yoke of his subjection. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e101610" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>Sang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101620">Our magnificos think us phlegmatic rascals</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101630">Created but for blows, and scorn, so far</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101640">In love with servitude as scarce to wish</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101650">Revenge or freedom. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e101660" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101670">They shall find at length</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101680">Patience oppressed will into fury turn;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101690">Nature, in spite of fortune gave us minds</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101700">That cannot like our bodies be enthralled;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101710">But soft, I doubt our early privacy</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101720">May render us suspected; leave to me</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101730">The manage of th'affair; only let thy</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101740">Virtue be now the dumb man's secrecy. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e101750">
            <pb facs="6"/>
            <head>Actus primus. Scaena secunda.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e101760">Spinola, Justiniano's.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e101770" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101780">The hateful sound of Imperiale's name</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101790">Would strike me deaf, my dear Justinian,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101800">Were it not tempered by thy gentle tongue,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101810">That had the art to make m'embrace and trust</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101820">A reconciled foe, who hath rejected</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101830">With scorn my hopeful son, as if his birth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101840">Fortune, and parts, had not deserved that flirt</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101850">His gilded daughter; but I tax not thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101860">Whose friendship is a gem without a foil,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101870">And hardly can be valued, never matched:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101880">I know thy milder studies chiefly bent</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101890">To weed out rancour from the minds of men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101900">Smoothing rough nature with morality,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101910">And this becomes philosophers: but I</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101920">That do profess the art of killing men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101930">Encouraged by all states, imposed by some</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101940">Must follow other precepts: he is sure</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101950">Of many wrongs, that will but one endure. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e101960" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101970">Thy character of me, loved Spinola,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101980">Thus far I may without vain glory own,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e101990">Truly to love my friend, yet hate no man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102000">And since mine own experience finds how well</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102010">Thou dost the one, I would persuade the other;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102020">Nor would I now convert thee to a Stoic,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102030">To make thee think there are no injuries,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102040">Or if there be, that wise men cannot feel 'em,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102050">These, I confess, are not compatible</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102060">With thy condition; on th'other side,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102070">I can encourage none, much less my friend</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102080">To take a scandal, when there is none given,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102090">To call that injury, which is in truth</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102100">A liberty that every man may challenge;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102110">Or if imperial ought to have waved the same,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102120"><pb facs="6"/> yet since the will is free, thou couldst expect</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102130">But fatherly persuasion, to incline</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102140">Th' affections of his daughter, all the rest</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102150">Is ravishment, or tyranny at best. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102160" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102170">I know not how the rigid schools define</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102180">A father's power, in their begged principles,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102190">As if the freedom of the will extended</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102200">To silly wenches, to restrain the power</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102210">Of them that gave them first and second being;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102220">No, it was only his inveterate malice</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102230">That closely lurked under a new feigned friendship</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102240">That stuck on me and mine this contumely,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102250">Which ought to be resented far above</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102260">An injury, by any generous spirit;</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102270" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102280">Let it be what thy fancy apprehends,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102290">Which scarce appears in the least circumstance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102300">Yet generous spirits at poor contumelies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102310">As seldom stoop as eagles do to flies. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102320" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102330">What is there that should wound an active spirit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102340">Like base contempt? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102350" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102360">The guilt of one base act. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102370" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102380">Should we not then be jealous of our fame? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102390" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102400">If we within find cause of jealousy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102410" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102420">Reports may brand, although they be untrue. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102430" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102440">Yes, those that take their honour upon trust. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102450" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102460">Our honour by opinion must subsist,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102470" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102480">Then every puff of wind will scatter it. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102490">How can we call that ours, which must depend</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102500">On the rash will, and vainer voice of others? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102510">But herein thou most slight'st thyself to doubt</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102520">Thou canst be undervalued by any,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102530">Much more contemned by him that dares not think</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102540">Himself to be the worthier, but that thou</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102550">Suggests it for him, in thy vain suspicion:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102560">They that believe themselves despised, confess</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102570">An inward doubt of their own worthiness. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102580" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102590">I am not for my part ambitious</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102600">Of the dull fame of stupid patience,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102610"><pb facs="7"/> to be admired for wanting common sense,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102620">Like Cato, that could let one spit in's face,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102630">And when he should have wiped off the disgrace</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102640">With his sharp sword, he did it with a jest</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102650">And his soft handkerchief: this was that spirit</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102660">Thou liftest above great Alexander's merit. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102670" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102680">Ay, and above the glory of Hercules,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102690">Or what bold Greece hath left in histories</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102700">Of her great captains, to their endless fame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102710">They monsters, kingdoms, and their jousts o'ercame:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102720">Cato fought not with beasts, nor did live when</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102730">Was thought that heaven might be born up by men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102740">But in an age when (Barbarism being fled)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102750">All industry and learning flourished;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102760">And in that time did bravely set upon</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102770">That monster, in many shapes, ambition,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102780">With all the crimes of Rome, and when the state</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102790">Was ready e'en to sink with its own weight</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102800">He it supported with his only hand;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102810">And did (As much as one man could) withstand</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102820">Rome's instant fate, till forced to let her go</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102830">He became partner in her overthrow;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102840">And so one ruin did them both oppress;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102850">Whom to have severed had been wickedness;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102860">For was it fit that liberty should die</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102870">And Cato live? that had been contumely,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102880">Not the purgation of a mouth that might</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102890">As well have done the sun or moon despite:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102900">But I will leave thee to thy thoughts a while,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102910">For wholesome counsel like safe physic is</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102920">Unpleasant in the taste, and must have time</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102930">To work upon the humour; thou that art master</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102940">Of so much worth, wilt master in the end</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102950">Those passions that with reason now contend. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e102960">
            <pb facs="7"/>
            <head>Actus primus. Scaena tertia.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e102970">Spinola.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e102980" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e102990">I must needs make a strong pretence to worth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103000">That dare pretend, Justinian, to thy love;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103010">But when I find how much I violate</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103020">The sacred jaws of friendship, that refuse</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103030">T'anatomize my very soul to thee;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103040">I am compelled t'acknowledge mine own shame</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103050">Or to suspect thy known fidelity:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103060">The plot, wherewith I labour, can admit</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103070">No council, but a necessary faith</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103080">In the bold actor, whose subsistence binds him</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103090">To resolution, and to secrecy;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103100">All friendly trust is folly, every man</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103110">Has one, to whom he will commit as much</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103120">As is to him committed: our designs</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103130">When once they creep from our own private breasts</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103140">Do in a moment through the city fly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103150">Who tells his secret sells his liberty:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103160">But shall I suffer this black treachery</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103170">To boil within my doubtful breast? mischief</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103180">Though it be safe, can never be secure,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103190">Or shall I ease my thoughts, and give it vent? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103200">Yes; prick a full swollen bladder to relax it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103210">Or bore a hole ith' bottom of the ship</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103220">To cool a calenture? dull fool thy life</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103230">Is with thy fame concerned: besides the base</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103240">Rejection of thy son (Lodged deeply here)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103250">He wrought the senate to confer the charge</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103260">Of our late aid lent Savoy against France,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103270">On rash marinò, so to blast thy merit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103280">Be confident, he that durst often venture</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103290">Taffront thee, meant to prosecute thy ruin;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103300">And 'tis no greater hazard to attempt</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103310">Death, than disgrace, that makes his life contemptible:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103320"><pb facs="8"/> on then, be bold and secret, Spinola,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103330">So shalt thou reap the double benefit</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103340">Of safety and revenge: all wickedness</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103350">Is counted virtue, when 'tis prosperous;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103360">Be not by any reconcilement led</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103370">To trust thy so, thou'rt safe when he is dead. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e103380">
            <head>Actus primus. Scaena quarta ▪</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e103390">Imperiale, Honoria, Angelica, Nugella attending.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e103400" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Impe.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103410">How comes it, dear, that the clear sky, thy looks,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103420">Is suddenly o'ercast? what misty vapour</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103430">Hath raised those stormy clouds? can bright Aurora</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103440">Rise cheerfully from shrivelled Tython's bed? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103450">And thou so discontentedly from mine? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103460">But I'll not doubt the cause to spring from me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103470">Rather from fear of young prince Doria's safety,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103480">Whose great affairs perhaps have made him stretch</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103490">His promise to the utmost, not to break it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103500">Though he could not prevent our expectation,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103510">He'll not deceive't, but like th'approaching sun,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103520">Will soon expel these mists, and cheer our hearts. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e103530" who="A01253-honoria">
              <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103540">I am solicitous, I must confess</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103550">Of his return, whom we have long expected,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103560">To whom we have designed our only daughter,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103570">And with her both our fortunes and our loves:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103580">But the true cause of all these perturbations</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103590">Which you discover in my countenance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103600">Is a strange dream (Heaven make it but a dream)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103610">And I perhaps should but have thought it so,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103620">Had not my daughter, e'en this very night,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103630">And the same hour, as near as we can guess,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103640">With the like vision been disquieted:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103650">Methought we harboured in our house a wolf,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103660">Bred up so tame, that all did handle him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103670"><pb facs="8"/> which like a dog would fawn on them that beat him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103680">Till on a time, accompanied with another</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103690">Of his own race, he rushed into the chamber</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103700">Where I together with my daughter sat,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103710">There they resumed their native cruelty:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103720">The one assaulted her, the other me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103730">And tearing first our jewels from our necks,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103740">They made us both at length their feral prey:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e103750" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103760">O, how the terror of that dreadful vision</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103770">Affrights my soul! I tremble when I think on't? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103780">Methought the heartstrings of prince Doria cracked</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103790">At the dire news, it proved the overthrow</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103800">Of our whole family: we differ but in this,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103810">The savage executioners to me</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103820">Seemed to be bears, creatures as bloody as wolves. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e103830" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103840">It is no wonder that your dreams concurred,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103850">Since there is that relation in your blood:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103860">I must believe, you had the day before</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103870">Communicated some sad thoughts together,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103880">Which in the night your wakeful fantasies</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103890">From a like temperature of brain reduced</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103900">Into like forms, suggesting that for truth</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103910">Which is at best but fond imagination;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103920">What can be vainer than a woman's dream? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103930">'Tis less to be regarded then her tears,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103940">Which are prepared to flow at her command. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e103950" who="A01253-honoria">
              <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103960">Cassandra's true predictions were despised. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e103970" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e103980">And well they might, had Troy been provident. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e103990" who="A01253-honoria">
              <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104000">Many at length deplore their unbelief. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104010" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104020">But more lament their rash credulity. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104030" who="A01253-honoria">
              <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104040">Future events by dreams have been revealed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104050" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104060">So did old wizards doubtful things unfold</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104070">By flights of birds, such witchcrafts now are seized,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104080">And we from those dark errors are released:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104090">To talk of visions is an indiscretion,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104100">Practised by children, and distempered persons:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104110">Go then; prepare yourselves for solid joys,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104120">On this day the republic yearly pays</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104130"><pb facs="9"/> a retribution to our family,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104140">And as I hear (The time being Carnival)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104150">Some mirth shall season our solemnity;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104160">If Doria come today, as we expect,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104170">To morrow nothing shall be heard of us</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104180">But songs of Hymen and Thalassius. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104190" who="A01253-honoria">
              <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104200">Never could any wretches be more glad</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104210">To be deceived. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104220" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104230">My heart continues sad. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e104240">
            <head>Actus primus. Scaena quinta.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104250" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imperiale.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104260">O wretched state of man, to whom the time:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104270">By nature made for ease, is found unquiet;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104280">Sleep, properly called rest, who can express</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104290">How restless it becomes through various dreams? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104300">Which are so strongly formed by the fancy</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104310">That though they be most false, and when we wake</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104320">Should wholly vanish, yet even then they leave</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104330">A deep impression in the troubled mind;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104340">Nor doth this only happen to weak women,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104350">But unto men of special eminence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104360">Working upon their hopes as well as fears,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104370">Who many times to their confusion</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104380">Have by such drowsy errors been seduced;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104390">Hence did Amilcar venture to assault</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104400">Strong Syracuse deluded by a dream;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104410">But though it be a folly beyond pardon</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104420">To venture life or fortune in pursuit</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104430">Of such a vanity, yet in all things</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104440">Abundant wariness can never hurt:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104450">My slave may not unfitly be compared ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104460">To a tame wolf, or bear, who may perchance</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104470">Resent his late sharp castigation;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104480">Him will I send to my own galley, where</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104490">He shall be chained from mischief, and to me</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104500">Not prove unuseful, when the smallest bolt</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104510"><pb facs="9"/> may easily be removed, who would omit it? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104520">Let others lose themselves in labyrinths</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104530">Of hidden superstition, and believe</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104540">The air to be replenished with spirits,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104550">Who by a natural and inherent virtue</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104560">Foreseeing things to come, and taking pity</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104570">Upon improvident man, reveal by visions</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104580">The dangers that approach, to th'end he may</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104590">By timely care prevent his misery;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104600">I'll not depend on such intelligence</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104610">T'inform me whether Spinola hath buried ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104620">Or only hid, his long continued malice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104630">I'll fetch my preservation nearer; hence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104640">That shall conserve this individual;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104650">No man can suffer ill but from himself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104660">Fate only awes the slothful; wisdom barres</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104670">The powerful operation of the stars. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A01253-e104680">Chorus of two.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104690" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104700">Those men that mischief do devise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104710">Had need to borrow Argus eyes</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104720">To look about; a poor slave may</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104730">By chance lie hid, and then betray. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104740" who="A01253-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104750">Within the house they may suspect</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104760">That walls and beds may them detect,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104770">And in the field they must provide,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104780">That not a bush a spy may hide. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104790" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104800">And albeit they shut the door,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104810">Having well searched the house before,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104820">Yet they may be betrayed; for proof,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104830">Jove in a shower did pierce the roof. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104840" who="A01253-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104850">Though in the field no tree, nor bush,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104860">Nor bird be near, nor wind doth rush,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104870">Yet undiscerned a fairy drab</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104880">Their whole discourse may hear and blab. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104890" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <pb facs="10"/>
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104900">Then since that neither house, nor field,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104910">To our black crumbs can safety yield,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104920">Let us be virtuous, and not fear</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104930">What all the world can see or hear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104940" who="A01253-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104950">Our dreams are often found to be</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104960">Fruits of a wand'ring fantasy;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104970">Yet many times they likewise are</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e104980">Sure pledges of celestial care. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e104990" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105000">Some men believe too much, and some</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105010">Conceive no truths by dreams can come;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105020">It is a knowledge given to few</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105030">To find if they be false or true. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e105040" who="A01253-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105050">Then as it is a rash misprision</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105060">To count each idle dream a vision;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105070">So it's an error at the least</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105080">To think all visions are quite ceased. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A01253-e105090">
          <head>Actus secundus.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e105100">
            <head>Scaena prima.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e105110" who="A01253-francisco">
              <speaker>Francisco.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105120">Can no advice of friends? nor mine own reason</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105130">Hold me from strong pursuit of what I find</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105140">Can never be obtained? am I so stupid</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105150">After so many scorns not to desist? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105160">An arrow shot sooner may be recalled</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105170">Then her affection; th'apennine, the Alps</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105180">Will eas'lier be removed then her father:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105190">Feed not thyself, fond fool, with desperate hopes:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105200">But shall I, armed with powerful love, consult</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105210">With timorous discretion? the weak child</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105220">Of feeble age? the towering eagle may</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105230">More easily be confined within high walls</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105240">Then that winged boy, that hovered over chaos</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105250"><pb facs="10"/> be tied to humane possibilities:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105260">What transformations did the antique poets</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105270">Affirm to have been wrought on men and gods</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105280">By his sole deity? which Jove himself</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105290">His frequent sport had found; what guards, what spies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105300">He hath deceived and forced; the fiery bull,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105310">The wakeful dragon, and gazed Argus' witness. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105320">Though she that's truly named Angelica</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105330">Should now abhor thy person; love can lend thee</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105340">The shape of him she loves; were she averse</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105350">From all mankind, if she like any thing</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105360">She may at length be brought to dote on thee:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105370">But may I not be taxed of too much sloth? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105380">Neglecting active industry, t'expect</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105390">To be assisted by such miracles? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105400">I yet have only trod the beaten path</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105410">Of vowed service, friends good will, and jointure;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105420">The elder brother's formal evidence:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105430">I am so far from practising the art</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105440">Of spells and philters, I have quite omitted</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105450">Corruption of her confidents and servants:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105460">I am too cheap a lover and too tame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105470">And hither to have taught her to deny</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105480">By easy asking; I must let her know</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105490">What I dare do: my father is incensed</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105500">At my repulse, his old suppressed hate</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105510">Renews itself; he'll rather condescend</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105520">To match me with a fury, then with her:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105530">It will be wisdom to decline th'alliance</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105540">Of him thy father counts his enemy:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105550">It would be wretchedness to make thy love</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105560">Depend upon th'affections of another:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105570">He never loved that can for any cause</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105580">Suspend his love: set then before thine eyes</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105590">Valiant Achilles, who acquired more honour</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105600">By constancy, even to his enemy's daughter,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105610">In spite of th'opposition of his friends,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105620">Then ere he did by Hector's overthrow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105630"><pb facs="11"/> redeem the time Francisco, though't be short,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105640">And let this one day satisfy the loss</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105650">Of weeks and months; her father keeps a slave</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105660">A cunning African, whose very soul</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105670">For money and hope of liberty I'll buy:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105680">Him will I straight employ; love ne'er refuses</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105690">The basest instruments, if they be useful,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105700">A drudge may find more corners in the house</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105710">Than ere the master knew; and may discover</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105720">A secret inlet to betray a city;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105730">There will I now begin, he shall advise</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105740">Where I shall plant my golden batteries. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e105750">
            <head>Actus secundus. Scaena secunda.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e105760">Imperiale. Molosso.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e105770" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105780">I am with wonder strucken, not with fear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105790">At thy relation of this barbarous plot,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105800">Contrived against my life, after faith given,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105810">Of firm atonement: but the leopard's spots</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105820">Or stains of virgin honour may as soon</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105830">Be wiped away, as hatred that hath seized</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105840">A cankered breast; this machination</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105850">Is so inhumane, that to lend it credit</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105860">Is a degree to inhumanity. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e105870" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105880">To give slow faith to such a horrid plot</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105890">Becomes a heart so full of piety;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105900">But in this black design many presumptions</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105910">Unite themselves to fortify belief;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105920">Nor is it to be thought, the wretch durst feign it</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105930">Giving so short a time to be disproved;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105940">The heavens forbid your virtuous diffidence</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105950">Should lead you to the hazard: I must count</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105960">This blessed discovery a large recompense,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105970">Of former ills fortune hath thrown on me:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105980">For I am bold to hope, it will by you</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e105990">Be graciously accepted, though I find</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106000"><pb facs="11"/> some late unhappy errors have enforced</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106010">Your patience to inflict just punishment</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106020">On him that is your slave, and might expect</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106030">The restless misery of the painful oar,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106040">With all the wants that ever were sustained</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106050">In a remorseless galley; but your goodness</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106060">(In spite of fate that meant all this) is pleased</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106070">To give me shelter under your own roof,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106080">And to the emulation of my fellows</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106090">To grant the favour of your household service;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106100">A bondage which I truly may prefer</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106110">Above the common people's liberty:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106120">These are the benefits, that invite my soul</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106130">To meditate your preservation,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106140">Which ere I cease to do, Tiber and Po</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106150">Shall quite abandon fruitful Italy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106160">And wash th'arabian sands; though I am rude,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106170">I must abhor churlish ingratitude. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106180" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106190">Fortune and thy integrity have found</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106200">A weighty occasion to confirm and fix thee</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106210">With roots of adamant, in my good opinion:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106220">Nor doth it happen often to a servant</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106230">T'enjoy the happy means t'account himself</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106240">The saviour of his master: Kings are born</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106250">More frequently, than such examples found:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106260">But if to this unvalued benefit</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106270">Thy pregnant industry can add a second,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106280">The mischief to divert upon himself</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106290">Thou having saved me now, shall crown me then. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106300" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106310">Great sir, you owe the thanks of what's yet done</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106320">To chance alone; I am ambitious</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106330">Of something that might merit, if at least</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106340">The diligence and industry of one</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106350">Of my condition, may deserve that title. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106360" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106370">It may, it may; great merit is in story</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106380">Ascribed sometimes to bondmen; all our souls</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106390">Are free and equal, thence our merits flow:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106400">Why should the person vilify the work,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106410"><pb facs="12"/> and not the work rather ennoble him? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106420">It is the benefit we look upon,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106430">And not the giver's mean condition. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106440" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106450">I have a ripe design that shall both give</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106460">Assurance of the truth of what I brought</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106470">And pour the vengeance on your enemy;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106480">Nor can it ever be discovered</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106490">To hurt your fame; it shall amaze the actor</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106500">And shall be speedy too; things of long time</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106510">Are ever doubtful, lost in expectation,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106520">Propounded usually for private ends,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106530">Gained by degrees; an acceptable deed</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106540">Hath double welcome when 'tis done with speed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106550" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106560">Noble Molosso, such thy virtues make thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106570">Proceed with courage in thy enterprise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106580">Which I'll not press to know ▪ till the event,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106590">But by implicit trust freely declare</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106600">What confidence I mean to place in thee;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106610">And take from me this just encouragement</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106620">To rest assured, thy service hath not met</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106630">With an ungrateful master: I shall never</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106640">Forgive my late credulity, that meant</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106650">T'have added to his former punishment. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e106660">
            <head>Actus secundus. Scaena tertia.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e106670">Molosso. Sango. Francisco.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106680" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106690">He's now made sure, I must with speed find out</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106700">Young Spinola, and speak with Sango too,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106710">Behold 'em both together, 'twill succeed;</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106720" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106730">See where Molosso comes, sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106740" who="A01253-francisco">
              <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106750">O 'tis he. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106760">How is't moloss? thy face hath business in't</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106770">I would thou wert at leisure. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106780" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106790">My toiled body</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106800">Will not admit a cheerful countenance;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106810">But I can throw of care if you command. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106820" who="A01253-francisco">
              <pb facs="12"/>
              <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106830">Wouldst thou embrace redemption? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106840" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106850">Ask me whether</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106860">I would not wish some shade if I were broiled</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106870">Upon the Libyan sands, where cancer reigns:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106880">But sir if I mistake not, you sustain</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106890">A greater servitude, yet seek not freedom. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106900" who="A01253-francisco">
              <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106910">Thou wouldst persuade me to shake off loves fetters. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106920" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106930">Rather to change them into chains of gold,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106940">To wealth and ornament; it may be done</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106950">Without your chemical projection. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106960" who="A01253-francisco">
              <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106970">Thou shouldst not stand in need of that t'enrich thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e106980">Could this b'effected. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e106990" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107000">Sir, I have no art,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107010">Nor leisure to discourse, but I have heard</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107020">There is by fare an opportunity</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107030">Allotted every man, to make him rich</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107040">And happy too, provided he take hold,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107050">And I am confident that's offered you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107060" who="A01253-francisco">
              <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107070">What? to enjoy divine Angelica? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107080">No treasure else can make me rich or happy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107090" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107100">When she is brought into your own possession,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107110">You can but blame yourself, if she depart. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107120" who="A01253-francisco">
              <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107130">I shall destroy myself if then she scape,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107140">But how? prithee convey thy joyful news</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107150">Into me by a reverend secrecy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107160">That I may be all ear, while thou art whispering. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A01253-e107170">They whisper.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107180" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107190">What plot should this be now? I long to know,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107200">Molosso doubts some accident may happen</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107210">Upon his master's death, and wisely seeks</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107220">To gain a friend, under whose safe protection</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107230">He may be sheltered from a sudden storm;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107240">I have an equal share in the success</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107250">Of his designs; his preservation's mine,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107260">And therefore need not be inquisitive,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107270">Th' assured fate of his obdurate lord</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107280">May make that good he promiseth; the daughter,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107290">If once the father were removed ▪ perhaps</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107300"><pb facs="13"/> would entertain new thoughts, methinks she should</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107310">Be sensible of Dorias neglects:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107320">Who can condemn this young man's hot desire? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107330">Were I as free, as noble as himself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107340">I should most willingly become her slave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107350">And I do hate my forc't condition</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107360">For no one ill so much, as that it brings</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107370">Despair of such transcendent happiness</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107380" who="A01253-francisco">
              <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107390">I'm ravished with it, 'tis the sprightful child</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107400">Of thine own brain, and will not brook delay. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107410" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107420">That's true: I'll see that all things be prepared:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107430">If the least wheel be out of frame, the watch</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107440">Is altogether useless. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107450" who="A01253-francisco">
              <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107460">Wind it up,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107470">That I may observe each minute of the time</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107480">That is the crisis of my life or death:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107490">First take a taste of my ensuing bounty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107500">It may relieve thee, should we be discovered:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107510">If by this plot my present hopes succeed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107520">All future lovers shall thy story read. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e107530">
            <head>Actus secundus. Scaena quarta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e107540">Sango. Molosso.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107550" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107560">I see thou hast a golden plot in hand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107570">Thou must impart. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107580" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107590">Half this is due to thee</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107600">By our establisht law of equal fortunes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107610" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107620">I would I might share with Francisco too ▪</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107630" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107640">That riddle quickly will unfold itself:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107650">But Sango, I'm glad I met thee, I was forced</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107660">For some important reasons to reveal</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107670">This weighty secret to my patron. San. how? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107680" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107690">I was compelled to do't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107700" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107710">What? to disclose it? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107720">And unto him? is this your dumb man's virtue? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107730">Canst thou so soon forget thine own vile wrongs? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107740"><pb facs="13"/>Hath the dull air of Europe chilled thy blood? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107750">For thy sole cause I hardly could contain</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107760">My present joy in the discovery,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107770">Though death stood gaping for me while I heard it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107780">And wouldst thou cowardly betray thy fortune? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107790" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107800">My obligation to my stars and thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107810">Their Mercury, can never be expressed;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107820">Which I have husbanded to my advantage. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107830">It is the ground from whence I'll take my rise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107840">To leap, and fall like dreadful thunder on him;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107850">It is not vengeance, but soft piety</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107860">To wish a foe's death, when he's fit to die,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107870">To let him live, and feel himself so wretched,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107880">That he shall seek and sue for absent death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107890">Is a revenge becomes me, and I'll have it;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107900">Thou knowest my patrons former trust was changed</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107910">Into a sudden jealousy, which sprang</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107920">From consciousness of his base injuries;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107930">This hath removed that doubt, and set me right</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107940">In his lost good opinion, which I mean</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107950">Still to confirm by my strict diligence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107960">Till time and opportunity shall show</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107970">How far this petty-mischief I'll outgo. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e107980" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e107990">Now are thy thoughts full plumed, it pleases me</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108000">To see thee mount, not flag in thy revenge:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108010">I must confess, I love a present mischief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108020">But, if it may conduce to thy brave ends,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108030">To make a feigned retreat, and then return</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108040">With greater violence; I must consent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108050">And when thou'rt ready for thy great assault,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108060">But, this, and I shall join; in the mean time</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108070">Let nothing be discovered to my patron;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108080">If that be, death's the best I can expect. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e108090" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108100">Rest thou secure, and to express my thanks,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108110">It shall not be the least part of my plot,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108120">To give thee means to gain the full fruition</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108130">Of her that Genua so admires and strives for. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e108140" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108150">Can there be hope of such a happiness? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e108160" who="A01253-molosso">
              <pb facs="14"/>
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108170">Ay, and a good assurance of success. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e108180" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108190">I shall embrac't with all the circumstance</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108200">Of danger, that bold treason undergoes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108210">Or what accompanies forbidden love</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108220">In the most jealous climes: I should desire</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108230">In the fruition of such bliss t'expire. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e108240" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108250">Stoutly resolved, come, let us lay our ground,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108260">We shall build sure, when our foundation's sound. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e108270">
            <head>Actus secundus. Scaena quinta.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e108280" who="A01253-verdugo">
              <speaker>Verdugo.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108290">Under a homely habit many times,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108300">Virtue lies hid; this rustic weed conceals</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108310">An engine that can frustrate providence:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108320">When I attempt the death of any man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108330">No town of garrison, not his own house,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108340">Nor any place of sanctuary can save him:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108350">Nor doth my praise consist in this alone,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108360">That I command the life of whom I list;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108370">A desperate wretch may claim that privilege:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108380">He that is weary of his own, may be</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108390">Lord of another's life; but such attempts</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108400">Hatched only by a frenzy, seldom prosper:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108410">My actions are the fruits of a bold spirit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108420">Tempered with judgement, done with secrecy:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108430">Hence is our brave profession found to be</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108440">Of special use to awe the insolent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108450">And secure those that seek to live in peace. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108460">What satisfaction is it to a man</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108470">That receives wrong, to call his enemy forth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108480">And then expose himself to equal hazard? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108490">Or in strict commonwealths t'appeal to law,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108500">As if a feigned submission in set words</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108510">Could cure the piercing sting of injury;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108520">No, 'tis assurance of a close revenge</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108530">That plants civility, deters and keeps men</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108540"><pb facs="14"/> from giving, and from suffering affronts;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108550">This benefit we bring to every man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108560">Yes, and the public states of Italy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108570">Howe'er they censure our particular actions,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108580">Receive no small security from us;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108590">Treason would hardly find just punishment</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108600">Within their narrow territories, if we</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108610">Should not, like eager hounds, pursue the traitors,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108620">And make them know, that in another country</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108630">The justice of their own can overtake them;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108640">Let then the slothful tax us, that our ends</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108650">Are not the public good, but private gain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108660">Which we prefer above mankind; this is</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108670">But what's objected to the soldier; he</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108680">Will fight against his brother for reward,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108690">Men ought to follow their vocation;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108700">The fountain of our livelihood is profit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108710">Without which, honour challenging the skill</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108720">To nourish arts, cannot provide us clothes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108730">Nor virtue, noised to be the greatest good,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108740">Procure us bread. Nor yet is our profession</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108750">More cruel than the gravest; I have heard</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108760">Of lawyers, that are privileged to cut</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108770">Their clients throats, with a perplexed indenture,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108780">A parchment saw. The learned physician</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108790">Following the long and beneficial way</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108800">Of reverend Galen, by degrees will purge</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108810">The humours of his patient, till he leaves</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108820">Nothing but bones for death, and hungry worms</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108830">To gnaw upon; as for his pliant skin,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108840">That, while he lives, by pieces is pulled off,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108850">Till he be wholly flayed: the usurer,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108860">Is't not his use to bind men first in bonds,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108870">And bring they then to execution,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108880">Extending both their bodies and their lands</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108890">Upon a rack; we are more pitiful,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108900">And by an unexpected way dispatch</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108910">Quicker than lightning, or a cunning headsman,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108920"><pb facs="15"/> for all the ill of death is apprehension;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108930">How's Imperiale wronged? if when he hath</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108940">But newly said his prayers, I release him</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108950">From the ensuing miseries of age;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108960">And when that work's performed, my charity</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108970">May do as much for Spinola himself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108980">Provided I be offered like conditions:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e108990">My hand of justice is not partial. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109000">But soft, this pleasing contemplation</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109010">May make m' omit the time of action,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109020">Which now draws near; my plot is so contrived,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109030">That being pursued with resolution,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109040">It cannot want success; our best designs</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109050">Are often crossed, when through a fond remorse</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109060">We change our counsels: few have learned the skill</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109070">To be or wholly good, or wholly ill. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A01253-e109080">Chorus of two.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109090" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109100">Fond youth to hope, where no hope is,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109110">And to be brought to place thy trust</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109120">On him, that makes deceit his bliss,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109130">And counts it folly to be just:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109140">Go wash an Aethiop white, and find</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109150">Faith harboured in a slavish mind. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109160" who="A01253-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109170">Love wanting eyes, makes all men blind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109180">That to his power submit their wills;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109190">No counsel can acceptance find,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109200">But such as their own lust fulfils. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109210">To be in love, and to be wise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109220">Apollo to himself denies. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109230" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109240">When he that hath received harm,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109250">Requites it with pretended love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109260">We must believe 'tis but a charm,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109270">Quick-eyed suspicion to remove. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109280">Some may do good for good, few will</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109290">Be brought to render good for ill. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109300" who="A01253-xxxx_2">
              <pb facs="15"/>
              <speaker>2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109310">Is it not strange to find a trade? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109320">Will act what our revenge devices? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109330">To see such formal bargains made</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109340">To kill, or wound at several prizes? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109350">At which those public states connive</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109360">That do by private faction thrive. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109370" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109380">But though some do commit these crimes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109390">Yet let not us believe we may,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109400">Only cry out against the times,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109410">And be ourselves as bad as they:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109420">But let our virtuous deeds prevent</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109430">Both theirs, and our own punishment. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A01253-e109440">
          <head>Actus tertius.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e109450">
            <head>Scaena prima.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e109460">Angelica, Nugella.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109470" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109480">Although my father hath resolved all doubts ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109490">My reason could object; yet still I feel</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109500">A chilling vapour hover in my breast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109510">Which many times breaks forth in sudden sighs,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109520">For which I can assign no other cause</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109530">Than that the world cannot afford a joy</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109540">Unmixed with real or supposed sorrow;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109550">Hence is it that most brides are found to weep,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109560">Yet know not why upon their wedding day. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109570" who="A01253-nugella">
              <speaker>Nug.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109580">Such follies are too common, I confess,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109590">But should I have the happiness to see</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109600">Young Hymen in his yellow socks my guest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109610">I'd entertain him with no other tears</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109620">Than such as from pressed grapes in autumn flow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109630">Wherewith his drowsy head and withered garland</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109640">I would bedew; till to his twinkling eyes</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109650">Each taper should present a double light,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109660">While waggish boys should with their wanton songs:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109670">Prepare our thoughts to our ensuing pleasures. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109680" who="A01253-angelica">
              <pb facs="16"/>
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109690">Fie, fie, Nugolla, no lasciviousness</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109700">Can ere become solemnities, that must</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109710">Create us matrons; there is cause to fear</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109720">Their chastity, that unchaste songs can hear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109730" who="A01253-nugella">
              <speaker>Nug.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109740">It is a shame to lend our ears to that</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109750">We are allowed to do? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109760" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109770">Yes many things</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109780">Are lawful, and yet shameful to be done</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109790">Or spoken publicly. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109800" who="A01253-nugella">
              <speaker>Nug.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109810">A woman may</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109820">Be free in outward gesture, yet preserve</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109830">An inward chastity; and I know many</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109840">Both rich and noble ladies so disposed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109850" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109860">'Tis not the glittering canopy of greatness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109870">But th'humble veil of modesty must guard</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109880">A woman's fame; which being once thrown off</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109890">Leaves her exposed to every bold assault. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109900" who="A01253-nugella">
              <speaker>Nug.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109910">But when she's found impregnable, 'twill stop</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109920">Their vain attempts. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109930" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109940">A fort cannot be thought</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109950">Impregnable, that offers frequent parleys. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109960" who="A01253-nugella">
              <speaker>Nug.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109970">Yet that (As I have heard) is often done</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e109980">To gain advantage and delude the foe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e109990" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110000">Can it beseem a virgin or a wife</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110010">To play with all th' allurements of desire;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110020">And think her honour's safe, if she abstain</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110030">From the bare act, the duller part of lust. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110040" who="A01253-nugella">
              <speaker>Nug.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110050">They do but imitate those chariot drivers</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110060">That you were wont to read of, whose praise was</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110070">To come as near as might be, and not touch;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110080">Love hath ordained by an antique law</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110090">Newly revived, that every place and room</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110100">In Venus' palace, be allowed for sport,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110110">Except her cabinet, that, must not be</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110120">Opened nor touched, at least not willingly. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110130" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110140">Thou wilt be waggish still, but hark who knocks? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110150">This wench that never felt the fire of love</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110160">Thinks like a wanton child, it may be played with,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110170"><pb facs="16"/> but she will one day find it far more raging</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110180">Than that which fierce Medea did convey</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110190">Into Creusa's robe: how now? who is't? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110200" who="A01253-nugella">
              <speaker>Nug.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110210">A stranger, with a letter, which he says</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110220">He must present to your own hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110230" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110240">Admit him;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110250">If it be from my Doria, I fear</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110260">Some unexpected accident, wherein</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110270">His honour is concerned, retards his coming;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110280">But I must likewise arm myself for wiles:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110290">Such love as ours, cannot want envious plots. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e110300">
            <head>Actus tertius. Scaena secunda.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e110310">Doria disguised. Angelica. Nugella.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110320" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110330">I shall not be discovered by my voice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110340">Italian virgins are at distance wooed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110350">And more by fame, then verbal courtship won:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110360">This speaks my errand, leaves no circumstance</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110370">To be related by the messenger;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110380">See how her blood retires, to aid her heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110390">So looks bright Phoebe, when Thessalian charms</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110400">Strike her with fear, or th'early rose, whose beauty</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110410">Nipped by a later frost, appears like snow:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110420">Now it returns, and settles in her cheeks,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110430">As if the news took no impression:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110440">Such orient beams when youthful day returns,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110450">By the bedewed shepherd are beheld. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110460" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110470">I may suppose you, sir, not ignorant</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110480">Of what you bring; and may believe you've heard</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110490">Some thing of young prince Doria and me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110500" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110510">Lady, I have; fame with her silver trumpet</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110520">Hath blazed your constant loves. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110530" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110540">And are you not</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110550">Strangely amazed to see me read these lines</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110560">Without a shower of tears? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110570" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110580">If they relate</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110590"><pb facs="17"/> any disaster, you then imitate</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110600">Those ancient worthies, that had bravely learned</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110610">To conquer passion at the first assault. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110620" who="A01253-nugella">
              <speaker>Nug.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110630">You think young women very impatient</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110640">To have their joys deferred: my lady's wise</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110650">To bear it thus, so long as he is safe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110660" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110670">He's dead, Nugella; the great. General</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110680">Writes me, that he having the sole command</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110690">Of an important place, forsook the same,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110700">And in his swift retreat, received a shot</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110710">I'th hinder part of's head. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110720" who="A01253-nugella">
              <speaker>Nug.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110730">O doleful accident! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110740" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110750">Canst thou be so ingrateful to my Doria,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110760">To lend it such a serious belief</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110770">As may deserve a tear? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110780" who="A01253-nugella">
              <speaker>Nug.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110790">I would I durst</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110800">Suspect what comes so to our woe confirmed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110810" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110820">Were it confirmed by the unerring seal</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110830">Of this wise state, it should not merit faith. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110840" who="A01253-nugella">
              <speaker>Nug.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110850">Alas, he was not to be thought immortal. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e110860" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110870">But was he not to be acknowledged valiant? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110880">That attribute his foes did not deny him:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110890">Had these contrived lines contained but this,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110900">Brave Doria's slain, a torrent, hence, had gushed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110910">That like Alpheus, had through earth and sea</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110920">Wandered unmixed, till in the gulf of death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110930">It should have lost itself in seeking him. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110940">But when I find impossibilities</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110950">Basely obtruded, my true love disdains</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110960">To lend belief to any circumstance. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110970">Mars could as soon be frighted from his sphere,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110980">As he from any charge he undertook:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e110990">'Tis a malicious scandal; and although</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111000">My nature e'en abhors to use a stranger</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111010">With any incivility, yet I'm forced</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111020">To tax the bearer with this vild imposture. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111030" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111040">By great saint George, the patron of this state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111050">Doria himself is not more innocent. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111060" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111070">That name is sacred, let me then conjure thee</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111080"><pb facs="17"/> to answer truly but to this one question. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111090" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111100">I shall. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111110" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111120">Was there before you left the army. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111130">Any report of this sad news you brought? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111140" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111150">I dare not say there was. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111160" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111170">The palace cracks</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111180">When such a pillar falls, the general</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111190">One of those many which my fortune wood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111200">Envious that Doria gained both that and me:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111210">And knowing well, that valour always is</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111220">The special object of a noble love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111230">Attempted thus to shake my constancy:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111240">But if the fates should prove so cruel to me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111250">To make me survive him; this is my vow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111260">To stand for ever like sad Niobe,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111270">A weeping statue to his memory. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111280" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111290">Never did such a virtuous courage reft</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111300">In the calm harbour of a virgin's breast. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e111310">
            <head>Actus tertius. Scaena tertia.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111320" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spinola.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111330">As the fly fowler, having over night,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111340">Set cunningly his artificial net,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111350">Early returns, with an assured hope</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111360">To find the foul ensnared, so are my thoughts</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111370">Wholly possessed with present expectation</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111380">Of the glad news of my successful plot;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111390">The managing whereof, I never can</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111400">Within myself sufficiently applaud:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111410">I have not like rash Piso, foolishly</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111420">Dispersed my trust, nor like the sons of Brutus,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111430">Disclosed my secret, where a servant might</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111440">Discover, and betray; my wariness</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111450">In a safe garden whispered my design,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111460">And but to one, that if it should miscarry,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111470">And he through fear or punishment confess,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111480">Yet I am sure to have but one accuser,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111490"><pb facs="18"/> whose testimony my power and bold denial</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111500">Would easily convince; but these mistrusts</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111510">Are altogether needless: I may be</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111520">As confident as those Sicilians,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111530">Who when their chief confederate was surprised,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111540">So much relied upon his resolution,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111550">As that not any one of them would fly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111560">And so conceal their bold conspiracy. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111570">Behold my kinsmen bringing joyful news. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e111580">
            <head>Actus tertius. Scaena quarta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e111590">Evagrio. Fidele. Spinola.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111600" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111610">O that I were snatched up into the sky! </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111620">And there transformed into a cloud, that so</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111630">I might dissolve into a shower of tears. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111640" who="A01253-fidele">
              <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111650">Can the day see such mischief, and be seen? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111660">And not make haste to shroud his guilty head</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111670">Under the gloomy canopy of night? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111680" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111690">What earthquake? what prodigious spectacle</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111700">Hath struck you both with horror? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111710" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111720">O he's dead! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111730" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111740">Why should that so amaze or you? or me? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111750">Since death must be the lot of every man. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111760" who="A01253-fidele">
              <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111770">Alas your son. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111780" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111790">How does it concern him? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111800" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111810">Great sir, your dear and only son is slain. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111820" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111830">How's this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111840" who="A01253-fidele">
              <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111850">He's murdered sacrilegiously,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111860">Even in the temple-porch, he was disguised,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111870">And thought of all t'have been imperial. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111880" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111890">I am undone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111900" who="A01253-fidele">
              <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111910">The desperate actor was</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111920">Clad in a country habit, and it seems,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111930">Mistook the person; when he saw his face,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111940">He tore his viperous hair; the judge was present,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111950">Who gave command to bring him instantly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111960">To receive speedy judgement,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e111970" who="A01253-spinola">
              <pb facs="18"/>
              <speaker>Spin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111980">Overreached? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e111990">In my own plot? the sword of my revenge</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112000">Turned on myself? and drowned in mine own bowels? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112010">I am betrayed, yet cannot suspect how;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112020">It could not be by any mortal subtlety,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112030">It was some devil lurking in the air;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112040">How shall I be revenged? O that he would</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112050">Assume a humane body, that I might</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112060">Encounter him! but I have found the way,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112070">I'll study the black art, turn conjurer,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112080">And then impose a labour on them all,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112090">Worse than Ixion, or the Belides</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112100">Are said to undergo. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112110" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112120">We have done ill,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112130">To rush upon him with such violence;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112140">The sudden grief hath half distracted him;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112150">We'll strive to temper it with better hopes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112160">Things may not be so bad as our affections</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112170">Have made us fear; Francisco Spinola</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112180">Was often named. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112190" who="A01253-fidele">
              <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112200">But neither of us both</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112210">Can say we saw him dead. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112220" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112230">Nay then I see</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112240">You're villains hired, suborned to undermine me. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112250">First you confound me with your horrid news,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112260">And then confess ye may be both mistaken:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112270">But I am armed with patience, if imperial</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112280">Retaining still his late abjured malice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112290">Hath by some hellish art contrived this mischief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112300">I may in just resentment of my wrongs,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112310">Implore heaven's vengeance, on his perjured head,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112320">And this is all you're like to screw from me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112330" who="A01253-fidele">
              <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112340">Let not your troubled thoughts make you doubt us,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112350">Who for his life would sacrifice our own. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112360" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112370">I will devise a stratagem, shall need</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112380">No other hand but this, which I'll conceal</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112390">From my own self, till th'instant time of action;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112400">For if I should disclose it in a place</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112410">Where there are trees, or flowers, I am betrayed:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112420"><pb facs="19"/> I would not breathe it forth, unless it were</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112430">After a dreadful thunder, that had purged</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112440">The air, and frighted thence those subtle spies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112450">That to our foes by night betray our plots. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112460" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112470">You have a faithful friend, to whom you may</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112480">Safely pour out the secrets of your heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112490">The wise Justinian. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112500" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112510">O that name is like</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112520">A precious balm to cure the wounds of fortune! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112530" who="A01253-fidele">
              <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112540">Please you retire, I'll bring him presently. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112550" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112560">No wild rebellion of my passions can</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112570">Make me neglect the friendship of that man. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e112580">
            <head>Actus tertius. Scaena quinta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e112590">Molosso, Imperiale.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112600" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112610">Now you may see, sir, you were not abused</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112620">In our discovery, and I hope you find</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112630">My undertakings and your trust made good;</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112640" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112650">The sun at noon is not more clearly seen;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112660">But may it not breed a suspicion</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112670">That he was clad like me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112680" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112690">Why sir you know</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112700">That it is now the time of Carnival,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112710">When every man takes what disguise he pleases. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112720" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112730">But I much wonder how he was persuaded</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112740">To put himself so soon into my habit. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112750" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112760">I brought him to a strong belief, that he</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112770">By that device and my assistance should</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112780">Convey away your daughter. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112790" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112800">I intended</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112810">The father should be punished, not the son. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112820" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112830">By this your vengeance is more exquisite;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112840">Make your account that with the son y' have thrust</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112850">The father through, who having found himself</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112860">O'erreached by you, or by his own just fare,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112870">In such a counterplot must needs at length</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112880"><pb facs="19"/> become his own dire executioner:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112890">In the mean time his life is worse than death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112900" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112910">True, true, death is the end of misery:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112920">To die is not wretched, but to live wretchedly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112930">Vengeance is mere compassion when we kill,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112940">I feel a joy beyond expression;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112950">There is no pleasure like to sweet revenge;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112960">But I desire things should be carried so</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112970">That I be still reputed innocent. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e112980" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e112990">That's my sole care, the brave in th'act was taken,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113000">And by commandment of the present judge,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113010">Is brought already to receive his trial. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113020" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113030">Thou shalt do well to hearken a loof off,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113040">I'll take no notice but in general,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113050">And will proceed in our intended mirth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113060" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113070">By all means sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113080" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113090">We must at this time shun</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113100">Unusual privacy; keep thou thy distance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113110">But know, that both my life and fortunes are</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113120">Most willingly committed to thy care. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e113130">
            <head>Actus tertius. Scaena sexta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e113140">Judge, doctòr, witnesses, Verdugo, officers.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113150" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113160">Since it hath been the custom of this state</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113170">To place a stranger on this high tribunal</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113180">Ordaining a professor of the laws,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113190">As his assistant (Being the place you hold)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113200">It is our duty to discharge that trust</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113210">With all integrity, and not to look</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113220">Upon men's persons, but to weigh their crimes</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113230">In equal balance, to which purpose now</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113240">Although a strange and horrid sacrilege</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113250">Has called us hither in unusual haste;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113260">Yet it must be our chief care to proceed</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113270">With due deliberation; otherwise</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113280">Though just our sentence be, we are unjust. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113290" who="A01253-doctor">
              <pb facs="20"/>
              <speaker>Doctor</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113300">I have for some years had the happiness</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113310">To be a witness of your constant session,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113320">In all which time I have not heard a sentence</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113330">Pronounced by you that envy could pervert. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113340" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113350">We must not think we deserve praise for that</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113360">Which to neglect would merit punishment. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113370" who="A01253-doctor">
              <speaker>Doctor</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113380">But yet there are degrees of good and ill,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113390">Wherein the actor takes a liberty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113400" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113410">Yet where the law prescribes a certain rule</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113420">A just judge cannot challenge liberty:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113430">But let us now pursue the work in hand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113440">Where is the prisoner? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113450" who="A01253-officer">
              <speaker>Officer</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113460">Here. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113470" who="A01253-doctor">
              <speaker>Doctor</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113480">Let him draw near. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113490" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113500">His name? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113510" who="A01253-officer">
              <speaker>Officer</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113520">He calls himself Virdugo, sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113530" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113540">Then know, Virdugo, though thy heinous fact</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113550">Be evident, yet the justice of this state</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113560">Grants thee free leave to answer for thyself. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113570" who="A01253-verdugo">
              <speaker>Ver ▪</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113580">I thank the state for their set compliment. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113590" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113600">Bring forth the witnesses that he may see them. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113610" who="A01253-officer">
              <speaker>Officer</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113620">They are both here an't please your excellence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113630" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113640">Have they been sworn? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113650" who="A01253-doctor">
              <speaker>Doctor</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113660">Yes both sir, before me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113670" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113680">Then, by the oath you took, declare the truth</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113690">Of what you know concerning this delinquent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113700">Begin you first. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113710" who="A01253-witness_1">
              <speaker>Wit 1.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113720">About some three hours since</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113730">Being in the domo, I espied this man</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113740">At his first entrance, and although I never</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113750">To my remembrance saw his face before,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113760">Yet instantly I found a strange mislike</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113770">Of his aspect, which did increase the more,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113780">Because I saw him often fix his eyes</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113790">On him he slew, whom I conceived to be</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113800">Signior imperial, I revealed my thoughts</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113810">To this young man who then stood next me, who</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113820">Concurring with me, did resolve as I</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113830">To watch him narrowly; we both agreed</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113840"><pb facs="20"/> to keep on either side of him, at length</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113850">In midst of all the crowd, raising his arm</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113860">To fetch his blow, he hit me with his elbow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113870">At which I suddenly laid hold on him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113880">Supposing he had snatched at some man's purse,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113890">But then I saw drop from his hand the sheath</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113900">Of that dire weapon, he had newly buried</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113910">In the warm bowels of that gentleman. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113920" who="A01253-witness_2">
              <speaker>Wit 2.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113930">Most part of this I aver, I stood so near him</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113940">That I perceived the motion of his arm,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113950">And looking down, spied blood upon his hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113960" who="A01253-verdugo">
              <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113970">The canker take your physiognomy</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e113980">That made you try conclusions upon me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e113990" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114000">There cannot be more clear and pregnant proof,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114010">What have you to allege in your defence? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114020" who="A01253-doctor">
              <speaker>Doctor</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114030">He hath confessed the fact. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114040" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114050">Hath he confessed</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114060">Who set him on? whether he meant to kill</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114070">Signior imperial, or young Spinola? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114080" who="A01253-verdugo">
              <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114090">The one had done me wrong, but destiny</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114100">Made th'other take a Carnival disguise</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114110">Somewhat too soon. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114120" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114130">Such recreations</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114140">Though in themselves they be in different,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114150">Yet in a sacred temple they're profane,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114160">And draw down vengeance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114170" who="A01253-verdugo">
              <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114180">Had there been but hope</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114190">To have enervated their testimony:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114200">The rack, nor the strappado, no nor yet</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114210">The subtler torment both of fire and water</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114220">Should have enforced me to the least confession:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114230">But 'tis my fate, and therefore let me hear</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114240">My passing bell, my doom quickly pronounced;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114250">For 't were ridiculous to expect favour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114260">Since your integrity (As you confessed)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114270">May not show any, where the law condemns. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114280" who="A01253-doctor">
              <speaker>Doctor</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114290">Darest thou deride the judge? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114300" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114310">Let him alone,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114320">He hath no sense of his own misery,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114330"><pb facs="21"/> his boldness moves not me, I shall proceed</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114340">With the unchanged countenance of law,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114350">And with a voice not furious, but severe;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114360">When I condemn a guilty man, 'tis done,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114370">As if I struck a serpent, not with passion. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114380" who="A01253-doctor">
              <speaker>Doctor</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114390">His wicked acts have hardened him, he came</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114400">No novice to this cruel enterprise. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114410">In Venice he climbing a ladder, shot</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114420">Through the glass window a clarissimo</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114430">Sitting at supper, flew a count of Naples</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114440">In his own garden, having first observed</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114450">A place where he might scale the wall to escape;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114460">And that his wants may not obtrude the guilt</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114470">Upon his fortune, he but lately ravished</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114480">A young and noble virgin in Sienna,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114490">The only daughter of Petruccio. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114500" who="A01253-verdugo">
              <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114510">Can that be thought to be a great offence? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114520" who="A01253-doctor">
              <speaker>Doctor</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114530">The harmless man thinks it no great offence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114540">With hot and beastly lust to vitiate</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114550">A damsel, at the most but ten years old. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114560" who="A01253-verdugo">
              <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114570">Believe it, I have found 'em good at eight;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114580">Why there are many like Quartella, sir,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114590">Remember not that they were ever maids. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114600" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114610">He takes delight not only in the act,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114620">But in the infamy of wickedness;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114630">But I will rid the world of such a monster;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114640">And therefore now, Verdugo, I pronounce,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114650">Because thou'st heaped up crimes, and drunk in vice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114660">Which is dispersed into every limb,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114670">Thy body shall be laid upon a wheel,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114680">And limb by limb be broken, till thou diest;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114690">Nor shalt thou then find any other grave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114700">Than the black maws of vultures, and remain</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114710">In the mean time a spectacle to men:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114720">This sentence justice hath declared by me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114730" who="A01253-verdugo">
              <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114740">Sir? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114750" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114760">Not to be revoked, take him away,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114770">And early in the morning see't be done. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114780" who="A01253-verdugo">
              <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114790">I'll bear it manfully, although I feel</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114800"><pb facs="21"/> Ixion ▪ like the torment of the wheel,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114810" who="A01253-judge">
              <speaker>Judge</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114820">Such malefactors in a state are like</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114830">To putrified members in man's body,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114840">Which like a skilful surgeon, law finds best</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114850">To cut off quite, lest they infect the rest. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A01253-e114860">Chorus of two.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114870" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114880">Love built on virtue, cannot be</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114890">Led by a rash credulity,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114900">To entertain reports that tend</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114910">To the dishonour of a friend. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114920">True love is confident, a doubt</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114930">That slakes loves fire will put out. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e114940" who="A01253-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114950">As they whose tongues are used to err</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114960">Are not believed, when they aver</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114970">That which is true, so when we know</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114980">A story false in part, we grow</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e114990">Jealous of all; if truth once touch</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115000">On falsehood, it is rendered such. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e115010" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115020">When men in their revengeful hate</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115030">Do study others ruins, fate</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115040">Acts justice part, to let them see</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115050">They plotted their own misery. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115060">'Tis just that they themselves should find,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115070">What they to others have designed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e115080" who="A01253-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115090">But how are these amazed, when they</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115100">Being about to seize their prey,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115110">Find themselves caught, yet do not know</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115120">From whence they did receive the blow:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115130">Like him that hid his gold in hope</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115140">To keep it safe, but found a rope. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e115150" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115160">Though they could blind and bribe the law,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115170">And keep all witnesses in awe</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115180">By their great power, though they could make</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115190">By cunning the whole stake mistake:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115200">Yet can they be so void of sense,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115210">To think to cozen providence? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e115220" who="A01253-xxxx_2">
              <pb facs="22"/>
              <speaker>2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115230">If mischief-workers would but bend</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115240">Their guilty thoughts, to weigh the end</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115250">Of their ill deeds, they would confess,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115260">No safety found in wickedness. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115270">How can those crimes that heaven doth see</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115280">And so abhor, unpunished be? </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A01253-e115290">
          <head>Actus quartus.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e115300">
            <head>Scaena prima.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e115310">Evagrio; Justiniane.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e115320" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115330">Believe it sir, has all the signs of frenzy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115340">His inflamed blood boils in his swelling veins,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115350">His eyes appear like fire, his colour changes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115360">He grates his teeth, and falters in his speech;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115370">Sometimes he folds his arms, and deeply sighs,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115380">Then strikes his angry foot against the ground. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e115390" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115400">Doth he continue in such violence</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115410">As at the first? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e115420" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115430">Yes sir, by fits; sometimes</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115440">A stupid silence seizeth him, and then</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115450">He breaks again into his former rage. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e115460" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115470">These are, I must confess, the noted symptoms</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115480">Of a hurt fancy; he's of a high spirit</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115490">Apt to resent a wrong (If it could be)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115500">From fate itself; but, where he takes, a friend,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115510">On whom a man may build, as on a rock. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e115520" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115530">True sir, his rising passions at your name,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115540">Like a tumultuous multitude, at sight</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115550">Of a grave judge, were for the time appeased;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115560">See where he comes, I pray observe, he vents</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115570">His passions often in poetic rage. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e115580">
            <head>Actus quartus. Scaena secunda.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e115590">Spinola, Justiniano's, Evagrio.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e115600" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115610">Ye furies, active ministers of hell,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115620">That have your heads environed with snakes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115630"><pb facs="22"/> and in your cruel hands be are fiery scourges,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115640">Lend me your bloody torches to find out,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115650">And punish th'author of my dear son murder,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115660">Assist Megaera with a new revenge,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115670">Such as even thou wouldst fear to execute:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115680">Let a vast sea of blood o'erflow his house,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115690">And never ebb till I shall pity him;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115700">Ease now th'infernal ghosts, remove the stone</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115710">From th' Attic thief, and lay it on his shoulders,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115720">Let the swift stream deceive his endless thirst,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115730">And let his hands wind the unquiet wheel,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115740">That hourly tortures the Thessalian King:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115750">Let vultures tire upon his growing liver,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115760">But let 'em never be tired; and since there is</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115770">One of the fifty Danaan sisters wanting,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115780">Let them admit that man into her room,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115790">And with their pitchers only load his arms;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115800">How am I sure 'tis he? or if it be? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115810">It is the law of retribution,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115820">And is but just, my conscience tells me so:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115830">Hence childish conscience, shall I live his scorn? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115840">And the whole cities Pasquill? I abhor it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115850">Were he protected by the thunderer,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115860">I'd snatch him from his bosom, and in spite</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115870">Of his revengeful thunder, throw him quick</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115880">Into the throat of the infernal dog;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115890">Or if that monster be not yet released,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115900">Since great Alcides dragged him in a chain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115910">Through th' amazed towns of Greece, Enceladus</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115920">That with his earth-bred flames affrighteth heaven,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115930">Rather than he shall scape, shall fire the world:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115940">But I delay, and wear away the time</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115950">With empty words, why do I call for furies? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115960">That bear in mine own breast a greater fury</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115970">Than Acheron and night did ever hatch;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115980">I'll dart myself like winged lightning on him;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e115990">Have I no friend? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116000" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116010">Yes, one that dares assist you</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116020">In a more valiant act, to crush that fury,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116030"><pb facs="23"/> and to restore brave Spinola to himself. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116040" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116050">O faithful soul, my dear Francisco's murdered. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116060" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116070">A heavy fate, yet such as should be born</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116080">Without so strange a tumult, what you give</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116090">T'unbridled rage, you take from your revenge. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116100" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116110">Wilt thou allow me to take vengeance, speak,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116120">But speak Justinian with thy wonted faith. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116130" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116140">Yes, such as law and justice shall allow. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116150" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116160">I have no skill in law, and as for justice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116170">Your learned Stoics make it but a fool,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116180">A very animal. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116190" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116200">'Tis now not seasonable</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116210">To tell you whether justice, fortitude,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116220">And th'other virtues may be called creatures;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116230">But I must tell you, that no creature can</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116240">Be happy, wanting them; whereof that man</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116250">Deprives himself, that subjugates his reason,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116260">On which they all depend, to brutish passion;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116270">Could you but be persuaded to reflect</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116280">Upon yourself, to see as in a glass,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116290">What a deformity this vice hath brought</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116300">Upon your soul, although you hated me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116310">You would embrace my counsel. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116320" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116330">Dear Justinian,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116340">Fortune hath nothing left that's worth my hope,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116350">But thy affection; at thy sole command,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116360">I would attempt to swim the midland sea,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116370">When Aeolus and Neptune are at wars,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116380">Expose myself to the fierce dragon's jaws,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116390">Enraged by the theft of Hercules;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116400">At thy command I'll live; hark, hark, what's that? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116410">It is the voice of my dead son, that calls</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116420">For vengeance; see, see where he stands and points</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116430">At his still-bleeding wound; he bids me think</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116440">What he had done ere now, had we changed fates;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116450">Did you not see him? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116460" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116470">No, nor you yourself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116480">'Twas nothing but a strong impression made</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116490">In your disturbed imagination. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116500" who="A01253-spinola">
              <pb facs="23"/>
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116510">Could both mine eyes and ears be so deceived. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116520" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116530">That happens often to perplexed minds. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116540" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116550">Alas, what shall I do? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116560" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116570">Let me persuade you</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116580">But to retire, perhaps some mild repose</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116590">May softly steal upon your troubled spirits,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116600">To give you ease. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116610" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116620">If you will have it so,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116630">My passions in my breast shall silence keep,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116640">I'll be as tame, as (What you wish me) sleep. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116650" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116660">Wait on him in, I'll follow presently. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e116670">
            <head>Actus quartus. Scaena tertia.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e116680" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Justiniano's.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116690">The unexpected death of his dear son,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116700">So wounds his soul, that his distracted fancy</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116710">Suggests belief, he saw and heard him speak,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116720">But that cannot seem strange, if we consider</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116730">How far imagination doth usurp</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116740">Upon the power of reason, though it be</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116750">A faculty coincident to bruits,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116760">Receiving objects from the common sense;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116770">But these his perturbations I suspect</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116780">To flow from mixed affections, grief, and anger,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116790">The last of which, sinks deepest in the hearts</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116800">Of most of us Italians, and I doubt</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116810">That he thereby having involved himself</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116820">In that, which is our nation's crime, revenge;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116830">Hath been by th'other faction undermined:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116840">If this be, his disease is curable,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116850">Yet so, as every virtuous man must think</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116860">The remedy as bad as the disease,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116870">Unless strict justice do become th'avenger,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116880">Or that their own sad fates appease his rage;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116890">Oh how it wounds my heart to see my friend</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116900">And one that truly meriteth that name</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116910">But for that vice, whereof not to be guilty</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116920"><pb facs="24"/> is made a vice here, by the tyrant custom)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116930">Plunged in distress, that cannot receive counsel:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116940">But could he once with safety be restored</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116950">To his own native ingenuity,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116960">He would detest such crimes; his candid soul</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116970">Appears in this, that in the midst of fury,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116980">The sight or name of him he loved before</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e116990">Can orpheus-like calm his enraged spirit:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117000">I therefore am obliged by sacred friendship</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117010">Even to devote myself to all just means</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117020">Of his recovery, and I will perform it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117030">To cure Orestes (If the heavens so please)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117040">There shall not want a faithful Pylades. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e117050">
            <head>Actus quartus. Scaena quarta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e117060">Imperiale, Honoria, Angelica, servants, friends, Doria, maskers.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117070" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117080">Are all things ready. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117090" who="A01253-servant">
              <speaker>Servant</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117100">Yes sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117110" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117120">Noble friends,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117130">Your presence gives addition to the honour</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117140">Which some young gentlemen are pleased to do me</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117150">In the free presentation of their mirth</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117160">Most seasonable in time of Carnival,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117170">And fit to celebrate this joyful feast</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117180">Which we may challenge as our holiday. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117190" who="A01253-friend_1">
              <speaker>Fri. 1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117200">The honour of this day chiefly belongs</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117210">To you and to your family, but yet</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117220">The benefit redounds to the whole state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117230">Which every year is thankfully acknowledged. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117240" who="A01253-friend_2">
              <speaker>Fri. 2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117250">The state, by such acknowledgement invites</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117260">All generous spirits beyond common duty</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117270">To venture life and fortune for her safety. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117280" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117290">This common wealth that makes them truly happy</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117300">That share the blessings of her government</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117310">Disdains not, like a tyranny, to owe</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117320">A benefit to subjects; nor rewards</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117330"><pb facs="24"/> with banishment, in stead of bays, their merit:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117340">But hark, music proclaims the maskers coming,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117350">Be pleased to take your places, there are seats. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117360" who="A01253-friend_1">
              <speaker>Fri. 1.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117370">I must crave leave to place your daughter, sir,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117380">She that is once betrothed is a bride. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117390" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117400">'Twere incivility in her, or us,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117410">If you request it, not to be uncivil,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117420">Sit down Angelica. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117430" who="A01253-honoria">
              <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117440">Sit down, sit down,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117450">Our friends desires are in our house, commands. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A01253-e117460">
                <p xml:id="A01253-e117470">A boy, clad like a nuptial genius sings this song. </p>
                <l xml:id="A01253-e117480">Come Hymen, light thy full branched pine,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01253-e117490">And let a rosy wreath intwine</l>
                <l xml:id="A01253-e117500">Thy reeking brow, let thy brave sire</l>
                <l xml:id="A01253-e117510">With liquid virtue thee inspire,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01253-e117520">While waggish boys in witty rhymes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01253-e117530">Taxing the follies of the times,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01253-e117540">Spare not their masters, who are now</l>
                <l xml:id="A01253-e117550">Content this freedom to allow;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01253-e117560">Thus the chaste girdle of the bride</l>
                <l xml:id="A01253-e117570">Must be by pleasant rites untied,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01253-e117580">But let dark silence bring to bed</l>
                <l xml:id="A01253-e117590">Such as want Hymen when they wed. </l>
                <p xml:id="A01253-e117600">The song ended, Hymen and his Fescennine youths appear clad in antique forms, dancing a wanton dance, at the end of which, prince Doria representing Thalassius, enters with other young gentlemen his friends, attired like Romans, with their swords drawn: at sight whereof Hymen and his company run away confusedly: than they put up their swords, and dance a warlike dance, at the end whereof Doria suddenly embraceth Angelica, the masquers all crying out</p>
              </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117610" who="A01253-masker">
              <speaker>Masker</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117620">For Thalassius, for Thalassius. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117630" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117640">Though custom challengeth a liberty</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117650">To take our wives and daughters forth to tread</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117660">A measure without scandal, yet t'embrace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117670">And whisper too, requires a better warrant</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117680"><pb facs="25"/> than carnival permission, it implies</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117690">Domestic privilege, or an affronted. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117700" who="A01253-masker">
              <speaker>Masker</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117710">For Thalassius, for Thalassius. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117720" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117730">That voice was frequent at a public rape,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117740">But sacred hospitality forbids</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117750">All jealousy of any ill intent. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117760" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117770">Not, as the Romans when they had betrayed</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117780">The Sabine virgins, do my glad friends make</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117790">These acclamations of Thalassius,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117800">But rather as a more auspicious name</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117810">Then that of drowsy and lascivious Hymen;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117820">Behold the late ambassador himself</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117830">Thus contradicts his own feigned embassy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117840" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117850">My Doria! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117860" who="A01253-honoria">
              <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117870">O perfect happiness! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117880" who="A01253-friend_2">
              <speaker>Fri. 2.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117890">See how prince Doria hath surprised us all,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117900">Transformed into a nuptial deity. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117910" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117920">My doubt is in the better sense resolved:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117930">You may perceive you're welcome by the joy</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117940">Expressed both by my daughter, and my wife,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117950">In no dry compliment, but in a moist</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117960">And silent oratory. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e117970" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117980">Which works more</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e117990">On my affections, than a golden tongue;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118000">But tell me my divine Angelica,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118010">How couldst thou at the tidings of my death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118020">Put on a valiant incredulity? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118030">And when thou findest me safe burst out in tears. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118040" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118050">To lend belief to any ill report</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118060">Of a known friend, although averred with boldness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118070">In common friendship were unpardonable,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118080">Much more in such a love as mine, which finding</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118090">In a main part a manifest untruth</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118100">Was for your honour bound to slight the rest:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118110">And though there be a contrariety</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118120">In the true causes of our joy and grief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118130">Yet both are often times expressed with tears,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118140" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118150">I could not entertain nor then nor now,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118160">The least suspicion of thy constancy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118170"><pb facs="25"/> but truest love delights to please itself</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118180">With such disguises, and to find by trials</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118190">Our own assurance many ways confirmed:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118200">Nor had I ventured to disturb thy thoughts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118210">Which thy discerning judgement did prevent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118220">But that I had a present remedy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118230" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118240">I might have safely tasted what the Mede,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118250">Or the fierce parthian dips his arrows in,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118260">So long as there was such an antidote. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118270" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118280">Were I left helpless by Machaon's art,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118290">Thy presence hath a virtue would restore me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118300">Pandora on whom each deity bestowed</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118310">A several gift, was not endowed like thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118320" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118330">So soon at strife? if you will needs contend</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118340">Who will love best, I'll put you both together. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118350" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118360">He whose ambition made him weep and sweat</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118370">Within the narrow limits of one world,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118380">Did never thirst so much for fame and glory,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118390">As I for that encounter, in which combat,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118400">Whether I vanquish, or am vanquished,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118410">I shall not envy Pompey or Caesar's triumphs:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118420">In the mean time I'll crave an hour or two</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118430">For preparation of some necessaries,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118440">Whereof my absence makes me destitute. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118450" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118460">Troth my occasions have the like request,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118470">And therefore if this noble company</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118480">Will honour us tomorrow with their presence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118490">We shall endeavour to requite their loves. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118500" who="A01253-friend_1">
              <speaker>1 Fri. </speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118510">Most willingly. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118520" who="A01253-friend_2">
              <speaker>2 Fri. </speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118530">And at your nuptial feast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118540">We'll wish that every grace may be your guest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118550" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118560">I'll soon return, my heart with thee shall stay</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118570">As a sure pawn. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118580" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118590">You carry mine away. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118600" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118610">You have some business too must be dispatched,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118620">Go, lose no time; Molosso come thou hither,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118630">I leave thee in my absence to take care,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118640">That supper be prepared, and tell the steward</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118650">That great revenue, parsimony, now</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118660"><pb facs="26"/> must be by us neglected: thriving men</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118670">In charges that come seldom, are profuse. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e118680">
            <head>Actus quartus. Scaena sexta.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118690" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Molosso.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118700">I shall sir, yes, by that time you return,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118710">You shall confess you have a skilful cater:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118720">Why should proud greatness undervalue us,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118730">And our condition? since all men are slaves;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118740">If we survey the greatest monarchies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118750">What art their courtiers else? with all the suits</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118760">They either beg or wear? the rich banker</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118770">Enthralls his debtor, and his money him:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118780">This captain is a captive to that wench;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118790">This magistrate to bribes; that lord to pride,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118800">This statesman to ambition; all to fear:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118810">From whence we only that have naught to lose,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118820">Are free, and that shall instantly appear;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118830">I'll send the servants forth, that Sango and I</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118840">May act our part with more security. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118850">See how the fates themselves have helped to bring</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118860">The beast into my toil, and made both him</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118870">And his whole house the subject of my vengeance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118880">My joy is such, I cannot temper it:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118890">As when the bloodhound in a leash being led,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118900">Noseth the ground, and while the prey's far off,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118910">Spares both his mouth and feet, but drawing near,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118920">Will open wide, and drag away his leader,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118930">So are my thoughts transported, I'll away,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118940">My fury calls for blood, and I obey. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A01253-e118950">Chorus of two.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e118960" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118970">Undoubted friendship having made</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118980">A strong impression in the mind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e118990"><pb facs="26"/> though wild distempers do invade</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119000">Our reason can their fury bind. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119010">Love in distracted thoughts may bear</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119020">As great a sway as servile fear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e119030" who="A01253-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119040">He whose strong passions are his foes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119050">Is happy in a faithful friend,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119060">That will assist him to compose</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119070">Those strifes that to his ruin tend. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119080">A true friend wishes not a cause,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119090">But when there's need, he never withdraws. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e119100" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119110">A lover with no ill intent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119120">Will proteus-like, new forms devise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119130">He feigns to be on errands sent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119140">And then himself he will disguise</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119150">Like to a god, love loves to stray,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119160">And seldom keeps the beaten way. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e119170" who="A01253-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119180">But now the fatal time draws near,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119190">Wherein the error and th' offence</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119200">Of imperial will appear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119210">To trust the slave he did incense,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119220">And to encourage him to act</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119230">What he once thought a heinous fact. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e119240" who="A01253-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119250">But may there not be some excuse? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119260">At least to mitigate his fault? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119270">That he could not expect a truce,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119280">And that he found his own life sought:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119290">It hath been counted justice still,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119300">Rather than to be killed, to kill. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e119310" who="A01253-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119320">There's no excuse can purge the guilt</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119330">That murder brings; we must not take</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119340">Our own revenge, blood by us spilt,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119350">Will our whole offspring guilty make:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119360">Then let's not blame heaven's justice, when</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119370">Great plagues do light on virtuous men. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A01253-e119380">
          <pb facs="27"/>
          <head>Actus quintus.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e119390">
            <head>Scaena prima.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e119400">Fidele, Evagrio.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e119410" who="A01253-fidele">
              <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119420">We see there is small hope that gentle sleep</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119430">Can find admittance to his troubled thoughts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119440">While rage distracts them; he's no sooner laid</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119450">To rest upon his couch, but up he starts. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e119460" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119470">The wise Justinian means this night to bring</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119480">Some curious music, that may rock his senses</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119490">Into a slumber by sweet harmony,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119500">Working on his affections, we are all</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119510">Eternally obliged to that good man;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119520">Who though he be with hearty sorrow moved</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119530">To see his friend in such necessity,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119540">E'en of his help, yet is resolved to employ</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119550">His constant care, nor will he ever think</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119560">His debt of friendship paid by my labour. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e119570" who="A01253-fidele">
              <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119580">What will become of us if he miscarry? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119590">We are his kinsmen, and have no subsistence</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119600">But by his only bounty; I received</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119610">A deadly wound in the deplored death</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119620">Of his dear son, who oft was pleased to bid me</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119630">Throw all my care on him, and now I find</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119640">My hopeful venture sunk in that brave ship. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e119650" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119660">To lose out friends and fortunes I confess,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119670">Is that which needs must shake the firmest minds,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119680">But when there is no hope for us to increase</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119690">Our own affliction, and to lose our spirits,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119700">Is an infirmity beneath a man:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119710">Why should we doubt his safe recovery? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119720">Since passion as we see, doth but disturb</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119730">His reason, not destroy't; when he's at worst,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119740">He'll hearken to the counsel of his friend. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119750">How earnestly he begs, that he may speak</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119760">With imperial, and it seems Justinian</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119770">Already condescends to his request;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119780">Methinks that should not be, since he suspects</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119790"><pb facs="27"/> him to be privy to Francisco's death;</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e119800" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119810">No doubt, Justinian understands what's fit;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119820">Perchance if once he shall his mind unburden</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119830">His passions may remit, or he may seem</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119840">To promise, cause he would not have him crossed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119850">These things we wholly must commit to him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119860">Whose judgement's not inferior to his love:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119870">He wished us but withdraw awhile, we must</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119880">Not be far off, lest he should chance to call,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119890">For whatsoe'er Occasion they should have</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119900">There's none but we t'assist: Sango the slave</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119910">Hath taken liberty to go abroad,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119920">At his own pleasure, who would think the villain</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119930">Durst venture to be absent at this time? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e119940" who="A01253-fidele">
              <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119950">I have observed a wondrous league of late</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119960">Between him and his cousin slave; howe'er </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119970">Their lords are far asunder, they are near. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e119980" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e119990">'Tis ever best when such as they are kept</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120000">To daily labour, the least ease corrupts them. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120010" who="A01253-fidele">
              <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120020">There might perchance be some discovery made</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120030">If they were both examined apart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120040">And made believe each other had confessed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120050" who="A01253-evagrio">
              <speaker>Eva.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120060">Some plot, 'tis like to steal a silver spoon</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120070">To purchase opium, or the drug tobacco;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120080">That is the height of their ambitious theft:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120090">But hark they knock I prithee go thou in,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120100">And I'll take order to have Sango sent for. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e120110">
            <head>Actus quintus. Scaena secunda.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e120120">Cater, porter, cook.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120130" who="A01253-cater">
              <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120140">Thou blowest as as he that carried</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120150">An ox upon his shoulders, set it down,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120160">There's for thy pains,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120170" who="A01253-porter">
              <speaker>Port.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120180">Troth was a heavy burden. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120190" who="A01253-cater">
              <speaker>Cat</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120200">There's two quatrines more. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120210" who="A01253-porter">
              <speaker>Porter</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120220">I thank you, sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120230" who="A01253-cook">
              <speaker>Cook.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120240">Methinks Molosso might have saved this charge ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120250">And been himself porter. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120260" who="A01253-cater">
              <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120270">Who the slave? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120280"><pb facs="28"/>He's now our major domo, our lord told me</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120290">He would deliver his commands by him. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120300">He gave me order to make this provision. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120310" who="A01253-cook">
              <speaker>Cook.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120320">I like him he begins his government</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120330">With bounty, now the cook may show his skill;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120340">Since I came hither, I have been confined</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120350">To several salads, porridge with scraped cheese,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120360">And a few vermicelle, such slight dishes:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120370">Oh when I served the grand-dukes master cook</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120380">How we were all employed! I can remember,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120390">What lectures of our mystery he'd read,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120400">Styling the belly master of all arts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120410">And by a model of his own invention</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120420">Demonstrate how the antique cooks were wont</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120430">To dress th'entire boar; he was a scholar</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120440">And would discourse of the delicious sumen</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120450">And of the noble patrons of the kitchen</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120460">Both Greeks and Romans; he was wont to speak</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120470">Most reverently of one Apitius,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120480" who="A01253-cater">
              <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120490">Why what was he? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120500" who="A01253-cook">
              <speaker>Cook.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120510">A man of a brave stomach,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120520">That spent upon his belly near three millions,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120530">And having cast up his accounts, and found</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120540">Only two hundred and odd thousand crowns</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120550">Remaining to support his appetite,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120560">Doubting he should be famished, rather chose</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120570">To live by fame, and end his life with poison:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120580">But prithee knock; there was another too,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120590">One Nomentanus, but far short of him:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120600">Will they not open? we shall all be shent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120610">Knock harder. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120620" who="A01253-cater">
              <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120630">Sure they are asleep , perhaps</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120640">The slave being overleavened with his favour</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120650">Hath made himself stark drunk; we shall disturb</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120660">Our lady and her daughter, I much wonder</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120670">Mistress Nugella comes not to the door. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A01253-e120680">Noise within. O.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120690" who="A01253-cook">
              <speaker>Cook.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120700">What noise is that within? somebody groans,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120710" who="A01253-cater">
              <pb facs="28"/>
              <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120720">I will go seek our patron. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120730" who="A01253-cook">
              <speaker>Cook</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120740">Here he comes. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e120750">
            <head>Actus quintus. Scaena tertia.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e120760">Imperiale, Cater, cook.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120770" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120780">What, no for warder? we're like to sup tonight </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120790">At a fine hour? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120800" who="A01253-cater">
              <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120810">We've been a good while here sir,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120820">Have often knocked, but cannot be let in. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120830" who="A01253-cook">
              <speaker>Cook</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120840">We thought we heard a groaning in the house. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120850" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120860">How? knock again, yet, this is very strange,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120870">Where should Molosso be; perhaps my wife</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120880">And daughter with their maids may all be busy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120890">For I suppose they were to take a bath;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120900">He certainly would not neglect my service:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120910">I know not what to think, my jealousy</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120920">Suggests a thousand fears, go presently,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120930">Desire the engineer to lend m' an engine,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120940">That I may force the door. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e120950">
            <head>Actus quintus. Scaena quarta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e120960">Molosso, Sango above, Imperiale below.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e120970" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120980">Sir, here are they</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e120990">Mean to make good this fort in spite of you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121000">And all your engineers. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121010" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121020">What's thy intent? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121030">Thou knowest how far I trust thee dear Molosso. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121040" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121050">It is not your untimely trust or favour</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121060">(That is to me but sunshine after shipwreck)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121070">Can satisfy your former injuries:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121080">I would have spent an age in base observance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121090">Only to gain this day, this happy hour</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121100">That shall produce what no time shall forget. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121110" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121120">I owe my life to thee and ever shall</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121130">Make that acknowledgement, then do not thou</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121140"><pb facs="29"/> destroy thine own great merit. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121150" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121160">Think not fond man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121170">I saved thy life for any love of thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121180">But to reserve thee for a greater plague. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121190" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121200">O my dear wife and daughter, where are they? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121210" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121220">Both yet alive, the mischief's done already,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121230">But not the vengeance, thou shalt that behold,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121240">Till then there's nothing can be called revenge:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121250">Go bring 'em Sango, thou hast had thy fill</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121260" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121270">Of nectar, sweeter far than that of Jove. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e121280">
            <head>Actus quintus. Scaena quinta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e121290">Justiniano's, Spinola, Imperiale, below, molosse, Sango, Honoria, Angelica above.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121300" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121310">The best physicians in extremities,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121320">Allow their patients what they most desire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121330">Though never so seeming hurtful: when diseases</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121340">Exceed their safe and usual remedies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121350">They many times are cured by contraries:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121360">What should this mean? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121370" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121380">I must exact your promise. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121390" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121400">Upon condition you'll forbear all outrage. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121410" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121420">Set me my bounds, and see if I transgress. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121430" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121440">Stand here then, and be silent. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121450" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121460">Like a statue. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121470" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121480">Behold a pair of brides, their hair displayed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121490">Muse not to see 'em weep, the cause is light. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121500" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121510">What is the woe that these strange signs import? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121520">Speak my Honoria, my Angelica. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121530" who="A01253-honoria">
              <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121540">That which no woman's tongue is fit to express,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121550">Nor any humane ear fit to receive. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121560" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121570">Mine ears may hear what such soft hearts can bear ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121580">I have a breast prepared for misery. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121590" who="A01253-honoria">
              <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121600">Behold the wolves, the bears, that our sad dreams</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121610">Forewarned us of, which you did so despise. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121620" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121630">You hear how light the cause is, but a dream. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121640" who="A01253-honoria">
              <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121650">Our wretched story's told and understood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121660">In the sole repetition of that vision;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121670">The jewels ravished from our innocent necks. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121680"><pb facs="29"/>When swords and direful threats could not 〈◊〉</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121690">By cruel force assisting one another,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121700">Wrung from us both. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121710" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121720">O that heavens power had pleased</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121730">According to my fervent invocation,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121740">To have transformed me to some ugly monster,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121750">That horror might have frighted away lust,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121760">Or else converted it to sudden rage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121770">Whereby my life had ransomed mine honour! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121780" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121790">Was there none near to aid? where was Nugella? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121800" who="A01253-honoria">
              <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121810">Bound, and then strangled, all the rest were forth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121820" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121830">What haste a wretched creature makes to hear</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121840">His own dire wretchedness? but now Molosso,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121850">Since thou hast cloyed thy furious appetite,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121860">Unbind their tender hands, and send them down,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121870">That we may all condole their heavy fortunes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121880" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121890">If my revenge could have been satisfied</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121900">With what's already done, it had done nothing;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121910">No, bears and wolves always persist to death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121920">And I lament to find so narrow a stage</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121930">To act my vengeance on, as but two women:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121940">Sango prepare. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121950" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121960">Command, and I obey. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e121970" who="A01253-angelica">
              <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121980">Then there is hope to find compassion</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e121990">In more than Scythian breasts, there's but that left</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122000">To expiate your former cruelty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122010" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122020">O spare their lives, and all shall be forgiven! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122030" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122040">We are too far embarked to hope or wish</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122050">To be forgiven, mischief's upheld by mischief. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122060" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122070">Alas poor souls, what crime have they committed? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122080" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122090">They are both thine imperial, that's their crime,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122100">And 'tis the height of our triumphant glory,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122110">That thou shalt see 'em die, cast thine eyes up. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122120" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122130">Villain, I will not, thus I snatch away</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122140">That part of thy revengeful insolence, pulls out his eyes. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122150">So shall the sun and moon, heaven's rolling eyes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122160">Drop from their spheres at the world's general ruin,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122170">To avoid the spectacle, 'tis fit my light</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122180">Should be extinguished with my dearest objects. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122190" who="A01253-molosso">
              <pb facs="30"/>
              <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122200">What? hast thou so deluded us? thine ears</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122210">Although thou wantest eyes to see, shall hear their groans ▪</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122220" who="A01253-honoria">
              <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122230">O, o! Ang. o, o! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122240" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122250">I would have laboured more for this revenge,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122260">Than those that search the bowels of the earth</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122270">For mines, or dive into the sea for pearls. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A01253-e122280">
            <head>Actus quintus. Scaena sexta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01253-e122290">Doria, Imperiale, Molosso, Sango, Justiniano's, Spinola.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122300" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122310">Whose fortune should I envy? that am going</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122320">To take possession of a happiness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122330">Great, and (What crowns felicity) secure? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122340">Such constant joy proceeds from virtuous love:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122350">But soft, what unexpected change is here? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122360">Either mine eyes mistake, or my imperial</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122370">Is quite deprived of his; alas, 'tis so:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122380">I am amazed at this sad spectacle. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122390" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122400">There can be none but young prince Doria left,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122410">So apprehensive of my misery. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122420" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122430">What strange eclipse? or dire Stymphalides</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122440">With their prodigious wings obscure the sun? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122450">What cruel hand hath made us all thus wretched? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122460" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122470">What thou beholdest, is the least part of mine,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122480">And thine own woe. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122490" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122500">Where's my Angelica? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122510" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122520">She and her mother both are vilely murdered;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122530">And that's not all, they both were ravished first</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122540">By those two savage beasts. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122550" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122560">'Tis thy fate Doria</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122570">To be involved in that man's vowed destruction. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122580" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122590">Where am I now, in fruitful Italy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122600">Or in Hyrcania, where there's nothing seen</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122610">But horrid monsters, and perpetual snow? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122620">O wickedness! that no age will believe! </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122630">And all posterity deny! malicious fate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122640">That to my boundless misery add'st this;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122650">To make me suffer barbarous wrongs from such</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122660">As are not capable of my revenge. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122670"><pb facs="30"/>Were the sole monarch of the world, the actor,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122680">Or had he but connived at the deed done</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122690">By his lustful son or minion; I might hope,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122700">Armed with the justice of my cause, to wrest</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122710">The ill-swayed sceptre from him, and reduce</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122720">Him and his race to unparalleled examples</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122730">Of woeful pride, and miserable greatness. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122740">Then if abstracted spirits knowledge have</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122750">Of humane vows, look down deflowered maid,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122760">But yet no less a virgin than a vestal:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122770">Since honour cannot stoop to punish slaves,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122780">Whose vile condition sinks beneath that vengeance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122790">Above which no tyrant's power could hope to climb. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122800">And since thy cruel sufferings (Blessed soul)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122810">Require strict satisfaction, lo, I turn</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122820">My fury on myself, and punish thus</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122830">Mine own malignant fortune: who holds me? </l>
              <stage xml:id="A01253-e122840">Offers to kill himself.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122850">Forbear, I may not be disarmed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122860" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122870">That man</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122880">That is transported by a desperate rage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122890">Disarms himself, he that may hinder mischief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122900">And yet permits it, is an accessary. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122910" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122920">Noble Justinian, thou wert wont to be</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122930">Full of compassion, show it now, and end</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122940">A loathed life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122950" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122960">That which had been a crime</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122970">Not to prevent, were wickedness to act. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e122980" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e122990">Restore me then my sword, it is not worse</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123000">To kill him that unwilling is to die,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123010">Than to hinder him that's willing. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e123020" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123030">If thou kill'st</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123040">Thyself, thereby thou dost confess a guilt. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e123050" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123060">The guilty seldom inflict punishment</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123070">Upon themselves; what wretch can keep a life</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123080">So full of misery? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e123090" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123100">'Tis wretchedness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123110">Not to be able to bear misery,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123120">It is not as thou think'st, renowned Doria,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123130"><pb facs="31"/> a virtue to hate life, but to endure</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123140">These weighty strokes of fortune valiantly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123150">And this becomes thy noble birth and spirit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123160">On which th'afflictions of the world should fall,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123170">But as tempestuous showers into the sea. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e123180" who="A01253-doria">
              <speaker>Dor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123190">Thy counsel comes too late, sentence is given</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123200">By me upon myself, nor canst thou save</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123210">Or yet reprieve me, he that resolves to die,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123220">Finds weapons everywhere , my mind could arm</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123230">These hands without a sword, but it disdains</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123240">All borrowed aid; my weapons are within:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123250">If sudden joy can speedy death command,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123260">Why should not grief? and mine above all others? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123270">Then summon all thy forces mighty sorrow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123280">Contract this stubborn heart and stifle it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123290">Deny it the bold privilege, to be</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123300">The last that feels the stroke of death: so, so,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123310">It shoots a vapour that will poison it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123320">And choke each passage of the vital spirits,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123330">And now I feel it beat against my breast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123340">As if it gave th'alarum unto all</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123350">The organs of my life; oh how it struggles,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123360">Disdaining to submit! proud rebel down,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123370">Thy ligaments are shrunk, and I approach</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123380">The place, where lovers after death reside,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123390">Where I a ghost will yet enjoy my bride:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123400">Wilt thou not yield? dost thou expect relief? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123410">Time, that releaseth sorrow, shall not join</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123420">With refreshed nature to repair thy ruin:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123430">I to a broken heart will add this doom,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123440">No substance within these lips shall come. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e123450" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123460">Thy daughter imperial is canonised:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123470">With contrite heart devout prince Doria,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123480">Hath vowed a fast to his saint Angelica. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e123490" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123500">I feel so great a weight of misery,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123510">That I can scarce be sensible of more,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123520">Although it be (What's harder to be born</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123530">Than my calamity) a villain's scorn. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e123540" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi ▪</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123550">Thus shall my silence break, into remorse,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123560">Not into rage, that fever of the soul</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123570"><pb facs="31"/> is quite converted to an apathy;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123580">Let me cry out to fate, as Hannibal</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123590">At can, to his bloody soldiers, spare;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123600">Imperial knowest thou the voice of Spinola? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123610">By the most faithful head of my Justinian</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123620">(Than which there cannot be a holier found)</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123630">I truly am moved with pity, thy sad story</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123640">Would melt a flinty heart into compassion;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123650">Procrustes, or the wild inhabitants</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123660">Of horrid Caucasus are mild to these. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e123670" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123680">I know not, gentle Spinola how thou</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123690">Canst accept thanks from me, that have from thee</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123700">Deserved so ill, it may not be supposed</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123710">●●an dissemble now, that villain there</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123720">Contrived thy dear son's death without my knowledge,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123730">Though I am guilty of as great a crime,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123740">For I was willing, to my too late grief</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123750">Upon discovery made by thine own slave</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123760">Of thy intent, to have the same retorted</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123770">Upon thyself, the rest that wretch did plot,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123780">In whom I placed a wicked confidence;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123790">And did at length too much applaud the fact,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123800">From whence our mutual misery's result. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e123810" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123820">Thy crime was but diversion of an evil,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123830">Whereof I hate the memory, and wish</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123840">I could drink deep of Lethe, to forget</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123850">That impious design, and for these villains,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123860">I'll study a new punishment, that shall</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123870">Transcend Perillus' bull, and all the torments</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123880">Invented by the fierce Sicilian tyrants. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e123890" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123900">'Tis wretchedness to fear where there's no hope,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123910">Couldst thou believe, vain Spinola, that we</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123920">Would undertake to act so bold a mischief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123930">And not resolve upon as brave an end? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123940">We that have gained such a full revenge,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123950">Mean not to lose it by a poor submission</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123960">To hopeless mercy, or your new found torments;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123970">Though fortune made us wretched slaves to you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123980">We both retain some sparks of th'active fire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e123990">Which the 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124000"><pb facs="32"/> did sometimes flame in our Numidean breasts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124010">Not yet so quench thy servitude, but we</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124020">Have will and power to free ourselves, behold</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124030">Our liberty; these shall restore us now</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124040">To that equality that nature gave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124050">In which blind chance hath put a difference:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124060">One blow from these deliverers, can make</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124070">An abject beggar equal to a King:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124080">Sango keep time. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e124090" who="A01253-sango">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124100">I'm ready. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A01253-e124110">The slave's 〈◊〉 each other</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e124120" who="A01253-molosso">
              <speaker>Mol.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124130">By consent</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124140">We thus avoid and mock your punishment. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e124150" who="A01253-spinola">
              <speaker>Spi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124160">The harpies are flown suddenly to hell,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124170">And hang already on that hideous rock;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124180">Where dreadful fiends lie gaping to receive 'em;</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124190">But let me, sir, become your faithful guide</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124200">To lead you to my house, where you shall live,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124210">And want no comfort love or cost can give. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e124220" who="A01253-imperiale">
              <speaker>Imp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124230">The only comfort of a wretched soul</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124240">Is to despair of comfort. I see not</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124250">The mansion guilty of such wickedness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124260">But I am seen, a wretch, in Genua,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124270">Where all my ancestors stand wreathed with honour:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124280">I'll wander to a desert, or else climb</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124290">Some remote mountain, where dark clouds that hung</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124300">About his high erected head, shall hide me</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124310">From all the eyes of men, there I'll lament</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124320">My miseries in willing banishment. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01253-e124330" who="A01253-justiniano">
              <speaker>Iust.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124340">What need we care how powerful our foes be? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124350">When slaves can bring us to such misery? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124360">Whose innate cruelties at length appear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124370">Though they the same may cunningly forbear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124380">For their own ends; it is not wisdom then</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124390">To place our trust in such conditioned men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124400">Whom punishments, and wants, and fears prepare</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124410">To hatred, to deceit, and to despair:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124420">Yet these are but poor instruments, the cause</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124430">That on our heads heavens indignation draws,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124440">Springs from ourselves, 'gainst which there's no defence</l>
              <l xml:id="A01253-e124450">
                <gap extent="1" unit="lines" xml:id="A01253-e124460" n="32-a-3400"/>
              </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <pb facs="32"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A01253"><item xml:id="A01253-imperiale" n="44">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-imperiale</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">44</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-molosso" n="44">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-molosso</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">44</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-spinola" n="33">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-spinola</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">33</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-justiniano" n="26">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-justiniano</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">26</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-angelica" n="25">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-angelica</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">25</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-doria" n="21">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-doria</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">21</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-sango" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-sango</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-judge" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-judge</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-xxxx_1" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-xxxx_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-evagrio" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-evagrio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A01253-xxxx_2" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-xxxx_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-honoria" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-honoria</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-fidele" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-fidele</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-nugella" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-nugella</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-francisco" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-francisco</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-verdugo" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-verdugo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-doctor" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-doctor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-cater" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-cater</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-cook" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-cook</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-friend_1" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-friend_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-officer" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-officer</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-friend_2" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-friend_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-masker" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-masker</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-porter" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-porter</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-witness_1" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-witness_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-servant" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-servant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01253-witness_2" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01253-witness_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

