<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A18403">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Bussy D'Ambois <date type="creation_date">1604</date></title>
        <author>Chapman, George</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A18403.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Bussy d'Ambois a tragedie: as it hath been often presented at Paules.</title>
            <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>37 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99843643</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 4966.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 246(a*).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">8389</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18403</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Bussy d'Ambois a tragedie: as it hath been often presented at Paules.</title>
            <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[2], 70 p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed [at Eliot's Court Press] for William Aspley,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1607.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Anonymous. By George Chapman.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Identification of printer from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Bussy d'Amboise, -- 1549?-1579 -- Drama -- Early works to 1800.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A18403-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A18403-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A18403-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A18403-e100040">Bussy D'ambois: a tragedy: as it hath been often presented at Paul's.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18403-e100050">London, printed for William Aspley. 1607.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A18403-e100060">
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A18403-e100070">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2" n="1"/>
        <head>Bussy D'ambois: a tragedy.</head>
        <head>Actus primi scaena prima.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e100080">Bussy solus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e100090" who="A18403-bussy">
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100100">Fortune, not reason, rules the state of things,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100110">Reward goes backwards, honour on his head;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100120">Who is not poor, is monstrous; only need</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100130">Gives form and worth to every humane seed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100140">As cedars beaten with incessant storms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100150">So great men flourish; and do imitate</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100160">Unskilful statuaries, who suppose</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100170">(In forging a colossus) if they make him</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100180">Straddle enough, strut, and look big, and gape,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100190">Their work is goodly: so our tympanous statists</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100200">(In their affected gravity of voice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100210">Sourness of countenance, manner's cruelty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100220">Authority, wealth, and all the spawn of fortune)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100230">Think they bear all the kingdom's worth before them;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100240">Yet differ not from those colossic statues,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100250">Which with heroic forms, without o'erspread,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100260">Within are naught but mortar, flint and lead. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100270">Man is a torch born in the wind; a dream</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100280">But of a shadow, summed with all his substance;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100290">And as great seamen using all their powers</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100300">And skills in Neptune's deep invisible paths,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100310">In tall ships richly built and ribbed with brass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100320">To put a girdle round about the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100330"><pb facs="3" n="2"/> when they have done it (Coming near their haven)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100340">Are glad to give a warning piece, and call</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100350">A poor staid fisherman, that never passed</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100360">His country's sight, to waft and guide them in:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100370">So when we wander furthest through the waves</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100380">Of glassy glory and the gulfs of state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100390">Topped with all titles, spreading all our reaches,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100400">As if each private arm would sphere the world;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100410">We must to virtue for her guide resort,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100420">Or we shall shipwreck in our safest port. <stage xml:id="A18403-e100430">Procumbit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e100440" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <stage xml:id="A18403-e100450">Monsieur with two pages.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100460">There is no second place in numerous state</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100470">That holds more than a cypher: in a King</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100480">All places are contained. His words and looks</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100490">Are like the flashes and the bolts of Jove,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100500">His deeds inimitable, like the sea</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100510">That shuts still as it opens, and leaves no tracts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100520">Nor prints of precedent for poor men's facts:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100530">There's but a thread betwixt me and a crown;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100540">I would not wish it cut, unless by nature;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100550">Yet to prepare me for that likely fortune,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100560">'Tis fit I get resolved spirits about me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100570">I followed D'ambois to this green retreat;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100580">A man of spirit beyond the reach of fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100590">Who (Discontent with his neglected worth)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100600">Neglects the light, and loves obscure abodes;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100610">But he is young and haughty, apt to take</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100620">Fire at advancement, to bear state and flourish;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100630">In his rise therefore shall my bounties shine:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100640">None loathes the world so much, nor loves to scoff it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100650">But gold and grace will make him surfeit of it. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100660">What, D'ambois? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e100670" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100680">He sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e100690" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100700">Turned to earth, alive? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100710">Up man, the sun shines on thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e100720" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100730">Let it shine. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100740">I am no mote to play in't, as great men are. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e100750" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <pb facs="3" n="3"/>
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100760">Thinkest thou men great in state, motes in the sun? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100770">They say so that would have thee freeze in shades,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100780">That (Like the gross Sicilian gourmandist)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100790">Empty their noses in the cates they love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100800">That none may eat but they. Do thou but bring</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100810">Light to the banquet fortune sets before thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100820">And thou wilt loathe lean darkness like thy death. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100830">Who would believe thy mettle could let sloth</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100840">Rust and consume it? If Themistocles</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100850">Had lived obscured thus in th'athenian state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100860">Xerxes had made both him and it his slaves. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100870">If brave Camillus had lurked so in Rome,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100880">He had not five times been dictator there,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100890">Nor four times triumphed. If Epaminondas</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100900">(Who lived twice twenty years obscured in Thebes)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100910">Had lived so still, he had been still unnamed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100920">And paid his country nor himself their right:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100930">But putting forth his strength, he rescue both</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100940">From imminent ruin; and like burnisht steel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100950">After long use he shined; for as the light</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100960">Not only serves to show, but render us</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100970">Mutually profitable; so our lives</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100980">In acts exemplary, not only win</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e100990">Ourselves good names, but doth to others give</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101000">Matter for virtuous deeds, by which we live. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101010" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101020">What would you wish me do? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101030" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101040">Leave the troubled streams,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101050">And live as thrivers do at the well head. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101060" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101070">At the well head? Alas what should I do</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101080">With that enchanted glass? See devils there? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101090">Or (Like a strumpet) learn to set my looks</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101100">In an eternal brake, or practise juggling,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101110">To keep my face still fast, my heart still loose;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101120">Or bear (Like dames schoolemistresses their riddles)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101130">Two tongues, and be good only for a shift;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101140">Flatter great lords, to put them still in mind</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101150">Why they were made lords: or please portly ladies</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101160">With a good carriage, tell them idle tales,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101170"><pb facs="4" n="4"/> to make their physic work; spend a man's life</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101180">In sights and visitations, that will make</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101190">His eyes as hollow as his mistress heart:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101200">To do none good, but those that have no need;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101210">To gain being forward, though you break for haste</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101220">All the commandments ere you break your fast? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101230">But believe backwards, make your period</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101240">And creeds last article; I believe in God:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101250">And (Hearing villainies preached) to unfold their art</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101260">Learn to commit them, 'tis a great man's part. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101270">Shall I learn this there? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101280" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101290">No, thou needst not learn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101300">Thou hast the theory, now go there and practise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101310" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101320">Ay, in a threadbare suit; when men come there,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101330">They must have high naps, and go from thence bare:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101340">A man may drown the parts often rich men</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101350">In one poor suit; brave barks, and outward gloss</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101360">Attract court eyes, be in parts never so gross. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101370" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101380">Thou shalt have gloss enough, and all things fit</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101390">T'enchase in all show, thy long smothered spirit:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101400">Be ruled by me then. The rude Scythians</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101410">Painted blind fortunes powerful hands with wings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101420">To show her gifts come swift and suddenly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101430">Which if her favourite be not swift to take,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101440">He loses them forever. Then be ruled:<stage xml:id="A18403-e101450">Exit mons. manet buss.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101460">Stay but a while here, and I'll send to thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101470" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101480">What will he send? some crowns? It is to sow them</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101490">Upon my spirit, and make them spring a crown</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101500">Worth millions of the feed crowns he will send:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101510">But he's no husband here; a smooth plain ground</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101520">Will never nourish any politic seed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101530">I am for honest actions, not for great:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101540">If I may bring up a new fashion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101550">And rise in court with virtue; speed his plow:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101560">The King hath known me long as well as he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101570">Yet could my fortune never fit the length</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101580">Of both their understandings till this hour. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101590">There is a deep nick in times restless wheel</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101600"><pb facs="4" n="5"/> for each man's good, when which nick comes it strikes;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101610">As rhetoric, yet works not persuasion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101620">But only is a mean to make it work:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101630">So no man riseth by his real merit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101640">But when it cries clink in his raiser's spirit:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101650">Many will say, that cannot rise at all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101660">Man's first hours rise, is first step to his fall. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101670">I'll venture that; men that fall low must die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101680">As well as men cast headlong from the sky. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A18403-e101690">Ent. Maffe.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101700">Humour of princes. Is this man endued</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101710">With any merit worth a thousand crowns? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101720">Will my lord have me be so ill a steward</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101730">Of his revenue, to dispose a sum</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101740">So great with so small cause as shows in him? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101750">I must examine this: is your name D'ambois? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101760" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101770">Sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101780" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101790">Is your name D'ambois? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101800" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101810">Who have we here? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101820">Serve you the monsieur? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101830" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101840">How? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101850" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101860">Serve you the monsieur? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101870" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101880">Sir, you're very hot. I serve the monsieur;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101890">But in such place as gives me the command</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101900">Of all his other servants: and because</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101910">His grace's pleasure is, to give your good</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101920">A pass through my command; methinks you might</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101930">Use me with more good fashion. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101940" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101950">Cry you mercy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101960">Now you have opened my dull eyes, I see you;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101970">And would be glad to see the good you speak of:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e101980">What might I call your name? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e101990" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102000">Monsieur Maffe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102010" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102020">Monsieur Maffe? Then good monsieur Maffe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102030">Pray let me know you better. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102040" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102050">Pray do so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102060">That you may use me better, for yourself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102070"><pb facs="5" n="6"/> by your no better outside, I would judge you</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102080">To be a poet; have you given my lord</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102090">Some pamphlet? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102100" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102110">Pamphlet? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102120" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102130">Pamphlet sir, I say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102140" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102150">Did his wise excellency leave the good</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102160">That is to pass your charge, to my poor use,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102170">To your discretion? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102180" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102190">Though he did not sir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102200">I hope 'tis no bad office to ask reason,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102210">How that his grace gives me in charge, goes from me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102220" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102230">That's very perfect sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102240" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102250">Why very good sir;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102260">I pray then give me leave: if for no pamphlet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102270">May I not know what other merit in you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102280">Makes his compunction willing to relieve you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102290" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102300">No merit in the world sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102310" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102320">That is strange. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102330">You're a poor soldier, are you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102340" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102350">That I am sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102360" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102370">And have commanded? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102380" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102390">Ay, and gone without sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102400" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102410">I see the man: a hundred crowns will make him</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102420">Swagger, and drink healths to his highness' bounty;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102430">And swear he could not be more bountiful. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102440">So there's nine hundred crowns, saft; here tall soldier,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102450">His grace hath sent you a whole hundred crowns. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102460" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102470">A hundred sire nay do his highness right;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102480">I know his hand is larger, and perhaps</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102490">I may deserve more than my outside shows:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102500">I am a scholar, as I am a soldier,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102510">And I can poetize; and (Being well encouraged)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102520">May sing his fame for giving; yours for delivering</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102530">(Like a most faithful steward) what he gives. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102540" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102550">What shall your subject be? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102560" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102570">I care not much,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102580">If to his excellence I sing the praise</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102590">Of fair great noses, and to your deserts</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102600"><pb facs="5" n="7"/> the reverend virtues of a faithful steward;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102610">What qualities have you sir (Beside your chain</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102620">And velvet jacket) can your worship dance? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102630" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102640">A merry fellow faith: it seems my lord</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102650">Will have him for his jester; and believe it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102660">Such men are now no fools, 'tis a knight's place:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102670">If I (To save my lord some crowns) should urge him</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102680">T'abate his bounty, I should not be heard;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102690">I would to heaven I were an errant ass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102700">For then I should be sure to have the ears</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102710">Of these great men, where now their jesters have them:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102720">'Tis good to please him, yet I'll take no notice</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102730">Of his preferment, but in policy</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102740">Will still be grave and serious, lest he think</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102750">I fear his wooden dagger: here sir Ambo,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102760">A thousand crowns I bring you from my lord;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102770">Serve God, play the good husband, you may make</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102780">This a good standing living, 'tis a bounty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102790">His highness might perhaps have bestowed better. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102800" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102810">Go, you're a rascal; hence, away you rogue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102820" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102830">What mean you sir? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102840" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102850">Hence; prate no more;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102860">Or by thy villain's blood thou pratest thy last:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102870">A barbarous groom, grudge at his master's bounty:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102880">But since I know he would as much abhor</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102890">His hind should argue what he gives his friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102900">Take that sir, for your aptness to dispute. <stage xml:id="A18403-e102910">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102920" who="A18403-maffe">
          <speaker>Maff.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102930">These crowns are sown in blood, blood be their fruit. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e102940">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e102950">Henry, Guise, Montsurry, Elenor, Tamyra, Beaupre, Pero, Charlotte, Pyr, Annable.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e102960" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102970">Duchess of Guise, your grace is much enriched,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102980">In the attendance of this English virgin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e102990">That will initiate her prime of youth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103000">(Disposed to court conditions) under hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103010">Of your prefered instructions and command,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103020"><pb facs="6" n="8"/> rather than any in the English court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103030">Whose ladies are not matched in Christendom,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103040">For graceful and confirmed behaviours;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103050">More than the court, where they are bred is equalled. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103060" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Guis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103070">I like not their court form, it is too crest-fallen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103080">In all observance; making semigods</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103090">Of their great nobles; and of their old Queen</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103100">An ever-young, and most immortal goddess. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103110" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103120">Assure you cousin Guise, so great a courtier,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103130">So full of majesty and royal parts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103140">No Queen in Christendom may boast herself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103150">Her court approves it, that's a court indeed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103160">Not mixed with rudeness used in common houses;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103170">But, as courts should be th'abstracts of their kingdoms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103180">In all the beauty, state, and worth they hold;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103190">So is hers, amply, and by her informed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103200">The world is not contracted in a man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103210">With more proportion and expression</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103220">Than in her court, her kingdom: our French court</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103230">Is a mere mirror of confusion to it:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103240">The King and subject, lord and every slave</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103250">Dance a continual Hay; our rooms of state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103260">Kept like our stables; no place more observed</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103270">Than a rude market place: and though our custom</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103280">Keep this assured deformity from our sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103290">'Tis never the less essentially unsightly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103300">Which they would soon see, would they change their form</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103310">To this of ours, and then compare them both;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103320">Which we must not affect, because in kingdoms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103330">Where the King's change doth breed the subjects' terror,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103340">Pure innovation is more gross than error. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103350" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103360">No question we shall see them imitate</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103370">(Though afar off) the fashions of our courts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103380">As they have ever aped us in attire;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103390">Never were men so weary of their skins,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103400">And apt to leap out of themselves as they;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103410">Who when they travel to bring forth rare men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103420">Come home delivered of a fine French suit:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103430"><pb facs="6" n="9"/> their brains lie with their tailors, and get babies</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103440">For their most complete issue; he's first born</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103450">To all the moral virtues, that first greets</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103460">The light with a new fashion, which becomes them</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103470">Like apes, disfigured with the attires of men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103480" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103490">No question they much wrong their real worth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103500">In affectation of outlandish scum;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103510">But they have faults, and we; they foolish-proud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103520">To be the pictures of our vanity;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103530">We proud, that they are proud of foolery. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e103540">Enter monsieur, D'ambois.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103550" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103560">Come mine own sweet heart I will enter thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103570">Sir, I have brought this gentleman t'attend you;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103580">And pray, you would vouchsafe to do him grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103590" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103600">D'ambois, I think. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103610" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103620">That's still my name, my lord, though I be something altered in attire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103630" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103640">I like your alteration, and must tell you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103650">I have expected th'offer of your service;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103660">For we (In fear to make mild virtue proud)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103670">Use not to seek her out in any man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103680" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103690">Nor doth she use to seek out any man:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103700">He that will win, must woo her; she's not shameless. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103710" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103720">I urged her modesty in him, my lord, and gave her those rites, that he says she merits.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103730" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e103740">If you have wooed and won, than brother wear him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103750" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103760">Thou'rt mine, my love; see here's the Guise's Duchess. The countess of Mountsurreave; Beaupres, come I'll enseam thee; ladies, you're too many to be in counsel: I have here a friend, that I would gladly enter in your graces.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103770" who="A18403-duchess">
          <speaker>Duchess</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103780">If you enter him in our graces, methinks by his blunt behaviour, he should come out of himself.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103790" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103800">Has he never been courtier, my lord?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103810" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103820">Never, my lady.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103830" who="A18403-beaupre">
          <speaker>Beaup.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103840">And why did the toy take him in th'head now?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103850" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103860">'Tis leap year, lady, and therefore very good to<pb facs="7" n="10"/> enter a courtier.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103870" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103880">The man's a courtier at first sight.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103890" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103900">I can sing pricksong, lady, at first sight; and why not be a courtier as suddenly?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103910" who="A18403-beaupre">
          <speaker>Beaup.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103920">Here's a courtier rotten before he be ripe.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103930" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103940">Think me not impudent, lady, I am yet no courtier, I desire to be one, and would gladly take entrance (Madam) under your princely colours.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103950" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103960">Sir, know you me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103970" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e103980">My lord?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e103990" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104000">I know not you: whom do you serve?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104010" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104020">Serve, my lord?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104030" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104040">Go to companion; your courtship's too saucy.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104050" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104060">Saucy? Companion? 'tis the Guise, but yet those terms might have been spared of the Guiserd.</p>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104070">Companion? He's jealous by this light: are you blind of that side sir? I'll to her again for that. Forth madam, for the honour of courtship.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104080" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104090">Cease your courtship, or by heaven I'll cut your throat.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104100" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104110">Cut my throat? cut a whetstone; good Accius Noevius, do as much with your tongue as he did with a razor; cut my throat?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104120" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104130">I'll do't by this hand.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104140" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104150">That hand dares not do't; you've cut too many</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104160">Throats already Guise; and robbed the realm of</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104170">Many thousand souls, more precious than thine own. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104180">Come madam, talk on; sfoot, can you not talk? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104190">Talk on I say, more courtship, as you love it. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e104200">Enter Barrisor, L' Anou, Pyrlot.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104210" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104220">What new-come gallant have we here, that dares mate the Guise thus?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104230" who="A18403-l'anou">
          <speaker>L' An.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104240">Sfoot 'tis D'ambois; the Duke mistakes him (On my life) for some knight of the new edition.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104250" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104260">Cut my throat? I would the King feared thy cutting of his throat no more than I fear thy cutting of mine.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104270" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104280">So sir, so.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104290" who="A18403-pyra">
          <pb facs="7" n="11"/>
          <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104300">Here's some strange distemper.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104310" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104320">Here's a sudden transmigration with D'ambois, out of the knight's ward, into the Duchess bed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104330" who="A18403-l'anou">
          <speaker>L'an.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104340">See what a metamorphosis a brave suit can work.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104350" who="A18403-pyra">
          <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104360">'Slight step to the Guise and discover him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104370" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104380">By no means, let the new suit work, we'll see the issue.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104390" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104400">Leave your courtship.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104410" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104420">I will not. I say mistress, and I will stand unto it, that if a woman may have three servants, a man may have threescore mistresses.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104430" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104440">Sirrah, I'll have you whipped out of the court for this insolence.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104450" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104460">Whipped? Such another syllable out a th' presence, if thou dar'st for thy dukedom.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104470" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104480">Remember, poltroon.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104490" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104500">Pray thee forbear.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104510" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104520">Passion of death! Were not the King here, he should strew the chamber like a rush.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104530" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104540">But leave courting his wife then.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104550" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104560">I will not: I'll court her in despite of him ▪ not court her! Come madam, talk on; fear me nothing: well mayst thou drive thy master from the court; but never D'ambois.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104570" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104580">His great heart will not down, 'tis like the sea</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104590">That partly by his own internal heat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104600">Partly the star's daily and nightly motion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104610">Ardour and light, and partly of the place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104620">The divers frames; and chiefly by the moon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104630">Bristled with surges, never will be won,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104640">(No, not when th'hearts of all those powers are burst)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104650">To make retreat into his settled home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104660">Till he be crowned with his own quiet foam. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104670" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104680">You have the mate. Another. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104690" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e104700">No more. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e104710">Exit Guise, after him the King, mons. whispering.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104720" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104730">Why here's the lion, scared with the throat of a dunghill cock; a fellow that has newly shaked off his shackles;<pb facs="8" n="12"/> now does he crow for that victory.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104740" who="A18403-l'anou">
          <speaker>L' An.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104750">'Tis one of the best jigs that ever was acted.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104760" who="A18403-unassigned">
          <speaker>Pry.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104770">Whom does the Guise suppose him to be trow?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104780" who="A18403-l'anou">
          <speaker>L' An.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104790">Out of doubt, some new denizened lord; and thinks that suit come new out a th' mercers books.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104800" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104810">I have heard of a fellow, that by a fixed imagination looking upon a bull-baiting, had a visible pair of horns grew out of his forehead: and I believe this gallant overjoyed with the conceit of monsieurs cast suit, imagines himself to be the monsieur.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104820" who="A18403-l'anou">
          <speaker>L' An</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104830">And why not? as well as the ass, stalking in the lion's case, bear himself like a lion, roaring all the huger beasts out of the forest?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104840" who="A18403-unassigned">
          <speaker>Pry.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104850">Peace, he looks this way.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104860" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104870">Marry let him look sir, what will you say now if the Guise be gone to fetch a blanket for him?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104880" who="A18403-l'anou">
          <speaker>L' An.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104890">Faith I believe it for his honour.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104900" who="A18403-pyra">
          <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104910">But, if D'ambois carry it clean?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104920" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104930">True, when he curvets in the blanket.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104940" who="A18403-pyra">
          <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104950">I marry sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104960" who="A18403-l'anou">
          <speaker>L' An.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104970">Sfoot, see how he stares on's.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e104980" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e104990">Lord bless us, let's away.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105000" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105010">Now sir, take your full view: how does the object please ye?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105020" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105030">If you ask my opinion sir, I think your suit sits as well as if't had been made for you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105040" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105050">So sir, and was that the subject of your ridiculous jollity?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105060" who="A18403-l'anou">
          <speaker>L' An.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105070">What's that to you sir?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105080" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105090">Sir, I have observed all your fleerings; and resolve yourselves ye shall give a strict account for't.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e105100">Enter Brisac Melynell.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105110" who="A18403-pyra">
          <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105120">O strange credulity! Do you think yourself such a singular subject for laughter, that none can fall into our merriment but you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105130" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105140">This jealousy of yours sir, confesses some close defect in yourself, that we never dreamed of.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105150" who="A18403-l'anou">
          <pb facs="8" n="13"/>
          <speaker>L An.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105160">We held discourse of a perfumed ass, that being disguised with a lion's case, imagined himself a lion: I hope that touched not you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105170" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105180">So sir: your descants do marvelous well fit this ground, we shall meet where your buffonly laughters will cost ye the best blood in your bodies.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105190" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105200">For life's sake let's be gone; he'll kill's outright.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105210" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105220">Go at your pleasures, I'll be your ghost to haunt you, and ye sleep an't, hang me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105230" who="A18403-l'anou">
          <speaker>L' An.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105240">Go, go sir, court your mistress.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105250" who="A18403-pyra">
          <speaker>Pyr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105260">And be advised: we shall have odds against you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105270" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105280">Tush, valour stands not in number: I'll maintain it, that one man may beat three boys.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105290" who="A18403-brisac">
          <speaker>Bris.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105300">Nay you shall have no odds of him in number sir: he's a gentleman as good as the proudest of you, and ye shall not wrong him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105310" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105320">Not sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105330" who="A18403-melynell">
          <speaker>Mely.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105340">Not sir: though he be not so rich, he's a better man than the best of you; and I will not endure it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105350" who="A18403-l'anou">
          <speaker>L' An.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105360">Not you sir?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105370" who="A18403-brisac">
          <speaker>Bris.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105380">No sir, nor I.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105390" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105400">I should thank you for this kindness, if I thought these perfumed muske-cats (Being out of this privilege) durst but once mew at us.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105410" who="A18403-barrisor">
          <speaker>Bar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105420">Does your confident spirit doubt that sir? Come follow us and try.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105430" who="A18403-l'anou">
          <speaker>L'an.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e105440">Come sir, we'll lead you a dance. <stage xml:id="A18403-e105450">Exeunt.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <trailer xml:id="A18403-e105460">Finis actus primi.</trailer>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A18403-e105470">
        <head>Actus secundi scaena prima.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e105480">Henry, Guise, Beaumond, nuncius.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105490" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105500">This desperate quarrel sprung out of their envies</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105510">To D'ambois sudden bravery, and great spirit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105520" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105530">Neither is worth their envy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105540" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105550">Less than either</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105560"><pb facs="9" n="14"/> will make the gall of envy overflow;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105570">She feeds on outcast entrails like a kite:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105580">In which foul heap, if any ill lies hid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105590">She sticks her beak into it, shakes it up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105600">And hurls it all abroad, that all may view it. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105610">Corruption is her nutriment; but touch her</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105620">With any precious ointment, and you kill her:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105630">When she finds any filth in men, she feasts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105640">And with her black throat bruits it through the world;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105650">(Being sound and healthful) but if she but taste</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105660">The slenderest pittance of commended virtue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105670">She surfeits of it, and is like a fly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105680">That passes all the bodies soundest parts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105690">And dwells upon the sores; or if her squint eye</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105700">Have power to find none there, she forges some:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105710">She makes that crooked ever which is straight;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105720">Calls valour giddiness, justice tyranny:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105730">A wise man may shun her, she not herself;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105740">Whither soever she flies from her harms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105750">She bears her foe still clasped in her own arms:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105760">And therefore cousin Guise let us avoid her. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A18403-e105770">Enter nuncius.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105780">What Atlas, or Olympus lifts his head</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105790">So far passed covert, that with air enough</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105800">My words may be informed? And from his height</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105810">I may be seen, and heard through all the world? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105820">A tale so worthy, and so fraught with wonder,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105830">Sticks in my jaws, and labours with event. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105840" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105850">Com'st thou from D'ambois? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105860" who="A18403-nuntius">
          <speaker>Nuntius</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105870">From him, and the rest</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105880">His friends and enemies; whose stern fight I saw,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105890">And heard their words before, and in the fray. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105900" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105910">Relate at large what thou hast seen and heard. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e105920" who="A18403-nuntius">
          <speaker>Nuntius</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105930">I saw fierce D'ambois, and his two brave friends</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105940">Enter the field, and at their heels their foes;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105950">Which were the famous soldiers; Barrisor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105960">L'anou, and Pyrrhot, great in deeds of arms:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105970"><pb facs="9" n="15"/> all which arrived at the evenest piece of earth</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105980">The field afforded; the three challengers</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e105990">Turned head, drew all their rapiers, and stood ranked:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106000">When face to face the three defendants met them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106010">Alike prepared, and resolute alike,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106020">Like bonfires of contributory wood:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106030">Every man's look showed, fed with either's spirit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106040">As one had been a mirror to another,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106050">Like forms of life and death, each took from other;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106060">And so were life and death mixed at their heights,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106070">That you could see no fear of death, for life;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106080">Nor love of life, for death: but in their brows</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106090">Pyrrho's opinion in great letters shone;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106100">That life and death in all respects are one. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e106110" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106120">Passed there no sort of words at their encounter? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e106130" who="A18403-nuntius">
          <speaker>Nuntius</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106140">As Hector, twixt the hosts of Greece and Troy ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106150">(When Paris and the Spartan King should end</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106160">The nine years war) held up his brazen lance</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106170">For signal, that both hosts should cease from arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106180">And hear him speak: so Barrisor (Advised)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106190">Advanced his naked rapier twixt both sides,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106200">Ripped up the quarrel, and compared six lives;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106210">Then laid in balance with six idle words,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106220">Offered remission and contrition too;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106230">Or else that he and D'ambois might conclude</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106240">The others dangers. D'ambois liked the last;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106250">But Barrisor's friends (Being equally engaged</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106260">In the main quarrel) never would expose</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106270">His life alone, to that they all deserved. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106280">And (For the other offer of remission)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106290">D'ambois (That like a laurel put in fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106300">Sparkled and spit) did much much more than scorn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106310">That his wrong should incense him so like chaff,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106320">To go so soon out; and like lighted paper,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106330">Approve his spirit at once both fire and ashes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106340">So drew they lots, and in them fates appointed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106350">That Barrisor should fight with fiery D'ambois;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106360">Pyrhot with Melinell; with Brisac L'anou:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106370"><pb facs="10" n="16"/> and then like flame and powder they commixed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106380">So sprightly, that I wished they had been spirits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106390">That the never shutting wounds, they needs must open,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106400">Might as they opened, shut, and never kill:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106410">But D'ambois sword (That lightened as it flew)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106420">Shot like a pointed comet at the face</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106430">Of manly Barrisor; and there it stuck:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106440">Thrice plucked he at it, and thrice drew on thrusts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106450">From him, that of himself was free as fire;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106460">Who thrust still as he plucked, yet (Past belief!) </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106470">He with his subtle eye, hand, body, 'scaped;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106480">At last the deadly bitten point tugged off,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106490">On fell his yet undaunted foe so fiercely,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106500">That (Only made more horrid with his wound)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106510">Great D'ambois shrunk, and gave a little ground;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106520">But soon returned, redoubled in his danger,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106530">And at the heart of Barrisor sealed his anger:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106540">Then, as in Arden I have seen an oak</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106550">Long shook with tempests, and his lofty top</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106560">Bent to his root, which being at length made loose</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106570">(Even groaning with his weight) he 'gan to nod</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106580">This way and that: as loath his curled brows</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106590">(Which he had oft wrapped in the sky with storms)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106600">Should stoop: and yet, his radical fever's burst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106610">Stormlike he fell, and hid the fear-cold earth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106620">So fell stout Barrisor, that had stood the shocks</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106630">Often set battles in your highness' war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106640">'Gainst the sole soldier of the world, Navarre. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e106650" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106660">O piteous and horrid murder! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e106670" who="A18403-beaumond">
          <speaker>Beau.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106680">Such a life</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106690">Methinks had mettle in it to survive</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106700">An age of men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e106710" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106720">Such, often soonest end. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106730">Thy felt report calls on, we long to know</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106740">On what events the other have arrived. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e106750" who="A18403-nuntius">
          <speaker>Nuntius</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106760">Sorrow and fury, like two opposite fumes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106770">Met in the upper region of a cloud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106780">At the report made by this worthies fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106790"><pb facs="10" n="17"/> broke from the earth, and with them rose revenge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106800">Entering with fresh powers his two noble friends;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106810">And under that odds fell surcharged Brisac,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106820">The friend of D'ambois, before fierce L'anou;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106830">Which D'ambois seeing, as I once did see</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106840">In my young travels through Armenia,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106850">An angry unicorn in his full carrier</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106860">Charge with too quick an eye a jeweller,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106870">That watched him for the treasure of his brow;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106880">And ere he could get shelter of a tree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106890">Nail him with his rich antler to the earth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106900">So D'ambois ran upon revenged L'anou,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106910">Who eyeing th'eager point born in his face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106920">And giving back, fell back, and in his fall</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106930">His foes uncurbed sword stopped in his heart:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106940">By which time all the life strings of the tw'other</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106950">Were cut, and both fell as their spirits flew</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106960">Upwards: and still hunt honour at the view. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106970">And now (Of all the six) sole D'ambois stood</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e106980">Untouched, save only with the others blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e106990" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107000">All slain outright? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107010" who="A18403-nuntius">
          <speaker>Nuntius</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107020">All slain outright but he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107030">Who kneeling in the warm life of his friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107040">(All feebled with the blood, his rapier reigned)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107050">He kissed their pale cheeks, and bade both farewell;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107060">And see the bravest man the French earth bears. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e107070">Enter monsieur, D'amb. bore.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107080" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107090">Now is the time, you're princely vowed my friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107100">Perform it princely, and obtain my pardon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107110" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107120">Else heaven, forgive not me: come on brave friend. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107130">If ever nature held herself her own,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107140">When the great trial of a King and subject</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107150">Met in one blood, both from one belly springing:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107160">Now prove her virtue and her greatness one,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107170">Or make the t'one the greater with the tother,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107180">(As true Kings should) and for your brother's love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107190">(Which is a special species of true virtue)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107200"><pb facs="11" n="18"/> do that you could not do, not being a King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107210" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107220">Brother I know your suit; these wilful murders</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107230">Are ever passed our pardon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107240" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107250">Manly slaughter</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107260">Should never bear th' account of wilful murder;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107270">It being a spice of justice, where with life</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107280">Offending passed law, equal life is laid</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107290">In equal balance, to scourge that offence</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107300">By law of reputation, which to men</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107310">Exceeds all positive law, and what that leaves</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107320">To true men's valours (Not prefixing rights</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107330">Of satisfaction, suited to their wrongs)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107340">A free man's eminence may supply and take. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107350" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107360">This would make every man that thinks him wronged,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107370">Or is offended, or in wrong or right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107380">Lay on this violence, and all vaunt themselves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107390">Law-menders and suppliers though mere butchers;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107400">Should this fact (Though of justice) be forgiven? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107410" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107420">O no, my lord; it would make cowards fear</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107430">To touch the reputations of full men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107440">When only they are left to imp the law,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107450">Justice will soon distinguish murderous minds</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107460">From just revengers: had my friend been slain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107470">(His enemy surviving) he should die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107480">Since he had added to a murdered fame</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107490">(Which was in his intent) a murthered man;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107500">And this had worthily been wilful murder:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107510">But my friend only saved his fame's dear life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107520">Which is above life, taking th'under value,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107530">Which in the wrong it did, was forfeit to him;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107540">And in this fact only preserves a man</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107550">In his uprightness; worthy to survive</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107560">Millions of such as murder men, alive. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107570" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107580">Well brother, rise, and raise your friend withal</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107590">From death to life: and D'ambois, let your life</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107600">(Refined by passing through this merited death)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107610">Be purged from more such foul pollution;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107620">Nor on your scape, nor valour more presuming,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107630"><pb facs="11" n="19"/> to be again so violent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107640" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107650">My lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107660">I loathe as much a deed of unjust death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107670">As law itself doth; and to tyrannize,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107680">Because I have a little spirit to date,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107690">And power to do, as to be tyrannised;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107700">This is a grace that (On my knees redoubled)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107710">I crave to double this my short life's gift;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107720">And shall your royal bounty centuple,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107730">That I may so make good what God and nature</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107740">Have given me for my good: since I am free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107750">(Offending no just law) let no law make</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107760">By any wrong it does, my life her slave:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107770">When I am wronged and that law fails to right me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107780">Let me be King myself (As man was made)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107790">And do a justice that exceeds the law:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107800">If my wrong pass the power of single valour</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107810">To right and expiate; then be you my King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107820">And do a right, exceeding law and nature:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107830">Who to himself is law, no law doth need,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107840">Offends no King, and is a King indeed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107850" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107860">Enjoy what thou intreatest, we give but ours. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107870" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107880">What you have given, my lord, is ever yours. <stage xml:id="A18403-e107890">Exit rex cum Beau.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107900" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107910">Mort dieu, who would have pardoned such a murder? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107920" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107930">Now vanish horrors into court attractions,<stage xml:id="A18403-e107940">Exit.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107950">For which let this balm make thee fresh and fair. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107960" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107970">How shall I quite your love? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e107980" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e107990">Be true to the end:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108000">I have obtained a kingdom with my friend. <stage xml:id="A18403-e108010">Exit,</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e108020">Montsur. Tamyra, Beaupre, Pero, Charlotte, Pyrha.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108030" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108040">He will have pardon sure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108050" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108060">'Twere pity else:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108070">For though his great spirit something overflow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108080">All faults are still born, that from greatness grow:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108090">But such a sudden courtier saw I never. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108100" who="A18403-beaumond">
          <speaker>Beau.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108110">He was too sudden, which indeed was rudeness. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108120" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108130">True, for it argued his no due conceit</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108140"><pb facs="12" n="20"/> both of the place, and greatness of the persons:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108150">Nor of our sex: all which (We all being strangers</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108160">To his encounter) should have made more manners</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108170">Deserve more welcome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108180" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108190">All this fault is found</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108200">Because he loved the Duchess and left you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108210" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108220">Alas, love give her joy; I am so far</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108230">From envy of her honour, that I swear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108240">Had he encountered me with such proud sleight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108250">I would have put that project face of his</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108260">To a more test, than did her duchessship. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108270" who="A18403-beaumond">
          <speaker>Be.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108280">Why (By your leave my lord) I'll speak it here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108290">(Although she be my aunt) she scarce was modest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108300">When she perceived the Duke her husband take</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108310">Those late exceptions to her servant's courtship</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108320">To entertain him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108330" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108340">Ay, and stand him still. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108350">Letting her husband give her servant place:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108360">Though he did manly, she should be a woman. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A18403-e108370">Enter Guise.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108380">D'ambois is pardoned: where's a King? where law? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108390">See how it runs, much like a turbulent sea;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108400">Here high, and glorious, as it did contend</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108410">To wash the heavens, and make the stars more pure:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108420">And here so low, it leaves the mud of hell</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108430">To every common view: come count Montsurry</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108440">We must consult of this. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108450" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108460">Stay not, sweet lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108470" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108480">Be pleased, I'll straight return. <stage xml:id="A18403-e108490">Exit cum Guise.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108500" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108510">Would that would please me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108520" who="A18403-beaumond">
          <speaker>Beau.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108530">I'll leave you madam to your passions. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108540">I see, there's change of weather in your looks. <stage xml:id="A18403-e108550">Exit cum suis.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108560" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108570">I cannot cloak it: but; as when a fume,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108580">Hot, dry and gross: within the womb of earth</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108590">Or in her superficies begotten:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108600">When extreme cold hath struck it to her heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108610">The more it is compressed, the more it rageth;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108620"><pb facs="12" n="21"/> exceeds his prison's strength that should contain it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108630">And then it tosseth temples in the air;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108640">All bars made engines, to his insolent fury:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108650">So, of a sudden, my licentious fancy</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108660">Riots within me: not my name and house</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108670">Nor my religion to this hour observed</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108680">Can stand above it: I must utter that</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108690">That will in parting break more strings in me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108700">Than death when life parts: and that holy man</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108710">That, from my cradle, counselled for my soul:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108720">I now must make an agent for my blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e108730">Enter monsieur.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108740" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108750">Yet, is my mistress gracious? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108760" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108770">Yet unanswered? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108780" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108790">Pray thee regard thine own good, if not mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108800">And cheer my love for that; you do not know</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108810">What you may be by me, nor what without me;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108820">I may have power t'advance and pull down any. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108830" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108840">That's not my study: one way I am sure</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108850">You shall not pull down me: my husband's height</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108860">Is crown to all my hopes: and his retiring</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108870">To any mean state, shall be my aspiring:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108880">Mine honour's in mine own hands, spite of Kings. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e108890" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108900">Honour, what's that? your second maidenhead:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108910">And what is that? A word: the word is gone</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108920">The thing remains: the rose is plucked, the stalk</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108930">Abides: an easy loss where no lack's found:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108940">Believe it there's as small lack in the loss,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108950">As there is pain ith' losing: archers ever</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108960">Have two strings to a bow: and shall great Cupid</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108970">(Archer of archers both in men and women)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108980">Be worse provided than a common archer? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e108990">A husband and a friend all wise wives have. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109000" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109010">Wise wives they are that on such strings depend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109020">With a firm husband, weighing a dissolute friend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109030" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109040">Still you stand on your husband, so do all</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109050">The common sex of you, when you're encountered</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109060"><pb facs="13" n="22"/> with one ye cannot fancy: all men know</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109070">You live in court here by your own election,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109080">Frequenting all our solemn sports and triumphs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109090">All the most youthful company of men:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109100">And wherefore do you this? To please your husband ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109110">'Tis gross and fulsome: if your husband's pleasure</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109120">Be all your object, and you aim at honour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109130">In living close to him, get you from court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109140">You may have him at home; these common puttofs</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109150">For common women serve: my honour? husband? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109160">Dame's meritorious, never were meritorious:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109170">Speak plain and say I do not like you sir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109180">You're an ill-favoured fellow in my eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109190">And I am answered. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109200" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109210">Then I pray be answered:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109220">For in good faith my lord I do not like you</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109230">In that sort you like. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109240" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109250">Then have at you here:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109260">Take (With a politic hand) this rope of pearl;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109270">And though you be not amorous: yet be wise:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109280">Take me for wisdom; he that you can love</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109290">Is near the further from you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109300" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109310">Now it comes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109320">So ill prepared, that I may take a poison,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109330">Under a medicine as good cheap as it:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109340">I will not have it were it worth the world. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109350" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109360">Horror of death: could I but please your eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109370">You would give me the like, ere you would lose me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109380">Honour and husband? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109390" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109400">By this light my lord</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109410">You're a vile fellow: and I'll tell the King</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109420">Your occupation of dishonouring ladies</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109430">And of his court: a lady cannot live</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109440">As she was born; and with that sort of pleasure</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109450">That fits her state: but she must be defamed</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109460">With an infamous lords detraction:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109470">Who would endure the court if these attempts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109480">Of open and professed lust must be born? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109490"><pb facs="13" n="23"/>Who's there? come on dame, you are at your book</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109500">When men are at your mistress; have I taught you</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109510">Any such waiting woman's quality? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109520" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109530">Farewell good husband. <stage xml:id="A18403-e109540">Exit mons.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109550" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109560">Farewell wicked lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e109570">Enter Mont.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109580" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109590">Was not the monsieur here? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109600" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109610">Yes, to good purpose. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109620">And your cause is as good to seek him too</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109630">And haunt his company. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109640" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109650">Why what's the matter? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109660" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109670">Matter of death, were I some husband's wife:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109680">I cannot live at quiet in my chamber</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109690">For opportunities almost to rapes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109700">Offered me by him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109710" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109720">Pray thee bear with him:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109730">Thou knowest he is a bachelor, and a courtier,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109740">Ay, and a prince: and their prerogatives</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109750">Are, to their laws, as to their pardons are</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109760">Their reservations, after parliaments</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109770">One quits another: form gives all their essence:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109780">That prince doth high in virtues reckoning stand</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109790">That will entreat a vice, and not command:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109800">So far bear with him: should another man</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109810">Trust to his privilege, he should trust to death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109820">Take comfort then (My comfort) nay triumph,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109830">And crown thyself, thou partest with victory:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109840">My presence is so only dear to thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109850">That other men's appear worse than they be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109860">For this night yet, bear with my forced absence:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109870">Thou knowest my business; and with how much weight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109880">My vow hath charged it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109890" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109900">True my lord, and never</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109910">My fruitless love shall let your serious profit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109920">Yet, sweet lord, do no stay, you know my soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109930">Is so long time without me, and I dead</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109940">As you are absent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109950" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <pb facs="14" n="24"/>
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109960">By this kiss, receive</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109970">My soul for hostage, till I see my love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e109980" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e109990">The morn shall let me see you:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e110000" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110010">With the sun</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110020">I'll visit thy more comfortable beauties. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e110030" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110040">This is my comfort, that the sun hath left</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110050">The whole world's beauty ere my sun leaves me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e110060" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110070">'Tis late night now indeed: farewell my light. <stage xml:id="A18403-e110080">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e110090" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110100">Farewell my light and life: but not in him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110110">Alas, that in the wave of our affections</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110120">We should supply it with a full dissembling,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110130">In which each youngest maid is grown a mother,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110140">Frailty is fruitful, one sin gets another:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110150">Our loves like sparkles are that brightest shine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110160">When they go out most vice shows most divine:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110170">Go maid, to bed, lend me your book I pray:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110180">Not like yourself, for form, I'll this night trouble</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110190">None of your services: make sure the doors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110200">And call your other fellows to their rest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e110210" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110220">I will, yet I will watch to know why you watch. Exit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e110230" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110240">Now all the peaceful regents of the night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110250">Silently-gliding exhalations,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110260">Languishing winds, and murmuring falls of waters,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110270">Sadness of heart, and ominous secureness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110280">Enchantments, dead sleeps, all the friends of rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110290">That ever wrought upon the life of man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110300">Extend your utmost strengths; and this charmed hour</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110310">Fix like the centre; make the violent wheels</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110320">Of time and fortune stand; and great existens</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110330">(The maker's treasury) now not seem to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110340">To all but my approaching friends and me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110350">They come, alas they come, fear, fear and hope</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110360">Of one thing, at one instant fight in me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110370">I love what most I loathe, and cannot live</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110380">Unless I compass that that holds my death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110390">For love is hateful without love again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110400">And he I love, will loathe me, when he sees</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110410">I fly my sex, my virtue, my renown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110420"><pb facs="14" n="25"/> to run so madly on a man unknown. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110430">See, see the gulf is opening, that will swallow</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110440">Me and my fame for ever; I will in,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110450">And cast myself off, as I never had been. <stage xml:id="A18403-e110460">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e110470" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110480">Come worthiest son, I am past measure glad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110490">That you (Whose worth I have approved so long)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110500">Should be the object of her fearful love;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110510">Since both your wit and spirit can adapt</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110520">Their full force to supply her utmost weakness:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110530">You know her worths and virtues, for report</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110540">Of all that know, is to a man a knowledge:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110550">You know besides, that our affections storm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110560">Raised in our blood, no reason can reform. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110570">Though she seek then their satisfaction,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110580">(Which she must needs, or rest unsatisfied)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110590">Your judgement will esteem her peace thus wrought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110600">Nothing less dear, than if yourself had sought:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110610">And (With another colour, which my art</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110620">Shall teach you to lay on) yourself must seem</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110630">The only agent, and the first orb move,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110640">In this our set, and cunning world of love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e110650" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110660">Give me the colour (My most honoured father)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110670">And trust my cunning then to lay it on. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e110680" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110690">'Tis this, good son; lord Barrisor (Whom you slew)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110700">Did love her dear, and with all fit means</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110710">Hath urged his acceptation, of all which</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110720">She keeps one letter written in his blood:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110730">You must say thus then, that you heard from me</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110740">How much herself was touched in conscience</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110750">With a report (Which is in truth dispersed)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110760">That your main quarrel grew about her love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110770">Lord Barrisor, imagining your courtship</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110780">Of the great Guise's Duchess in the presence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110790">Was by you made to his elected mistress:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110800">And so made me your mean now to resolve her,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110810">Choosing (By my direction) this night's depth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110820">For the more clear avoiding of all note,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110830">Of your presumed presence, and with this</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110840"><pb facs="15" n="26"/> (To clear her hands of such a lover's blood)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110850">She will so kindly thank and entertain you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110860">( methinks I see how) ay, and ten to one,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110870">Show you the confirmation in his blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110880">Lest you should think report and she did feign,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110890">That you shall so have circumstantial means,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110900">To come to the direct, which must be used:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110910">For the direct is crooked; love comes flying;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110920">The height of love is still won with denying. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e110930" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110940">Thanks honoured father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e110950" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Commolet.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110960">She must never know</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110970">That you know any thing of any love</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110980">Sustained on her part: for learn this of me;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e110990">In any thing a woman does alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111000">If she dissemble, she thinks 'tis not done;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111010">If not dissemble, nor a little chide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111020">Give her her wish, she is not satisfied;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111030">To have a man think that she never seeks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111040">Does her more good than to have all she likes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111050">This frailty sticks in them beyond their sex;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111060">Which to reform, reason is too perplex:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111070">Urge reason to them, it will do no good;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111080">Humour (That is the chariot of our food</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111090">In everybody ) must in them be fed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111100">To carry their affections by it bred. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111110">Stand close. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e111120">Enter Tamyra.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e111130" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111140">Alas, I fear my strangeness will retire him:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111150">If he go back, I die; I must prevent it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111160">And cheer his onset with my sight at least,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111170">And that's the most; though every step he takes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111180">Goes to my heart, I'll rather die than seem</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111190">Not to be strange to that I most esteem. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e111200" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111210">Madam. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e111220" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111230">Ah. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e111240" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111250">You will pardon me, I hope,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111260">That, so beyond your expectation,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111270"><pb facs="15" n="27"/> (And at a time for visitants so unfit)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111280">I (With my noble friend here) visit you:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111290">You know that my access at any time</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111300">Hath ever been admitted; and that friend</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111310">That my care will presume to bring with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111320">Shall have all circumstance of worth in him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111330">To merit as free welcome as myself. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e111340" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111350">O father, but at this suspicious hour</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111360">You know how apt best men are to suspect us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111370">In any cause, that makes suspicious shadow</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111380">No greater than the shadow of a hair:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111390">And you're to blame: what though my lord and husband</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111400">Lie forth tonight ? and since I cannot sleep</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111410">When he is absent, I sit up tonight ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111420">Though all the doors are sure, and all our servants</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111430">As sure bound with their sleeps; yet there is one</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111440">That sits above, whose eye no sleep can bind:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111450">He sees through doors, and darkness, and our thoughts;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111460">And therefore as we should avoid with fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111470">To think amiss ourselves before his search;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111480">So should we be as curious to shun</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111490">All cause that other think not ill of us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e111500" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111510">Madam, 'tis far from that: I only heard</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111520">By this my honoured father, that your conscience</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111530">Was something troubled with a false report;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111540">That Barrisor's blood should something touch your hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111550">Since he imagined I was courting you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111560">When I was bold to change words with the Duchess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111570">(And therefore made his quarrel; which my presence</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111580">Presumed on with my father at this season,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111590">For the more care of your so curious honour)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111600">Can well resolve your conscience, is most false. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e111610" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111620">And is it therefore that you come good sir? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111630">Then crave I now your pardon and my fathers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111640">And swear your presence does me so much comfort,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111650">That all I have, it binds to your requital:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111660">Indeed sir, 'tis most true that a report</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111670">Is spread, alleging that his love to me</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111680"><pb facs="16" n="28"/> was reason of your quarrel, and because</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111690">You shall not think I feign it for my glory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111700">That he importuned me for his court service,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111710">I'll show you his own hand, set down in blood</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111720">To that vain purpose: good sir, then come in. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111730">Father I thank you now a thousand fold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e111740" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111750">May it be worth it to you honoured daughter. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer xml:id="A18403-e111760">Finis actus secundi.</trailer>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A18403-e111770">
        <head>Actus tertij scaena prima.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e111780">Bucy, Tamyra.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e111790" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111800">O my dear servant, in thy close embraces,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111810">I have set open all the doors of danger</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111820">To my encompassed honour, and my life:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111830">Before I was secure against death and hell;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111840">But now am subject to the heartless fear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111850">Of every shadow, and of every breath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111860">And would change firmness with an aspen leaf:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111870">So confident a spotless conscience is;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111880">So weak a guilty: oh the dangerous siege</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111890">Sin lays about us? and the tyranny</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111900">He exercises when he hath expugned:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111910">Like to the horror of a winter's thunder,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111920">Mixed with a gushing storm, that suffer nothing</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111930">To stir abroad on earth, but their own rages;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111940">Is sin, when it hath gathered head above us:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111950">No roof, no shelter can secure us so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111960">But he will drown our cheeks in fear or woe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e111970" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111980">Sin is a coward madam, and insults</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e111990">But on our weakness, in his truest valour:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112000">And so our ignorance tames us, that we let</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112010">His shadows fright us: and like empty clouds</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112020">In which our faulty apprehensions forge</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112030">The forms of dragons, lions, elephants,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112040">When they hold no proportion: the sly charms</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112050">Of the witch policy makes him, like a monster</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112060"><pb facs="16" n="29"/> kept only to show men for goddess money:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112070">That false hag often paints him: in her cloth</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112080">Ten times more monstrous than he is in troth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112090">In three of us, the secret of our meeting,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112100">Is only guarded, and three friends as one</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112110">Have ever been esteemed: as our three powers</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112120">That in our one soul, are, as one united:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112130">Why should we fear then? for my truth I swear</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112140">Sooner shall torture, be the sire to pleasure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112150">And health be grievous to men long time sick,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112160">Than the dear jewel of your fame in me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112170">Be made an outcast to your infamy;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112180">Nor shall my value (Sacred to your virtues)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112190">Only give free course to it, from myself:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112200">But make it fly out of the mouths of Kings</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112210">In golden vapours, and with awful wings. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112220" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112230">It rests as all Kings seals were set in thee. <stage xml:id="A18403-e112240">Exit d' Amb. manet tamy.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112250" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Ta.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112260">It is not I, but urgent destiny,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112270">That (As great states men for their general end</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112280">In politic justice, make poor men offend)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112290">Enforceth my offence to make it just:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112300">What shall weak dames do, when th'whole work of nature</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112310">Hath a strong finger in each one of us? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112320">Needs must that sweep away the silly cobweb</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112330">Of our still-undone labours; that lays still</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112340">Our powers to it: as to the line, the stone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112350">Not to the stone, the line should be opposed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112360">We cannot keep our constant course in virtue:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112370">What is alike at all parts? every day</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112380">Differs from other: every hour and minute:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112390">Ay, every thought in our false clock of life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112400">Oft times inverts the whole circumference:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112410">We must be sometimes one, sometimes another:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112420">Our bodies are but thick clouds to our souls;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112430">Through which they cannot shine when they desire:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112440">When all the stars, and even the sun himself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112450">Must stay the vapours times that he exhales</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112460">Before he can make good his beams to us:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112470"><pb facs="17" n="30"/> oh how can we, that are but motes to him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112480">Wand'ring at randon in his ordered rays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112490">Disperse our passions fumes, with our weak labours,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112500">That are more thick and black than all earth's vapours? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e112510">Enter Mont.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112520" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112530">Good day, my love: what up and ready too! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112540" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112550">Both, (My dear lord) not all this night made I</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112560">Myself unready, or could sleep a wink. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112570" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112580">Alas, what troubled my true love? my peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112590">From being at peace within her better self? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112600">Or how could sleep forbear to seize thy beauties</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112610">When he might challenge them as his just prize? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112620" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112630">I am in no power earthly, but in yours;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112640">To what end should I go to bed my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112650">That wholly missed the comfort of my bed? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112660">Or how should sleep possess my faculties,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112670">Wanting the proper closer of mine eyes? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112680" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112690">Then will I never more sleep night from thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112700">All mine own business, all the Kings affairs</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112710">Shall take the day to serve them: every night</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112720">I'll ever dedicate to thy delight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112730" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112740">Nay, good my lord esteem not my desires</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112750">Such doters on their humours, that my judgement</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112760">Cannot subdue them to your worthier pleasure:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112770">A wife's pleased husband must her object be</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112780">In all her acts, not her soothed fantasy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112790" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112800">Then come my love, now pay those rites to sleep</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112810">Thy fair eyes owe him: shall we now to bed? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112820" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112830">O no my lord, your holy friar says,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112840">All couplings in the day that touch the bed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112850">Adulterous are, even in the married;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112860">Whose grave and worthy doctrine, well I know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112870">Your faith in him will liberally allow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112880" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112890">He's a most learned and religious man;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112900">Come to the presence then, and see great D'ambois</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112910">(Fortunes proud mushroom shot up in a night)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112920">Stand like an Atlas underneath the King;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112930"><pb facs="17" n="31"/> which greatness with him monsieur now envies</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112940">As bitterly and deadly as the Guise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112950" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112960">What, he that was but yesterday his maker? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112970">His raiser and preserver? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e112980" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e112990">Even the same. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113000">Each natural agent works but to this end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113010">To render that it works on, like itself;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113020">Which since the monsieur in his act on D'ambois,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113030">Cannot to his ambitious end effect,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113040">But that (Quite opposite) the King hath power</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113050">(In his love born to D'ambois) to convert</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113060">The point of monsieurs aim on his own breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113070">He turns his outward love to inward hate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113080">A prince's love is like the lightnings fume,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113090">Which no man can embrace, but must consume. <stage xml:id="A18403-e113100">Exeunt.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e113110">Henry, D'ambois, monsieur, Guise, Monts. Elenor, Tam. Pero.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113120" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113130">Speak home my Bussy, thy impartial words</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113140">Are like brave falcons that dare truss a fowl</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113150">Much greater than themselves; flatterers are kites</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113160">That check at nothing; thou shalt be my eagle,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113170">And bear my thunder underneath thy wings:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113180">Truths words like jewels hang in th'ears of Kings. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113190" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113200">Would I might live to see no Jews hang there</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113210">In steed of jewels; sycophants I mean,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113220">Who use truth like the devil, his true foe</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113230">Cast by the angel to the pit of fears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113240">And bound in chains; truth seldom decks King's ears:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113250">Slave flattery (Like a rippiers legs rolled up</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113260">In boots of haie-ropes) with Kings soothed guts</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113270">Swaddled and strappled, now lives only free. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113280">O 'tis a subtle knave; how like the plague</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113290">Unfelt, he strikes into the brain of truth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113300">And rageth in his entrails when he can,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113310">Worse than the poison of a red haired man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113320" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113330">Fly at him and his brood, I cast thee off,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113340">And once more give thee surname of mine eagle. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113350" who="A18403-bussy">
          <pb facs="18" n="32"/>
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113360">I'll make you sport enough then, let me have</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113370">My lucerns too (Or dogs enured to hunt</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113380">Beasts of most rapine) but to put them up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113390">And if I truss not, let me not be trusted:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113400">Show me a great man (By the people's voice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113410">Which is the voice of God) that by his greatness</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113420">Bombasts his private roofs, with public riches;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113430">That affects royalty, rising from a clapdish;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113440">That rules so much more than his suffering King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113450">That he makes Kings of his subordinate slaves:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113460">Himself and them graduate like woodmongers</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113470">(Piling a stack of billets) from the earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113480">Raising each other into steeples heights;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113490">Let him convey this on the turning props</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113500">Of Protean law, and (His own counsel keeping)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113510">Keep all upright; let me but hawk at him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113520">I'll play the vulture, and so thump his liver,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113530">That (Like a huge unlading argosy)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113540">He shall confess all, and you then may hang him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113550">Show me a clergy man, that is in voice</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113560">A lark of heaven; in heart a mole of earth;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113570">That hath good living, and a wicked life;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113580">A temperate look, and a luxurious gut;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113590">Turning the rends of his superfluous cures</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113600">Into your pheasants and your partridges;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113610">Venting their quintessence as men read hebrew:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113620">Let me but hawk at him, and, like the other,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113630">He shall confess all, and you then may hang him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113640">Show me a lawyer that turns sacred law</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113650">(The equal renderer of each man his own,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113660">The scourge of rapine and extortion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113670">The sanctuary and impregnable defence</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113680">Of retired learning, and oppressed virtue)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113690">Into a harpy, that eats all but's own,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113700">Into the damned sins it punisheth;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113710">Into the synagogue of thieves and atheists;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113720">Blood into gold, and justice into lust:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113730">Let me but hawk at him, as at the tother,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113740"><pb facs="18" n="33"/> he shall confess all, and you then may hang him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113750" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113760">Where will you find such game as you would hawk at? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113770" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113780">I'll hawk about your house for one of them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113790" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113800">Come, you're a glorious ruffian, and run proud</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113810">Of the Kings headlong graces; hold your breath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113820">Or by that poisoned vapour not the King</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113830">Shall back your murderous valour against me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113840" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113850">I would the King would make his presence free</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113860">But for one charge betwixt us: by the reverence</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113870">Due to the sacred space twixt Kings and subjects,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113880">Here would I make thee cast that popular purple,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113890">In which thy proud soul sits and braves thy sovereign. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113900" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113910">Peace, peace, I pray thee peace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113920" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113930">Let him peace first that made the first war. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113940" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113950">He's the better man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113960" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113970">And therefore may do worst? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e113980" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e113990">He has more titles. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114000" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114010">So Hydra had more heads. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114020" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114030">He's greater known. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114040" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114050">His greatness is the peoples, mine's mine own. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114060" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114070">He's nobly born. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114080" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114090">He is not, I am noble. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114100">And noblesse in his blood hath no gradation,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114110">But in his merit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114120" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114130">Thou'rt not nobly born,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114140">But bastard to the Cardinal of Ambois. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114150" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114160">Thou liest proud Guiserd; let me fly (My lord.) </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114170" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114180">Not in my face; (My eagle) violence flies</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114190">The sanctuaries of a prince's eyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114200" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114210">Still shall we chide? and some upon this bit? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114220">Is the Guise only great in faction? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114230">Stands he not by himself? Proves he th'opinion</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114240">That men's souls are without them? Be a Duke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114250">And lead me to the field. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114260" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Guis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114270">Come, follow me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114280" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114290">Stay them, stay D'ambois; cousin Guise, I wonder</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114300">Your equal disposition brooks so ill</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114310">A man so good, that only would uphold</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114320"><pb facs="19" n="34"/> man in his native noblesse, from whose fall</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114330">All our dissensions rise; that in himself</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114340">(Without the outward patches of our frailty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114350">Riches and honour) knows he comprehends</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114360">Worth with the greatest: King's had never born</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114370">Such boundless eminence over other men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114380">Had all maintained the spirit and state of D'ambois;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114390">Nor had the full impartial hand of nature</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114400">That all things gave in her original,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114410">Without these definite terms of mine and thine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114420">Been turned unjustly to the hand of fortune:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114430">Had all preserved her in her prime, like D'ambois;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114440">No envy, no disjunction had dissolved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114450">Or plucked out one stick of the golden faggot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114460">In which the world of Saturn was comprised,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114470">Had all been held together with the nerves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114480">The genius and th'ingenuous soul of D'ambois. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114490">Let my hand therefore be the Hermean rod</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114500">To part and reconcile, and so conserve you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114510">As my combined embracers and supporters. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114520" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114530">'Tis our King's motion, and we shall not seem</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114540">(To worst eyes) womanish, though we change thus soon</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114550">Never so great grudge for his greater pleasure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114560" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114570">I seal to that, and so the manly freedom</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114580">That you so much profess, hereafter prove not</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114590">A bold and glorious licence to deprave:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114600">To me his hand shall prove the Hermean rod</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114610">His grace affects, in which submissive sign</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114620">On this his sacred right hand, I lay mine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114630" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114640">'Tis well my lord, and so your worthy greatness</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114650">Engender not the greater insolence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114660">Nor make you think it a prerogative,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114670">To rack men's freedoms with the ruder wrongs;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114680">My hand (Stuck full of laurel, in true sign</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114690">'Tis wholly dedicate to righteous peace)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114700">In all submission kisseth th'other side. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114710" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Hen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114720">Thanks to ye both: and kindly I invite ye</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114730">Both to a banquet where we'll sacrifice</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114740"><pb facs="19" n="35"/> full cups to confirmation of yours loves;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114750">At which (Fair ladies) I entreat your presence. <stage xml:id="A18403-e114760">Exeunt Henry, D'amb. Ely. Ta.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114770" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114780">What had my bounty drunk when it raised him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114790" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114800">You've stuck us up a very proper flag</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114810">That takes more wind than we with all our sails. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114820" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114830">O so he spreads and flourishes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114840" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114850">He must down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114860">Upstarts should never perch too near a crown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e114870" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114880">'Tis true my lord; and as this doting hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114890">Even out of earth, (Like Juno) struck this giant,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114900">So Jove's great ordinance shall be here implied</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114910">To strike him under th'aetna of his pride:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114920">To which work lend your hands and let us cast</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114930">Where we may set snares for his gadding greatness. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114940">I think it best, amongst our greatest women:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114950">For there is no such trap to catch an upstart</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114960">As a loose downfall; and indeed their falls</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114970">Are th'ends of all men's rising: if great men</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114980">And wise; make scapes to please advantage</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e114990">'Tis with a woman: women that worst may</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115000">Still hold men's candles: they direct and know</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115010">All things amiss in all men; and their women</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115020">All things amiss in them: through whose charmed mouths</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115030">We may see all the close scapes of the court:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115040">When the most royal beast of chase (Being old,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115050">And cunning in his choice of layres and haunts)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115060">Can never be discovered to the bow</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115070">The piece or hound: yet where his custom is</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115080">To beat his vault, and he ruts with his hind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115090">The place is marked, and by his venery</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115100">He still is taken. Shall we then attempt</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115110">The chiefest mean to that discovery here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115120">And court our greatest lady's greatest women,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115130">With shows of love, and liberal promises? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115140">'Tis but our breath. If something given in hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115150">Sharpen their hopes of more; 'twilbe well ventured. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115160" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115170">No doubt of that: and 'tis an excellent point</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115180">Of our devised investigation. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115190" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <pb facs="20" n="36"/>
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115200">I have already broke the ice, my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115210">With the most trusted woman of your countess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115220">And hope I shall wade through to our discovery,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115230" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115240">Take say of her my lord, she comes most fitly</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115250">And we will to the other. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e115260">Enter Charlot, Anable, Pero.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115270" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115280">You're engaged. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115290" who="A18403-annabell">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115300">Nay pray my lord forbear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115310" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115320">What skittish, servant? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115330" who="A18403-annabell">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115340">No my lord I am not so fit for your service:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115350" who="A18403-charlotte">
          <speaker>Char.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115360">Pray pardon me now my lord? my lady expects me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115370" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115380">I'll satisfy her expectation, as far as an uncle may. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115390" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115400">Well said: a spirit of courtship of all hands:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115410">Now mine own Pero: hast thou remembered me</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115420">For the discovery I entreated thee to make concerning</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115430">Thy mistress? speak boldly, and be sure of all things I have promised. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115440" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Pero.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115450">Building on that you have sworn (My lord) I may speak: and much the rather, because my lady hath not trusted me with that I can tell you; for now I cannot be said to betray her.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115460" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115470">That's all one: so it be not to one that will betray thee: forth I beseech thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115480" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115490">To tell you truth, my lord, I have made a strange discovery.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115500" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115510">Excellent Pero thou revivest me: may I sink quick into earth here, if my tongue discover it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115520" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115530">'Tis thus then: this last night my lord lay forth: and I wondering my ladies sitting up, stole at midnight from my palate: and (Having before made a hole both through the wall and arras to her inmost chamber) I saw D'ambois and she set close at a banquet.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115540" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115550">D'ambois?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115560" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115570">Even he my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115580" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115590">Dost thou not dream wench?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115600" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115610">No my lord, he is the man.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115620" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115630">The devil he is, and thy lady his dam: infinite regions<pb facs="20" n="37"/> betwixt a woman's tongue and her heart: is this our goddess of chastity? I thought I could not be so slighted: if she had not her freight besides: and therefore plotted this with her woman: dear Pero I will advance thee for ever: but tell me now: god's precious it transforms me with admiration: sweet Pero, whom should she trust with his conveyance? Or, all the doors being made sure, how could his conveyance be performed?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115640" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115650">Nay my lord, that amazes me: I cannot by any study so much as guess at it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115660" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115670">Well, let's favour our apprehensions with forbearing that a little: for if my heart were not hooped with adamant, the conceit of this would have burst it: but hark thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115680" who="A18403-charlotte">
          <speaker>Char.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115690">I swear to your grace, all that I can conjecture touching my lady your niece, is a strong affection she bears to the English mylor.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115700" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115710">All quod you? 'tis enough I assure you, but tell me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115720" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115730">I pray thee resolve me: the Duke will never imagine that I am busy about's wife: hath D'ambois any privy access to her?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115740" who="A18403-annabell">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115750">No my lord, D'ambois neglects her (As she takes it) and is therefore suspicious that either your lady, or the countess Beaupre hath closely entertained him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115760" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115770">By'r lady a likely suspicion, and very near the life, if she marks it; especially of my wife.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115780" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115790">Come we'll put off all, with seeming only to have courted; away dry palm: sh'as a liver as hard as a biscuit: a man may go a whole voyage with her, and get nothing but tempests at her windpipe.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115800" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115810">Here's one: (I think) has swallowed a porcupine, she casts pricks from her tongue so.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115820" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115830">And here's a peacock seems to have devoured one of the Alps, she has so swelling a spirit, and is so cold of her kindness.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115840" who="A18403-charlotte">
          <speaker>Char.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115850">We be no windfalls my lord; ye must gather us with the ladder of matrimony, or we'll hang till we be rotten.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115860" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115870">Indeed that's the way to make ye right opens. But alas ye have no portions fit for such husbands as we wish you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115880" who="A18403-pero">
          <pb facs="21" n="38"/>
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115890">Portions my lord, yes and such portions as your principality cannot purchase.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115900" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115910">What woman? what are those portions?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115920" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115930">Riddle my riddle my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115940" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e115950">I marry wench, I think thy portion is a right riddle, a man shall never find it out: but let's hear it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e115960" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115970">You shall my lord. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115980">What's that, that being most rare's most cheap? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e115990">That if you sow, you never reap? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116000">That when it grows most, most you in it? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116010">And still you lose it when you win it:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116020">That when 'tis commonest, 'tis dearest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116030">And when 'tis farthest off 'tis nearest? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116040" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116050">Is this your portion?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116060" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116070">Even this my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116080" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116090">Believe me I cannot riddle it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116100" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116110">No my lord, 'tis my chastity, which you shall neither riddle nor fiddle.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116120" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116130">Your chastity? let me begin with the end of you; how is a woman's chastity nearest a man, when 'tis furthest off?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116140" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116150">Why my lord, when you cannot get it, it goes toth' heart on you; and that I think comes most near you: and I am sure it shall be far enough off; and so I leave you to my mercy. <stage xml:id="A18403-e116160">Exit.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116170" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116180">Farewell riddle.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116190" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116200">Farewell medlar.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116210" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116220">Farewell winter plum.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116230" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116240">Now my lords, what fruit of our inquisition? feel you nothing budding yet? Speak good my lord Montsurry.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116250" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116260">Nothing but this: D'ambois is negligent in observing the Duchess, and therefore she is suspicious that your niece or my wife closely entertains him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116270" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116280">Your wife, my lord? Think you that possible?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116290" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116300">Alas, I know she flies him like her last hour.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116310" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116320">Her last hour? why that comes upon her the more she flies it: does D'ambois so think you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116330" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e116340">That's not worth the answering: 'tis horrible to think with what monsters women's imaginations engross them<pb facs="21" n="39"/> when they are once enamoured, and what wonders they will work for their satisfaction. They will make a sheep valiant, a lion fearful.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116350" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116360">And an ass confident, my lord, 'tis true, and more</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116370">Will come forth shortly, get you to the banquet. <stage xml:id="A18403-e116380">Exit Guise cum Mont.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116390">O the unfounded sea of women's bloods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116400">That when 'tis calmest, is most dangerous;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116410">Not any wrinkle creaming in their faces,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116420">When in their hearts are Scylla and Charybdis,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116430">Which still are hid in monster-formed clouds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116440">Where never day shines, nothing ever grows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116450">But weeds and poisons, that no statesman knows;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116460">Not Cerberus ever saw the damned nooks</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116470">Hid with the veils of women's virtuous looks:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116480">I will conceal all yet, and give more time</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116490">To D'ambois trial, now upon my hook;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116500">He awes my throat; else like Sibylla's cave</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116510">It should breathe oracles; I fear him strangely,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116520">And may resemble his advanced valour</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116530">Unto a spirit raised without a circle,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116540">Endangering him that ignorantly raised him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116550">And for whose fury he hath learned no limit. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e116560">Enter D'ambois.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116570" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116580">How now, what leapest thou at? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116590" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116600">O royal object. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116610" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116620">Thou dreamest awake: object in th'empty air? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116630" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116640">Worthy the head of Titan, worth his chair. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116650" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116660">Pray thee what meanest thou? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116670" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116680">See you not a crown</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116690">Impale the forehead of the great King Monsieur? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116700" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116710">O fie upon thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116720" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116730">Sir, that is the subject</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116740">Of all these your retired and sole discourses. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116750" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116760">Wilt thou not leave that wrongful supposition? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116770">This still hath made me doubt thou dost not love me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116780">Wilt thou do one thing for me then sincerely? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116790" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116800">Ay, any thing, but killing of the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116810" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <pb facs="22" n="40"/>
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116820">Still in that discord, and ill taken note? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116830" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116840">Come, do not doubt me, and command me all things. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116850" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116860">I will not then, and now by all my love</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116870">Shown to thy virtues, and by all fruits else</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116880">Already sprung from that affection,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116890">I charge thee utter (Even with all the freedom</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116900">Both of thy noble nature and thy friendship)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116910">The full and plain state of me in thy thoughts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116920" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116930">What, utter plainly what I think of you? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116940">Why this swims quite against the stream of greatness:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116950">Great men would rather hear their flatteries,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116960">And if they be not made fools, are not wise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e116970" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116980">I am no such great fool, and therefore charge thee</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e116990">Even from the root of thy free heart, display me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e117000" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117010">Since you affect it in such serious terms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117020">If yourself first will tell me what you think</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117030">As freely and as heartily of me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117040">I'll be as open in my thoughts of you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e117050" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117060">A bargain of mine honour; and make this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117070">That prove we in our full dissection</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117080">Never so foul, live still the sounder friends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e117090" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117100">What else sir? come begin, and speak me simply. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e117110" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117120">I will I swear. I think thee then a man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117130">That dares as much as a wild horse or tiger;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117140">As headstrong and as bloody; and to feed</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117150">The ravenous wolf of thy most cannibal valour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117160">(Rather than not employ it) thou wouldst turn</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117170">Hackster to any whore, slave to a Jew,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117180">Or English usurer, to force possessions,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117190">And cut men's throats of mortgaged estates;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117200">Or thou wouldst tire thee like a tinker's wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117210">And murder market folks, quarrel with sheep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117220">And run as mad as Aiax; serve a butcher,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117230">Do any thing but killing of the King:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117240">That in thy valour thou'rt like other naturals,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117250">That have strange gifts in nature, but no soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117260">Diffused quite through, to make them of a piece,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117270"><pb facs="22" n="41"/> but stop at humours, that are more absurd,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117280">Childish and villainous than that hackster, whore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117290">Slave, cutthroat, tinker's bitch, compared before:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117300">And in those humours wouldst envy, betray,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117310">Slander, blaspheme, change each hour a religion;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117320">Do any thing, but killing of the King;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117330">That in that valour (Which is still my dunghill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117340">To which I carry all filth in thy house)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117350">Thou'rt more ridiculous and vainglorious</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117360">Than any mountebank; and impudent</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117370">Than any painted bawd; which, not to soothe</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117380">And glorify thee like a Jupiter Hammon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117390">Thou eatest thy heart in vinegar; and thy gall</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117400">Turns all thy blood to poison, which is cause</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117410">Of that toadpole that stands in thy complexion;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117420">And makes thee (With a cold and earthy moisture,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117430">Which is the dam of putrefaction,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117440">As plague to thy damned pride) rot as thou liv'st;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117450">To study calumnies and treacheries;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117460">To thy friends slaughters, like a screech-owl sing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117470">And to all mischiefs, but to kill the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e117480" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117490">So: have you said? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e117500" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117510">How thinkest thou? Do I flatter? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117520">Speak I not like a trusty friend to thee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e117530" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117540">That ever any man was blessed withal;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117550">So here's for me. I think you are (At worst)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117560">No devil, since you're like to be no King;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117570">Of which, with any friend of yours I'll lay</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117580">This poor stillado here, 'gainst all the stars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117590">Ay, and 'gainst all your treacheries, which are more;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117600">That you did never good, but to do ill;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117610">But ill of all sorts, free and for itself:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117620">That (Like a murdering piece, making lanes in armies</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117630">The first man of a rank, the whole rank falling)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117640">If you have once wronged one man, you're so far</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117650">From making him amends, that all his race,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117660">Friends and associates fall into your chase:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117670">That you're for perjuries the very prince</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117680"><pb facs="23" n="42"/> of all intelligencers; and your voice</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117690">Is like an Eastern wind, that where it flies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117700">Knits nets of caterpillars, with which you catch</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117710">The prime of all the fruits the kingdom yields. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117720">That your political head is the cursed fount</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117730">Of all the violence, rapine, cruelty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117740">Tyranny and atheism flowing through the realm. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117750">That you've a tongue so scandalous, 'twill cut</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117760">A perfect crystal; and a breath that will</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117770">Kill to that wall a spider; you will jest</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117780">With God, and your soul to the devil tender</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117790">For lust; kiss horror, and with death engender. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117800">That your foul body is a Lernaean fen</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117810">Of all the maladies breeding in all men. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117820">That you are sourly without a soul:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117830">And (For your life) the thread of that was spun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117840">When Clotho slept, and let her breathing rock</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117850">Fall in the dirt; and Lachesis still draws it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117860">Dipping her twisting fingers in a bowl</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117870">Defiled, and crowned with virtues forced soul. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117880">And lastly (Which I must for gratitude</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117890">Ever remember) that of all my height</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117900">And dearest life, you are the only spring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117910">Only in royal hope to kill the King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e117920" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117930">Why now I see thou lovest me, come to the banquet. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer xml:id="A18403-e117940">Finis actus terty.</trailer>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A18403-e117950">
        <head>Actus quarti scaena prima.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e117960">Henry, monsieur, Guise, Montsurry, Bussy, Elynor, Tamyra, Beaupre, Pero, Charlotte, Anable, Pyrha, with four pages.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e117970" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117980">Ladies, ye have not done our banquet right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e117990">Nor looked upon it with those cheerful rays</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118000">That lately turned your breathes to floods of gold;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118010">Your looks, methinks , are not drawn out with thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118020">So clear and free as heretofore, but fare</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118030"><pb facs="23" n="43"/> as if the thick complexions of men</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118040">Governed within them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118050" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118060">'Tis not like my lord</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118070">That men in women rule; but contrary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118080">For as the moon (Of all things God created)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118090">Not only is the most appropriate image</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118100">Or glass to show them how they wax and wane,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118110">But in her light and motion, likewise bears</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118120">Imperial influences that command</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118130">In all their powers, and make them wax and wane;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118140">So women, that (Of all things made of nothing)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118150">Are the most perfect images of the moon</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118160">(Or still-unweaned sweet moon-calves with white faces)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118170">Not only are patterns of change to men:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118180">But as the tender moonshine of their beauties</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118190">Clears, or is cloudy, make men glad or sad. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118200" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118210">But here the moons are changed (As the King notes)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118220">And either men rule in them, or some power</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118230">Beyond their voluntary motions:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118240">For nothing can recover their lost faces. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118250" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118260">None can be always one: our griefs and joys</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118270">Hold several sceptres in us, and have times</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118280">For their predominance: which grief now, in them</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118290">Doth claim, as proper to his diadem:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118300">And grief's a natural sickness of the blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118310">That time to part, asks as his coming had;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118320">Only sleight fools grieved, suddenly are glad;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118330">A man may say t'a dead man, be revived,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118340">As well as to one sorrowful, be not grieved. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118350">And therefore (Princely mistress) in all wars</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118360">Against these base foes that insult on weakness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118370">And still fight housed, behind the shield of nature,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118380">Of tyrannous law, treachery, or beastly need,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118390">Your servant cannot help; authority here</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118400">Goes with corruption; something like some states,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118410">That back worst men: valour to them must creep</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118420">That (To themselves left) would fear him asleep. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118430" who="A18403-ely">
          <speaker>Ely.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118440">Ye all take that for granted, that doth rest</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118450"><pb facs="24" n="44"/> yet to be proved; we all are as we were</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118460">As merry, and as free in thought as ever. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118470" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118480">And why then can ye not disclose your thoughts? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118490" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118500">Methinks the man hath answered for us well. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118510" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118520">The man? why madam d'ye not know his name? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118530" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118540">Man is a name of honour for a King:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118550">Additions take away from each chief thing:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118560">The school of modesty, not to learn, learns dames:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118570">They sit in high forms there, that know men's names. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118580" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118590">Hark sweet heart, here's a bound set to your valour:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118600">It cannot enter here; no, not to notice</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118610">Of what your name is; your great eagles beak</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118620">(Should you fly at her) had as good encounter</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118630">An Albion cliff, as her more craggy liver. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118640" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118650">I'll not attempt her sir; her sight and name</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118660">(By which I only know her) doth deter me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118670" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118680">So do they all men else. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118690" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118700">You would say so</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118710">If you knew all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118720" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118730">Knew all my lord? what mean you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118740" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118750">All that I know madam. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118760" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118770">That you know? speak it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118780" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118790">No 'tis enough I feel it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118800" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118810">But methinks </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118820">Her courtship is more pure than heretofore:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118830">True courtiers should be modest, but not nice:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118840">Bold, but not impudent: pleasure love, not vice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118850" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118860">Sweet heart: come hither, what if one should make</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118870">Horns at Montsurry? would it strike him jealous</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118880">Through all the proofs of his chaste lady's virtues? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118890" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118900">No I think not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118910" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118920">Not if I named the man</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118930">With whom I would make him suspicious</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118940">His wife hath armed his forehead? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118950" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118960">So, you might</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118970">Have your great nose made less indeed: and slit:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e118980">Your eyes thrust out. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e118990" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119000">Peace, peace, I pray thee peace. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119010"><pb facs="24" n="45"/>Who dares do that? the brother of his King? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119020" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119030">Were your King brother in you: all your powers</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119040">(Stretched in the arms of great men and their bawds)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119050">Set close down by you; all your stormy laws</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119060">Spouted with lawyer's mouths; and gushing blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119070">Like to so many torrents: all your glories:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119080">(Making you terrible, like enchanted flames</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119090">Fed with bare coxcombs: and with crooked hams)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119100">All your prerogatives, your shames and tortures:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119110">All daring heaven, and opening hell about you:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119120">Were I the man, ye wronged so and provoked:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119130">(Though never so much beneath you) like a box tree</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119140">I would (Out of the toughness of my root)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119150">Ram hardness, in my lowness, and like death</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119160">Mounted on earthquakes, I would trot through all</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119170">Honours and horrors: through foul and fair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119180">And from your whole strength toss you into air. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119190" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119200">Go, thou'rt a devil; such another spirit</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119210">Could not be styled, from all th'armenian dragons. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119220">O my love's glory: heir to all I have:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119230">That's all I can say, and that all I swear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119240">If thou outlive me, as I know thou must,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119250">Or else hath nature no proportioned end</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119260">To her great labours: she hath breathed a spirit</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119270">Into thy entrails, of effect to swell</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119280">Into another great Augustus Caesar:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119290">Organs, and faculties fitted to her greatness:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119300">And should that perish like a common spirit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119310">Nature's a courtier and regards no merit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119320" who="A18403-henry">
          <speaker>Henr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119330">Here's naught but whispering with us: like a calm</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119340">Before a tempest, when the silent air</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119350">Lays her soft ear close to the earth to hearken</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119360">For that she fears is coming to afflict her;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119370">Some fate doth join our ears to hear it coming. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119380">Come, my brave eagle, let's to covert fly:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119390">I see almighty aether in the smoke</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119400">Of all his clouds descending: and the sky</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119410">Hid in the dim ostents of tragedy. <stage xml:id="A18403-e119420">Exit Hen. with D'amb.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119430" who="A18403-guise">
          <pb facs="25" n="46"/>
          <speaker>Guis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119440">Now stir the humour, and begin the brawl. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119450" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119460">The King and D'ambois now are grown all one. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119470" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119480">Nay, they are two my lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119490" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119500">How's that? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119510" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119520">No more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119530" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119540">I must have more my lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119550" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119560">What more than two? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119570" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119580">How monstrous is this? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119590" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119600">Why? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119610" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119620">You make me horns. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119630" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119640">Not I, it is a work, without my power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119650">Married men's ensigns are not made with fingers:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119660">Of divine fabric they are, not men's hands;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119670">Your wife, you know, is a mere Cynthia,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119680">And she must fashion horns out of her nature. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119690" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119700">But doth she? dare you charge her? speak false prince. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119710" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119720">I must not speak my lord: but if you'll use</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119730">The learning of a noble man, and read</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119740">Here's something to those points: soft you must pawn</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119750">Your honour having read it to return it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119760" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119770">Not I, I pawn mine honour, for a paper? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119780" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119790">You must not buy it under. <stage xml:id="A18403-e119800">Ent. Tamy. Pero.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119810" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119820">Keep it then! </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119830">And keep fire in your bosom. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119840" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119850">What says he? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119860" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119870">You must make good the rest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119880" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119890">How fares my lord? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119900">Takes my love any thing to heart he says? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119910" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119920">Come you're a. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119930" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119940">What my lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119950" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119960">The plague of Herod</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119970">Feast in his rotten entrails. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e119980" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e119990">Will you wreak</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120000">Your angers just cause given by him, on me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120010" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120020">By him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120030" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120040">By him my lord, I have admired</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120050">You could all this time be at concord with him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120060">That still hath played such discords on your honour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120070" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <pb facs="25" n="47"/>
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120080">Perhaps 'tis with some proud string of my wives. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120090" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120100">How's that, my lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120110" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120120">Your tongue will still admire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120130">Till my head be the miracle of the world. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120140" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120150">O woe is me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120160" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Pero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120170">What does your lordship mean? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120180">Madam, be comforted; my lord but tries you. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120190">Madam? Help good my lord ▪ are you not moved? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120200">Do your set looks print in your words, your thoughts? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120210">Sweet lord, clear up those eyes, for shame of noblesse:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120220">Merciless creature; but it is enough,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120230">You have shot home, your words are in her heart;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120240">She has not lived to bear a trial now. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120250" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120260">Look up my love, and by this kiss receive</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120270">My soul amongst thy spirits for supply</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120280">To thine, chased with my fury. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120290" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120300">O my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120310">I have too long lived to hear this from you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120320" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120330">'Twas from my troubled blood, and not from me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120340">I know not how I fare; a sudden night</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120350">Flows through my entrails, and a headlong chaos</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120360">Murmurs within me, which I must digest;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120370">And not drown her in my confusions,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120380">That was my life's joy, being best informed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120390">Sweet, you must needs forgive me, that my love</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120400">(Like to a fire disdaining his suppression)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120410">Raged being discouraged; my whole heart is wounded</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120420">When any least thought in you is but touched,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120430">And shall be till I know your former merits:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120440">Your name and memory altogether crave</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120450">In loathed oblivion their eternal grave;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120460">And than you must hear from me, there's no mean</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120470">In any passion I shall feel for you:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120480">Love is a razor cleansing being well used,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120490">But fetcheth blood still being the least abused:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120500">To tell you briefly all; the man that left me</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120510">When you appeared, did turn me worse than woman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120520">And stabbed me to the heart thus, with his hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120530" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <pb facs="26" n="48"/>
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120540">O happy woman! Comes my stain from him? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120550">It is my beauty, and that innocence proves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120560">That slew chimaera, rescued Peleus</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120570">From all the savage beasts in Peleon;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120580">And raised the chaste Athenian prince from hell:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120590">All suffering with me; they for women's lusts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120600">I for a man's; that the Egean stable</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120610">Of his foul sin would empty in my lap:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120620">How his guilt shunned me? sacred innocence</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120630">That where thou fearest, art dreadful; and his face</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120640">Turned in flight from thee, that had thee in chase:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120650">Come, bring me to him: I will tell the serpent</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120660">Even to his teeth (Whence, in mine honour's soil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120670">'A pitched field starts up twixt my lord and me)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120680">That his throat lies, and he shall curse his fingers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120690">For being so governed by his filthy soul. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120700" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120710">I know not, if himself will vaunt t'have been</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120720">The princely author of the slavish sin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120730">Or any other; he would have resolved me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120740">Had you not come; not by his word, but writing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120750">Would I have sworn to give it him again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120760">And pawned mine honour to him for a paper. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120770" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120780">See how he flies me still: 'tis a foul heart</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120790">That fears his own hand: good my lord make haste</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120800">To see the dangerous paper: be not nice</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120810">For any trifle, jeweled with your honour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120820">To pawn your honour; and with it confer</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120830">My nearest woman here, in all she knows;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120840">Who (If the sun or Cerberus could have seen</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120850">Any stain in me) might as much as they:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120860">And Pero, here I charge thee by my love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120870">And all proofs of it, (Which I might call bounties)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120880">By all that thou hast seem seem good in me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120890">And all the ill which thou shouldst spit from thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120900">By pity of the wound, my lord hath given me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120910">Not as thy mistress now, but a poor woman</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120920">(To death given over:) rid me of my pains,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120930">Pour on thy powder: clear thy breast of me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120940"><pb facs="26" n="49"/> my lord is only here: here speak thy worst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120950">Thy best will do me mischief; if thou sparest me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120960">Never shine good thought on thy memory:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120970">Resolve my lord, and leave me desperate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e120980" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Pero.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e120990">My lord? My lord hath played a prodigals part,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121000">To break his stock for nothing; and an insolent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121010">To cut a Gordian when he could not lose it:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121020">What violence is this, to put true fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121030">To a false train? To blow up long crowned peace</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121040">With sudden outrage? and believe a man</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121050">Sworn to the shame of women, 'gainst a woman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121060">Born to their honours: I'll attend your lordship. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121070" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121080">No, I will write (For I shall never more</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121090">Speak with the fugitive) where I will defy him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121100">Were he ten times the brother of my King. <stage xml:id="A18403-e121110">Exeunt.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e121120">Music: and she enters with her maid, bearing a letter.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121130" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121140">Away, deliver it: oh may my lines</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121150">(Filled with the poison of a woman's hate</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121160">When he shall open them) shrink up his eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121170">With torturous darkness, such as stands in hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121180">Stuck full of inward horrors, never lighted;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121190">With which are all things to be feared, affrighted;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121200">Father? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e121210">Ascendit Bussy with Comolet. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121220" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121230">How is it with my honoured mistress? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121240" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121250">O servant help, and save me from the gripes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121260">Of shame and infamy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121270" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121280">What insensate stock,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121290">Or rude inanimate vapour without fashion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121300">Durst take into his Epimethean breast</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121310">A box of such plagues as the danger yields,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121320">Incurred in this discovery? He had better</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121330">Ventured his breast in the consuming reach</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121340">Of the hot surfeits cast out of the clouds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121350">Or stood the bullets that (To wreak the sky)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121360"><pb facs="27" n="50"/> the Cyclops ram in Jove's artillery. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121370" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121380">We soon will take the darkness from his face</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121390">That did that deed of darkness; we will know</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121400">What now the monsieur and your husband do;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121410">What is contained within the secret paper</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121420">Offered by Monsieur, and your love's events:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121430">To which ends (Honoured daughter) at your motion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121440">I have put on these exorcising rites,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121450">And, by my power of learned holiness</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121460">Vouchsafed me from above, I will command</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121470">Our resolution of a raised spirit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121480" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121490">Good father raise him in some beauteous form,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121500">That with least terror I may brook his sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121510" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121520">Stand sure together then, whate'er ye see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121530">And stir not, as ye tender all our lives. </l>
          <p xml:id="A18403-e121540">Occidentalium legionum spiritalium imperator (Magnus ille Behemoth) veni, veni, comitatus cum asaroth locotenente invicto. Adiuro te per stygis inscrutabilia arcana, per ipsos irremeabiles anfractus averni: adesto o Behemoth, tu cvi pervia sunt magnatum scrinia; veni, per noctis et tenebrarum abdita profundissima;<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A18403-e121550">thunder. </note>per labentia sydera; per ipsos motus horarum furtivos, hecatesque altum silentium: appare in forma spiritali, lucente splendida et amabili. <stage xml:id="A18403-e121560">Ascendit.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121570" who="A18403-behemoth">
          <speaker>Behemoth</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121580">What would the holy friar? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121590" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121600">I would see</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121610">What now the monsieur and Montsurry do;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121620">And see the secret paper that the monsieur</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121630">Offered to count Montsurry, longing much</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121640">To know on what events the secret loves</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121650">Of these two honoured persons shall arrive. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121660" who="A18403-behemoth">
          <speaker>Behemoth</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121670">Why called'st thou me to this accursed light? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121680">To these light purposes? I am emperor</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121690">Of that inscrutable darkness, where are hid</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121700">All deepest truths, and secrets never seen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121710">All which I know, and command legions</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121720">Of knowing spirits that can do more than these. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121730">Any of this my guard that circle me</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121740">In these blue fires, and out of whose dim fumes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121750"><pb facs="27" n="51"/> vast murmurs use to break, and from their sounds</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121760">Articulate voices; can do ten parts more</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121770">Than open such sleight truths, as you require. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121780" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121790">From the last nights black depth, I called up one</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121800">Of the inferior ablest ministers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121810">And he could not resolve me; send one then</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121820">Out of thine own command, to fetch the paper</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121830">That Monsieur hath to show to count Montsurry. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121840" who="A18403-behemoth">
          <speaker>Behemoth</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121850">I will: Cartophylax: thou that properly</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121860">Hast in thy power all papers so inscribed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121870">Glide through all bars to it and fetch that paper. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121880" who="A18403-cartophylax">
          <speaker>Car.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121890">I will. <stage xml:id="A18403-e121900">A torch removes.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121910" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121920">Till he returns (Great prince of darkness)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121930">Tell me, if Monsieur and the count Montsurry</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121940">Are yet encountered. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121950" who="A18403-behemoth">
          <speaker>Behemoth</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121960">Both them and the Guise</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121970">Are now together. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e121980" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e121990">Show us all their persons,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122000">And represent the place, with all their actions. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122010" who="A18403-behemoth">
          <speaker>Behemoth</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122020">The spirit will straight return: and then I'll show thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122030">See he is come; why broughtest thou not the paper? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122040" who="A18403-cartophylax">
          <speaker>Cart.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122050">He hath prevented me, and got a spirit</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122060">Raised by another, great in our command</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122070">To take the guard of it before I came. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122080" who="A18403-behemoth">
          <speaker>Behemoth</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122090">This is your slackness, not t'invoke our powers</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122100">When first your acts, set forth to their effects;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122110">Yet shall you see it, and themselves: behold</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122120">They come here and the Earl now holds the paper. <stage xml:id="A18403-e122130">Ent. mons. Gui. Mont.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122140" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Bus.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122150">May we not hear them? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122160" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122170">No, be still and see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122180" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Bus.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122190">I will go fetch the paper. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122200" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122210">Do not stir:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122220">There's too much distance and too many locks</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122230">Twixt you and them: (How near so ere they seem)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122240">For any man to interrupt their secrets. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122250" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122260">O honoured spirit: fly into the fancy</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122270">Of my offended lord: and do not let him</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122280">Believe what there the wicked man hath written. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122290" who="A18403-unassigned">
          <pb facs="28" n="52"/>
          <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122300">Persuasion hath already entered him</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122310">Beyond reflection; peace till their departure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122320" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122330">There is a glass of ink wherein you see</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122340">How to make ready black faced tragedy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122350">You now discern, I hope through all her paintings</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122360">Her gasping wrinkles, and fames sepulchres. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122370" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122380">Think you he feigns my lord? what hold you now? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122390">Do we malign your wife: or honour you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122400" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122410">What stricken dumb? nay fie, lord be not daunted:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122420">Your case is common: were it never so rare</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122430">Bear it as rarely: now to laugh were manly:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122440">A worthy man should imitate the weather</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122450">That sings in tempests: and being clear is silent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122460" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122470">Go home my lord, and force your wife to write</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122480">Such loving stuff to D'ambois as she used</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122490">When she desired his presence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122500" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122510">Do my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122520">And make her name her conceald messenger:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122530">That close and most inennerable pander</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122540">That passeth all our studies to exquire:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122550">By whom convey the letter to her love:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122560">And so you shall be sure to have him come</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122570">Within the thirsty reach of your revenge;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122580">Before which, lodge an ambush in her chamber</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122590">Behind the arras of your stoutest men</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122600">All close and soundly armed: and let them share</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122610">A spirit amongst them, that would serve a thousand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122620" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122630">Yet stay a little: see she sends for you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122640" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122650">Poor, loving lady, she'll make all good yet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122660">Think you not so my lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122670" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122680">Alas poor soul. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122690" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122700">This was ill done i'faith. <stage xml:id="A18403-e122710">Exit Mont.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122720" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122730">Was nobly done. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122740">And I forgive his lordship from my soul. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122750" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122760">Then much good do't thee Pero: hast a letter? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122770" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122780">I hope it be, at least, if not a volume</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122790">Of worthy curses for your perjury. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122800" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122810">Now out upon her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122820" who="A18403-guise">
          <pb facs="28" n="53"/>
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122830">Let me see my lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122840" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122850">You shall presently: how fares my Pero? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122860">Who's there? take in this maid sh'as caught a clap:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122870">And fetch my surgeon to her; come my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122880">We'll now peruse our letter. <stage xml:id="A18403-e122890">Exeunt mons. Guise.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122900" who="A18403-pero">
          <speaker>Per.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122910">Furies rise<stage xml:id="A18403-e122920">Lead her out.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122930">Out of the black lines, and torment his soul. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122940" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122950">Hath my lord slain my woman? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122960" who="A18403-behemoth">
          <speaker>Behemoth</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122970">No, she lives. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e122980" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e122990">What shall become of us? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e123000" who="A18403-behemoth">
          <speaker>Behemoth</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123010">All I can say</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123020">Being called thus late, is brief, and darkly this:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123030">If D'ambois mistress, stay not her white hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123040">With his forced blood he shall remain untouched:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123050">So father, shall yourself, but by yourself:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123060">To make this augury plainer: when the voice</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123070">Of D'ambois shall invoke me I will rise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123080">Shining in greater light: and show him all</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123090">That will betide ye all; mean time be wise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123100">And let him curb his rage, with policy. <stage xml:id="A18403-e123110">Descendit cum suis:</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e123120" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123130">Will he appear to me, when I invoke him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e123140" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123150">He will: be sure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e123160" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123170">It must be shortly then:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123180">For his dark words have tied my thoughts on knots</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123190">Till he dissolve, and free them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e123200" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123210">In mean time</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123220">Dear servant, till your powerful voice revoke him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123230">Be sure to use the policy he advised:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123240">Lest fury in your too quick knowledge taken</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123250">Of our abuse, and your defence of me</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123260">Accuse me more than any enemy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123270">And father, you must on my lord impose</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123280">Your holiest charges, and the church's power</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123290">To temper his hot spirit: and disperse</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123300">The cruelty and the blood, I know his hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123310">Will shower upon our heads, if you put not</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123320">Your finger to the storm, and hold it up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123330">As my dear servant here must do with Monsieur. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e123340" who="A18403-bussy">
          <pb facs="29" n="54"/>
          <speaker>Bus.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123350">I'll soothe his plots: and strew my hate with smiles</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123360">Till all at once the close mines of my heart</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123370">Rise at full date, and rush into his blood:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123380">I'll bind his arm in silk, and rub his flesh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123390">To make the vain swell, that his soul may gush</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123400">Into some kennel, where it longs to lie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123410">And policy shall be flanked with policy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123420">Yet shall the feeling centre where we meet</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123430">Groan with the wait of my approaching feet:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123440">I'll make th'inspired thresholds of his court</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123450">Sweat with the weather of my horrid steps</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123460">Before I enter: yet will I appear</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123470">Like calm security, before a ruin;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123480">A politician, must like lightning melt</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123490">The very marrow, and not print the skin:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123500">His ways must not be seen: the superficies</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123510">Of the green centre must not taste his feet:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123520">When hell is ploughed up with his wounding tracts:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123530">And all his harvest reaped, from hellish facts. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer xml:id="A18403-e123540">Finis actus quarti.</trailer>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A18403-e123550">
        <head>Actus quinti scaena prima.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e123560">Montsurry bore, unbraced, pulling Tamyra in, Comolet, one bearing light, a standish and paper, which sets a table.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e123570" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123580">My lord remember that your soul must seek</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123590">Her peace, as well as your revengeful blood:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123600">You ever, to this hour have proved yourself</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123610">A noble, zealous, and obedient son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123620">T'our holy mother: be not an apostate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123630">Your wife's offence serves not, (Were it the worst</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123640">You can imagine, without greater proofs)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123650">To sever your eternal bonds, and hearts;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123660">Much less to touch her with a bloody hand:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123670">Nor is it manly (Much less husbandly)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123680">To expiate any frailty in your wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123690">With churlish strokes, or beastly odds of strength:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123700">The stony birth of clouds, will touch no laurel:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123710"><pb facs="29" n="55"/> nor any sleeper; your wife is your laurel:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123720">And sweetest sleeper; do not touch her then</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123730">Be not more rude than the wild seed of vapour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123740">To her that is more gentle than it rude;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123750">In whom kind nature suffered one offence</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123760">But to set of, her other excellence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e123770" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123780">Good father leave us: interrupt no more</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123790">The course I must run for mine honour's sake. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123800">Rely on my love to her, which her fault</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123810">Cannot extinguish; will she but disclose</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123820">Who was the hateful minister of her love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123830">And through what maze he served it, we are friends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e123840" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123850">It is a damned work to pursue those secrets,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123860">That would open more sin, and prove springs of slaughter;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123870">Nor is't a path for Christian feet to touch;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123880">But out of all way to the health of souls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123890">A sin impossible to be forgiven:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123900">Which he that dares commit;</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e123910" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123920">Good father cease:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123930">Tempt not a man distracted; I am apt</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123940">To outrages that I shall ever rue:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123950">I will not pass the verge that bounds a christian,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123960">Nor break the limits of a man nor husband. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e123970" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123980">Then God inspire ye both with thoughts and deeds</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e123990">Worthy his high respect, and your own souls. <stage xml:id="A18403-e124000">Exit Com.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e124010" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124020">Who shall remove the mountain from my heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124030">Open the seventimes-heat furnace of my thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124040">And set fit outcries for a soul in hell? <stage xml:id="A18403-e124050">Mont. turns a key.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124060">O now it nothing fits my cares to speak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124070">But thunder, or to take into my throat</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124080">The trump of heaven; with whose determinate blasts</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124090">The winds shall burst, and the enraged seas</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124100">Be drunk up in his sounds; that my hot woes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124110">(Vented enough) I might convert to vapour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124120">Ascending from my infamy unseen;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124130">Shorten the world, preventing the last breath</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124140">That kills the living, and regenerates death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e124150" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124160">My lord, my fault (As you may censure it</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124170"><pb facs="30" n="56"/> with too strong arguments) is passed your pardon:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124180">But how the circumstances may excuse me</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124190">God knows, and your more temperate mind hereafter</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124200">May let my penitent miseries make you know. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e124210" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124220">Hereafter? 'tis a supposed infinite,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124230">That from this point will rise eternally:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124240">Fame grows in going; in the scapes of virtue</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124250">Excuses damn her: they be fires in cities</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124260">Enraged with those winds that less lights extinguish. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124270">Come Siren, sing, and dash against my rocks</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124280">Thy ruffian galley, laden for thy lust:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124290">Sing, and put all the nets into thy voice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124300">With which thou drewest into thy strumpet's lap</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124310">The spawn of Venus; and in which ye danced;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124320">That, in thy laps steed, I may dig his tomb,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124330">And quit his manhood with a woman's sleight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124340">Who never is deceived in her deceit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124350">Sing, (That is, write) and then take from mine eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124360">The mists that hide the most inscrutable pandar</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124370">That ever leapt up an adulterous vomit:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124380">That I may see the devil, and survive</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124390">To be a devil, and then learn to wive:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124400">That I may hang him, and then cut him down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124410">Then cut him up, and with my soul's beams search</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124420">The cranks and caverns of his brain, and study</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124430">The errant wilderness of a woman's face;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124440">Where men cannot get out, for all the comets</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124450">That have been lighted at it; though they know</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124460">That adders lie a sunning in their smiles,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124470">That basilisks drink their poison from their eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124480">And no way there to coast out to their hearts;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124490">Yet still they wander there, and are not stayed</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124500">Till they be fettered, nor secure before</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124510">All cares distract them; nor in humane state</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124520">Till they embrace within their wives two breasts</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124530">All Pelion and Cithaeron with their beasts. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124540">Why write you not? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e124550" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124560">O good my lord forbear</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124570"><pb facs="30" n="57"/> in wreak of great sins, to engender greater,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124580">And make my love's corruption generate murder. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e124590" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124600">It follows needfully as child and parent;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124610">The chain-shot of thy lust is yet aloft,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124620">And it must murder; 'tis thine own dear twin:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124630">No man can add height to a woman's sin. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124640">Vice never doth her just hate so provoke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124650">As when she rageth under virtue's cloak. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124660">Write: for it must be; by this ruthless steel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124670">By this impartial torture, and the death</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124680">Thy tyrannies have invented in my entrails,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124690">To quicken life in dying, and hold up</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124700">The spirits in fainting, teaching to preserve</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124710">Torments in ashes, that will ever last. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124720">Speak: will you write? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e124730" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124740">Sweet lord enjoin my sin</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124750">Some other penance than what makes it worse:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124760">Hide in some gloomy dungeon my loathed face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124770">And let condemned murderers let me down</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124780">(Stopping their noses) my abhorred food. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124790">Hang me in chains, and let me eat these arms</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124800">That have offended: bind me face to face</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124810">To some dead woman, taken from the cart</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124820">Of execution, till death and time</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124830">In grains of dust dissolve me; I'll endure:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124840">Or any torture that your wrath's invention</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124850">Can fright all pity from the world withal:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124860">But to betray a friend with show of friendship,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124870">That is too common, for the rare revenge</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124880">Your rage affecteth; here then are my breasts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124890">Last night your pillows; here my wretched arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124900">As late the wished confines of your life:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124910">Now break them as you please, and all the bounds</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124920">Of manhood, noblesse, and religion. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e124930" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124940">Where all these have been broken, they are kept,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124950">In doing their justice there: thine arms have lost</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124960">Their privilege in lust, and in their torture</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124970">Thus they must pay it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e124980" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <pb facs="31" n="58"/>
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e124990">O lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125000" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125010">Till thou writest</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125020">I'll write in wounds (My wrongs fit characters)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125030">Thy right of sufferance. Write. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125040" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125050">O kill me, kill me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125060">Dear husband be not crueler than death;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125070">You have beheld some Gorgon: feel, o feel</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125080">How you are turned to stone; with my heart blood</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125090">Dissolve yourself again, or you will grow</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125100">Into the image of all tyranny. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125110" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125120">As thou art of adultery, I will still</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125130">Prove thee my like in ill, being most a monster:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125140">Thus I express thee yet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125150" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125160">And yet I live. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125170" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125180">Ay, for thy monstrous idol is not done yet:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125190">This tool hath wrought enough: now torture use</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125200">This other engine on th'habituate powers</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125210">Of her thrice damned and whorish fortitude. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125220">Use the most madding pains in her that ever</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125230">Thy venoms soaked through, making most of death;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125240">That she may weigh her wrongs with them, and then</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125250">Stand vengeance on thy steepest rock, a victor. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125260" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125270">O who is turned into my lord and husband? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125280">Husband? My lord? None but my lord and husband. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125290">Heaven, I ask thee remission of my sins,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125300">Not of my pains: husband, o help me husband. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125310" who="A18403-comolet">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125320"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A18403-e125330">ascendit Comolet. </note>what rape of honour and religion? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125340">O wrack of nature. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125350" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125360">Poor man: o my father,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125370">Father? look up; o let me down my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125380">And I will write. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125390" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125400">Author of prodigies! </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125410">What new flame breaks out of the firmament,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125420">That turns up counsels never known before? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125430">Now is it true, earth moves, and heaven stands still;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125440">Even heaven itself must see and suffer ill:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125450">The too huge bias of the world hath swayed</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125460">Her backpart onwards, and with that she braves</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125470"><pb facs="31" n="59"/> this hemisphere, that long her mouth hath mocked:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125480">The gravity of her religious face:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125490">(Now grown too weighty with her sacrilege</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125500">And here discerned sophisticate enough)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125510">Turns to th'antipodes: and all the forms</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125520">That her illusions have impressed in her,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125530">Have eaten through her back: and now all see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125540">How she is riveted with hypocrisy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125550">Was this the way? was he the mean betwixt you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125560" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125570">He was, he was, kind innocent man he was. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125580" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125590">Write, write a word or two. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125600" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125610">I will, I will. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125620">I'll write, but in my blood that he may see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125630">These lines come from my wounds and not from me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125640" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125650">Well might he die for thought: methinks the frame</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125660">And shaken joints of the whole world should crack</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125670">To see her parts so disproportionate;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125680">And that his general beauty cannot stand</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125690">Without these stains in the particular man. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125700">Why wander I so far? here here was she</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125710">That was a whole world without spot to me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125720">Though now a world of spots; o what a lightning</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125730">Is man's delight in women? what a bubble,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125740">He builds his state, fame, life on, when he marries? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125750">Since all earth's pleasures are so short and small,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125760">The way t'enjoy it, is t'abjure it all:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125770">Enough: I must be messenger myself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125780">Disguised like this strange creature: in, I'll after,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125790">To see what guilty light gives this cave eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125800">And to the world sing new impieties. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e125810">D' Ambois with two pages.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125820" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125830">Sit up tonight , and watch, I'll speak with none</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125840">But the old friar, who bring to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125850" who="A18403-unassigned">
          <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125860">We will sir. <stage xml:id="A18403-e125870">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125880" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125890">What violent heat is this? methinks the fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125900">Of twenty lives doth on a sudden flash</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125910">Through all my faculties: the air goes high</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125920"><pb facs="32" n="60"/> in this close chamber, and the frighted earth! </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125930">Trembles, and shrinks beneath me: the whole house</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125940">Cracks with his shaken burden; bless me, heaven. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e125950">Enter vmb. Comol.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e125960" who="A18403-umbra">
          <speaker>Vmb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125970">Note what I want, my son, and be forewarned:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125980">Oh there are bloody deeds passed and to come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e125990">I cannot stay: a fate doth ravish me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126000">I'll meet thee in the chamber of thy love. <stage xml:id="A18403-e126010">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126020" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126030">What dismal change is here? the good old friar</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126040">Is murdered; being made known to serve my love;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126050">Note what he wants? he wants his utmost weed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126060">He wants his life, and body: which of these</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126070">Should be the want he means, and may supply me</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126080">With any fit forewarning? this strange vision,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126090">(Together with the dark prediction</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126100">Used by the prince of darkness that was raised</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126110">By this embodied shadow) stir my thoughts</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126120">With reminiscion of the spirits promise;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126130">Who told me, that by any invocation</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126140">I should have power to raise him; though it wanted</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126150">The powerful words, and decent rites of art;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126160">Never had my set brain such need of spirit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126170">T'instruct and cheer it; now then, I will claim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126180">Performance of his free and gentle vow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126190">T'appear in greater light; and make more plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126200">His rugged oracle: I long to know</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126210">How my dear mistress fares; and be informed</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126220">What hand she now holds on the troubled blood</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126230">Of her incensed lord: methought the spirit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126240">(When he had uttered his perplexed presage)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126250">Threw his changed countenance headlong into clouds;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126260">His forehead bent, as it would hide his face;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126270">He knocked his chin against his darkened breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126280">And struck a churlish silence through his powers;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126290">Terror of darkness: oh thou King of flames,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126300">That with thy music-footed horse dost strike</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126310">The clear light out of crystal, on dark earth;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126320"><pb facs="32" n="61"/> and hurlest instructive fire about the world:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126330">Wake, wake, the drowsy and enchanted night;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126340">That sleeps with dead eyes in this heavy riddle:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126350">Or thou great prince of shades where never sun</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126360">Sticks his far-darted beams: whose eyes are made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126370">To see in darkness: and see ever best</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126380">Where sense is blindest: open now the heart</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126390">Of thy abashed oracle: that for fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126400">Of some ill it includes, would fain lie hid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126410">And rise thou with it in thy greater light. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e126420">Surgit spiritus cum suis.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126430" who="A18403-spirit">
          <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126440">Thus to observe my vow of apparition,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126450">In greater light: and explicate thy fate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126460">I come; and tell thee that if thou obey</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126470">The summons that thy mistress next will send thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126480">Her hand shall be thy death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126490" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126500">When will she send? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126510" who="A18403-spirit">
          <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126520">Soon as I set again, where late I rose. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126530" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126540">Is the old friar slain? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126550" who="A18403-spirit">
          <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126560">No, and yet lives not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126570" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126580">Died he a natural death? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126590" who="A18403-spirit">
          <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126600">He did. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126610" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126620">Who then,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126630">Will my dear mistress send? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126640" who="A18403-spirit">
          <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126650">I must not tell thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126660" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126670">Who lets thee? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126680" who="A18403-spirit">
          <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126690">Fate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126700" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Am.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126710">Who are fates ministers? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126720" who="A18403-spirit">
          <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126730">The Guise and Monsieur. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126740" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126750">A fit pair of shears</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126760">To cut the threads of Kings, and kingly spirits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126770">And consorts fit to sound forth harmony,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126780">Set to the falls of kingdoms: shall the hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126790">Of my kind mistress kill me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126800" who="A18403-spirit">
          <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126810">If thou yield,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126820">To her next summons, you're fair warned: farewell. <stage xml:id="A18403-e126830">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e126840" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D' Amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126850">I must fare well, however : though I die</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126860"><pb facs="33" n="62"/> my death consenting with his augury;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126870">Should not my powers obey, when she commands</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126880">My motion must be rebel to my will:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126890">My will: to life, if when I have obeyed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126900">Her hand should so reward me: they must arm it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126910">Bind me and force it: or I lay my soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126920">She rather would convert it, many times</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126930">On her own bosom: even to many deaths:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126940">But were there danger of such violence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126950">I know 'tis far from her intent to send:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126960">And who she should send, is as far from thought</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126970">Since he is dead, whose only mean she used</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126980">Who's there? look to the door: and let him in,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e126990">Though politic monsieur, or the violent Guise. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e127000">Enter Montsurry like the friar.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e127010" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127020">Haile to my worthy son. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e127030" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127040">O lying spirit: welcome loved father</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127050">How fares my dearest mistress? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e127060" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127070">Well, as ever</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127080">Being well as ever thought on by her lord:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127090">Whereof she sends this witness in her hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127100">And prays, for urgent cause, your speediest presence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e127110" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127120">What? writ in blood? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e127130" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127140">Ay, 'tis the ink of lovers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e127150" who="A18403-d'ambois">
          <speaker>D'amb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127160">O 'tis a sacred witness of her love. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127170">So much elixir of her blood as this</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127180">Dropped in the lightest dame, would make her firm</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127190">As heat to fire: and like to all the signs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127200">Commands the life confined in all my veins;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127210">Oh how it multiplies my blood with spirit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127220">And makes me apt t'encounter death and hell:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127230">But, come kind father; you fetch me to heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127240">And to that end your holy weed was given. <stage xml:id="A18403-e127250">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e127260">Enter monsieur, Guise above.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e127270" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127280">Now shall we see, that nature hath no end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127290">In her great works, responsive to their worths,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127300"><pb facs="33" n="63"/> that she who makes so many eyes, and souls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127310">To see and foresee, is stark blind herself:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127320">And as illiterate men say Latin prayers</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127330">By root of heart, and daily iteration;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127340">In whose hot zeal, a man would think they knew</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127350">What they ran so away with, and were sure</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127360">To have rewards proportioned to their labours;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127370">Yet may implore their own confusions</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127380">For any thing they know, which oftentimes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127390">It falls out they incur: so nature lays</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127400">A mass of stuff together, and by use,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127410">Or by the mere necessity of matter,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127420">Ends such a work, fills it, or leaves it empty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127430">Of strength, or virtue, error or clear truth;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127440">Not knowing what she does; but usually</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127450">Gives that which we call merit to a man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127460">And believe should arrive him on huge riches,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127470">Honour, and happiness, that effects his ruin;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127480">Right as in ships of war, whole lasts of powder</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127490">Are laid (Men think) to make them last, and guard them;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127500">When a disordered spark that powder taking,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127510">Blows up with sudden violence and horror</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127520">Ships that kept empty, had sailed long with terror. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e127530" who="A18403-guise">
          <speaker>Gui.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127540">He that observes, but like a worldly man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127550">That which doth oft succeed, and by th'events</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127560">Values the worth of things; will think it true,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127570">That nature works at random just with you:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127580">But with as much decorum she may make</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127590">A thing that from the feet up to the throat</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127600">Hath all the wondrous fabric man should have,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127610">And leave it headless for an absolute man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127620">As give a whole man valour, virtue, learning,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127630">Without an end more excellent than those,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127640">On whom she no such worthy part bestows. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e127650" who="A18403-monsieur">
          <speaker>Monsieur</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127660">Why you shall see it here, here will be one</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127670">Young, learned, valiant, virtuous, and full manned;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127680">One on whom nature spent so rich a hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127690">That, with an ominous eye, she wept to see</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127700"><pb facs="34" n="64"/> so much consumed her virtuous treasury;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127710">Yet, as the winds sing through a hollow tree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127720">And (Since it lets them pass through) let it stand</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127730">But a tree solid, since it gives no way</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127740">To their wild rages, they rend up by th' root:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127750">So this full creature now shall reel and fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127760">Before the frantic puffs of purblind chance</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127770">That pipes thorough empty men, and makes them dance:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127780">Not so the sea raves on the Lybian sands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127790">Tumbling her billows in each others neck:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127800">Not so the surges of the Euxine sea</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127810">(Near to the frosty pole, where free Bootes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127820">From those dark-deep waves turns his radiant team)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127830">Swell being enraged, even from their inmost drop,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127840">As fortune swings about the restless state</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127850">Of virtue, now thrown into all men's hate. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A18403-e127860">Intrat umbra, Comolet to the countess, wrapped in a canopy.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127870">Revive those stupid thoughts, and sit not thus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127880">Gathering the horrors of your servant's slaughter,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127890">(So urged by your hand, and so imminent)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127900">Into an idle fancy; but device</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127910">How to prevent it; watch when he shall rise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127920">And with a sudden outcry of his murder,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127930">Blow his retreat before he be engaged. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e127940" who="A18403-count">
          <speaker>Count.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127950">O father, have my dumb woes waked your death? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127960">When will our humane griefs be at their height? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127970">Man is a tree, that hath no top in cares;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127980">No root in comforts; all his power to live</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e127990">Is given to no end, but to have power to grieve. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128000" who="A18403-umbra">
          <speaker>Vmb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128010">'Tis the just curse of our abused creation,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128020">Which we must suffer here, and scape hereafter:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128030">He hath the great mind that submits to all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128040">He sees inevitable; he the small</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128050">That carps at earth, and her foundation shaker,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128060">And rather than himself, will mend his maker. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e128070"><pb facs="34" n="65"/>D'amb. at the gulf. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128080" who="A18403-count">
          <speaker>Count.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128090">Away, (My love) away, thou wilt be murdered. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128100" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128110">Murdered? I know not what that hebrew means:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128120">That word had never been named had all been D'ambois. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128130">Murdered? By heaven he is my murderer</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128140">That shows me not a murderer; what such bug</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128150">Abhorreth not the very sleep of D'ambois? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128160">Murdered? Who dares give all the room I see</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128170">To D'ambois' reach? or look with any odds</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128180">His fight ith' face, upon whose hand sits death;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128190">Whose sword hath wings, and every feather pierceth? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128200">Let in my politic visitants, let them in,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128210">Though entering like so many moving armours,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128220">Fate is more strong than arms, and sly than treason,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128230">And I at all parts buckled in my fate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128240">Dare they not come? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128250" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128260">They come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128270" who="A18403-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128280">Come all at once. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128290" who="A18403-umbra">
          <speaker>Vmb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128300">Back coward murderers, back. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128310" who="A18403-omnes">
          <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128320">Defend us heaven. <stage xml:id="A18403-e128330">Exeunt.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128340" who="A18403-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128350">Come ye not on? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128360" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128370">No, slave, nor goest thou off. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128380">Stand you so firm? Will it not enter here? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128390">You have a face yet: so in thy life's flame</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128400">I burn the first rites to my mistress fame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128410" who="A18403-umbra">
          <speaker>Vmb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128420">Breath thee brave son against the other charge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128430" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128440">O is it true then that my sense first told me? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128450">Is my kind father dead? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128460" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128470">He is my love. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128480">'Twas the Earl my husband in his weed that brought thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128490" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128500">That was a speeding sleight, and well resembled. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128510">Where is that angry Earl my lord? Come forth</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128520">And show your own face in your own affair;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128530">Take not into your noble veins the blood</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128540">Of these base villains, nor the light reports</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128550">Of blistered tongues, for clear and weighty truth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128560">But me against the world, in pure defence</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128570"><pb facs="35" n="66"/> of your rare lady, to whose spotless name</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128580">I stand here as a bulwark, and project</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128590">A life to her renown, that ever yet</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128600">Hath been untainted even in envy's eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128610">And where it would protect a sanctuary. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128620">Brave Earl come forth, and keep your scandal in:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128630">'Tis not our fault if you enforce the spot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128640">Nor the wreak yours if you perform it not. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18403-e128650">Enter mont with others.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128660" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128670">Cowards, a fiend or spirit beat ye off? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128680">They are your own faint spirits that have forged</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128690">The fearful shadows that your eyes deluded:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128700">The fiend was in you; cast him out then thus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128710" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128720">Favour (My lord) my love, o favour him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128730" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128740">I will not touch him: take your life, my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128750">And be appeased: oh then the coward fates</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128760">Have maimed themselves, and ever lost their honour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128770" who="A18403-umbra">
          <speaker>Vmb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128780">What have ye done slaves? irreligious lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e128790" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128800">Forbear them, father; 'tis enough for me</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128810">That Guise and Monsieur, death and destiny</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128820">Come behind D'ambois: is my body then</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128830">But penetrable flesh? And must my mind</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128840">Follow my blood? Can my divine part add</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128850">No aid to th'earthly in extremity? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128860">Then these divines are but for form, not fact:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128870">Man is of two sweet courtly friends compact;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128880">A mistress and a servant: let my death</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128890">Define life nothing but a courtier's breath. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128900">Nothing is made of naught, of all things made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128910">Their abstract being a dream but of a shade. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128920">I'll not complain to earth yet, but to heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128930">And (Like a man) look onwards even in death. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128940">Prop me, true sword, as thou hast ever done:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128950">The equal thought I bear of life and death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128960">Shall make me faint on no side; I am up</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128970">Here like a Roman statue; I will stand</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128980">Till death hath made me marble: o my fame</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e128990"><pb facs="35" n="67"/> live in despite of murder; take thy wings</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129000">And haste thee where the grey-eyed morn perfines,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129010">Her rosy chariot with Sabaean spices,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129020">Fly, where the evening from th'iberian vales,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129030">Takes on her swarthy shoulders, Hecate</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129040">Crowned with a grove of oaks: fly where men feel</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129050">The burning axletree: and those that suffer</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129060">Beneath the chariot of the snowy bear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129070">And tell them all that D'ambois now is hasting</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129080">To the eternal dwellers; that a thunder</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129090">Of all their sighs together (For their frailties</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129100">Beheld in me) may quit my worthless fall</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129110">With a fit volley for my funeral. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e129120" who="A18403-umbra">
          <speaker>Vmb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129130">Forgive thy murderers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e129140" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Buss.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129150">I forgive them all;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129160">And you my lord, their fautor; for true sign</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129170">Of which unfeigned remission, take my sword;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129180">Take it, and only give it motion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129190">And it shall find the way to victory</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129200">By his own brightness, and th' inherent valour</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129210">My fight hath stilled into't, with charms of spirit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e129220" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Bus.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129230">And let me pray you, that my weighty blood</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129240">Laid in one scale of your impartial spleen</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129250">May sway the forfeit of my worthy love</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129260">Weighed in the other: and be reconciled</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129270">With all forgiveness to your matchless wife. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e129280" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129290">Forgive thou me dear servant, and this hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129300">That lead thy life to this unworthy end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129310">Forgive it, for the blood with which 'tis stained</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129320">In which I writ the summons of thy death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129330">The forced summons, by this bleeding wound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129340">By this here in my bosom: and by this</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129350">That makes me hold up both my hands imbrued</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129360">For thy dear pardon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e129370" who="A18403-bussy">
          <speaker>Bus.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129380">O, my heart is broken</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129390">Fate, nor these murderers, monsieur, nor the Guise. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129400">Have any glory in my death, but this:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129410">This killing spectacle: this prodigy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129420"><pb facs="36" n="68"/> my sun is turned to blood 'gainst whose red beams</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129430">Pindas and Ossa (Hid in endless snow</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129440">Laid on my heart and liver; from their veins)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129450">Melt like two hungry torrents: eating rocks</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129460">Into the ocean of all humane life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129470">And make it bitter, only with my blood:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129480">Oh frail condition of strength, valour; virtue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129490">In me (Like warning fire upon the top</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129500">Of some steep beacon, on a steeper hill)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129510">Made to express it: like a falling star</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129520">Silently glanced, that like a thunderbolt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129530">Looked to have stuck and shook the firmament. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e129540" who="A18403-umbra">
          <speaker>Vmb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129550">Son of the earth, whom my unrested soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129560">Rues t'have begotten in the faith of heaven;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129570">(Since thy revengeful spirit hath rejected</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129580">The charity it commands, and the remission</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129590">To serve and worship, the blind rage of blood)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129600">Assay to gratulate and pacify,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129610">The soul fled from this worthy by performing</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129620">The Christian reconcilement he besought</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129630">Betwixt thee and thy lady, let her wounds</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129640">Manlesly digged in her, be eased and cured</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129650">With balm of thine own tears: or be assured</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129660">Never to rest free from my haunt and horror. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e129670" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129680">See how she merits this: still sitting by</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129690">And mourning his fall, more than her own fault. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e129700" who="A18403-umbra">
          <speaker>Vmb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129710">Remove, dear daughter, and content thy husband:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129720">So piety wills thee, and thy servant's peace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e129730" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tamy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129740">O wretched piety, that art so distract</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129750">In thine own constancy; and in thy right</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129760">Must be unrighteous: if I right my friend</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129770">I wrong my husband: if his wrong I shun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129780">The duty of my friend I leave undone;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129790">Ill plays on both sides; here and there, it riseth;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129800">No place: no good so good, but ill compriseth;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129810">My soul more scruple breeds, than my blood, sin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129820">Virtue imposeth more than any stepdame:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129830">Oh had I never married but for form,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129840"><pb facs="36" n="69"/> never vowed faith but purposed to deceive:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129850">Never made conscience of any sin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129860">But cloaked it privately and made it common:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129870">Nor never honoured been, in blood, or mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129880">Happy had I been then, as others are</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129890">Of the like licence; I had then been honoured:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129900">Lived without envy: custom had benumbed</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129910">All sense of scruple, and all note of frailty:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129920">My fame had been untouched, my heart unbroken:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129930">But (Shunning all) I strike on all offence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129940">Oh husband? dear friend? O my conscience? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e129950" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129960">I must not yield to pity nor to love</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129970">So servile and so traitorous: cease my blood</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129980">To wrestle with my honour, fame and judgement:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e129990">Away, forsake my house, forbear complaints</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130000">Where thou hast bred them: here all things full,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130010">Of their own shame and sorrow, leave my house. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e130020" who="A18403-tamyra">
          <speaker>Tam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130030">Sweet lord forgive me, and I will be gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130040">And till these wounds, that never balm shall close</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130050">Till death hath entered at them (So I love them</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130060">Being opened by your hands) by death be cured</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130070">I never more will grieve you with my sight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130080">Never endure that any roof shall part</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130090">Mine eyes and heaven: but to the open deserts</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130100">(Like to hunted tigers) I will fly:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130110">Eating my heart, shunning the steps of men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130120">And look on no side till I be arrived. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e130130" who="A18403-montsurry">
          <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130140">I do forgive thee, and upon my knees</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130150">With hands (Held up to heaven) wish that mine honour</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130160">Would suffer reconcilement to my love:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130170">But since it will not, honour, never serve</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130180">My love with flourishing object till it starve:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130190">And as this taper, though it onwards look,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130200">Downwards must needs consume, so let our love;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130210">As having lost his honey, the sweet taste</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130220">Runs into savour, and will needs retain</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130230">A spice of his first parents, till (Like life)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130240">It sees and dies; so let our love: and lastly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130250"><pb facs="37" n="70"/> as when the flame is suffered to look up</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130260">It keeps his luster: but, being thus turned down</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130270">(His natural course of useful light inverted)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130280">His own stuff puts it out: so let our love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130290">Now turn from me, as here I turn from thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130300">And may both points of heavens straight axletree</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130310">Conjoin in one, before thyself and me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18403-e130320" who="A18403-umbra">
          <speaker>Vmb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130330">My terrors are struck inward, and no more</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130340">My penance will allow they shall enforce</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130350">Earthly afflictions but upon myself:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130360">Farewell brave relics of a complete man:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130370">Look up and see thy spirit made a star,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130380">Join flames with Hercules: and when thou setst</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130390">Thy radiant forehead in the firmament,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130400">Make the vast continent, crack with thy receipt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130410">Spread to a world of fire: and th'aged sky,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18403-e130420">Cheer with new sparks of old humanity. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer xml:id="A18403-e130430">Finis actus quinti et ultimi.</trailer>
        <pb facs="37"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A18403"><item xml:id="A18403-monsieur" n="94">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-monsieur</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">94</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-tamyra" n="71">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-tamyra</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">71</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-bussy" n="68">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-bussy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">68</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-montsurry" n="61">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-montsurry</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">61</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-dambois" n="44">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-d'ambois</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">44</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-guise" n="35">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-guise</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">35</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-henry" n="27">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-henry</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">27</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-comolet" n="19">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-comolet</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">19</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-pero" n="18">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-pero</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">18</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-maffe" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-maffe</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-barrisor" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-barrisor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-lanou" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-l'anou</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-umbra" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-umbra</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-spirit" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-spirit</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-behemoth" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-behemoth</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-pyra" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-pyra</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-nuntius" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-nuntius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-beaumond" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-beaumond</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-unassigned" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-charlotte" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-charlotte</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-annabell" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-annabell</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-count" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-count</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-xxxx_1" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-xxxx_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-cartophylax" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-cartophylax</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-brisac" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-brisac</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-beaupre" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-beaupre</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A18403-ely" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-ely</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-omnes" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-omnes</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-duchess" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-duchess</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18403-melynell" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18403-melynell</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

