<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A18729">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Entertainment in Suffolk and Norfolk <date type="creation_date">1578</date></title>
        <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A18729.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A discourse of the Queenes Maiesties entertainement in Suffolk and Norffolk with a description of many things then presently seene. Deuised by Thomas Churchyarde, Gent. with diuers shewes of his own inuention sette out at Norwich: and some rehearsal of hir Highnesse retourne from progresse. Wherevnto is adioyned a commendation of Sir Humfrey Gilberts ventrous iourney.</title>
            <author>Churchyard, Thomas, 1520?-1604.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>45 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 September (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99840706</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 5226.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 76.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">5233</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18729</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A discourse of the Queenes Maiesties entertainement in Suffolk and Norffolk with a description of many things then presently seene. Deuised by Thomas Churchyarde, Gent. with diuers shewes of his own inuention sette out at Norwich: and some rehearsal of hir Highnesse retourne from progresse. Wherevnto is adioyned a commendation of Sir Humfrey Gilberts ventrous iourney.</title>
            <title type="alt">Qu. Maiesties entertaynement in Suffolke and Norffolke.</title>
            <title type="alt">Entertainment in Norfolk and Suffolk.</title>
            <author>Churchyard, Thomas, 1520?-1604.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[88] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Imprinted by Henrie Bynneman, seruante to the right Honourable Sir Christofer Hatton Vizchamberlayne,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
            <date>[1578]</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Partly in verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Publication date from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>"A welcome home to Master Martin Frobusher" begins on L1.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-L4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>H1 is a cancel in all copies, with a list of new knights on the verso.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Heading of dedication varies: to (1) William Iarret; (2) Gilbert Gerard; (3) Gilbert Gerrard.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Frobisher, Martin, -- Sir, -- ca. 1535-1594 -- Poetry.</term>
          <term>Gilbert, Humphrey, -- Sir, -- 1539?-1583 -- Poetry.</term>
          <term>Elizabeth, -- I, -- Queen of England, -- 1533-1603 -- Poetry.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A18729-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A18729-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A18729-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e100040">A discourse of the Queen's majesty's entertainment in Suffolk and Norfolk: with a description of many things then presently seen.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e100050">Devised by Thomas Churchyard, gent. with divers shows of his own invention set out at Norwich: and some rehearsal of her highness' return from progress.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e100060">Whereunto is adjoined a commendation of sir Humphrey gilberts venturous journey. </p>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e100070">
          <figure xml:id="A18729-e100080">
            <head>
              <quote xml:id="A18729-e100090">Cerva charissima et gratissimus hinnvlvs·</quote>
              <bibl xml:id="A18729-e100100">pro: 5</bibl>
            </head>
            <figDesc xml:id="A18729-e100110">printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e100120">At London, imprinted by Henry Bynneman ▪ servant to the right honourable sir Christoper Hatton vice-chamberlain. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A18729-e100140">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To the right worshipful master Gilbert Gerrard, the Queen's majesty's attorney general, Thomas churchyard gent. sendeth this sign of good will, and wisheth increase of worthy fame.</head>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e100150">Having a desire (Right worshipful) to continue in your favour and amity, I devised sundry ways to give you some cause of recreation, amid the multitude of your grave studies, and weighty affairs, and knowing that no one thing is more welcome to a worthy wit, than the understanding of matter, wherein the duty of good subjects is expressed, and the greatness of good minds is made manifest,<pb facs="3"/> I have presented you with a little book, that makes not only report of the noble receiving of the Queen's majesty into Suffolk and Norfolk, but also of the good order, great cheer, and charges that her highness subjects were at, during her abode in those parties. And because I saw most of it, or heard it so credibly rehearsed, as I know it to be true, I mean to make it a mirror and shining glass, that all the whole land may look into, or use it for an example in all places (Where the prince cometh) to our posterity hereafter for ever. For in very deed, if the dutiful usage of Suffolk and Norfolk had not surmounted in greatness and goodness any five shears in England, for hospitality, bravery, and frank dealing, I had not made mention of these causes, nor written so large a discourse of their behavioures, and bountiful manner of duty: but finding these two shears so well furnished of gentlemen, and so flourishing,<pb facs="3"/> and ready to attend in time of triumph, on her that is our triumph and earthly felicity, I can do no less, but with immortal fame, sound their praises, and use my pen to their great glory and thanks, as a guerdon due for their worthy and honest dezerts, hoping that every other sheer, where the Queen's highness hath not been, will rather strive to follow this lantern when occasion is offered, than any way think me affectionate, or that I have partially proceeded in this exercise of pen. And now right worshipful, if you muse why I do enterlard this discourse with some such words or sentences, as may seem to digress from my purposed cause, I pray you conceive, both for variety, and the virtue of the matter, that my judgement is carried by circumstances, to treat at large those things, that shortness of speech will not suffer, and that my cunning can not aptly place every thing in his order: but yet as I<pb facs="4"/> may (Under your correction) I will boldly hold on my matter which I have penned, for those people that dwell far off the court, that they may see with what majesty a prince reigneth, and with what obedience and love good subjects do receive her: not that I think, but all the shears of England are most willing to do their duties to the uttermost of their powers: but that in deed the like of this entertainment hath not been seen: I have presumed to set out these things, and namely, because at Norwich I was employed to set forth some shows, which here I have imprinted, as well those that her highness saw not, by means of evil weather, as those she saw and heard, and gave gracious thanks for. And as I mind to wright what truly happeneth in my memory, so mean I to touch a little, the manner and inclination of the common people, whose civil sort and courtesy is greatly to be commended. Withal, I have<pb facs="4"/> placed at the end of this discourse, a few verses, in the honoring of good minds, and travelling bodies, meaning thereby sir Humphrey Gilbert, master Henry Knolles, and others, right worthy and honest gentlemen, presently passed towards a happy voyage as I hope. These pains and purposes of mine, proceed only on the good will I bear to all virtuous actions, and so I trust you will take them, and giving my small book a little countenance (If it so stand with your pleasure) I shall find myself greatly bound unto you therefore, and among the rest that speaketh well (Which are not a few) of your upright government of life, I will not be the last shall yield you deserved laud, as knoweth God, who increase his grace and good gifts in you, and make your end as honourable, as your days have been blessed.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A18729-e100160">
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <head>To the reader.</head>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e100170">If I should not good reader as well show thee some matter of delight, as publish to the world these penned discourses, thy wits would wax a weary of my frivolous words, and I should gain but little fruit by my labour and travel: and greater delight can not be presented, than here to show thee the good disposition of some people, bred up, and nourished out of the bowels of thine own nation. And albeit it seemeth strange, that people nurtured far from court, should use much courtesy, yet will I prove by the humbleness of the common people, where lately the prince hath passed, that if in a manner all civility were utterly decayed, it might have been found freshly flourishing in many of those parties and places specified before: for so soon as the presence of the prince was entered in their bounds, by a mere motion of homage and fealty, a general consent of duty and obedience was seen through the whole country, and well were they that might first find occasion by any means to welcome a courtier,<pb facs="6"/> and not with feigned ceremonies, but with friendly entertainment. And although it be a custom, and most laudable manner for the poor commons to run in flocks to see their sovereign, yet there, as methought , their desire was so great, that they had never enough of the sight so long wished and desired: and such reverence and humility they used towards all the train, wheresoever they encountered any of them, that the inward affections of the people was plainly expressed by their outward appearance, and manifest courtesies: in so much, that the meanest persons that followed the court, stood marvellously contented with that they saw, and wondered at the rare and good manner of the people, especially in Norwich, where the entertainment was so great, that all degrees, from the highest to the lowest, were had in such admiration, that it seemed another world to behold: which new kind of reverence, and comely custom of the country (As it may be properly applied) makes the old haughtiness, and stiffnecked behaviour of some places, to blush, and become odious, yea in soils, that the prince generally keepeth her residence, and most abode in, where proud people will pass by many of the nobility, without moving either cap or knee, a stubborn stoutness, and an unmannerly<pb facs="6"/> disordered boldness, bred up and fostered on the long familiarity had with the noble men's servants, and daily view of their masters, with which sight they are so cloyed and wearied, that their duty is forgotten, and utterly rejected, that ought to be ashamed of abuse, and should use more reverent manners. If they would (To leave off this audacious fashion) but look on divers shears in this land, as Lancashire, Cheshire, Shropshire, and other shears far from the court, they might soon be learned to clap on more comeliness, and use less obstinacy. And if they think scorn to be taught at home of our own people, it were good they were shipped into France or Flanders, our near neighbours, where the meaner sort are not only known by their garments and going, but perceived by their gestures, and humbleness of countenance and speech. Now gentle reader, think no other of this my discourse in the commendation of courtesy, but that I rejoice to see such ancient humility as yet held up and maintained in England, when pride and vainglory would overthrow the good dispositions of the people, and breed both to God and man a common contempt. And, as I have rehearsed a piece of those<pb facs="7"/> things I saw in Suffolk and Norfolk, to further thy delight towards the reading of my simple book, so look for presently at my hands the rest of that progress which I am truly instructed of, or may come to my memory. Thus committing to thy hands and head the boldness of my enterprise, and view of those verses and matter I here have set out. I bid thee farewell.</p>
        <trailer type="illustration" xml:id="A18729-e100180">
          <figure xml:id="A18729-e100190"/>
        </trailer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A18729-e100200">
      <div type="entertainment" xml:id="A18729-e100210">
        <pb facs="7"/>
        <head>¶ The entertaynement of the Queen's majesty into Suffolk, and Norfolk.</head>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e100220">To wright of the receiving of her highness into Suffolk and Norfolk in every point, as matter may move me, would contain a great time, in making a just rehearsal thereof: wherefore I will but briefly recite it, and commit the circumstance and manner of the same, to your discretion and judgement. The troth is, albeit they had but small warning certainly to build upon, of the coming of the Queen's majesty into both those shears, the gentlemen had made such ready provision, that all the velvets and silks were taken up that might be laid hand on, and bought for any money, and soon converted to such garments and suits of robes, that the show thereof might have beautified the greatest triumph that was in England these many years: for (As I heard) there were two hundred young gentlemen, clad all in white velvet, and thrée hundred of the graver sort apparelled in black velvet coats, and fair chains, all ready at one instant and place, with fifteen hundred serving men more on horseback, well and bravely mounted in good order, ready to receive the Queen's highness into Suffolk, which surely was a comely troop, and a noble sight to behold: and all these waited on the sheriff sir William spring, during the Queen's majesty's abode in those parties, and to the very confines of Suffolk. But before her highness passed to Norfolk, there was<pb facs="8"/> in Suffolk such sumptuous feasting and banquets, as seldom in any part of the world hath been seen before. The master of the rolls, sir William Cordall, was one of the first that began this great feasting, and did light such a candle to the rest of the sheer, that many were glad bountifully and frankly to follow the same example, with such charges and cost, as the whole train were in some sort pleased therewith. And near bury, sir William Drury for his part at his house, made the Queen's highness a costly and delicate dinner, and sir Robert Jermyn of Roeshbroke feasted the French ambassadors two several times, with which charges and courtesy they stood marvellously contented. The sheriff sir William spring, sir Thomas Kidson, sir Arthur Higham, and divers other of worship, kept great houses, and sundry either at the Queens coming, or return, solemnly feasted her highness, yea and defrayed the whole charges for a day or twain, presented gifts, made such triumphs and devises, as in deed was most noble to behold, and very thankfully accepted. The Norfolk gentlemen hearing how dutifully their neighbours had received the prince, prepared in like sort to show themselves dutiful, and so in most gallantest manner, assembled and set forward with five and twenty hundred horsemen, whereof as some affirm, were six hundreth gentlemen, so bravely attired, and mounted, as in deed was worthy the noting, which goodly company waited on their sheriff a long season: but in good sooth (As I have heard credibly spoken) the banquets and feasts began here afresh, and all kind of triumphs that might be devised, were put in practice and proof. The Earl of Surrey did show most sumptuous cheere, in whose park were speeches well set out, and a special device much commended: and the rest, as a number of gentlemen, whose names I have not, were no whit behind to the uttermost of their abilities, in all that might be done and devised. But when the Queen's highness came to Norwich, the substance of the whole triumph and feasting, was in a manner there new to begin, for order was taken<pb facs="8"/> there, that every day, for six days together, a show of some strange device should be seen, and the mayor and aldermen, appointed among themselves and their brothers, that no one person, retaining to the Queen, should be unfeasted, or unbidden to dinner and supper, during the space of those six days: which order was well and wisely observed, and gained their city more fame and credit, than they wot of: for that courtesy of theirs shall remain in perpetual memory, whiles the walls of their city standeth. Besides the money they bestowed on divers of the train, and those that took pains for them (Albeit myself but slenderly considered) will be a witness of their well doing and good will, whiles the report of these things may be called to remembrance. I can not nor ought not, considering their great charges (And discrete government in these causes) but give them due laud and reputation, as far as my pen or report may do them good, and stretch out their credit. For most assuredly, they have taught and learned all the towns and cities in England a lesson, how to behave themselves in such like services and actions.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e100230">Now to return to the shows and purposed matter penned out by me (To shorten the season, and move pastime to the prince) I thought it convenient to print them in order, as they were invented: for I was the first that was called, and came to Norwiche about that business, and remained there thrée long weeks before the court came thither, devising and studying the best I could for the city, albeit other gentlemen, as master Goldingham, master garter, and others, did seep in after, and brought to pass that already is set in print in a book, where the orations and speeches of divers are set out plainly and truly: and for that my meaning was orderly to proceed, I have here plainly drawn out my device, not that I think it merits any great memory, nor claimeth credit, but only that mine honest intent may been thereby expressed, and my friends may see how glad I am to honour God, my prince,<pb facs="9"/> and my country, trusting to set forth other works as time will permit, and that right shortly, that shall hold you longer tack, and better please you. In the meanwhile I pray you take in worth and good part my little pains and great good will, and read (As your fancy favours) the verses and devises that follow.</p>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A18729-e100240">
          <head>The song on Saturday at her highness' entry, song on the great stage that was next the market place, by the waits and best voices in the city.</head>
          <lg xml:id="A18729-e100250">
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100260">The dew of heaven drops this day</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100270">On dry and barren ground,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100280">Wherefore let fruitful hearts I say</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100290">At drum and trumpet sound</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100300">Yield that is due, show that is meet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100310">To make our joy the more,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100320">In our good hope, and her great praise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100330">We never saw before. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A18729-e100340">
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100350">The sun doth shine where shade hath been,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100360">Long darkness brought us day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100370">The star of comfort now coms in,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100380">And here a while will stay. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100390">Ring out the bells, pluck up your sprights,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100400">And dress your houses gay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100410">Run in for flowers to straw the streets,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100420">And make what joy you may. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100430">The dew of heaven. Etc. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A18729-e100440">
            <pb facs="9"/>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100450">Full many a winter have we seen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100460">And many storms withal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100470">Since here we saw a King or Queen</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100480">In pomp and princely pall. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100490">Wherefore make feast, and banquet still,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100500">And now to triumph fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100510">With duty let us show good will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100520">To glad both great and small. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100530">The dew of heaven. Etc. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A18729-e100540">
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100550">The realm throughout will ring of this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100560">And sundry regions more</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100570">Will say, full great our fortune is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100580">When our good hap they know. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100590">O Norwich, here the well spring runs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100600">Whose virtue still doth flow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100610">And lo this day doth shine two suns</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100620">Within thy walls also. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e100630">The dew of heaven. Etc. </l>
          </lg>
          <p xml:id="A18729-e100640">This song ended, her highness passed towards her lodging, and by the way in a churchyard, over against master pecks door (A worthy alderman) was a scaffold set up and bravely trimmed. On this scaffold, was placed an excellent boy, well and gallantly decked, in a long white robe of taffeta, a crimson scarf wrought with gold, folded on the Turkish fashion about his brows, and a gay garland of fine flowers on his head, which boy was not seen, till the Queen had a good season marked the music, which was marvelous sweet and good, albeit the rudeness of some ringer of bells did somewhat hinder the noise and harmony: and as soon as the music ended, the boy stepped reverently before the Queen, and spoke these words that follow.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A18729-e100650">
          <pb facs="10"/>
          <head>The boy's speech at master pecks door.</head>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100660">Great things were meant to welcome thee (O Queen,)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100670">If want of time had not cut off the same:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100680">Great was our wish, but small is that was seen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100690">For us to show, before so great a dame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100700">Great hope we have it pleased our prince's eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100710">Great were the harms that else our pains should reap:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100720">Our grace or foil, doth in your judgement lie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100730">If you mislike, our griefs do grow on heap:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100740">If for small things, we do great favour find,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100750">Great is the joy, that Norwich feels this day:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100760">If well we weighed the greatness of your mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100770">Few words would serve, we had but small to say. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100780">But knowing that your goodness takes things well</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100790">That well are meant, we boldly did proceed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100800">And so good Queen, both welcome and farewell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100810">Thine own we are, in heart, in word, and deed. </l>
          <p xml:id="A18729-e100820">The boy thereupon flang up his garland, and the Queen's highness said, this device is fine.</p>
          <p xml:id="A18729-e100830">Then the noise of music began again, to hear the which, the Queen stayed a good while, and after departed to the cathedral church, which was not far from thence. And the next day after, which was Sunday, when princes commonly come not abroad (And time is occupied with sermons, and laudable exercises) I was to watch a convenient season, where and how might be uttered the things that were prepared for pastime. And so upon Monday before supper, I made a device, as though Mercury had been sent from the gods, to request the Queen to come abroad, and behold what: was devised for her welcome, the whole matter whereof doth follow.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A18729-e100840">
          <pb facs="10"/>
          <head>Monday's device.</head>
          <head type="sub">The manner of Mercury's coach and message to the Queen, requesting her highness to come abroad, and see what pastime the gods had provided for a noble prince.</head>
          <p xml:id="A18729-e100850">The coach that Mercury came into 〈◊〉 Queen, was closely kept in secret a long season, and when the time came it must pass towards the court, it had a trumpeter with it, and the coachman was made to drive so fast, as the horses should seem to fly, which was so well observed, as the people wondered at the swiftness thereof, and followed it in such flocks and multitudes, that scarce in a great green (Where the preaching place is) might be found room for any more people. And when the coach approached in the hearing of a trumpet, the trumpeter sounded, and so came in to the green sounding, until the coach was full placed before a window at the which the Queen stood, and might be plainly seen, and openly viewed. When Mercury had espied her highness, he skipped out of the coach, and being on the ground, gave a n●●p or two, and advanced himself in such a sort, that the Queen smiled at theboldness of the boy. Thus Mercury beholding the Queen with great courage and audacity, at the length bowed down his head, and immediately stood bolt upright, and shaked his rod, and so began his speech with a most assured countenance, and bravely pronounced it in deed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A18729-e100860">
          <pb facs="11"/>
          <head>Mercury's speech.</head>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100870">Muse not good Queen at me that message brings</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100880">From love, or just 〈◊〉, lord of might,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100890">No earthly God, yet governs mortal things,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100900">And sprites divine, and shining angels bright. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100910">This lord of late to show his mighty power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100920">Hath wonders wrought, when world looked lest therefore:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100930">For at his beck, this day, and present hour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100940">The heavens shaked, the thunder bolts did roar. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100950">The earth did move, the dead therein did rise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100960">And out of grave, the ghosts of men are gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100970">The wand'ring sprites that hovered in the skies</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100980">Dropped down from air, for world to wonder on. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e100990">The saints themselves, that sat in glory great,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101000">Were sent in haste, to work Jehovah's will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101010">And I that oft my restless wings do beat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101020">Was called, to use my wings and office still. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101030">A common post is Mercury you know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101040">When he commands that made the world of naught,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101050">And flies as fast, as arrow out of bow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101060">When message may express Jehovah's thought. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101070">Whose power divine full long ere this hath seen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101080">That in this place should lodge a sacred Queen. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101090">And weighing well, the prince whereof I speak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101100">Might weary wax of common pastimes here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101110">(For that he knows her judgement is not weak,)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101120">Devised above, below there should appear</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101130">(To welcome her) some sights that rare should seem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101140">And careless stood, what world thereof did deem:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101150">So that good Queen, you take them well in worth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101160">No sooner had Jehovah meant these things,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101170">But clouds clapped hands, and souls of men came forth</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101180">Of heaven gates, yea goodly crowned Kings</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101190">Were flown abroad, from blessed Abraham's breast:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101200">Some in the air, and tops of trees did rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101210"><pb facs="11"/> some fell on 〈…〉 houses high,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101220">Some sunk in seas, 〈…〉 were drowned now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101230">And some did light on land where every eye</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101240">May them behold, and note their manners throw. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101250">And therewithal, the black infernal sprites</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101260">Ran out of hell, the earth so trembling than,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101270">And like young lads they hopped about the streets. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101280">The satires wild, in form and shape of man</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101290">Crept through the woods, and thickets full of briars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101300">The water nymphs, and fairies straight appears</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101310">In uncouth forms, and fashion strange to view:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101320">The hags of hell that hateful are of kind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101330">To please the time, had learned a nature new,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101340">And all those things that man can call to mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101350">Were glad to come, and do their duty throw. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101360">I seeing this, called for my coach in haste,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101370">Abide sir boy, then said Jehovah now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101380">Thou goest not yet, until a prince be placed</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101390">Where I appoint, thou hast nothing to say. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101400">Then still I stood, to know what should be done. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101410">With that, a swarm of people every way</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101420">Like little ants, about the fields 'gan run,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101430">Some to provide for pomp and triumph great,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101440">Some for good fare, yea household cates and meat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101450">And some they ran to seek where poets dwell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101460">To pen forth shows, and paint our trifles well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101470">Some hauled and pulled, to bring the carriage in,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101480">Some ran to gaze on triumph near at hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101490">And some stood mute, as they amazed had been</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101500">To see a court, and princely noble band</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101510">Come marching on, and make here their abode:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101520">But when I saw the carriage here unload,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101530">And well had weighed the wonders I have told,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101540">Oh mighty God (Quoth I) now give me leave</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101550">To go from thee, some message to unfold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101560">That by my speech the hearers may conceive</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101570">Thy godhead great, hath brought this Princess here. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101580"><pb facs="12"/>It shall be so (Quoth he) dispatch and 〈◊〉,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101590">And tell her, that she is to me so 〈◊〉. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101600">That I appoint by man's device and art,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101610">That every day she shall see sundry shoe●,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101620">If that she please to walk and take the air:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101630">And that so soon as out of door she goes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101640">(If time do serve, and weather wareth fair)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101650">Some odd device shall meet her highness straight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101660">To make her smile, and ease her burdened breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101670">And take away the cares and things of weight</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101680">That princes feel, that findeth greatest rest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101690">When I had thus received my charge at full,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101700">My golden rod in lively hand I took,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101710">And bad in haste my flying horses pull. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101720">But ear I passed, I 'gan about me look</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101730">To see that coach, and each thing gallant were:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101740">So down I came, all winged as you see. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101750">And since I have espied that Princess there,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101760">That greatest Kings do sue to by degree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101770">And many more that sues no whit, do fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101780">I kiss her steps, and show my master's will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101790">And leave with her such graces from above,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101800">As always shall command her people's love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101810">(Uphold her reign, maintain her regal state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101820">Find out false hearts, and make of subjects true,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101830">Plant perfect peace, and root up all debate)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101840">So with this grace, good Queen now here 〈◊〉,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101850">For I may now on earth no longer stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18729-e101860">Than servants must to masters will obey. </l>
          <p xml:id="A18729-e101870"><pb facs="12"/>Mercury having thus spoken to the Queen (Whose gracious inclination is such, as will not have any thing dutifully offered to pass unregarded) was well heard, her highness standing at a window, and (As I know,) the speech very well taken and understood. Mercury as he came, passed away, at whose coach the people (That had seldom seen such a device) marvelled, and gazed very much: for it had horses to draw it finely painted as winged, to as great show and order of that it presented, as wit might imagine: the coachman suitable to the same: and a trumpeter in right good garments, as decente for that purpose as could be devised. But the coach was made and framed on such a fashion, as few men have seen: the whole whereof was covered with birds, and naked sprites hanging by the heels in the air and clouds, cunningly painted out, as though by some thunder crack they had been shaken and tormented, yet stayed by power divine in their places, to make the more wonder and miraculous show. And on the middle of that coach stood a high compassed tower, bedecked with golden and gay jewels, in the top whereof was placed a fair plume of white feathers, all to be spanged and trimmed to the most bravery: Mercury himself in blue satin lined with cloth of gold, his garments cut and slashed on the finest manner, a peaked hat of the same colour, as though it should cut and sever the wind asunder, and on the same a pair of wings, and wings on his heels likewise. And on his golden rod were little wings also, about the which rod, were two wriggling or scrawling serpents, which seemed to have life when the rod was moved or shaken. So in this sort and form was Mercury and his coach set forth, and in deed at such a season, as a great number looked not for any show, nor things were ready, as some thought, to perform that was necessary and expected. Yet hap was so good, and the gracious favour of the prince, that all was well taken, and construed to the best meaning of the devisor. So ended that day's device, which offered occasion to further matter.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A18729-e101880">
          <pb facs="13"/>
          <head>Tuesday's device.</head>
          <p xml:id="A18729-e101890">At this season, although I was not well provided of things necessary for a show (By mean of some crossing causes in the city) yet hearing the Queen road abroad, determined as I might (And yet by help of friends and hap) very well to venture the hazard of a show, and to be full in the way where her highness should pass towards her dinner, in which determination many doubts were to be cast, and many men persuaded to tarry a better time, but considering how time rolled on, and days and hours did waste (Without doing any thing promised, and not performed) I hastily prepared my boys and men, with all their furnitures, and so set forward with two coaches, handsomely trimmed. The common people beholding the manner thereof, and greedy to gaze on that should been done, followed, as their fancies did lead them: so that when we came into the open field, there was as great a train and press about the show, as came with the court at that instant, which graced much the matter, and gave it some expected hope of good success: and for that you shall (And please you) imagine you see the thing, I have here set down the whole manner of the show, and after that every part as they were played, shall be here expressed.</p>
          <p xml:id="A18729-e101900">First, there is a feigned device, that Venus and Cupid were thrust out of heaven, and walking on the earth, met a philosopher, who demanded from whence they came, they told the philosopher what they were, and he replied, and began with troth and taunts to tickle them so near, that Venus fell in a great anger, and Cupid ran away, and left his mother and the philosopher disputing together, but Cupid because he would be nourished somewhere , ran to the court, and there sought for succour, and encountering the Queen, began to complain his state and his mothers, and told how the philosopher had handled them both: but<pb facs="13"/> finding neither answer nor aid, returned again, but not to his mother, for she was fallen mad (Upon a conceit that she was not made of) and Cupid wandering in the world, met with dame chastity and her maids, called modesty, Temperance, good exercise, and shamefastness, and she with her four maids encountering Cupid in a goodly coach, and without any honest guard waiting on him, set upon him, threw him out of his golden seat, trodden on his pomp, spoilt him of his counterfeit godhead and cloak, and took away his bow and his quiver of arrows, (The one headed with lead, and the other with gold) and so sent him like a fugitive away, and mounted up into the coach herself and her maids, and so came to the Queen, and rehearsed what had happened (Although this was done in her view) and because (Said chastity) that the Queen had chosen the best life, she gave theQueen Cupid's bow, to learn to shoot at whom she pleased, since none could wound her highness' heart, it was meet (Said chastity) that she should do with Cupid's bow and arrows what she pleased: and so did chastity depart as she said to the powers divine. Cupid in the meanwhile wandering in the world, had found out wantonness and riot, who soon fell in beggary and ruin (A spectacle to be looked into) and felt such daily misery with wantonness and riot, that Cupid was forced to fling away once again, and hazard himself to fall into the hands of naughty people, or where fortune assigned, and coming abroad, happened upon the philosopher, who talked with him again, and told him his errors, and other points of pride and presumption, declaring it was a great blaspheme and abuse, to report and believe that in heaven were any other gods but one, and he had the only rule of all, that made all of naught. In which reasoning and discourses, Cupid waxed warm, and yet in his greatest heat knew not how nor where to cool himself, at which time came wantonness and riot, and persuaded Cupid to play 〈◊〉 longer the fool (In striving with philosophers) and go away with them, so Cupid<pb facs="14"/> departed, and went away with wantonness and riot, and the philosopher remained, and declared that all abuses and folly's should come to no better end, than presently was expressed by the misery of wantonness, riot, and Cupid. Then modesty and her fellows, leaving their mistress dame chastity, with the powers divine, came soft and fair in their mistress coach, singing a song of chaste life, and when the song was ended, Modesty sent, as she said she was, from her mistress, spoke to the Queen a good season, and so the matter ended, for the which show, I had gracious words of the Queen openly and often pronounced by her highness. Now before you read the parts, you must thoroughly note what my discourse thereof hath been, and carrying that care and good will with you, the matter shall seem to have the better life, and I shall think my labour and study well bestowed.</p>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A18729-e101910">
            <head>Cupid coming, as he reports, out of heaven (From whence his mother and he is banished) encountres the Queen, and speaketh as followeth, he riding in a coach: and you must presuppose, that before his coming to the Queen, he and his mother had met with the philosopher.</head>
            <div type="subsection" xml:id="A18729-e101920">
              <head>The show of chastity.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e101930">Alas poor boy, where shalt thou wander not,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e101940">I am thrust out of heaven in despite,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e101950">My mother too begins to bend the brow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e101960">For both we walk, as we were banished quite. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e101970">She mourns and weeps, and blubbers like a child,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e101980">By which great grief, in rage now may she fall,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e101990">And I have leave to walk the wood so wild,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102000">To howl, to cry, and ●ore complain withal. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102010">For lo of late, where she and I did go,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102020">A man we met, a father grave and wise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102030"><pb facs="14"/> who 〈…〉 you the troth will know)</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102040">We were the dro●●e, 〈…〉 of earth and 〈◊〉</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102050">Fond 〈…〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102060">A lewd delight, a flying fancy light,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102070">A shadow fond, that 〈◊〉 no shape, but name. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102080">The whole abuse of each good wit or wight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102090">An idle ground, whereon vain poets walk,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102100">A cause of ●are, a spring where folly ●●oes</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102110">A wicked mean, to nourish wanton talk,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102120">And to conclude, sharp nettle under rose</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102130">We were: thus said the father that we me●. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102140">My mother blushed, these thundering words to hear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102150">And from them both, away in haste ● get,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102160">To see if I in court find better cheere,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102170">But if no friend, nor favour I may find,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102180">Nor answer have of that which here I speak,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102190">Farewell, I seek my fortune in the wind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102200">For Cupid hath in head 〈…〉. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102210">If heaven's 〈…〉</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102220">In earth below, I 〈◊〉 to hide my face. </l>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A18729-e102230">
            <head>Chastity suddenly in the view of the Queen, sets upon Cupid, and spoils him of his coach,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A18729-e102240">music the mean tyme.</note> bow and all, and sets him afoot, and so rides, in his coach to the Queen, and speaks as followeth.</head>
            <div type="subsection" xml:id="A18729-e102250">
              <head>Chastity speaketh.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102260">To strive with boys that stands on brags and braves</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102270">I thought great scorn, till Cupid I espied,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102280">But that proud lad, that makes so many 〈◊〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102290">Must needs find one, to daunt his peacock's pride. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102300">Dame chastity is she that wins the field,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102310">Whose breast is armed with thoughts of virtue's 〈◊〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102320">Who to the fight doth bring no glittering shield,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102330">But clean conceits, which pure and blessed are,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102340"><pb facs="15"/> that strikes down lust, and tames the wilful mind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102350">Maintains the just, and holds up learning both;</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102360">And wisdom great, through me the sages find,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102370">Philosophers, the lovers of the troth. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102380">Yea Kings and Queens by me work wonders still,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102390">Do conquer realms, and wisdom do attain. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102400">The studious minds, whose knowledge, wit, and skill,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102410">And all the world doth fame and glory gain</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102420">That chastely lives, it talks with God above,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102430">It climbs the clouds from pomp and pleasures vain. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102440">It is a thing that shining angels love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102450">And in the world to come shall live and reign. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102460">It triumph makes of fickle fond desire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102480">It breeds great force and courage still in men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102490">It quencheth sparks and flames of fancies fire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102500">It quicks the wits, and helps the art of pen,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102510">Yea all good gifts from chastity doth rise</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102520">That worthy are of honour under skies. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102530">Then sith (O Queen) chaste life is thus thy choice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102540">And that thy heart is free from bondage yoke,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102560">Thou shalt (Good Queen) by my consent and voice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102570">Have half the spoil, take either bow or cloak. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102580">The bow (I think) more fit for such a one</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102590">In fleshly form, that bears a heart of stone</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102600">That none can wound, nor pierce by any mean. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102610">Wherefore take here the bow, and learn to shoot</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102620">At whom thou wilt, thy heart it is so clean,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102630">Blind Cupid's bolts therein can take no root. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102640">Now will I say in this poor coach of mine,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102650">To mount the skies, and see the god's divine. </l>
              <p xml:id="A18729-e102660">Cupid comes running afoot like a vagabond towards the Queen, from wantonness and riot where he was succoured, and meets again in open show the philosopher, whose habitation was in a rock, and the philosopher demands of Cupid where he hath been, and what is the cause he comes abroad in such disorder.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection" xml:id="A18729-e102670">
              <pb facs="15"/>
              <head>The philosopher speaketh.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102680">How now my friend, where hast thou 〈◊〉 other plight I trow</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102690">Thou wast, when lately I thee met, hath Cupid lost his bow? </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102700">His cloak? his coach: his wit and all? and fled from mother's face? </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102710">Or else hath Cupid gone to school, to learn some pretty grace? </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102720">To play the god, fie foolish boy, leave of these toys in time,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102730">Thy mother (As the poets fain,) when beauty was in prime</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102740">A strumpet was, it may be so, as well appeareth yet,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e102750">Thou art not of the race of gods, thou art some beggars chit. </l>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e102760" who="A18729-cupid">
                <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102770">Nay doting fool, that still dost pore on books,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102780">Though coach be gone, and golden cloak be lost,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102790">Yet like a god, I tell thee Cupid looks,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102800">When old grey beard shows like a rotten post. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102810">It ill becomes an aged man to rail</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102820">On women thus, that are not now in place,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102830">But sure thy words are spent to small avail,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102840">They can not blot my mother, nor my race. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e102850" who="A18729-philosopher">
                <speaker>Philosopher.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102860">But dost thou think thou art a God: then show some proof thereof. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e102870" who="A18729-cupid">
                <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102880">That can I do, but you old men, with boys will jest and scoff,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102890">And either laugh to scorn our words, or taunt us passed the nick. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e102900" who="A18729-philosopher">
                <speaker>Philosopher.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102910">Believe not that, but when in deed we enter near the quick,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102920">Ye wink like colts, and fling away from wit and feeling seen,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102930">Well Cupid, prove thou art a God, and show some good defence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102940">To this thy talk, I will give ear, and silence keep a while,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102950">Until thy words have gone so far, thy folly makes me smile. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e102960" who="A18729-cupid">
                <pb facs="16"/>
                <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102970">The greatest clerks that erst have been, three thousand years ago,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102980">When they on Venus' talk or treat, takes Cupid's part ye know. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e102990">Their books, their scrolls, their pamphlets large, makes mention of my name,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103000">You need no further search for proof, to try out Cupid's fame. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e103010" who="A18729-philosopher">
                <speaker>Philosopher.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103020">Boast not of books, for books they be, that plainly witness bears</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103030">How Cupid's art infects good minds, and cankers honest ears. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103040">And though fond men in liables show on you a flourish fine,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103050">Such gewgaws 'grees not with good rules, nor holds on gifts divine. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e103060" who="A18729-cupid">
                <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103070">Why sir, you will believe, that Jove and many more</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103080">Of other gods in heaven are, where I have been before? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e103090" who="A18729-philosopher">
                <speaker>Philosopher.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103100">In heaven? there you trip, why boy how came you thence? </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103110">You went abroad to take the air, and have been walking sense</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103120">Like daws along the coast, oh boy, thy proof is bare,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103130">In heaven is but one that rules, no other gods there are. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e103140" who="A18729-cupid">
                <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103150">And doth not Jove and Mars bear sway? 〈◊〉 that is true. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e103160" who="A18729-philosopher">
                <speaker>Philosopher.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103170">Then put in Tom and Tib, and all bears sway as much as you. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e103180" who="A18729-cupid">
                <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103190">I told you sir before, your taunting tongue would bite. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e103200" who="A18729-philosopher">
                <speaker>Philosopher.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103210">I come too near the sore, and please not your delight. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103220">But since you 〈◊〉 for naught, and can not hear the truth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103230"><pb facs="16"/> I will not shame my hoary hairs, to strive with wanton youth. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103240">This Cupid, Venus' son, as men suppose to be,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103250">Is neither god nor man in form, nor monster as you see,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103260">But such a kind of shade, as can no substance shoe,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103270">Begotten by brainless blind delight, and nursed with nature's foe. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103280">Fed up with faithless food, and trained in trifling toys,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103290">Awaked with vice, and lulled asleep again with irksome joys. </l>
              </sp>
              <stage xml:id="A18729-e103300">Wantonness and riot comes in, and talks with Cupid, and so takes him away.</stage>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e103310" who="A18729-wantonness">
                <speaker>Wantonness.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103320">Art thou so fond to talk with doting age,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103330">This man did bring thy mother in a rage,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103340">And told her plain, a goddess feigned she was,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103350">Most lewd of life, and brittle as the glass,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103360">I wantonness know well that tale is true,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103370">To this my friend now riot what say you? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e103380" who="A18729-riot">
                <speaker>Riot.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103390">I could say much, but I will hold my peace,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103400">Foul is that bird that his own nest defiles. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103410">If riot should not speak, that Venus knows so well,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103420">(With whom since Cupid bore a name, did wanton Venus dwell)</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103430">Much pity were it sure, that riot life should bear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103440">For I am father of delight and pleasure everywhere . </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103450">Without the help of whom, dame Venus can not live,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103460">For unto lust and riot both, doth Venus honour give. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103470">And lust is riots joy, a spright that pleads for place</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103480">In every soil, since world began to boast of Adam's race. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103490">And now to tell you plain, from me, or from my stock,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103500">(An endless swarm of idle of folk, a merry careless flock)</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103510">As prating poets fain, at first did Venus spring,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103520">But Venus was no strumpet sure; she was some finer thing</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103530">That always furthers love, in French a 〈◊〉 ● plain,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103540">A better of good bargains oft, and root of fancies vain. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103550"><pb facs="17"/>Though goddess were she not, yet fair and fine was she,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103560">As I have heard good clerks report, and you in books shall 〈◊〉</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103570">Of her great stories made, and great account this day</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103580">We make of Venus' darlings still, wherefore in brief to say,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103590">Both I and thousands more, with 〈◊〉 needs must hold. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103600">'Twas she, to whom King Priam's son did give the apple of gold</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103610">That cost so many 〈◊〉 but r●●de the siege of troy,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103620">And you shall see what pretty pranks the mother and this boy</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103630">Hath played in many parts, my knowledge is but small,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103640">I tell by hearsay many things, but am not learned at all</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103650">Good wantonness thou knowest, but pass o'er that awhile</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103660">I could tell tales of Venus yet, would make the hearers smile. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e103670" who="A18729-wantonness">
                <speaker>Wantonness.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103680">O speak no more, come comfort Cupid now ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103690">Let Venus go, that ●ate and saw with eye</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103700">The order great, and all the manner how</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103710">Dame chastity did mount to starry sky</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103720">With such a coach, and such a noble spoil,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103730">As seldom hath in heaven oft been seen. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103740">She said, when she had Cupid put to foil,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103750">She gave his bow and shafts unto a Queen. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103760">And Cupid straight came running unto me. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103770">I saw him bare, and sent him bare away,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103780">And as we are in deed but bore all three,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103790">So must we part as poorly as we may. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103800">No reasoning here with him that learned is,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103810">Philosophers knows more than wanton fools,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103820">If we had once been beaten well ere this</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103830">And loud our books, and truly plied our schools,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103840">We had been learned, yea lived, and felt no lack,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103850">Where now our wealth is all upon our back. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e103860" who="A18729-unassigned">
                <speaker>Riot.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103870">By sweet saint John we are in goodly weeds,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103880">To dance with bells a morris through the streets. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103890"><pb facs="17"/>If any here, three idle people needs,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103900">Call us in time, for we are fine for sheets:</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103910">Yea, for a shift, to steal them from the hedge,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103920">And lay both sheets, and linen all to gauge. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103930">We are best be gone, lest some do hear allege</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103940">We are but rogues, and clap us in the cage. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103950">Come Cupid come, if thou wilt hear a song,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103960">Dame chastity hath sent her coach along,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103970">To comfort those, that daily lives in woe. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A18729-e103980" who="A18729-cupid">
                <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e103990">Nay Cupid will, go hang himself i trow. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e104000">Much better were, to fall on point of knife,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e104010">Than from rich state, to lead a beggar's life. </l>
              </sp>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A18729-e104020">
            <head>Cupid, wantonness, and riot, departs, and the coach softly comes on, with such music as is devised, and sings not, until the coach be before the Queen, in the meanwhile the philosopher speaketh.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e104030" who="A18729-philosopher">
              <speaker>Philosopher.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104040">Now world may judge what fables are, and what vain gods their be,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104050">What names and titles foundlings give, to them, likewise you see,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104060">And that one god alone doth rule, the rest no virtue show,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104070">Vain Venus and blind Cupid both, and all the ragment row</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104080">And rabble of gods, are feigned things, to make the season short,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104090">As wisdom knows that well can weigh, the worth and weight of sport. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104100">Through trifles light, sad things are seen, through vice is virtue found,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104110">By hollow ways, and crooked paths, appears the plainest ground. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104120">Thus leaving unto wisdom's reach, the things that here are done,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104130">And fearing foil, if here we should, in further folly run,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104140">We stay, save that, some music comes, to knit in order due,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104150">The substance of this 〈◊〉 show, that we present to you. </l>
            </sp>
            <div type="subsection" xml:id="A18729-e104160">
              <pb facs="18"/>
              <head>Modesty speaketh.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104170">Dame chastity we serve, and wait upon her still,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104180">Save now, that she is called to clouds, to know 〈◊〉 will. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104190">She bade us walk abroad, and search, where might be seen</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104200">In stately troop, and royal court, a worthy noble Queen. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104210">Salute her in my name, and look in secret sort</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104220">(Quoth she) you do with all your force, maintain her princely port. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104230">Good exercise as chief, thy humble duty do,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104240">Let shamefastness, and modesty, and sober temperance too,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104250">Attend as handmaids still, upon that sacred dame. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104260">We hearing what our mistress said, and marking well the same,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104270">Did haste us hither straight, but ere we went at large,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104280">Jehovah sent us graces great, and gave us pour and charge,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104290">(When pomp is most in place) to creep in princely heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104300">And gide the mind, and thoroughly search, the soul and every part. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104310">That still the fear of God, be burning in her breast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104320">There is the only house oh Queen, where we four maids will rest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104330">There we will service show, there shall our 〈◊〉 bud,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104340">There is the plot, the seat, the soil, and place to do most good. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104350">Yea under richest robes, we have a power to go,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104360">In fairest weeds are cleanest thoughts, and purest minds I know. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104370">The earlish country cloyne, yea clad in smeared cloak,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104380">With cankered heart, and currish looks, sits grinning in the smoke. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104390">The comely clean attire, doth carry mind aloft,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104400">Makes man think scorn to stoop to vice, and look to virtue oft. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104410">The sun that shineth bright, hath virtues manifold,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104420">A gallant flower hath pleasant smell, great goodness is in gold. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104430">So gay and glittering dame, thy graces are not small,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104440">Thy heavenly gifts in greatest press, in deed surmounts them all. </l>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A18729-e104450">
          <pb facs="18"/>
          <head>Wednesday.</head>
          <p xml:id="A18729-e104460">The Wednesday her highness' 〈◊〉 at my lord of Surrey's, where were the French ambassadors also, and a most rare and delicate dinner and banquet. At which season I did watch with a show (Called manhood and desert,) at my lord of Surrey's back door, going to the Queen's barge: but the row●e was so little, that neither the shot, the armed men, nor the players, could have place convenient: whereupon we took boats, and conveyed our people down the water, towards a landing place that we hoped the Queen would come unto. And there having all things in a readiness, hovered on the water thrée long hours, by which mean the night came on, and so we were fain to withdraw ourselves and go homeward, trusting for a better time and occasion, which in deed was offered the next day after by the Queen's majesties own good motion, who told me she would see what pastimes were prepared, as hereafter you shall perceive by the discourse of these matters that I mean to make, and by this show of manhood, and the show of the nymphs, which I mind fully and truly to treat of.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A18729-e104470">
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <head>Thursday.</head>
          <p xml:id="A18729-e104480">The Thursday in the morning, my lord chamberlain gave me warning the Queen's highness would ride abroad in the afternoon , and he commanded me to be ready, dutifully to present her with some show. Then knowing which way the Queen would ride (By conjecture and instructions given) I caused a place to be made and digged for the nymphs of the water, the manner and proportion whereof, was in this form and fashion. First, there was measure taken for thréescore foot of ground every way, the hole to be made deep and four square, which ground was covered with a canvas painted green like the grass, and at every side on the canvas, ran a string through curtain rings, which string might easily be drawn any kind of way, by reason of two great poles that lay along in the ground, and answered the curtain or canvas on each side so, that drawing a small cord in the middle of the canvas, the earth would seem to open, and so shut again, as theother end of the cord was drawn backward. And in the same cave was a noble noise of music of all kind of instruments, severally to be sounded and played upon, and at one time they should be sounded all together, that might serve for a consort of broken music. And in the same cave likewise was placed twelve water nymphs, disguised or dressed most strangely, each of them had either upon white silk, or fine linen, green sedges, stitched cunningly on a long garment, so well wrought, and set on, as scarce 〈◊〉 whit might be perceived. And every nymph had in her hand a great bundle of bulrushes, and had on her head a garland of lavender the which ivy was a coif of moss, and under the moss was there long goodly hair like golden tresses that covered her shoulders, and in a manner, raught down unto her middle. And touching the beauty of the nymphs, they ●rmed to be the chosen children of a world, and became their<pb facs="19"/> attire so well, that their beauty might have abused a right good judgement, for divers of those that knew them before, (Albeit they were bare faced) could scarce know them in their garments, and sundry took them to be young girls and wenches, prepared for the nonce, to procure a laughter. These nymphs thus apparelled, and all things in very good plight and readiness, there was devised, that at the Queens coming near the water side (As this cave stood at the brim of the river) one nymph should pop up out of the cave first, and salute the Queen with a speech, and then another, and so till four of them had finished their speeches, there they should remain, and when they retired into their cave, the music should begin, which sure had been a noble hearing, and the more melodious, for the variety thereof, and because it should come secretly and strangely out of the earth. And when the music was done, then should all the twelve nymphs have issued together, and danced a dance with timbrels that were trimmed with bells, and other jangling things, which timbrels were as broad as a sieve, having bottoms of fine parchment, and being sounded, made such a confused noise, and pastime, that it was to be wondered at, besides the strangeness of the timbrels (Yet known to our forefathers) was a matter of admiration to such as were ignorant of that new found toy, gathered and borrowed from our elders. So in order and readiness stood that show for the time. And to keep that show company (But yet far off) stood the show of manhood and Dezart, as first to be presented, and that show was as well furnished as the other, men all, saving one boy, called beauty, for the which manhood, favour, and desert, did strive (Or should have contended) but good fortune (As victor of all conquests) was to come in, and overthrow manhood, favour, desert, and all their powers, and only by fine force (Upon a watchword spoken) should lay hand on beauty, and carry or lead her away. The other suitors troubled with this kind of dealing, should talk together, and swear to be in one mind, for an open revenge, and upon that fortune should cry arm, arm. <pb facs="20"/>The other side called for their friends, at which 〈◊〉 should appear both their strengths: but good fortune should fair in power exceed his enemies: and yet to show that destiny, (And who best can conquer) shall govern all, fortune should make an offer, that sir to six with sword and target should end the brawl and business: then six gentlemen on either side with rebated swords and targets (Only in doublet and hose, and Morion on head) approached, and would claim the combat, and deal together twelve blows a piece, and in the end fortune should be victor: and then the shot, and armed men should fall at variance so sharply (Upon mistaking of the matter) that fortune's side should triumph and march over the bellies of their enemies: in which time was legs and arms of men (Well and lively wrought) to be let fall in numbers on the ground, as bloody as might be. Fortune regarding nothing but victory, marcheth so away in great triumph, and then should have come into the place a doleful song for the death of manhood, favour, and deserts, and so the show should have ended. But now note what befell after this great business and preparation, for as the Queen's highness was appointed to come to her coach, and the lords and courtiers were ready to mount on horseback, there fell such a shower of rain (And in the neck thereof came such a terrible thunder) that every one of us were driven to seek for covert and most comfort, in so much, that although some of us in boat stood under a bridge, we were all so dashed and washed, thatit was a greater pastime to see us look like drowned rats, than to have beheld the uttermost of the shows rehearsed. Thus you see, a show in the open field is always subject to the sudden change of weather, and a number of more inconveniences than jerpresse. But what should I say of that which the city lost by this cause, velvets, silks, tinsels, and some cloth of gold, being cut out for these purposes, and could not serve to any great effect after. Well, there was no more to say, but an old adage, that man doth purpose, and God doth dispose, to whose disposition and pleasure I<pb facs="20"/> commit the guide of greater matters. So this 〈◊〉 took his leave from us, and left us looking one upon another, and he that thought he had received most injury, kept greatest silence, and lapping up, among a bundle of other misfortunes this evil chance, every person quietly passed to his lodging. The next day was the Queen to depart the town, and I fearing that all my labour should be lost, devised to convert the nymphs of the water, to the fairies on the land, as hereafter shall appear: in the meanwhile I have set down the four speeches that four nymphs should have spoken at the waterside, where the Queen was looked for: and withal, I have written the order and parts of the show of manhood and deserts, that no one thing that was well meant, should sleep in silence. And first and formost you must conceive, that the show of manhood was invented to be played in a garden, or wheresoever had been found a convenient place, the prince then being in presence. And unto her highness should there have come a lady called beauty, humbly on knees, requiring aid and succour, or else judgement, in a matter disputable, and in great controversy, upon whose suit and humble intercession, the disputation was to begin in order as followeth, in manner of a dialogue, the parts whereof are here for you to read at your leisure, and after the same, as the show of the nymphs should have been, shall their parts follow in like sort.</p>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A18729-e104490">
            <pb facs="21"/>
            <head>First, lady beauty speaketh, and she attired in very goodly garments as becometh such a dame.</head>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e104500">Most royal prince, speed on thy comely pace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e104510">Make haste in time, to do thy subjects good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e104520">Go run with me, to stay this heavy case,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e104530">Take pains good Queen, to gain the guiltless blood. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e104540">In one man's life, save lives of many more,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e104550">Save him in whom, the state of others stays,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e104560">For I poor wretch, God knows am minded so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e104570">With him to live, with him to end my days. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e104580">Who now in force, of tyrant's hands doth lie,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e104590">And vainly strives, to scape his helpless fate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e104600">Who seeth his death, and doleful date so nigh,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18729-e104610">Go haste to help, and yet perhaps too late. </l>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e104620" who="A18729-manhood">
              <speaker>Manhood.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104630">Yet were I best, to kill this peevish boy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104640">Whom now she makes, her chief and sole delight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104650">In whom she finds, such pleasure and such joy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104660">That causeless I, am clean defaced quite. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104670">Such gaudies gay, are in his peacock's face,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104680">And skin smooth up, with show of idle hue,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104690">That I do lodge, and languish in disgrace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104700">Though she of me, hath proof of promise true. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104710">Well, make thy choice ▪ and see what likes thee best,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104720">View he ere the death, of this thy darling now,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104730">Or yield thy love, to fancy my request,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104740">Whose manly force, shall win the conquest throw. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e104750" who="A18729-beauty">
              <speaker>Beauty.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104760">Naught shalt thou win, by that which I shall lose,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104770">Thou ge●st no gains, though I be thus bereft,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104780">And though that I, between two mischiefs goes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104790">Where naught but bale, and wretched woe is less ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104800"><pb facs="21"/> yet thy reward, which dost assault my friend,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104810">(In whose delight, my heart was fed long while)</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104820">Shall be disdain, and hatred in the end,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104830">A guerdo●●itte, for such a tyrant vile. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e104840" who="A18729-manhood">
              <speaker>Manhood.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104850">This wretch is he, by whom I am annoyed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104860">He hath thy heart, though I deserve the same,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104870">If wisely then, I do my harms avoid,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104880">Why stay I sword, I can not purchase blame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104890">By cutting off, the cause of my distress,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104900">When he is gone, my let shall be the less. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e104910" who="A18729-beauty">
              <speaker>Beauty.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104920">How canst thou say, thou dost deserve my heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104930">Which killest my heart, and causest all my woe,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e104940" who="A18729-manhood">
              <speaker>Manhood.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104950">Since that thou takest, my dealing in such part,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104960">I will delight, to wreak my wrath on foe. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104970">In grieving thee, most glad to hear me groan,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e104980">And art most pleased, when manhood makes his moan. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e104990" who="A18729-beauty">
              <speaker>Beauty.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105000">O gracious prince, to thee my moan I make,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105010">And prostrate fall, oh prince before thy foot,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105020">With wonted grace, on me some pity take,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105030">Oh salve my sore, let sorrow find some boot. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105040">I swelled in sighs, and sure shall die to see</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105050">My friend dispatched, and murdered in this wise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105060">Oh bid the wretch, come thrust his sword in me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105070">For from my love, the cause of grief doth rise. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105080">I made the fault, then punish me therefore,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105090">Shall silly lamb, be led to slaughter thus? </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105100">Do either help, with death my endless sore,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105110">Or with remorse, and ruth the case discuss,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105120">If he do die, by mighty Jove I swear</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105130">I will not live, if sword or knife be found,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105140"><pb facs="22"/> with scratched face, 〈…〉 ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105150">I know at first, my 〈…〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105160">And then ad●●, my 〈…〉, steal away</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105170">Oh Queen, in haste, 〈…〉</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e105180" who="A18729-manhood">
              <speaker>Manhood.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105190">Since 〈◊〉 oh prince, forbidst revenge to take,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105200">〈◊〉 wilt that men ▪ should lose their time in love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105210">Then mark my case, and give me leave to make</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105220">Mine own defence, and 〈◊〉 allege and prove,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105230">And I will show 〈◊〉 right and title good,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105240">And that I do, deserve the 〈…〉. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105250">Though this fond wretch, always my suit withstood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105260">As one who long, 〈…〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105270">Whom lewd delight, hath led out of the way,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105280">(Which good advice, and ord●ed judgement keep)</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105290">Whom beauty's blast hath sounst against the 〈◊〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105300">Where craggy tockes, and sands lie ●idde in deep,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105310">A fond device to trust to paynted face,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105320">And fasten faith upon so fickle ●l●y,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105330">To whom dame Hebe, lends often guileful grace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105340">Which every year and day doth pluck away,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105350">Whom sickness spoils, and 〈…〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105360">Whom time doth eat and age 〈…〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105370">Whom cares of mind do shake and alter so,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105380">As winter winds defaceth 〈…〉 ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105390">A snare for wit, a b●yte for wanton youth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105400">A false conceit, an error of the mind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105410">A fond delight, wherein there is no truth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105420">A poisoned dish, that doth the reason blind ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105430">A colour cast on things that are but 〈◊〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105440">A glorious show, to shroud a homely part,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105450">A rule to run, a lewd and reckless 〈◊〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105460">A deep deceit, which daunteth oft the heart. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105470">In rage of youth, these pricking thistles grows,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105480">Pages riot reigns, and folly bears the sway</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105490"><pb facs="22"/> in hoary age, 〈…〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105500">Where 〈…〉. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105510">The weaker sex, in 〈…〉</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105520">The infant hath, the, 〈…〉 ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105530">The hurtful weed, which 〈…〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105540">To view of eye, doth 〈…〉. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105550">In outward shower, in deed the trust in small,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105560">They are but cloaks, and 〈…〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105570">The virtuous mind, and 〈…〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105580">Which gains 〈…〉. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105590">Dame Venus loves, the 〈◊〉 and warlike knight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105600">Though once alas, she loud 〈…〉. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105610">And ladies which, do love 〈…〉,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105620">Love such as can, their 〈…〉. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105630">What could this 〈…〉 ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105640">Whom could this 〈…〉</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105650">Judge thou oh Queen, which of us two could make</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105660">The better shift, and force the worst to yield. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e105670" who="A18729-favour">
              <speaker>Good favour.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105680">Yet let me plead, my cause before my Queen</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105690">As thou hast done, and sentence after crave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105700">Then shall the truth, of our two 〈◊〉 be seen,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105710">I crave no spoil, but wish the thing I have. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105720">Why should my beauty, purchase my 〈◊〉 ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105730">Why should my praise, become 〈…〉 ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105740">Why should dame nature's gifts be thought so base,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105750">Which heretofore have been in greater name? </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105760">Who ever could, enforce the gods with might,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105770">To yield themselves, as conquered with his strength? </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105780">Yet beauty hath, subdued them with his sight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105790">And made them send, and bow to him at length. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105800">Whom force subdues, with sad unwilling heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105810">Submits themselves, and grieve at every stroke:</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105820">Who beauty wins, and gains unto his part,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105830">They gladly grant, to take the pleasant yoke. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105840"><pb facs="23"/>Thy strength thou mayst, full many a winter ●●ide,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105850">Till time doth serve, to show the same in place,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105860">Sweet beauty can, no moment be unspied,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105870">But doth delight, each one with gladsome grace. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105880">Dame nature's show, and riches beauty is,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105890">A heavenly gift, to ravish every eye,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105900">A perfect pearl, wherein is naught but bliss,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105910">Delight of men, delight of gods on high. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105920">Apollo pleased, himself with golden hair,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105930">H●a●e delights, the gods with comely ●●ue,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105940">God Venus oft, her tender breast did tear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105950">When she Adonis death was fain to 〈◊〉. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105960">Phoebus did mourn, when his delight was slain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105970">With great mishap, and error of his hand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105980">But Ganymede, above with Jove doth reign. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e105990">And waiting on, his nectars cup doth stand. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106000">What should I speak, of him who at the brook,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106010">The wanton nymphs, in love surprised away,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106020">Or him whom Phoeb, in to her chariot took,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106030">Or him, whose beauty died the morning grey,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106040">The gods in beauty, pass each mortal wight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106050">And men surmount, in form the fairest beast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106060">And yet of them, some are more brave in sight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106070">Whose natures are, more fined than the rest. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106080">The ugly toad, swel● out his poison cold,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106090">A crabbed corpse, comes of a churlish kind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106100">No ragged mould, the virtue rare can hold,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106110">A seemly face, declares a modest mind. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106120">The fairest horse will swiftest run his race,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106130">The gallantest hound, will soonest wind his game,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106140">What need I more, to treat upon this case,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106150">The hearers shall, be judgers of the same,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106160">If beauty's gifts, and favour you exile,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106170">Than manhood must, be here preferred the while. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e106180" who="A18729-desert">
              <pb facs="23"/>
              <speaker>Dezart.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106190">Stay judgement prince, and let my case be know</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106200">Whose friendly toil, deserves to rea●e his gain</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106210">Mine earnest suit, may not be thus oveerthrown,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106220">So long employed, in hope and endless pain. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106230">I see these men, press boldly here in place,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106240">Unfolds great words, and long debates the case:</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106250">And braves it out, with goodly gallant shows,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106260">Which I will not, eclipse nor blot at all,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106270">My claim is good, and that just God he knows,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106280">What need I then, my right in question call. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106290">I have no force, nor skill in martial field,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106300">I boast not of my fresh and flowering hue,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106310">Nor yet need not, in any point to yield,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106320">That can allege, deserts and service true. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106330">My travel then, and truth may not be lost,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106340">Nor my good will, be recompensed with wrong ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106350">Nor he that hath, with tempests sore been tossed ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106360">And tasted griefs, and bitter torments long,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106370">May not so soon, be shaken off for naught,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106380">I take fine terms ▪ to show my secret thought:</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106390">The gods accepts, our duty in good part,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106400">The prince rewards, the bills of our request,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106410">The greatest men, consider but the heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106420">The friendly means, can tame the wildest beast. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106430">And women who, in softest moulds be cast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106440">Whose tender hearts, rues on our careful cries,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106450">Must needs be won, with loving means at last,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106460">To ease our plaints, and wipe our watered eyes. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106470">True love of right, must recompensed be,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106480">Dezart must needs, fly far beyond the rest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106490">Then grant oh prince, this precious prize to me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e106500">Whose loyal love, claims place above the best. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e106510" who="A18729-fortune">
              <pb facs="24"/>
              <speaker>Good fortune.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A18729-e106520">
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106530">Much words are spent, where speech shall not prevail,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106540">Long time is lost, in threats and fond dispute,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106550">Though I good hap, have born but simple sail,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106560">And went aloof, 'tis I must end this suit,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106570">And reason bring, as victor of the field,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106580">Unto whose troth, your weak discourse shall yield. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A18729-e106590">
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106600">Fair beauty here, for whom you foundlings strive,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106610">May move, I grant, a god to like her well,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106620">But though she were, the fairest thing alive,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106630">(As sure indeed, her beauty doth excel)</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106640">Is that a proof, that you in love must fall,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106650">With that which naught pertains to you at all? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A18729-e106660">
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106670">Admit her mind, by mean of some conceit,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106680">With sweet delight, of fancy may be led,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106690">Your eager eyes, most greedy of such bait,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106700">In forward hope, a season hath been fed. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106710">Shall she be spoilt, for favour she bestows</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106720">In friendly sort, and not in faithful wise? </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106730">Nay sure, she shall, ne fame nor freedom lose,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106740">For frailties faults, or use of gracious eyes. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106750">But to the point, and purpose of your strife,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106760">One pleads good will, by shape and favour got,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106770">(A gallant boy, to please a pleasant wife)</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106780">Another tells a penned tale by rote,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106790">Bedecked and filled with inkhorn terms enough. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106800">The third comes in, and calls himself Dezart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106810">And each of them are seen in stories throw,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106820">And finely seeks to conquer love by art. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106830">Great sleight is used, and clerkly cunning both,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106840">To force a right, and judgement in this case,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106850">Dezart, he tells a trim discourse of troth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106860">The 〈◊〉 wig makes boast of shining face. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106870"><pb facs="24"/>And courage he, by manhood claimeth all. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106880">Great points they are, that pleaded are this day,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106890">And unto whom, the lady now should fall,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106900">Some doubts may rise, if reason bore the sway. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106910">But to be brief, fair shape and comely port,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106920">The wise men hold, but outward blossoms vain,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106930">And manhood's force, may here be knit up short,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106940">Stout hearts may not, alone the glory gain:</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106950">Nor yet desert, that nearest goes the goal,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106960">May win the prize, and thrust his better back,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106970">For he it is, that hath the greatest dole,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106980">That doth in deed, no piece of fortune lack. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e106990">Good fortune still, a lord of worldly chance</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107000">Is only judge, himself, of all is done,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107010">Bid strength stand back, good fortune leads the dance,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107020">Fine shape likewise, with fortune dare not run. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107030">Dezart is dead, where fortune men advance. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107040">So here I prove, since I good fortune have,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107050">This dame is mine, her destiny wills it so,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107060">In mother's womb, the gods this gift me gave,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107070">She ordained was, with me away to go. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107080">Each worldly grace, and rule with fortune flies,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107090">A wife must needs, then stoop to destiny's lot. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107100">Wherefore I here, possess this noble prize,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107110">As jewel rich, by hap and fortune got. </l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107120">Who strives to take, her now from me by force,</l>
                <l xml:id="A18729-e107130">Shall have withal, my breath and vital corpse. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A18729-e107140">Then talk the other thrée privily together, and manhood speaks to good fortune as follows.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e107150" who="A18729-manhood">
              <speaker>Manhood.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107160">Methinks most fond, and weakly comes be here</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107170">Alone to three, if we together stood:</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107180">And though in deed, we buy the quarrel dear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107190">And pay therefore, the sweetest of our blood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107200"><pb facs="25"/> yet let us show, the noble hearts of men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107210">For since he say, we all our labour lose,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107220">Not one of us, shall need to sorrow then,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107230">Nor care a fig, howe'er the matter goes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e107240" who="A18729-desert">
              <speaker>Dezart.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107250">Agreed , though I Dezart have double wrong,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107260">I will revenge the same by dint of sword,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107270">And you shall see, I will not dally long</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107280">To do my best, sith I have spoke the word. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107290">Despaired men, dare fight with fortune still,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107300">And scratch for life, as long as breath will last,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107310">When hope is gone, I know no better skill,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107320">But bide the brunt, till all the broil be passed. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107330">Let love and life, together make an end,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107340">The heart shall feel, and hand shall head defend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A18729-e107350" who="A18729-favour">
              <speaker>Good favour.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107360">Though I speak last, that first found special grace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107370">In foremost sight, look you for tender years,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107380">And judge him not, a milksop by his face,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107390">That stoutly like a man at need appears. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107400">Great scorn I think, good fortune should have all,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107410">And reap the right, that labour long hath sown,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107420">Yea, favour hath perhaps more friends at call,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107430">Than you would think, or to the world is known. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A18729-e107440">
            <head>Here follow the speeches of the water nymphs, which should have been showed upon the Thursday, had not evil weather hindered the same.</head>
            <lg n="1" xml:id="A18729-e107450">
              <pb facs="25"/>
              <head>The first nymph's speech.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107460">We water nymphs have time to sport, and skip in every place,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107470">When days are long, and nights be short, and Phoebus hides his face ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107480">And hearing that there came a Queen, along this water side,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107490">So long as we poor silly nymphs, on land dare well abide,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107500">We dance, we hop, and bounce it up, in honour of her name,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107510">To whom Diana and her train, doth give immortal fame. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2" xml:id="A18729-e107520">
              <head>The second.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107530">We shun the sun, yet love the moon, and hate the open light,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107540">We hide our heads amid the reeds, in blustering stormy night. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107550">In calmest weather do we play, yet seldom seen we are,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107560">We watch our times, and flee from those, that still do on us stare. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107570">We harm no wight, yet fearful be, to those that have no spirit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107580">We are some hold of women's sex, and glad with men to meet. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3" xml:id="A18729-e107590">
              <head>The third.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107600">The fairies are another kind, of elves that dance in dark,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107610">Yet can light candles in the night, and vanish like a spark,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107620">And make a noise and rumbling great, among the dishes oft,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107630">And wake the sleepy sluggish maids, that lies in kitchen loft. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107640">And when in field, they tread the grass, from water we repair,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107650">And hop and skip, with them sometime, as weather waxeth fair ▪</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4" xml:id="A18729-e107660">
              <head>The fourth and last that called them into their cave.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107670">What rule is this, what tales tell you, what babble do you make ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107680">Will you tell secrets out of school? beware, if bugs awake</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107690">You will be shent, come hie you hence, can ye abide the view,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107700">The gaze, and staring such a while, of all this noble crew? </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107710">Though that we came to honour her, that gods on high have blessed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107720">It is a shame for water nymphs, on earth so long to rest. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="A18729-e107730">Then suddenly should they all have departed into the ground, where was an heavenly noise of all kind of music prepared, and nothing seen at all, when the painted canvas had been drawn over their heads, as the description thereof doth declare.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A18729-e107740">
          <pb facs="26"/>
          <head>Friday's device.</head>
          <p xml:id="A18729-e107750">On the Friday, the court upon remove, the city troubled with many causes, and some seeking to do service like myself, moved me to do somewhat of myself, because mine aids (As many tunes they were before) were drawn from me, each one about his own business, and I left to mine own inventions and policy, at which erigente, or casual things of fortune, I drew my boys unto me, that were the nymphs on the water, and so departed the city, with such garments and stuff necessary as fitted my purpose and the matter I went about. Then chose I a ground, by the which the Queen must pass, enclosing my company in the corner of a field, being defenced with high and thick bushes, and there some parts I made, which the boys might miss, because the time was short for the learning of those parts. But I being resolved to do some what might make the Queen laugh, appointed that seven boys of twelve, should pass through a hedge from the place of our abode (Which was gallantly trimmed) and deliver seven speeches, which follow in the next leaf. And these boys (You must understand) were dressed like nymphs of the water, and were to play by a device and degrees the phayries, and to dance (As near as could be imagined) like the phayries. Their attire, and coming so strangely out, I know made the Queen's highness smile and laugh withal. And I hearing this good hope, being apparelled like a water sprite, began to sound a timbrel, and the rest with me, all the twelve nymphs together (When the seven had repaired in) sounded timbrels likewise. And although I had no great harting, yet as I durst, I led the young foolish phayries a dance, which boldness of mine bred no disgrace, and as I heard said, was well taken. The Queen upon our retiring in,<pb facs="26"/> hasted to her highness' lodging, which was seven miles off, and at that present, when the show ended, it was passed five of the clock.</p>
          <p xml:id="A18729-e107760">Thus have you truly heard the report of mine own works and inventions, with the which did no any one deal but myself. And as I have made a recital of matters done in Norwich, so mean I a little to treat of the Queen's return from thence, in as short and brief order as I may, and the briefer, because I have not all the gentlemen's names, in whose houses the Queen lay, and who bestowed some entertainment on the train, but those, in whose houses I was (And where I saw or heard any thing worthy memory) I mind to speak of, and touch, praying you that shall read the same, to pardon me, where I omit any matter or men that merits commendation, for it is not want of good will that shall make me forget any good entertainments bestowed on the court, but it is want of knowledge that shall cause me so slightly run over the causes, and make a brief report thereof, as knoweth God, who grant and send our Queen often to such pleasant progresses, and increase good people and loving subjects to show the like duty and order, as hath been orderly seen in this season, and time of triumph.</p>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A18729-e107770">
            <pb facs="27"/>
            <head>The Queen of phayries speech.</head>
            <lg n="1" xml:id="A18729-e107780">
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107790">Though clean against the phayries kind, we come in open view,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107800">(And that the Queen of phayries here, presents herself to you)</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107810">Some secret cause procures the same: the gods at first, ye know,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107820">In field to honour thee good Queen, did make a gallant show:</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107830">Should we that are but sprites of th'air, refuse to do the same? </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107840">No sure, for gods and mortal men, shall serve thee noble dame. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2" xml:id="A18729-e107850">
              <head>The second.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107860">When Mercury came first in coach, a message to unfold,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107870">(And mask of gods amid the night, in chamber secrets told)</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107880">We warned were to shape ourselves, to do what Jove assigned,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107890">But water nymphs stepped in the while, and so expressed their mind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107900">And thrust poor phayries out of place, yet we: for fear of soil,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107910">Watched here our time, and for our sports, did choose this certain soil. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3" xml:id="A18729-e107920">
              <head>The third.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107930">Yea out of hedge we crept in deed, where close in caves we lay,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107940">And knowing by the brute of fame, a Queen must pass this way,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107950">To make her laugh, we clapped on coats, of sedges and bulrush both,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107960">That she should know, and world should say, lo there the phayries goeth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107970">Like furies mad, and satires wild yet lo, we have in store</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e107980">Fine timbrels, that the ancients use, to make the show the more. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4" xml:id="A18729-e107990">
              <head>The fourth.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108000">When saints and souls, and sprites of men, from heaven down did fling ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108010">(And Jehovah spoke, and clouds did shake, and many a crowned King. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108020">Crept out of grave, to honour thee, we ready were to wait,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108030">But hags of hell, and damned fiends, that feeds on false desayt</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108040">Did blush to see thy presence Queen, but we that harmless were,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108050">Kept love in store, to show at length our duty void of fear. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5" xml:id="A18729-e108060">
              <pb facs="27"/>
              <head>The fifth.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108070">But when that Cupid was condemned, and Venus fell in rage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108080">And wantonness and riot rude, for knacks were clapped in cage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108090">And all the ragment row of gods, to one great God gave place,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108100">We silly phayries were afeard, therewith to show our face. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108110">Yet when we saw a mask well liked, and gods condemned appear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108120">We did consult, at last farewell, the phayries should be here. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6" xml:id="A18729-e108130">
              <head>The sixth.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108140">But with orations good and great, to wall the weak was thrust,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108150">Yet when the strongest did their best, of force yet speak we must. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108160">For Jove that all commands, and doth, bade us to watch the hour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108170">And show no more at this adieu, than was in phayries power. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108180">So keeping course of Jove's command, we speak that is in breast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108190">And leave the Queen and all the train, with wit to judge the rest. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7" xml:id="A18729-e108200">
              <head>The seventh.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108210">With gods, yea Kings and Queens, begans your entry to this place,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108230">With gentle ghosts and merry sprites, we mind to end the case. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108240">So in good sign of happy chance, to thee oh sacred Queen,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108250">To knit up all, we mean to dance with timbrels on this green. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108260">And then farewell, we can no more, salute thee in our Gise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18729-e108270">All that is done, by great good will, is offered to the wise. </l>
            </lg>
            <stage xml:id="A18729-e108280">Then came the phayries out with timbrels, and danced a while, and so departed, and there withal the Queen went on her way to her highness' lodging.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="summary_of_royal_Progress" xml:id="A18729-e108290">
        <pb facs="28"/>
        <head>Her highness' return from Norwich.</head>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e108300">Now to come to the return of the Queen's majesty from Norwich, I think it as necessary to be told, as the rest of matter penned before, not chiefly for the cheer and entertainment found returning, but for other causes meet to be rehearsed. But to be tedious in that behalf, and dwell longer on the discourses of the entertainment than is requisite, I should but weary you with the reading thereof. So to avoid the doubts of mi●●●king, and danger of this fine world, and sifting senses, I will plainly fall to the troth of things that I mean to have understood. And so as I have heretofore said, the Queen passing from Norwich, came to master Woodhouse's that night, where she was well received, and nobly entertained. From thence to wood rising, the cheer and entertainment there I saw not, wherefore I give it no great commendation. From thence to Thetford at sir Edward clears. The train have told me (That was there) how they were worthily feasted. From thence to sir Thomas Kidson's, where in very deed, the fare and banquets did so exceed a number of other places, that it is worthy the mention. A show representing the phayries (As well as might be) was there seen, in the which show, a rich jewel was presented to the Queen's highness. From thence to master Reevet's, where all things were well, and in very good order, and meat liberally spent.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e108310">But now to speak a little by the way of God's mighty hand and power, that framed men's hearts so well in many parts, before the Queen's highness came to Cambridge sheer, and to tell how blessedly our great and good God did deal with our dear sovereign lady, in causing every person to show their duty, is a matter of great discourse, and of no little weight and comfort to all good minds that shall confess<pb facs="28"/> of the same, such a lord is our great God, that can frame all things to the best, and such a sovereign lady we have, that can make the crooked paths straight where she cometh, and draw the hearts of the people after her wheresoever she travels. I had almost passed the bounds of my discourse, by a desire of doing well, but remembering where I left, I begin again, and follow my first intention, to show the return of the Queen from Norfolk and Suffolk. So from master revets, her highness came to my lord North's, who was no whit behind any of the best for a frank house, a noble heart, and well ordered entertainment, and there was an oration made by a gentleman of Cambridge, and a stately and fair cup presented from the university, 〈…〉 ambassadors of France beholding the same, and the gentlemen of the shire (As in many other places) did bear the queen's meat to the table, which was a great liking, and gladnèsse to the gentlemen, and a solemn sight for strangers and subjects to look upon. From my lord North's, to sir Gyles Allingtons, and there things were well, and well liked. From thence, to sir John cuts, but what cheer there was found, I know not, for I was not there. From thence to master Kapel's, where was excellent good cheer, and entertainment. From thence to hide hall, where I heard of no great cheer nor banketting. From thence to Rockwood hall, but how the train was there entertained, I am ignorant of. From thence to master Stonars, and from thence to my l. of Leicester's house, where the progress ended, and to knit up all, the good there was revived, not only with making a great feast to theQueen, and the French ambassador, but also in feasting solemnly (At several times) the whole guard, on Sunday and Monday before the Queen came, at his own table, using such courtesy unto them for the space of two days, as was and is worthy of perpetual memory. Thus ●old I have been a little, to speak of the Queen's highness' return, who God hath so well preserved, that she like a worthy prince to our great comfort, prospers in peace, to thegreat disgrace of the enemies of God, and adversaries of our common weal and country.</p>
        <trailer xml:id="A18729-e108320">Finis</trailer>
        <closer xml:id="A18729-e108330">
          <signed xml:id="A18729-e108340">Quod Tho. Churchyard.</signed>
        </closer>
        <pb facs="29"/>
        <pb facs="29"/>
      </div>
      <div type="list_of_knights" xml:id="A18729-e108350">
        <pb facs="30"/>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e108360">Good reader, I had almost forgotten the names of the gentlemen that the Queen made knights in Suffolk and Norfolk, which oversight had been a blot and blemish to my book, because her highness advanced them to the more worship, for that they should all their life time after, have the greater regard to God, and to their prince.</p>
        <list xml:id="A18729-e108370">
          <head>Their names follow.</head>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108380">Master colt.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108390">Master Parker.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108400">Master Jermyn.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108410">Master spring.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108420">Master Kydson.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108430">Master Heygham.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108440">Master knevet.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108450">Master Bacon.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108460">Master pastons.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108470">Master Grear.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108480">Master Shelton.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108490">Master Henry Woodhouse.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108500">Master gaudy.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108510">Master wood mayor of Norwich.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18729-e108520">Master Roger Woodhouse.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="poem" xml:id="A18729-e108530">
        <pb facs="30"/>
        <head>¶ A matter touching the journey of sir Humphrey Gilbart knight.</head>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108540">The man that travels much,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108550">With mind and body both,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108560">(Whose restless limbs, and labouring thoughts,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108570">Through heaps of hazards goeth,)</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108580">A while would gladly rest,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108590">And so some solace taste,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108600">To sharp the sense, and ease the heart,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108610">That toil doth wear and waste. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108620">But though with charged breast,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108630">I seek to steal a nap,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108640">In hope sound sleeps would soon forget,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108650">The grief of thankless hap:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108660">Some cause calls up my muse,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108670">And bids my wits awake,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108680">That down is laid on quiet couch,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108690">A little ease to take:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108700">As lately lo you heard,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108710">By verses penned well,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108720">Which sounds so shrilly through my ears,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108730">And tings so like a bell,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108740">That though in sad dead sleep,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108750">My weary body were,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108760"><pb facs="31"/> I must rise up and whet my wits,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108770">And lend a loving ear</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108780">To that new tale I here,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108790">Of friends that hence do go</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108800">Unto a soil they never saw,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108810">Another world I trow</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108820">That few or none have found,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108830">Well, what should more be said,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108840">The journey that my friends do take,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108850">Full long in head I weighed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108860">Yet thought to pause awhile,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108870">(Ere pen to paper passed)</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108880">To see how course of world would go,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108890">And things fell out at last. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108900">And thus in my delay</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108910">I caught a slumber sweet,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108920">And sure methought in fearful dream,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108930">Or sweavon did I meet</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108940">The golden heart, and other ships,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108950">That to this voyage goes,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108960">Which barks were bravely under sail,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108970">Where water ebbs and floes. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108980">And where the view of country soil,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e108990">Was far from sailor's sight,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109000">And men were forced to try the seas</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109010">In storm or darkest night,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109020">But ear my dream could end,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109030">A voice 'gan call aloud,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109040"><pb facs="31"/> 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109050">Or is he crept in cloud,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109060">To shun the use of pen</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109070">And matter worthy note? </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109080">Whereat I started out of bed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109090">And straight weigh up I goat,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109100">And to my study door</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109110">In haste therewith I went,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109120">As one that fain would write some thing</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109130">That might the world content. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109140">Then brought I unto mind,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109150">The heavy dream I had,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109160">Yet ere I wrote one English verse,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109170">I called my little lad,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109180">And bade him run with speed</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109190">Abroad, and bring some news,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109200">And learn the troth of every thing,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109210">That I might shape my muse</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109220">To please the people's ears</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109230">With fruit of poet's pen. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109240">My lackey had not walked in Paul's</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109250">Not twenty paces then,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109260">But heard that sundry friends</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109270">Of mine, had taken leave</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109280">At court, and were all shipped away.</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109290">This brute may thee deceive</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109300">Thou foolish boy (Quoth I)</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109310">Nay sir by sweet saint John</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109320"><pb facs="32"/> (Quoth he) 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109330">And all his troop is gone. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109340">But whether, no man ●nowes,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109350">Save they that are in bark,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109360">Who with one mind, and one consent,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109370">Do hope to hit one mark. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109380">A ha sir boy (Quoth I)</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109390">I knew this long ago,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109400">Shut study door, pack hence a while,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109410">And musing even so,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109420">I marvelled how this knight,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109430">Could leave his lady here,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109440">His friends, and pretty-tender babes,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109450">That he did hold so dear,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109460">And take him to the seas,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109470">Where daily dangers are. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109480">Then weighed I how, immortal fame,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109490">Was more than worldly care,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109500">And where great mind remains,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109510">The body's rest is small,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109520">For countries' wealth, for private gain,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109530">Or glory seek we all. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109540">And such as marks this world,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109550">And notes the course of things,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109560">The weak and tickle stay of states,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109570">And great affairs of Kings,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109580">Desires to be abroad,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109590">For causes more than one,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109600"><pb facs="32"/> content to live as God appoints,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109610">And let the world alone. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109620">Yea such as deeply look,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109630">Into these worldly toys,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109640">And freedom of the body still,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109650">And noble mind enjoys,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109660">Are glad to trudge and toil,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109670">And drive off time awhile,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109680">And at our idle pleasures laughs,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109690">Or at our follies smile:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109700">That will not take some pains,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109710">And try both land and seas,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109720">For knowledge seek, and heap of hap,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109730">To do our country ease. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109740">O Gilbert noble knight,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109750">God send thee thy desire,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109760">Oh manly Knolles, and worthy wight,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109770">Whose heart doth still aspire,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109780">I wish thee great renown,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109790">And noble carry too,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109800">And noble North, with Wigmore wise,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109810">I wish you well to do. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109820">O Raleigh ripe of sprite,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109830">And rare right many ways,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109840">And lively n●●well, God you guide,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109850">To purchase endless praise. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109860">Go comely Cotten too,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109870">And march amid the rank,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109880"><pb facs="33"/> and honest Dennie with the best,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109890">Must needs deserve some thank. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109900">George carry forth I call,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109910">And sure John Roberts here,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109920">A special spark with present wit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109930">In person shall appear. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109940">Miles Morgan gains good fame,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109950">And whetstone steps in place,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109960">And seeks by travel, and by toil,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109970">To wine him double grace. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109980">John Udall is not hid,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e109990">Nor rolls I do forget,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110000">The rest I vow to publish out,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110010">And so dwell in their debt. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110020">But though that Frances Knolles</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110030">Comes last unto my mind,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110040">Among the first that shall do well,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110050">He will not be behind. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110060">O faithful friend's farewell,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110070">I named you all aroe,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110080">For world to view, whiles world doth last,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110090">What courage you do shoe. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110100">What charges you are at,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110110">What venture you have made,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110120">And how you seek to traffic there,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110130">Where never yet was trade. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110140">And most of you such men,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110150">As livings have at home,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110160"><pb facs="33"/> so great and good, that sure abroad</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110170">Ye need not for to roam:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110180">Fair houses, lands, and wives,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110190">Great friends, and of the best,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110200">Good stays and pillars, whereupon</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110210">The strongest here may rest:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110220">Well known, and honoured both,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110230">In credit every way,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110240">In perfect plight and state to live,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110250">And laugh, though world say nay. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110260">This strange adieu of yours,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110270">Doth argue noble hearts,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110280">And in your breasts are noble gifts</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110290">And many noble parts. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110300">For having wealth at will,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110310">And world at beck and call,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110320">Propped up with prince's favour still,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110330">So sure ye could not fall:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110340">And yet to leave that hope,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110350">To seek uncertain hap,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110360">And so commit your goods and lives,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110370">To every stormy clap</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110380">That sudden tempest brings:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110390">Methink the venture great,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110400">The value of your valiant minds,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110410">Surmounts the fire in heat. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110420">Whereof such hot desires</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110430">Of doing good, doth rise,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110440"><pb facs="34"/> the kind 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110450">Do sparkle thro●●● 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110460">Some people ha 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110470">A greedy hope 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110480">And heap 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110490">Doth make you 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110500">O sure that 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110510">Conceive the case who 〈◊〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110520">For having that 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110530">Already in 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110540">You mean to 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110550">As high as eye may look 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110560">And search 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110570">And every secret nook, 〈◊〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110580">As far as ship may 〈◊〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110590">I trust for count 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110600">And for the 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110610">You offer life and blood 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110620">Let world now speak 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110630">And babble what they please 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110640">What thing 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110650">●and so forsake your 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110660">It God moved not 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110670">To things he liek●● well</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110680">And that your good and deep 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110690">Wherein you long 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110700">Did lead and hall you 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110710">As men prepared and 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110720"><pb facs="34"/> to she● 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110730">And serve the makers thought</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110740">That all thing clearly 〈◊〉.</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110750">'Tis God and your good mind,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110760">That drives you 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110770">For any thing I find. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110780">And as he sent you out,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110790">So can he bring you in,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110800">Yea safely home 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110810">At large where you 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110820">And now to tell it plain,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110830">Not one of all 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110840">(Of gentle race) 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110850">Did hold down head 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110860">But bravely bore 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110870">Which shows no need 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110880">That did pro 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110890">From hence in haste to pass. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110900">Thus sure some other thing</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110910">Than gain, did cause you go,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110920">Some noble fire that 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110930">Whose flames of force 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110940">Good meaning and good 〈◊〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110950">Good fruit and grain 〈◊〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110960">When season serves, and 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110970">And hope for hire doth call. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110980">You might have walked the streets,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e110990">As other gallants do,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111000"><pb facs="35"/> yea kept the court and country both,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111010">In Paul's have jetted too. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111020">If mind had not been drawn,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111030">To things of greater weight,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111040">And had not hearts held up your heads</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111050">Another kind of height,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111060">Perhaps in idle days,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111070">You would set men a work,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111080">And call them to account in haste,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111090">That close in corners lurk:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111100">And ask in open place,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111110">How they would spend their time,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111120">And if they say they had no mind</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111130">The lofty clouds to climb,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111140">Yet would you wish they should</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111150">See what on earth is found,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111160">And search the proof, and sail by art,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111170">About the world so round. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111180">At home to tarry still,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111190">But breeds gross blood and wit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111200">Then better with the falcon fly,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111210">Than here on dunghill ●itte,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111220">And see how crows do feed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111230">On tainted carrion bate,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111240">Or live a lewd and wretched life,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111250">Upon a hungry share. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111260">At home much time is lost,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111270">And never found again,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111280"><pb facs="35"/> much household cares, and common griefs,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111290">Do break both sleep and brain. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111300">Abroad men win great wealth,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111310">Or knowledge gain at least,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111320">At home we run to wanton sports,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111330">And smell out every feast. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111340">Abroad small banquets are,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111350">It will not quit the cost,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111360">At home is naught but making love</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111370">To every painted post. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111380">Abroad the flesh is tamed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111390">And brought in fear and frame,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111400">At home oft times pride goes before,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111410">And after cometh shame. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111420">Abroad we ▪ wisdom learn,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111430">And do from folly flee,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111440">At home some dance so in a net,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111450">Their selves they can not see. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111460">Abroad where service is,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111470">Much honour may be won,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111480">At home our gay vainglory goes,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111490">Like shadow in the sun. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111500">Abroad bare robes are best,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111510">And manhood makes the show,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111520">At home young master must be fine,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111530">Or all is lost you know. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111540">Abroad few quarrels are,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111550">A brawl is bought so sre,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111560"><pb facs="36"/> at home they cog, they 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111570">And 〈◊〉 all 〈◊〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111580">Abroad is 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111590">And civil order still,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111600">At home where rudeness keeps no rule,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111610">Wild wantons take their will. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111620">Abroad may health be got,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111630">For labour lengthens life,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111640">At home the gout, the 〈◊〉, the cold,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111650">And each disease is rife. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111660">Abroad the sights are strange,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111670">And wonders may be seen,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111680">At home a stale and bald device,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111690">But dulls the sprites I ween. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111700">Abroad we learn to spare,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111710">To serve our turn in th'end,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111720">At home men set the cock on hoop,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111730">And vainly spoil and spend. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111740">Abroad few thieves you have,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111750">They find so little grace,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111760">At home foul, shifts and robberies both,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111770">Abound in every place. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111780">Thus prove I travels best,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111790">For body, soul, and sense,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111800">And ease a nurse to pamper vice,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111810">And buckler of defence. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111820">Where virtue can not strike,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111830">Nor enter any way,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111840"><pb facs="36"/> the 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111850">Dame virtue's force to stay. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111860">With rest lewd lust doth rise,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111870">And soon subdues the 〈◊〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111880">And toil 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111890">And strikes vain fancy blind. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111900">Much rest runs riot still,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111910">And breedeth treasons oft,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111920">And toil plucks down those 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111930">That looks to mount aloft. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111940">Rest maketh mischief ripe,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111950">And sets bad things abroach,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111960">Toil teacheth men to conquer fame,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111970">And flee from foul reproach. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111980">Rest loves to 〈◊〉 much,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e111990">Like whelp that waves the tail,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112000">Toil is for virtue quick as bee,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112010">For vice as slow as 〈◊〉. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112020">Rest sows no blessed feed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112030">Yet reaps a cursed grain,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112040">Toil weeds the ground, and planteth flowers</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112050">Where nettles did remain ▪</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112060">Rest will no duty know,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112070">But shakes off shackles still,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112080">Toil makes the body apt to stoop,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112090">To bend and show good will. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112100">Rest is a reckless joy,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112110">That sees not his 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112120"><pb facs="37"/> toil casts out many a vain conceit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112130">That rest brings in by swarms. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112140">If toil bring these good things</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112150">That I have told before,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112160">And rest but want and beggary breeds,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112170">With sundry mischiefs more:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112180">They ought have endless laud,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112190">That in these loitering days</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112200">Set idle hands and heads a work,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112210">To win immortal praise. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112220">And they that first found out</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112230">The strange and foreign soil,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112240">Are gone themselves to win the prize,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112250">Or take the open foil,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112260">Which shows them more than men,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112270">Half gods if I say troth,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112280">Whole kingdoms scarcely can suffice</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112290">Their minds and manhood both. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112300">Now have they taken leave</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112310">Of worldly pleasures all,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112320">That young and lusty were to live,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112330">And now to toil they fall</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112340">That finely were brought up,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112350">Yea now they bid adieu,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112360">The glittering court, the gallant town,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112370">The gorgeous garments new,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112380">The bravery of this world,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112390">The pride and pomp of earth,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112400"><pb facs="37"/> and look not backward any way,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112410">To riches, race, or birth. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112420">To worthy wife nor friend,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112430">To babes nor nearest kin,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112440">But only to the lord above,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112450">And journey they are in. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112460">And all for country's cause,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112470">And to enrich the same,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112480">Now do they hazard all they have:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112490">And so for wealth and fame,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112500">They fare along the seas,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112510">They sail and tide it out,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112520">They hale and stretch the sheets aloft,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112530">They toil and dread no doubt. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112540">They feed on biscuit hard,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112550">And drink but simple beer,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112560">Salt beef, and stockfish dry as keck,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112570">Is now their greatest cheer. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112580">And still a fulsome smell</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112590">Of pitch and tarre they feel,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112600">And when sea-sick (God wot) they are,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112610">About the ship they reel. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112620">And stomach belcheth up,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112630">A dish that haddocks seek,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112640">A bitter mess of sundry meats,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112650">A syrup green as leek. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112660">Then head and heart doth heave,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112670">And body waxeth cold:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112680"><pb facs="38"/> yet face 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112690">The same is to behold</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112700">But they must need●● 〈◊〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112710">A greater brunt than this,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112720">And hope that 〈…〉 pains,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112730">There comes a time of 〈◊〉. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112740">Yet note the torments strange,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112750">That toiling sailors have,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112760">Who lives 〈…〉 the seas:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112770">Yea surge and 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112780">Would swallow up the 〈◊〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112790">If pilots were not good,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112800">And some 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112810">Unto their 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112820">Sometime a flaw 〈◊〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112830">Blows 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112840">And 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112850">And at a cord doth 〈◊〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112860">To save his silly life,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112870">Aloof than 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112880">No 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112890">And on the 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112900">And plying for abo●●●,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112910">About the vessel 〈◊〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112920">And through 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112930">A gale of wind there blows,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112940">That seems to shake the bark,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112950">In sunder every rib●●,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112960"><pb facs="38"/> then is no time to 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112970">To cry carouse and bibb●●</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112980">But each man to 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e112990">They fall and fly 〈◊〉 ▪</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113000">In neck of this 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113010">That seeks to give the 〈◊〉 ▪</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113020">They spy in half a 〈◊〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113030">Up should yours 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113040">The captain calls, 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113050">A sort of them are placed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113060">To bear the 〈…〉,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113070">That should the Shipp● assail,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113080">At length the cannon bullet flies,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113090">And shot as thick as 〈◊〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113100">Goes off to murder m●n,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113110">And such a smoke doth rise,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113120">As few may well regard the seas,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113130">Or scarce behold the skies. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113140">Some groan and 〈◊〉 goodnight,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113150">Their day watch waxeth dim,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113160">Some can not speak their heads are off,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113170">And some have lost a limb. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113180">Some lies on 〈◊〉 lame,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113190">They have no legs to stand,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113200">And some have lost the use of arm,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113210">Or maimed of a hand ▪</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113220"><pb facs="39"/> and some are fighting still,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113230">And gets no harm at all,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113240">But he that speedeth best the while,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113250">Makes boast thereof but small. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113260">These brawls and bloody broils</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113270">To end or quiet brought,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113280">A new begins, as ill a storm,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113290">That troubles more their thought ▪</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113300">The rocks and wretched straits,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113310">That they must safely pass,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113320">The narrow creeks and doubts they find</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113330">In compass of their glass,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113340">Is danger wonders great,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113350">So that these sailor's toil,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113360">Rests all on hazards, ere they come</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113370">To any certain soil. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113380">I could rehearse a heap</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113390">Of sorrows that they have,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113400">But you that live in peace at home,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113410">And mince the matter brave,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113420">Will scarce believe a troth,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113430">And toil that travellers take. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113440">Well noble pilgrims, as in verse</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113450">I write this for your sake,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113460">In prose at your return,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113470">Look for a greater praise,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113480"><pb facs="39"/> a book that to the lofty skies,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113490">Your rare renown shall raise. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113500">This write I for your friends</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113510">That you have left behind,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113520">Your worthy wives, whose patient hearts</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113530">Bear many things in mind,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113540">And sit and shakes their heads</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113550">At that they can not mend,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113560">And many a sigh and sad con●aite,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113570">Along the seas they send,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113580">To follow those that fly</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113590">From them god wot to fast,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113600">And carried are in rotten barks</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113610">About with every blast,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113620">And tossed up and down</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113630">The seas, our lord knows where. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113640">O husbands when you saw your wives,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113650">Shed many a bitter tear,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113660">How could you part from them?</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113670">The case is answered thus,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113680">You are not ruled by love of babes,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113690">Nor women's wills iwis. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113700">But guided by such grace,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113710">As God himself hath sent,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113720">And that you do, is done indeed</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113730">Unto a good intent. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113740"><pb facs="40"/>God grant you good success,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113750">The whole heart's ease you crave,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113760">As much of wealth and honour both</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113770">As ever men may have. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113780">A safe and short return,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113790">Not long from home to dwell,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113800">A quiet happy journey still,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113810">And so dear friends farewell. </l>
        <trailer xml:id="A18729-e113820">Finis.</trailer>
        <pb facs="40"/>
      </div>
      <div type="poem" xml:id="A18729-e113830">
        <pb facs="41"/>
        <pb facs="41"/>
        <head>A welcome home to master Martin Frobusher, and all those gentlemen and soldiers, that have been with him this last journey, in the country called (Met● incognita) which welcome was written since this book was put to the printing, and joined to the same book, for a true testimony of churchyards good will, for the furtherance of master frobushers fame.</head>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113840">Five hundreth times, most welcome home</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113850">My friends that far have been,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113860">When thousands thought, that all was lost</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113870">Your fleet came safely in:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113880">To glad their hearts, that long bewailed</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113890">Your toil and hazard great:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113900">Oh give me leave, in English verse</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113910">A while on this to treat,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113920">That doth deserve, such world's renown</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113930">And come to such good end,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113940">As forceth friends to favour much</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113950">And foes may well commend. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113960">You sloth full snails, that creep not far,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113970">And love your shells so well,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113980"><pb facs="42"/> and you cold crusts, that have small crumbs</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e113990">In cottage poor that dwell,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114000">Now will you blush, or bend the brow,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114010">To see how travellers thrive,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114020">Nay, now you ought go help yourselves</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114030">And rather seek to strive</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114040">Against ill hap, that holds you here,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114050">When others work for wealth,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114060">And trudge abroad, to lengthened life,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114070">And nourish wished health. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114080">But addle heads, and idle brains,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114090">And babbling tongues, I trow,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114100">Had rather sit in smoky house</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114110">(Or on the dunghill crow</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114120">Like craven cocks) than go abroad</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114130">Where fortune may be found,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114140">And search where gold, and treasure lies</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114150">In bowels of the ground. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114160">A peck of dross, doth more content</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114170">The base and beggar's mind,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114180">Than heaped bushels, of good hap,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114190">That painful toil doth find,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114200"><pb facs="42"/> the thriftless will, not let to say,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114210">O give me ease and rest,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114220">A groat in purse, a coat on back,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114230">A homely house and nest,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114240">And fie on fame, and profit both,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114250">That comes by break of sleep,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114260">And but vain pleasures of this world,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114270">Both hard to win and keep. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114280">O miser's minds, and wretches hearts,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114290">If all men sought their ease,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114300">And none should search out golden mines,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114310">Nor seek their gain by seas,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114320">The world would soon be at an end,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114330">Or meat and clothe would fail,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114340">And those that now do laugh and smile,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114350">At length would weep and wail. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114360">And all a like, should lord and lad</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114370">Be set by ery where,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114380">The fool and wise man, would be one:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114390">And void of love or fear</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114400">The world should stand; for wealth and wit</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114410">Is that which governs all,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114420"><pb facs="43"/> and makes us know the mighty sort</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114430">And shoes the great from small. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114440">If each man were a like in wealth,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114450">As rogues and beggars are,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114460">And none had skill, nor great foresight</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114470">For countries' cause to care,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114480">Adieu good rule, and riches too</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114490">And farewell virtue's praise:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114500">But God be thanked, that we are born</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114510">To live in happier days,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114520">When wits will work for wealths avail</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114530">And sundry ride and run,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114540">Yea hoist up sail, and go themselves</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114550">As far as shines the sun</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114560">Through thick and thin, and fear no foil,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114570">As though to their good minds</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114580">The gods had made the land and seas,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114590">The skies, the air and winds,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114600">To follow that they have devised</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114610">That take these toils in hand. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114620">And of late days, 〈◊〉 great a flock</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114630">Of these are in this land,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114640"><pb facs="43"/> that I have scarce good leisure left,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114650">To write their names a right,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114660">And yield the praise, and lively lawd</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114670">Is due to every wight. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114680">In deed our age for many things</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114690">Exceeds the season past,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114700">And yet some say, all things be old</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114710">And shall whiles world doth last. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114720">But if no new device, did help</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114730">The age of that is gone,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114740">Full weak and lame would be old toys</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114750">These days to look upon. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114760">I grant the grave, old sages wise,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114770">Began to break thee ye,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114780">Made smooth rough ways, set virtue up,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114790">And flatly threw down vice,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114800">Built goodly towers, reared walls aloft,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114810">And to be brief and short,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114820">Sailed throw a world, saw every creek</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114830">And knew each common port,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114840">But all they did, hath time reformed</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114850">Or made more perfect still,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114860"><pb facs="44"/> 〈…〉</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114870">Took place from ancient skill. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114880">So though our elders travelled far,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114890">Yea, went the world about:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114900">Yet many things, our father's wits,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114910">As yet could ne'er find out:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114920">Which they did leave, to younger heads,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114930">And men of later birth,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114940">To search, and see, what hidden wealth,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114950">Lay lurking deep in earth:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114960">As lo, in (Meta cognita)</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114970">Is known, and found of laet,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114980">By those, that through their venture great</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e114990">Both gold and glory gaet. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115000">O Frobusher, thy brute and name</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115010">Shall be enrolled in books,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115020">That whosoever after comes,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115030">And on thy labour looks</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115040">Shall muse and marvel at thine acts,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115050">And greatness of thy mind. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115060">I say no more, lest some affirm</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115070">I fan thy face with wind,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115080"><pb facs="44"/> I flatter for affection's sake:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115090">Well, God shall witness be,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115100">In this thy praise (And other books)</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115110">I speak but right of thee. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115120">A book I made, at thy farewell,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115130">In prose (Where ere it is)</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115140">Another for thy welcome home,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115150">Thou shalt have after this,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115160">If this mislike thee any whit. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115170">So here mine own good friend</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115180">I bid thee welcome once again,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18729-e115190">And therewith make an end. </l>
        <p xml:id="A18729-e115200">Thus have I plainly expressed with pen, what portion of good will I bear to all those that valiantly and worthily are workers to the enriching and honour of our common wealth: and surely I think, I am as well bound to write in the praise of those that accompanied master Frobusher this voyage, as all together give one alone the commendations of a general labour and manly enterprise: but I want their names, that gladly I wish great fame unto, and willingly I would put in a register of good report, which in time to come may be touched, not in the respect only of the pains they have taken, which merits much, but to the encouraging of others to the like adventure, I would bestow some verses on this rare band, where in is a knot of right honest gentlemen, and a crew of good companions, whose for wardness may not be forgotten, and whose faithful service claims a great consideration and a good regard. For, although that commonly a<pb facs="45"/> captain carries away the credit of battles and victories where the soldiers have done their duties, and have been an occasion of triumph and conquest: yet by the judgement of a sound sense and uncorrupted wit, the branches of the 〈◊〉 that bring forth leaves, blossoms and fruit, ought as much to be spoken of, as the ●are bod●e of the same, 〈◊〉 without branches, (Though it have never so great sap) is but barren or little esteemed. I remember of late days a victory won against the Turks on the sea, and one man went away with the glo● of the same, which b●edde such disdain among the rest in whom the force deadly, that from that time in this present hour, the great man that went away with this glory was never called or desired to take the same charge in ●ande again. Nevertheless some one general and captain, is more happier and more necessary than a number of the mercenary people: for I read, that a great conqueror after he had received his death's wound, with causing himself to be carried about the ●●elde in a chair, gave such a terror and fear to the enemies, that they ran away, and had not the courage to defend their lives and liberties, the dignity, and name, and presence of the person before rehearsed, had so daunted them and taken away the use of their 〈◊〉. And many matters and noble histories make mention, that one man's hap, courage and conduit, is far better (At some instant and season) than the inconstant opinions of a multitude. But yet for all that, it is good to have wise and stout soldiers, whose obedience and manhood deserves as much commendation, as their captains can wish to themselves. When in another work this may come in question, I will more largely deal therewith among the discourses of war. And so for this presents I trouble you no further.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A18729-e115210">
          <signed xml:id="A18729-e115220">Thomas churchyard.</signed>
        </closer>
        <pb facs="45"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A18729"><item xml:id="A18729-philosopher" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A18729-philosopher</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18729-cupid" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A18729-cupid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18729-manhood" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A18729-manhood</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18729-beauty" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A18729-beauty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18729-wantonness" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18729-wantonness</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18729-favour" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18729-favour</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18729-desert" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18729-desert</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18729-riot" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18729-riot</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18729-unassigned" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18729-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18729-fortune" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18729-fortune</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

