<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A73704">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Coelum Britannicum <date type="creation_date">1634</date></title>
        <author>Carew, Thomas</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Madeline Burg</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A73704.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title>Early English books online.</title>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Cœlum Britanicum: A masque at White-Hall in the Banquetting-House, on Shrove-Tuesday-night, the 18. of February, 1633.</title>
            <title type="alt">Cœlum Britannicum</title>
            <author>Carew, Thomas, 1595?-1639?</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>21 400dpi TIFF images (displayed as GIF) and XML-encoded text (displayed as HTML).</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2011 April (TCP phase 2)</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73704</idno>
            <idno type="vid">132967</idno>
            <idno type="Aleph">5372186</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 4618</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg II, 496(a)</idno>
            <idno type="bibno">(UnM)99898413e</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>Where applicable, subject to copyright. Other restrictions on distribution may apply. Please go to http://www.umdl.umich.edu/ for more information.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Cœlum Britanicum: A masque at White-Hall in the Banquetting-House, on Shrove-Tuesday-night, the 18. of February, 1633.</title>
            <title type="alt">Cœlum Britannicum</title>
            <author>Carew, Thomas, 1595?-1639?</author>
            <author>Bruno, Giordano, 1548-1600. Spaccio de la bestia trionfante.</author>
            <author>Jones, Inigo, 1573-1652.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[4], 35, [1] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>printed for Thomas VValkley, and are to be sold at his shop neare White-Hall,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1634.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>By Thomas Carew.</note>
            <note>The designer for the masque was Inigo Jones, whose name appears on the internal title page for "Cœlum Britannicum" in subsequent editions of Carew's works.</note>
            <note>Based in part on: Bruno, Giordano. Spaccio de la bestia trionfante.</note>
            <note>Signatures: A² B-E⁴ F² .</note>
            <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
            <note>Most of the sheets are in two settings, and C outer forme and D inner forme are in three. Some copies have final pages numbered 31, 32, 30, 28, 29.</note>
            <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">eng</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A73704-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A73704-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A73704-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <p xml:id="A73704-e100040">Coelum britanicum. </p>
        <p xml:id="A73704-e100050">A masque at Whitehall in the banqueting-house, on shrove-tvesday-night, the 18. of February, 1633.</p>
        <quote xml:id="A73704-e100060">
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100070">Non habeo ingenium; Caesar sed jussit: habebo. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100080">Cur me posse negem, posse quod ille putat? </l>
        </quote>
        <p xml:id="A73704-e100090">By Thomas Carew. </p>
        <p xml:id="A73704-e100100">London: printed for Thomas Walkley, and are to be sold at his shop near white-hall. 1634.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A73704-e100110">
      <div type="masque" xml:id="A73704-e100120">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <pb facs="3" n="1"/>
        <head>The description of the scene.</head>
        <p xml:id="A73704-e100130">The first thing that presented itself to the sight, was a rich ornament, that enclosed the scene; in the upper part of which, were great branches of foliage growing out of leaves and husks, with a coronice at the top; and in the midst was placed a large compartment composed of grotesque work, wherein were harpies with wings and lions claws, and their hinder parts converted into leaves and branches: over all was a broken frontispiece, wrought with scrolls and mask heads of children; and within this a table adorned with a lesser compartment, with this inscription, coelum britannicvm. The two sides of this ornament were thus ordered: first, from the ground arose a square basement, and on the plinth stood a great vase of gold, richly enchased, and beautified with sculptures of great Relief, with fruitages hanging from the upper part: at the foot of this sat two youths naked, in their natural colours; each of these with one arm supported the vase; on the cover of which stood two young women in draperies, arm in arm; the one figuring the glory of princes, and the other mansuetude: their other arms bore up an oval, in which, to the King's majesty was this impreze, a lion with an imperial crown on his head; the word, animum sub pectore forti: on the other side was the like composition, but the design of the figures varied; and in the oval on the top, being born up by nobility and fecundity, was this impreze to the Queen's majesty<pb facs="4" n="2"/> a lily growing with branches and leaves, and three lesser lilies springing out of the stem; the word, semper inclit a virtus: all this ornament was heightened with gold, and for the invention and various composition was the newest and most gracious that hath been done in this place.</p>
        <p xml:id="A73704-e100140">The curtain was watchet and a pale yellow in pains, which flying up on the sudden, discovered the scene, representing old arches, old palaces, decayed walls, parts of temples, theatres, Basilita's and therm, with confused heaps of broken columns, bases, cornices and statues, lying as underground, and altogether resembling the ruins of some great city of the ancient Romans, or civilized Britons. This strange prospect detained the eyes of the spectators some time, when to a loud music Mercury descends; on the upper part of his chariot stands a cock in action of crowing: his habit was a coat of flame colour girt to him, and a white mantle trimmed with gold and silver; upon his head a wreath with small falls of white feathers, a caduceus in his hand, and wings at his heels: being come to the ground he dismounts and goes up to the state,</p>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e100150" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Mercury.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100160">From the high senate of the gods, to you</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100170">Bright glorious twins of love and majesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100180">Before whose throne three warlike nations bend</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100190">Their willing knees, on whose imperial brows</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100200">The regal circle prints no awful frowns</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100210">To fright your subjects, but whose calmer eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100220">Shed joy and safety on their melting hearts</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100230">That flow with cheerful loyal reverence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100240">Come I Cyllenius, Jove's ambassador:</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100250">Not, as of old, to whisper amorous tales</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100260">Of wanton love, into the glowing ear</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100270">Of some choice beauty in this numerous train;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100280">Those days are fled, the rebel flame is quenched</l>
          <pb facs="4" n="3"/>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100290">In heavenly breasts, the gods have sworn by Styx</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100300">Never to tempt yielding mortality</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100310">To lose embraces. Your exemplar life</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100320">Hath not alone transfused a zealous heat</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100330">Of imitation through your virtuous court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100340">By whose bright blaze your palace is become</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100350">The envied pattern of this underworld,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100360">But the aspiring flame hath kindled heaven;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100370">Th' immortal bosoms burn with emulous fires,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100380">Jove rivals your great virtues, royal sir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100390">And Juno, madam, your attractive graces;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100400">He his wild lusts, her raging jealousies</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100410">She lays aside, and through th' Olympic hall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100420">As yours doth here, their great example spreads. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100430">And though of old, when youthful blood conspired</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100440">With his new empire, prone to heats of lust,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100450">He acted incests, rapes, adulteries</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100460">On earthly beauties, which his raging Queen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100470">Swollen with revengeful fury, turned to beasts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100480">And in despite he retransformed to stars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100490">Till he had filled the crowded firmament</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100500">With his loose strumpets, and their spurious race,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100510">Where the eternal records of his shame</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100520">Shine to the world in flaming characters;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100530">When in the crystal mirror of your reign</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100540">He viewed himself, he found his loathsome stains;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100550">And now, to expiate the infectious guilt</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100560">Of those detested luxuries, he'll chase</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100570">Th' infamous lights from their usurped sphere,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100580">And drown in the Lethae an flood, their cursed</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100590">Both names and memories. In whose vacant rooms</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100600">First you succeed, and of the wheeling orb</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100610">In the most eminent and conspicuous point,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100620">With dazzling beams, and spreading magnitude,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100630">Shine the bright polestar of this hemisphere. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100640">Next, by your side, in a triumphant chair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100650">And crowned with Ariadne's diadem,</l>
          <pb facs="5" n="4"/>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100660">Sits the fair consort of your heart, and throne;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100670">Diffused about you, with that share of light</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100680">As they of virtue have derived from you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100690">He'll fix this noble train, of either sex;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100700">So to the British stars this lower globe</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100710">Shall owe its light, and they alone dispense</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100720">To'th' world a pure refined influence. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e100730">Enter Momus attired in a long darkish robe all wrought over with poniards, serpents tongues, eyes and ears, his beard and hair party coloured, and upon his head a wreath stuck with feathers, and a porcupine in the forepart.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e100740" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Momus.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e100750">By your leave, mortals. God-den cousin Hermes; your pardon good my lord ambassador: I found the tables of your arms and titles, in every inn betwixt this and Olympus, where your present expedition is registered, your nine thousandth nine hundred ninety ninth legation. I cannot reach the policy why your master breeds so few statesmen, it suits not with his dignity that in the whole empyraeum there should not be a god fit to send on these honourable errands but yourself, who are not yet so careful of his honour as your own, as might become your quality, when you are itinerant: the hosts upon the highway cry out with open month upon you for supporting pilfery in your train; which, though as you are the god of petty larceny, you might protect, yet you know it is directly against the new orders, and opposes the reformation in diameter.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e100760" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100770">Peace railer, bridle your licentious tongue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100780">And let this presence teach you modesty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e100790" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e100800">Let it if it can; in the mean time I will acquaint it with my condition. Know (Gay people) that though your poets who enjoy by patent a particular privilege to draw down any of the deities from twelfth-night till Shrove-tuesday,<pb facs="5" n="5"/> at what time there is annually a most familiar enter course between the two courts, have as yet never invited me to these solemnities, yet it shall appear by my intrusion this night, that I am a very considerable person upon these occasions, and may most properly assist at such entertainments. My name is Momus-ap-somnus-ap-erebus-ap-chaos-up-demogorgon-ap-eternity. My offices and titles are, the supreme Theomastix, hypercritic of manners, protonotary of abuses, arch-informer, dilator general, universal calumniator, eternal plaintiff, and perpetual foreman of the grand inquest. My privileges are an ubiquitary, circumambulatory, speculatory, interrogatory, redargutory immunity over all the privy lodgings, behind hangings, doors, curtains, through keyholes, chinks, windows, about all venereal lobbies, sconces or redoubts, though it be to the surprise of a perdu page or chambermaid, in, and at all courts of civil and criminal judicature, all counsels, consultations, and parliamentary assemblies, where though I am but a woolsack god, and have no vote in the sanction of new laws, I have yet a prerogative of wresting the old to any whatsoever interpretation, whether it be to the behoof, or prejudice, of Jupiter his crown and dignity, for, or against the rights of either house of patrician or plebeian gods. My natural qualities are to make Jove frown, Juno pout, Mars chafe, Venus blush, Vulcan glow, Saturn quake, Cynthia pale, Phoebus hide his face, and Mercury here take his heels. My recreations are witty mischiefs, as when Saturn guelt his father; the smith caught his wife and her bravo in a net of cobweb-iron; and Hebe through the lubricity of the pavement tumbling over the halfpace, presented the emblem of the forked tree, and discovered to the tanned Ethiops the snowy cliffs of Culabria with the grotta of Puteolum. But that you may arrive at the perfect knowledge of me by the familiar illustration of a bird of mine own feather, old Peter Aretine, who reduced all the sceptres and mitres of that age tributary to his wit,<pb facs="6" n="6"/> was my parallel; and Frank Rublais sucked much of my milk too; but your modern French hospital of oratory, is mere counterfeit, an arrant mountebank, for though fearing no other tortures than his sciatica, he discourse of Kings and Queens with as little reverence as of grooms and chambermaids, yet he wants their fangteeth, and scorpions tail; I mean that fellow, who to add to his stature thinks it a greater grace to dance on his tiptoes like a dog in a doublet, than to walk like other men on the soles of his feet.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e100810" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100820">No more impertinent Trifler, you disturb</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100830">The great affair with your rude scurrilous chat:</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100840">What doth the knowledge of your abject state</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100850">Concern Jove's solemn message? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e100860" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e100870">Sir, by your favour, though you have a more especial commission of employment from Jupiter, and a larger entertainment from his exchequer, yet as a freeborn god I have the liberty to travel at mine own charges, without your pass or countenance Legacine; and that it may appear a sedulous acute observer, may know as much as a dull phlegmatic ambassador, and wears a treble key to unlock the mysterious ciphers of your dark secrecies, I will discourse the politic state of heaven to this trim audience. —</p>
          <stage xml:id="A73704-e100880">
            <p xml:id="A73704-e100890">At this the scene changeth, and in the heaven is discovered a sphere, with stars placed in their several images; born up by a huge naked figure (Only a piece of drapery hanging over his thigh) kneeling, and bowing forwards, as if the great weight lying on his shoulders oppressed him, upon his head a crown, by all which he might easily be known to be Atlas. </p>
          </stage>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e100900">— You shall understand, that Jupiter upon the inspection of I know not what virtuous presidents extant (As they say) here in this court, but as I more probably guess out of the consideration of the decay of his natural abilities,<pb facs="6" n="7"/> hath before a frequent convocation of the superlunary peers in a solemn oration recanted, disclaimed, and utterly renounced all the lascivious extravagancies, and riotous enormities of his forepast licentious life, and taken his oath on Juno's breviary, religiously kissing the two-leaved book, never to stretch his limbs more betwixt adulterous sheets, and hath with pathetical remonstrances exhorted, and under strict penalties enjoined a respective conformity in the several subordinate deities; and because the libertines of antiquity, the ribald poets, to perpetuate the memory and example of their triumphs over chastity, to all future imitation, have in their immortal songs celebrated the martyrdom of those strumpets under the persecution of the wives, and devolved to posterity the pedigrees of their whores bawds, and bastards; it is therefore by the authority aforesaid enacted, that this whole army of constellations be immediately disbanded and cashiered, so to remove all imputation of impiety from the celestial spirits, and all lustful influences upon terrestrial bodies; and consequently that there be an inquisition erected to expunge in the ancient, and suppress in the modern and succeeding poems and pamphlets, all past, present, and future mention of those abjured heresies, and to take particular notice of all ensuing incontinences, and punish them in their high commission court. Am not I in election to be a tall statesman think you, that can repeat a passage at a counsel-table thus punctually?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e100910" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100920">I shun in vain the importunity</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100930">With which this snarler vexeth all the gods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100940">Jove cannot scape him: well, what else from heaven? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e100950" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e100960">Heaven! Heaven is no more the place it was; a cloister of Carthusians, a monastery of converted gods, Jove is grown old and fearful, apprehends a subversion of his empire, and doubts lest fate should introduce a legal succession in the legitimate heir, by repossessing the Titanian line, and hence springs all this innovation. We have had new orders read in the presence chamber, by<pb facs="7" n="8"/> the vi-president of pernassies, too strict to be observed long. Monopolies are called in, sophistication of wares punished, and rates imposed on commodities. Injunctions are gone out to the nectar brewers, for the purging of the heavenly beverage of a narcotic weed which hath rendered the ideas confused in the divine intellects, and reducing it to the composition used in Saturn's reign. Edicts are made for the restoring of decayed housekeeping, prohibiting the repairs of families to the metropolis, but this did endanger an Amazonian mutiny, till the females put on a more masculine resolution of soliciting businesses in their own persons, and leaving their husbands at home for stallions of hospitality. Bacchus hath commanded all taverns to be shut, and no liquor drawn after ten at night. Cupid must go no more so scandalously naked, but is enjoined to make him breeches though of his mother's petticoats. Ganymede is forbidden the bedchamber, and must only minister in public. The gods must keep no pages, nor grooms of their chamber under the age of 25. and those provided of a competent stock of beard. Pan may not pipe, nor Proteus juggle, but by especial permission. Vulcan was brought to an oretenus and fined, for driving in a plate of iron into one of the sun's chariot-wheels and frost-nailing his horses upon the fifth of November last, for breach of a penal statute prohibiting work upon holidays, that being the annual celebration of the gigantomacchy. In brief, the whole state of the hierarchy suffers a total reformation, especially in the point of reciprocation of conjugal affection. Venus hath confessed all her adulteries, and is received to grace by her husband, who conscious of the great disparity betwixt her perfections and his deformities, allows those levities as an equal counterpoise; but it is the prettiest spectacle to see her stroking with her ivory hand his collied cheeks, and with her sinewy fingers combing his sooty beard. Jupiter too begins to learn to lead his own wife, I left him practising in the milky way; and there is no doubt of an universal<pb facs="7" n="9"/> obedience, where the lawgiver himself in his own person observes his decrees so punctually; who besides to eternize the memory of that great example of matrimonial union which he derives from hence, hath on his bed chamber door, and ceiling, fretted with stars in capital letters, engraven the inscription of Carlomaria. This is as much I am sure as either your knowledge or instructions can direct you to, which I having in a blunt round tale, without state-formality, politic inferences, or suspected rhetorical elegancies, already delivered, you may now dexteriously proceed to the second part of your charge, which is the raking of yond heavenly sparks up in the embers, or reducing the etherial lights to their primitive opacity, and gross dark subsistence; they are all unriveted from the sphere, and hang loose in their sockets, where they but attend the waving of your caduce, and immediately they reinvest their pristine shapes, and appear before you in their own natural deformities.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e100970" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100980">Momus thou shalt prevail, for since thy bold</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e100990">Intrusion hath inverted my resolves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101000">I must obey necessity, and thus turn</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101010">My face, to breathe the thunderers just decree</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101020">'Gainst this adulterate sphere, which first I purge</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101030">Of loathsome monsters, and misshapen forms:</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101040">Down from her azure concave, thus I charm</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101050">The Lyrnean Hydra, the rough unlicked bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101060">The watchful dragon, the storm-boding whale,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101070">The centaur, the horned goatfish Capricorn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101080">The snake-haired Gorgon, and fierce sagittar:</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101090">Divested of your gorgeous starry robes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101100">Fall from the circling orb, and ere you suck</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101110">Fresh venom in, measure this happy earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101120">Then to the fens, caves, forests, deserts, seas,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101130">Fly, and resume your native qualities. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e101140">They dance in those monstrous shapes the first antimasque of natural deformity.</stage>
        <pb facs="8" n="10"/>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e101150" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e101160">Are not these fine companions, trim playfellows for the deities? yet these and their fellows have made up all our conversation for some thousands of years. Do not you fair ladies acknowledge yourselves deeply engaged now to those poets your servants, that in the height of commendation have raised your beauties to a parallel with such exact proportions, or at least ranked you in their spruce society. Hath not the consideration of these inhabitants rather frighted your thoughts utterly from the contemplation of the place? but now that those heavenly mansions are to be void, you that shall hereafter be found unlodged will become inexcusable; especially since virtue alone shall be sufficient title, fine, and rent: yet if there be a lady not competently stocked that way, she shall not on the instant utterly despair, if she carry a sufficient pawn of handsomeness; for however the letter of the law runs, Jupiter notwithstanding his age and present austerity, will never refuse to stamp beauty, and make it currant with his own impression; but to such as are destitute of both, I can afford but small encouragement. Proceed cousin Mercury, what follows?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e101170" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101180">Look up, and mark where the bright zodiac</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101190">Hangs like a belt about the breast of heaven;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101200">On the right shoulder, like a flaming jewel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101210">His shell, with nine rich topazes adorned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101220">Lord of this tropic, sits the scalding crab:</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101230">He, when the sun gallops in full career</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101240">His annual race; his ghastly claws upreared,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101250">Frights at the confines of the torrid zone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101260">The fiery team, and proudly stops their course,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101270">Making a solstice, till the fierce steeds learn</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101280">His backward paces, and so retrograde</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101290">Post downhill to th' opposed Capricorn. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101300">Thus I depose him from his lofty throne;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101310">Drop from the sky, into the briny flood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101320">There teach thy motion to the ebbing sea,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101330">But let those fires that beautified thy shell</l>
          <pb facs="8" n="11"/>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101340">Take humane shapes, and the disorder show</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101350">Of thy regressive paces here below. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e101360">The second antimasque is danced in retrograde paces, expressing obliquity in motion.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e101370" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e101380">This crab, I confess, did ill become the heavens; but there is another that more infests the earth, and makes such a solstice in the politer arts and sciences, as they have not been observed for many ages to have made any sensible advance: could you but lead the learned squadrous with a masculine resolution passed this point of retrogradation, it were a benefit to mankind worthy the power of a god, and to be paid with altars; but that not being the work of this night, you may pursue your purposes: what now succeeds?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e101390" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101400">Vice, that unbodied, in the appetite</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101410">Erects his throne, hath yet, in bestial shapes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101420">Branded, by nature, with the character</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101430">And distinct stamp of some peculiar ill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101440">Mounted the sky, and fixed his trophies there:</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101450">As fawning flattery in the little dog;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101460">I'th bigger, churlish murmur; cowardice</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101470">I'th timorous hare: ambition in the eagle;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101480">Rapine and avarice in th' adventurous ship</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101490">That sailed to Colchos for the golden fleece;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101500">Drunken distemper in the goblet flows;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101510">I'th dart and scorpion, biting calumny;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101520">In Hercules and the lion, furious rage;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101530">Vain ostentation in Cassiope:</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101540">All these I to eternal exile doom,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101550">But to this place their emblemed vices summon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101560">Clad in those proper figures, by which best</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101570">Their incorporeal nature is expressed. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e101580">The third antimasque is danced of these several vices, expressing the deviation from virtue.</stage>
        <pb facs="9" n="12"/>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e101590" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e101600">From henceforth it shall be no more said in the proverb, when you would express a riotous assembly, that hell, but heaven is broke loose: this was an arrant goal-delivery, all the prisons of your great cities could not have vomited more corrupt martyr: but cousin Cylleneus, in my judgement it is not safe that these infectious persons should wander here to the hazard of this island, they threatened less danger when they were nailed to the firmament: I should conceive it a very discreet course since they are provided of a tall vessel of their own ready rigged, to embark them all together in that good ship called the Argo, and send them to the plantation in New-england, which hath purged more virulent humours from the politic body, then guacum and all the West-indian drugs have from the natural bodies of this kingdom: can you devise how to dispose them better?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e101610" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101620">They cannot breathe this pure and temperate air</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101630">Where virtue lives, but will with hasty flight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101640">'Mongst fogs and vapours, seek unsound abodes. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101650">Fly after them, from your usurped seats,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101660">You foul remainders of that viperous brood:</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101670">Let not a star of the luxurious race</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e101680">With his loose blaze stain the skies crystal face. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A73704-e101690">All the stars are quenched, and the sphere darkened.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A73704-e101700">
            <p xml:id="A73704-e101710">Before the entry of every antimasque, the stars in those figures in the sphere which they were to represent, were extinct; so as, by the end of the antimasques in the sphere no more stars were seen.</p>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e101720" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e101730">Here is a total eclipse of the eighth sphere, which neither Booker, Allestre, nor any of your prognosticators, no nor their great master Tico were aware of; burr yet in my opinion there were some innocent, and some generous constellations, that might have been reserved for noble uses: as the Skales and sword to adorn the<pb facs="9" n="13"/> statue of justice, since she resides here on earth only in picture and effigy. The eagle had been a fit present for the Germans, in regard their bird hath mewed most of her feathers lately. The dolphin too had been most welcome to the French, and then had you but clapped Perseus on his Pegasus, brandishing his sword, the dragon yawning on his back under the horses feet, with Pytheus' dart through his throat, there had been a divine st. George for this nation: but since you have improvidently shuffled them altogether, it now rests only that we provide an immediate succession, and to that purpose I will instantly proclaim a free election,</p>
          <quote xml:id="A73704-e101740">Oh yes, oh yes, oh yes, by the father of the gods, and the King of men,</quote>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e101750">Whereas we having observed a very commendable practice taken into frequent use by the princes of these latter ages, of perpetuating the memory of their famous enterprises, sieges, battles, victories, in picture, sculpture, tapestry, embroideries, and other manufactures, wherewith they have embellished their public palaces, and taken into our more distinct and serious consideration, the particular Christmas hangings of the guard-chamber of this court, wherein the naval victory of 88. is to the eternal glory of this nation exactly delineated: and whereas we likewise out of a prophetical imitation of this so laudable custom, did for many thousand years before, adorn and beautify the eighth room of our celestial mansion, commonly called the star-chamber, with the military adventures, stratagems, achievements, feats and defeats, performed in our own person, whilst yet our standard was erected, and we a combatant in the amorous warfare. It hath notwithstanding, after mature deliberation, and long debate, held first in our own inscrutable bosom, and afterwards communicated with our privy<pb facs="10" n="14"/> counsel, seemed meet to our omnipotency, for causes to ourself best known, to unfurnish and disarray our foresaid star-chamber of all those ancient constellations which have for so many ages been sufficiently notorious, and to admit into their vacant places, such persons only as shall be qualified with exemplar virtue and eminent desert, there to shine in indelible characters of glory to all posterity. It is therefore our divine will and pleasure, voluntarily, and out of our own free and proper motion, mere grace and special favour, by these presents to specify and declare to all our loving people, that it shall be lawful for any person whatsoever, that conceiveth him or herself to be really endued with any heroical virtue or transcendent merit, worthy so high a calling and dignity, to bring their several pleas and pretences before our right trusty and well-beloved cousin, and counsellor, don Mercury, and god Momus, etc. Our peculiar delegates for that affair, upon whom we have transferred an absolute power to conclude, and determine without appeal or revelation, accordingly as to their wisdoms it shall in such cases appear behooveful and expedient. Given at our palace in Olympus the first day of the first month, in the first year of the reformation.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A73704-e101760">
            <p xml:id="A73704-e101770">Plutus enters, an old man full of wrinkles, a bald head, a thin white beard, spectacles on his nose, with a bunched back, and attired in a robe of cloth of gold.</p>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e101780">Plutus appears.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e101790" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e101800">Who's this appears?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e101810" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e101820">This is subterranean fiend, Plutus, in this dialect termed riches, or the god of gold; a poison, hid by providence in the bottom of seas, and navel of the earth, from man's discovery, where if the seeds begun to sprout aboveground, the excrescence was carefully guarded by dragons, yet at last by humane curiosity brought<pb facs="10" n="15"/> to light, to their own destruction; this being the true Pandora's box, whence issued all those mischiefs that now fill the universe.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e101830" who="A73704-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A73704-e101840">
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101850">That I prevent the message of the gods</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101860">Thus with my haste, and not attend their summons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101870">Which ought in justice call me to the place</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101880">I now require of right, is not alone</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101890">To show the just precedence that I hold</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101900">Before all earthly, next th' immortal powers;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101910">But to exclude the hope of partial grace</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101920">In all pretenders, who, since I descend</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101930">To equal trial, must by my example,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101940">Waving your favour, claim by sole desert. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A73704-e101950">
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101960">If virtue must inherit, she's my slave;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101970">I lead her captive in a golden chain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101980">About the world: she takes her form and being</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e101990">From my creation; and those barren seeds</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102000">That drop from heaven, if I not cherish them</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102010">With my distilling dews, and fotive heat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102020">They know no vegetation; but exposed</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102030">To blasting winds of freezing poverty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102040">Or not shoot forth at all, or budding, wither:</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102050">Should I proclaim the daily sacrifice</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102060">Brought to my temples by the toiling rout,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102070">Not of the fat and gore of abject beasts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102080">But human sweat, and blood poured on my altars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102090">I might provoke the envy of the gods. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102100">Turn but your eyes and mark the busy world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102110">Climbing steep mountains for the sparkling stone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102120">Piercing the centre for the shining ore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102130">And th' ocean's bosom to rake pearly sands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102140">Crossing the torrid and the frozen zones,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102150">Midst rocks and swallowing gulfs, for gainful trade,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102160">And though opposing swords, fire, murdering cannon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102170">Scaling the walled town for precious spoils:</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102180">Plant in the passage to your heavenly seats,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102190">These horrid dangers, and then see who dares</l>
            <pb facs="11" n="16"/>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102200">Advance his desperate foot; yet am I sought,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102210">And oft in vain, through these, and greater hazards;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102220">I could discover how your deities</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102230">Are for my sake slighted, despised, abused,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102240">Your temples, shrines, altars, and images</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102250">Uncovered, rifled, robbed, and disarrayed</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102260">By sacrilegious hands: yet is this treasure</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102270">To th' golden mountain, where I sit adored</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102280">With superstitious solemn rights conveyed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102290">And becomes sacred there, the sordid wretch</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102300">Not daring touch the consecrated ore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102310">Or with profane hands lessen the bright heap;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102320">But this might draw your anger down on mortals</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102330">For rendering me the homage due to you:</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102340">Yet what is said may well express my power</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102350">Too great for earth, and only fit for heaven. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A73704-e102360">
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102370">Now, for you pastime, view the naked root,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102380">Which in the dirty earth, and base mould drowned,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102390">Sends forth this precious plant, and golden fruit. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102400">You lusty swains, that to your grazing flocks</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102410">Pipe amorous roundelays; you toiling hinds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102420">That barb the fields, and to your merry teams</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102430">Whistle your passions; and you mining moles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102440">That in the bowels of your mother-earth</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102450">Dwell the eternal burden of her womb,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102460">Cease from your labours, when wealth bids you play,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102470">Sing, dance, and keep a cheerful holiday. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e102480">They dance the fourth antimasque consisting of country people, music and measures.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e102490" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102500">Plutus, the gods know and confess your power</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102510">Which feeble virtue seldom can resist;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102520">Stronger than towers of brass, or chastity;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102530">Jove knew you when he courted Danae,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102540">And Cupid wears you on that arrows head</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102550">That still prevails. But the gods keep their thrones</l>
          <pb facs="11" n="17"/>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102560">To install virtue, not her enemies. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102570">They dread thy force, which even themselves have felt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102580">Witness Mount-ida, where the martial maid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102590">And frowning Juno, did to mortal eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102600">Naked, for gold, their sacred bodies show,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102610">Therefore for ever be from heaven banished. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102620">But since with toil from undiscovered worlds</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102630">Thou art brought hither, where thou first didst breathe</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102640">The thirst of empire, into regal breasts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102650">And frightedst quiet peace from her meek throne,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102660">Filling the world with tumult, blood, and war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102670">Follow the camps of the contentious earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102680">And be the conquerors slave, but he that can</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102690">Or conquer thee, or give thee virtues stamp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e102700">Shall shine in heaven a pure immortal lamp. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e102710" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e102720">Nay stay, and take my benediction along with you. I could, being here a co-judge, like others in my place, now that you are condemned, either rail at you, or break jests upon you, but I rather choose to lose a word of good counsel, and entreat you to be more careful in your choice of company, for you are always found either with misers, that not use you at all; or with fools, that know not how to use you well: be not hereafter so reserved and coy to men of worth and parts, and so you shall gain such credit, as at the next sessions you may be heard with better success. But till you are thus reformed, I pronounce this positive sentence, that wheresoever you shall choose to abide, your society shall add no credit or reputation to the party, nor your discontinuance, or total absence, be matter of disparagement to any man; and whosoever shall hold a contrary estimation of you, shall be condemned to wear perpetual motley, unless he recant his opinion. Now you may void the court.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A73704-e102730">
            <p xml:id="A73704-e102740">Paenia enters, a woman of a pale colour, large brims of a hat upon her head, through which her hair started up like a fury, her robe was of a dark colour full of patches,<pb facs="12" n="18"/> about one of her hands was tied a chain of iron, to which was fastened a weighty stone, which she bore up under her arm.</p>
          </stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e102750">Paenia enters.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e102760" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e102770">What creature's this?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e102780" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e102790">The antipodes to the other, they move like two buckets, or as two nails drive out one another; if riches depart, poverty will enter.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e102800" who="A73704-poverty">
          <speaker>Poverty</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A73704-e102810">
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102820">I nothing doubt (Great and immortal powers)</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102830">But that the place, your wisdom hath denied</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102840">My foe, your justice will confer on me;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102850">Since that which renders him incapable,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102860">Proves a strong plea for me. I could pretend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102870">Even in these rags, a larger sovereignty</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102880">Then gaudy wealth in all his pomp can boast;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102890">For mark how few they are that share the world;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102900">The numerous armies, and the swarming ants</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102910">That fight and toil for them, are all my subjects,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102920">They take my wages, wear my livery:</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102930">Invention too and wit, are both my creatures,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102940">And the whole race of virtue is my offspring;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102950">As many mischief's issue from my womb,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102960">And those as mighty, as proceed from gold. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102970">Oft o'er his throne I wave my awful scepter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102980">And in the bowels of his state command,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e102990">When 'Midst his heaps of coin, and hills of gold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103000">I pine, and starve the avaritious fool. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103010">But I decline those titles, and lay claim</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103020">To heaven, by right of divine contemplation;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103030">She is my darling, ay, in my soft lap,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103040">Free from disturbing cares, bargains, accounts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103050">Leases, rends, stewards, and the fear of thieves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103060">That vex the rich, nurse her in calm repose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103070">And with her, all the virtues speculative,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103080">Which, but with me, find no secure retreat. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A73704-e103090">
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103100">For entertainment of this hour, I'll call</l>
            <pb facs="12" n="19"/>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103110">A race of people to this place, that live</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103120">At nature's charge, and not importune heaven</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103130">To chain the winds up, or keep back the storms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103140">To stay the thunder, or forbid the hail</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103150">To thresh the unreaped ear; but to all weathers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103160">Both chilling frost, and scalding sun, expose</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103170">Their equal face, come forth, my swarthy train,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103180">In this fair circled dance, and as you move,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103190">Mark, and foretell happy events of love. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e103200">They dance the fifth antimasque of gypsies.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e103210" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e103220">I cannot but wonder that your perpetual conversation with poets and philosophers hath furnished you with no more logic, or that you should think to impose upon us so gross an inference, as because Plutus and you are contrary, therefore whatsoever is denied of the one, must be true of the other; as if it should follow of necessity, because he is not Jupiter, you are. No, I give you to know, I am better versed in cavils with the gods, than to swallow such a fallacy, for though you two cannot be together in one place, yet there are many places that may be without you both, and such is heaven, where neither of you are likely to arrive: therefore let me advise you to marry yourself to content, and beget sage apothegms, and goodly moral sentences in dispraise of riches, and contempt of the world.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e103230" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103240">Thou dost presume too much, poor needy wretch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103250">To claim a station in the firmament,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103260">Because thy humble cottage, or thy tub</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103270">Nurses some lazy or pedantic virtue</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103280">In the cheap sunshine, or by shady springs</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103290">With roots and potherbs; where thy rigid hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103300">Tearing those humane passions from the mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103310">Upon whose stocks fair blooming virtues flourish,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103320">Degradeth nature, and benummeth sense,</l>
          <pb facs="13" n="20"/>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103330">And gorgonlike, turns active men to stone. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103340">We not require the dull society</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103350">Of your necessitated temperance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103360">Or that unnatural stupidity</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103370">That knows nor joy nor sorrow; nor your forced</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103380">Falsely exalted passive fortitude</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103390">Above the active: this low abject brood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103400">That fix their seats in mediocrity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103410">Become your servile minds; but we advance</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103420">Such virtues only as admit excess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103430">Brave bounteous acts, regal magnificence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103440">All-seeing prudence, magnanimity</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103450">That knows no bound, and that heroic virtue</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103460">For which antiquity hath left no name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103470">But patterns only, such as Hercules,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103480">Achilles, Theseus. Back, to thy loathed cell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103490">And when thou seest the new enlightened sphere,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e103500">Study to know but what those worthies were. </l>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e103510">Tiche, enters, hor head bald behind, and one great lock before, wings at her shoulders, and in her hand a wheel, her upper parts naked, and the skirt of her garment wrought all over with crowns, sceptres, boakes, and such other things as express both her greatest and smallest gifts.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e103520" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e103530">See where dame fortune comes, you may know her by her wheel, and that veil over eyes, with which she hopes like a seeled pigeon to mount above the clouds, and perch in the eighth sphere: listen, she begins.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e103540" who="A73704-fortuna">
          <speaker>Fort.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A73704-e103550">
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103560">I come not here (You gods) to plead the right</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103570">By which antiquity assigned my deity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103580">Though no peculiar station 'mongst the stars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103590">Yet general power to rule their influence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103600">Or boast the title of omnipotent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103610">Ascribed me then, by which I rivalled Jove,</l>
            <pb facs="13" n="21"/>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103620">Since you have cancelled all those old records;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103630">But confident in my good cause and merit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103640">Claim a succession in the vacant orb. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103650">For since Astraa fled to heaven, I sit</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103660">Her deputy on earth, I hold her scales</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103670">And weigh men's fates out, who have made me blind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103680">Because themselves want eyes to fee my causes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103690">Call me inconstant, cause my works surpass</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103700">The shallow fathom of their human reason;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103710">Yet here, like blinded justice, I dispense</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103720">With nay impartial hands, their constant lots,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103730">And if desertless, impious men engross</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103740">My best rewards, the fault is yours, you gods,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103750">That scant your graces to mortality,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103760">And niggards of your good, scarce spare the world</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103770">One virtuous, for a thousand wicked men. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103780">It is no error to confer dignity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103790">But to bestow it on a vicious man;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103800">I gave the dignity, but you made the vice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103810">Make you men good, and I'll make good men happy</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103820">That Plutus is refused, dismays me not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103830">He is my drudge, and the external pomp,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103840">In which he decks the world, proceeds from me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103850">Not him; like harmony, that not resides</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103860">In strings, or notes, but in the hand and voice. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103870">The revolutions of empires, states,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103880">Sceptres, and crowns, are but my game and sport,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103890">Which as they hang on the events of war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103900">So those depend upon my turning wheel. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A73704-e103910">
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103920">You warlike squadrons, who in battles joined,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103930">Dispute the right of Kings, which I decide,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103940">Present the model of that martial frame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e103950">By which, when crowns are staked, I rule the game. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e103960">They dance the sixth antimasque, being the representation of a buttell.</stage>
        <pb facs="14" n="20"/>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e103970" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e103980">Madam, I should censure you, pro falso clamore, for preferring a scandalous cross-bill of recrimination against the gods, but your blindness shall excuse you. Alas! what would it advantage you, if virtue were as universal as vice is? it would only follow, that as the world now exclaims upon you for exalting the vicious, it would then rail as fast at you for depressing the virtuous; so they would still keep their tune, though you changed their ditty.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e103990" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104000">The mists, in which future events are wrapped,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104010">That oft succeed beside the purposes</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104020">Of him that works, his dull eyes not discerning</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104030">The first great cause, offered thy clouded shape</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104040">To his enquiring search; so in the dark</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104050">The groping world first found thy deity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104060">And gave thee rule over contingencies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104070">Which, to the piercing eye of providence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104080">Being fixed and certain, where past and to come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104090">Are always present, thou dost disappear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104100">Losest thy being, and art not all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104110">Be thou then only a deluding phantom,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104120">At best a blind guide, leading blinder fools;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104130">Who, would they but survey their mutual wants,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104140">And help each other, there were left no room</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104150">For thy vain aid. Wisdom, whose strong-built plots</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104160">Leave naught to hazard, mocks thy futile power. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104170">Industrious labour drags thee by the locks. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104180">Bound to his toiling car, and not attending</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104190">Till thou dispense, reaches his own reward. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104200">Only the lazy sluggard yawning lies</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104210">Before thy threshold, gaping for thy dole,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104220">And licks the easy hand that feeds his sloth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104230">The shallow, rash, and unadvised man</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104240">Makes thee his stale, disburdens all the follies</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104250">Of his misguided actions, on thy shoulders. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104260">Vanish from hence, and seek those idiots out</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104270">That thy fantastic godhead hath allowed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104280">And rule that giddy superstitious crowd. </l>
          <pb facs="14" n="21"/>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e104290">Hedone, pleasure, a young woman with a smiling face, in a light lascivious habit, adorned with silver and gold, her temples crowned with a garland of roses, and over that a rainbow circling her head down to her shoulders.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e104300">Hedone enters.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e104310" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e104320">What wanton's this?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e104330" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e104340">This is the sprightly lady Hedone, a merry gamester, this people call her pleasure.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e104350" who="A73704-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A73704-e104360">
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104370">The reasons (Equal judges) here alleged</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104380">By the dismist pretenders, all concur</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104390">To strengthen my just title to the sphere. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104400">Honour, or wealth, or the contempt of both,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104410">Have in themselves no simple real good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104420">But as they are the means to purchase pleasure;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104430">The paths that lead to my delicious palace;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104440">They for my sake, I for mine own am prized. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104450">Beyond me nothing is, I am the goal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104460">The journeys end, to which the sweating world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104470">And wearied nature travels. For this, the best</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104480">And wisest sect of all philosophers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104490">Made me the seat of supreme happiness. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104500">And though some, more austere, upon my ruins,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104510">Did to the prejudice of nature, raise</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104520">Some petty low-built virtues, 'twas because</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104530">They wanted wings to reach my soaring pitch. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104540">Had they been princes born, themselves had proved</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104550">Of all mankind the most luxurious. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104560">For those delights, which to their low condition</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104570">Were obvious, they with greedy appetite</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104580">Sucked and devoured: from offices of state,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104590">From cares of family, children, wife, hopes, fears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104600">Retired, the churlish cynic in his tub</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104610">Enjoyed those pleasures which his tongue defamed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104620">Nor am I ranked amongst the superfluous goods;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104630">My necessary offices preserve</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104640">Each single man, and propagate the kind. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104650">Then am I universal as the light,</l>
            <pb facs="15" n="24"/>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104660">Or common air we breathe; and since I am</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104670">The general desire of all mankind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104680">Civil Felicity must reside in me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104690">Tell me what rate my choicest pleasures bear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104700">When for the short delight of a poor draught</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104710">Of cheap cold water, great Lysimachus</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104720">Rendered himself slave to the Scythians. </l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104730">Should I the curious structure of my seats,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104740">The art and beauty of my several objects,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104750">Rehearse at large, your bounties would reserve</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104760">For every sense a proper constellation;</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104770">But I present their persons to your eyes. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A73704-e104780">
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104790">Come forth my subtle organs of delight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104800">With changing figures please the curious eye,</l>
            <l xml:id="A73704-e104810">And charm the ear with moving harmony. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e104820">They dance the seventh antimasque of the five senses.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e104830" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104840">Bewitching Siren's, guilded rottenness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104850">Thou hast with cunning artifice displayed</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104860">Th' enamelled outside, and the honeyed verge</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104870">Of the fair cup, where deadly poison lurks. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104880">Within, a thousand sorrows dance the round;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104890">And like a shell, pain circles thee without,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104900">Grief is the shadow waiting on thy steps,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104910">Which, as thy joys ''gin towards their West decline,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104920">Doth to a giant's spreading form extend</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104930">Thy dwarfish stature. Thou thyself art pain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104940">Greedy, intense desire, and the keen edge</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104950">Of thy fierce appetite, oft strangles thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104960">And cuts thy slender thread; but still the terror</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104970">And apprehension of thy hasty end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104980">Mingles with gall thy most refined sweets;</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e104990">Yet thy Cyrcaean charms transform the world. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105000">Captains, that have resisted war and death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105010">Nations, that over fortune have triumphed,</l>
          <pb facs="15" n="25"/>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105020">Are by thy magic made effeminate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105030">Empires, that knew no limits but the poles,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105040">Have in thy wanton lap melted away. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105050">Thou wert the author of the first excess</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105060">That drew this reformation on the gods. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105070">Canst thou then dream, those powers, that from heaven have</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105080">Banished th' effect, will there enthrone th' cause? </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105090">To thy voluptuous den, fly witch, from hence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105100">There dwell, for ever drowned in brutish sense. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e105110" who="A73704-momus">
          <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e105120">I concur, and am grown so weary of these tedious pleadings, as I'll pack up too and be gone: besides, I see a crowd of other suitors pressing hither, I'll stop 'em, take their petitions and prefer 'em above; and as I came in bluntly without knocking, and nobody bid me welcome; so I'll depart as abruptly without taking leave, and bid nobody fare well.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A73704-e105130" who="A73704-mercury">
          <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105140">These, with forced reasons, and strained arguments,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105150">Urge vain pretences, whilst your actions plead,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105160">And with a silent importunity</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105170">Awake the drowsy justice of the gods</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105180">To crown your deeds with immortality. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105190">The growing titles of your ancestors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105200">These nations glorious acts, joined to the stock</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105210">Of your own royal virtues, and the clear</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105220">Reflex they take from th'imitation</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105230">Of your famed court, make honour's story full,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105240">And have to that secure fixed state advanced</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105250">Both you and them, to which the labouring world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105260">Wading through streams of blood, sweats to aspire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105270">Those ancient worthies of these famous isles,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105280">That long have slept, in fresh and lively shapes</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105290">Shall straight appear, where you shall see yourself</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105300">Circled with modern heroes, who shall be</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105310">In act, whatever elder times can boast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105320">Noble, or great; as they in prophesy</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105330">Were all but what you are. Then shall you see</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105340">The sacred hand of bright eternity</l>
          <pb facs="16" n="26"/>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105350">Mould you to stars, and six you in the sphere. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105360">To you, your royal half, to them she'll join</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105370">Such of this train, as with industrious steps</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105380">In the fair prints your virtuous feet have made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105390">Though with unequal paces, follow you. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105400">This is decreed by Jove, which my return</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105410">Shall see performed; but first behold the rude</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105420">And old abiders here, and in them view</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105430">The point from which your full perfections grew. </l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105440">You naked, ancient wild inhabitants,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105450">That breathed this air, and pressed this flowery earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105460">Come from those shades where dwells eternal night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A73704-e105470">And see what wonders time hath brought to light. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e105480">
          <p xml:id="A73704-e105490">Atlas, and the sphere vanisheth, and a new scene appears of mountains, whose eminent height exceed the clouds which passed beneath them, the lower parts were wild and woody: out of this place comes forth a more grave antimasque of Picts, the natural inhabitants of this isle, ancient Scots and Irish, these dance a Perica or martial dance.</p>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e105500">When this antimasque was passed, there began to arise out of the earth the top of a hill, which by little and little grew to be a huge mountain that covered all the scene; the underpart of this was wild and craggy, and above somewhat more pleasant and flourishing: about the middle part of this mountain were seated the three kingdoms of England, Scotland, and Ireland; all richly attired in regal habits, appropriated to the several nations, with crowns on their heads, and each of them bearing the ancient arms of the kingdoms they represented: at a distance above these sat a young man in a white embroidered robe, upon his fair hair an olive garland with wings at his shoulders, and holding in his hand a cornucopia filled with corn and fruits, representing the genius of these kingdoms.</p>
        </stage>
        <pb facs="16" n="27"/>
        <floatingText xml:id="A73704-e105510">
          <body xml:id="A73704-e105520">
            <div n="1" type="song" xml:id="A73704-e105530">
              <head>The first song.</head>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e105540" who="A73704-genius">
                <speaker>Genius.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105550">Raise from these rocky cliffs, your heads,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105560">Brave sons, and see where glory spreads</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105570">Her glittering wings, where majesty</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105580">Crowned with sweet smiles, shoots from her eye</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105590">Diffusive joy, where good and fair,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105600">United sit in honour's chair. </l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105610">Call forth your aged priests, and crystal streams,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105620">To warm their hearts, and waves in these bright beam. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e105630" who="A73704-kingdoms">
                <speaker>Kingdom's.</speaker>
                <l n="1" xml:id="A73704-e105640">1. From your consecrated woods,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105650">Holy druids. 2. Silver floods,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105660">From your channels fringed with flowers,</l>
                <l n="3" xml:id="A73704-e105670">3. Hither move; for your hours</l>
                <l n="1" xml:id="A73704-e105680">1. Strewed with hallowed oaken leaves,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105690">Decked with flags and sedgy sheaves,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105700">And behold a wonder. 3. Say,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105710">What do your duller eyes survey? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e105720" who="A73704-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus of Drvids and rivers.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105730">We see at once in dead of night</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105740">A sun appear, and yet a bright</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105750">Noonday, springing from starlight. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e105760" who="A73704-genius">
                <speaker>Genius.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105770">Look up, and see the darkened sphere</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105780">Deprived of light, her eyes shine there;</l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e105790" who="A73704-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105800">These are more sparkling than those were. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e105810" who="A73704-kingdoms">
                <speaker>Kingdom's.</speaker>
                <l n="1" xml:id="A73704-e105820">1. These shed a nobler influence,</l>
                <l n="2" xml:id="A73704-e105830">2. These by a pure intelligence</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105840">Of more transcendent virtue move,</l>
                <l n="3" xml:id="A73704-e105850">3. These first feel, then kindle love. </l>
                <l n="1.2" xml:id="A73704-e105860">1.2. From the bosoms they inspire,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105870">These receive a mutual fire;</l>
                <l n="1.2.3" xml:id="A73704-e105880">1.2.3. And where their flames impure return,</l>
                <pb facs="17" n="28"/>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105890">These can quench as well as burn. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e105900" who="A73704-genius">
                <speaker>Genius.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105910">Here the fair victorious eyes. </l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105920">Make worth only beauty's prize,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105930">Here the hand of virtue ties</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105940">About the heart loves amorous chain,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105950">Captives triumph, vassals reign,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105960">And none live here but the slain. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e105970" who="A73704-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105980">These are th' Hesperian bowers, whose fair trees bear</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e105990">Rich golden fruit, and yet no dragon near. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106000" who="A73704-genius">
                <speaker>Genius.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106010">Then, from your imprisoning womb,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106020">Which is the cradle and the tomb</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106030">Of British worthies (Fair sons) send</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106040">A troop of heroes, that may lend</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106050">Their hands to case this loaden grove,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106060">And gather the ripe fruits of love. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106070" who="A73704-kingdoms">
                <speaker>Kingdom's.</speaker>
                <l n="1.2.3" xml:id="A73704-e106080">1.2.3. Open thy stony entrails wide,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106090">And break old Atlas, that the pride</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106100">Of three famed kingdoms may be spied. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106110" who="A73704-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106120">Pace forth thou mighty British Hercules,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106130">With thy choice band, for only thou, and these,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106140">May revel here, in love's hesperides. </l>
              </sp>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e106150">
          <p xml:id="A73704-e106160">At this the underpart of the rock opens, and out of a cave are seen to come the masquers, richly attired like ancient heroes, the colours yellow, embroidered with silver, their antique helms curiously wrought, and great plumes on the top; before them a troop of young lords and noblemen's sons bearing torches of virgin-wax, these were apparelled after the old British fashion in white coats, embroidered with silver, girt, and full gathered, cut square collared, and round caps on their heads, with a white feather wreath about them; first these dance with their lights in their hands: after which, the<pb facs="17" n="29"/> masquers descend into the room, and dance their entry.</p>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e106170">The dance being passed, there appears in the further part of the heaven coming down a pleasant cloud, bright and transparent, which coming softly downwards before the upper part of the mountain, embraceth the genius, but so as through it all his body is seen; and then rising again with a gentle motion bears up the genius of the three kingdoms, and being passed the airy region, pierceth the heavens, and is no more seen: at that instant the rock with the three kingdoms on it sinks, and is hidden in the earth. This strange spectacle gave great cause of admiration, but especially how so huge a machine, and of that great height could come from under the stage, which was but six foot high.</p>
        </stage>
        <floatingText xml:id="A73704-e106180">
          <body xml:id="A73704-e106190">
            <div n="2" type="song" xml:id="A73704-e106200">
              <head>The second song.</head>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106210" who="A73704-kingdoms">
                <speaker>Kingdom's.</speaker>
                <l n="1" xml:id="A73704-e106220">1. Here are shapes formed fit for heaven,</l>
                <l n="2" xml:id="A73704-e106230">2. These move gracefully and even,</l>
                <l n="3" xml:id="A73704-e106240">3. Here the air and paces meet</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106250">So just, as if the skilful feet</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106260">Had struck the vials. 1.2.3. So the ear</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106270">Might the tune full footing hear. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106280" who="A73704-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106290">And had the music silent been,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106300">The eye a moving tune had seen. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106310" who="A73704-genius">
                <speaker>Genius.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106320">These must in the unpeopled sky</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106330">Succeed, and govern destiny,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106340">Jove is tempering purer fire,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106350">And will with brighter flames attire</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106360">These glorious lights. I must ascend</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106370">And help the work. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106380" who="A73704-kingdoms">
                <speaker>Kingdom's.</speaker>
                <l n="1" xml:id="A73704-e106390">1. We cannot lend</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106400">Heaven so much treasure. 2. Nor that pay,</l>
                <pb facs="18" n="30"/>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106410">But rendering what it takes away. </l>
                <l n="3" xml:id="A73704-e106420">3. Why should they that here can move</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106430">So well, be ever-fixed above? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106440" who="A73704-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106450">Or be to one eternal posture tied,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106460">That can into such various figures slide. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106470" who="A73704-genius">
                <speaker>Genius.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106480">Jove shall not, to enrich the sky,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106490">Beggar the earth, their fame shall fly</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106500">From hence alone, and in the sphere</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106510">Kindle new stars, whilst they rest here. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106520" who="A73704-kingdoms">
                <speaker>Kingdom's.</speaker>
                <l n="1.2.3" xml:id="A73704-e106530">1.2.3. How can the shaft stay in the quiver,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106540">Yet hit the mark? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106550" who="A73704-genius">
                <speaker>Genius.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106560">Did not the river</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106570">Eridanus, the grace acquire</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106580">In heaven and earth to flow,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106590">Above in streams of golden fire,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106600">In silver waves below? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106610" who="A73704-kingdoms">
                <speaker>Kingdom's</speaker>
                <l n="1.2.3" xml:id="A73704-e106620">1.2.3. But shall not we, now thou art gone</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106630">Who wert our nature, wither,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106640">Or break that triple union</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106650">Which thy soul held together? </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e106660" who="A73704-genius">
                <speaker>Genius.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106670">In concord's purse immortal spring</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106680">I will my force renew,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106690">And a more active virtue bring</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106700">At my return. Adieu. </l>
              </sp>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e106710">Kingdom's adieu, chorus adieu.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e106720">
          <p xml:id="A73704-e106730">The masquers dance their main dance; which done, the scene again is varied into a new and pleasant prospect, clean differing from all the other, the nearest part showing a delicious garden with several walks and perterras set round with low trees, and on the sides against<pb facs="18" n="31"/> these walks, were fountains and grots, and in the furthest part a palace, from whence went high walks upon arches, and above them open terraces planted with cypress trees, and all this together was composed of such ornaments as might express a princely villa.</p>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e106740">From hence the chorus descending into the room, goes up to the state.</p>
        </stage>
        <floatingText xml:id="A73704-e106750">
          <body xml:id="A73704-e106760">
            <div n="3" type="song" xml:id="A73704-e106770">
              <head>The third song.</head>
              <stage xml:id="A73704-e106780">By the chorus going up to the Queen.</stage>
              <lg xml:id="A73704-e106790">
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106800">While thus the darlings of the gods</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106810">From honour's temple, to the shrine</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106820">Of beauty, and these sweet abodes</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106830">Of love, we guide, let thy divine</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106840">Aspects (Bright deity) with fair</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106850">And, halcyon beams, becalm the air. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A73704-e106860">
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106870">We bring prince Arthur, or the brave</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106880">St. George himself (Great Queen) to you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106890">You'll soon discern him; and we have</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106900">A Guy, a Beavis, or some true</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106910">Round-table knight, as ever fought</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106920">For lady, to each beauty brought. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A73704-e106930">
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106940">Plant in their martial hands, war's seat,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106950">Your peace full pledges of warm snow,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106960">And, if a speaking touch, repeat</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106970">In loves known language, tales of woe;</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106980">Say, in soft whispers of the palm,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e106990">As eyes shoot darts, so lips shed balm. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A73704-e107000">
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107010">For though you seem like captives, lid</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107020">In triumph by the foe away,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107030">Yet on the conquerors neck you tread,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107040">And the fierce victor proves your prey. </l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107050">What heart is then secure from you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107060">That can, though vanquished, yet subdue? </l>
              </lg>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <pb facs="19" n="32"/>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e107070">
          <p xml:id="A73704-e107080">The song done they retire, and the masquers dance the revels with the ladies, which continued a great part of the night.</p>
          <p xml:id="A73704-e107090">The revels being passed, and the King's majesty seated under the state by the Queen; for conclusion to this masque there appears coming forth from one of the sides, as moving by a gentle wind, a great cloud, which arriving at the middle of the heaven, stayeth; this was of several colours, and so great, that it covered the whole scene. Out of the further part of the heaven begins to break forth two other clouds, differing in colour and shape; and being fully discovered there appeared sitting in one of them, religion, truth, and wisdom. Religion was apparelled in white, and part of her face was covered with a light veil, in one hand a book, and in the other a same of fire. Truth in a watchet robe, a sun upon her forehead and bearing in her hand a palm. Wisdom in a mantle wrought with eyes and hands, golden rays about her head, and Apollo's Cythera in her hand. In the other cloud fate concord, government, and reputation. The habit of concord was carnation, bearing in her hand a little faggot of sticks bound together, and on the top of it a heart, and a garland of corn on her head: government was figured in a coat of armour, bearing a shield, and on it a Medusa's head; upon her head a plumed helm, and in her right hand a lance. Reputation, a young man in purple robe wrought with gold, and wearing a laurel wreath on his head. These being come down in an equal distance to the middle part of the air, the great cloud began to break open, out of which stroke beams of light; in the midst suspended in the air, sat eternity on a globe, his garment was long of a light blue, wrought all over with stars of gold, and bearing in his hand a serpent bent into a circle, with his tail in his mouth. In the firmament about him, was a troop of fifteen stars, expressing the stellifying of our British heroes; but one more great and eminent than the rest, which was over his head, figured<pb facs="19" n="30"/> his majesty. And in the lower part was seen afar off the prospect of Windsor castle, the famous seat of the most honourable order of the garter.</p>
        </stage>
        <floatingText xml:id="A73704-e107100">
          <body xml:id="A73704-e107110">
            <div n="4" type="song" xml:id="A73704-e107120">
              <head>The fourth song.</head>
              <stage xml:id="A73704-e107130">Eternity, Eusebia, Alethia, Sophia, Homonoia, dicaearche, Euphemia.</stage>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107140" who="A73704-eternity">
                <speaker>Eternitie.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107150">Be fixed you rapid orbs, that bear</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107160">The changing seasons of the year</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107170">On your swift wings, and see the old</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107180">Decrepit sphere grown dark and cold;</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107190">Nor did Jove quench her fires, these bright</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107200">Flames, have eclipsed her sullen light:</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107210">This royal pair, for whom fate will</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107220">Make motion cease, and time stand still;</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107230">Since good is here so perfect, as no worth</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107240">Is left for after-ages to bring forth. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107250" who="A73704-eusebeia">
                <speaker>Evsebia.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107260">Mortality cannot with more</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107270">Religious zeal, the gods adore. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107280" who="A73704-aletheia">
                <speaker>Alethia.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107290">My truths, from human eyes concealed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107300">Are naked to their sight revealed. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107310" who="A73704-sophia">
                <speaker>Sophia.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107320">Nor do their actions, from the guide</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107330">Of my exactest precepts slide. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107340" who="A73704-homonoia">
                <speaker>Homonoia.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107350">And as their own pure souls entwined,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107360">So are their subjects' hearts combined. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107370" who="A73704-dicaearche">
                <speaker>Dicaearches.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107380">So just, so gentle is their sway,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107390">As it seems empire to obey. </l>
              </sp>
              <pb facs="20" n="28"/>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107400" who="A73704-euphemia">
                <speaker>Euphemia.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107410">And their fair fame, like incense hurled</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107420">On altars, hath pefumed the world. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107430" who="A73704-sophia">
                <speaker>So.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107440">Wisdom. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107450" who="A73704-aletheia">
                <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107460">Truth. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107470" who="A73704-eusebeia">
                <speaker>Eus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107480">Pure adoration. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107490" who="A73704-homonoia">
                <speaker>Ho.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107500">Concord. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107510" who="A73704-dicaearche">
                <speaker>Di.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107520">Rule. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107530" who="A73704-euphemia">
                <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107540">Clear reputation,</l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107550" who="A73704-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107560">Crown this King, this Queen, this nation. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107570" who="A73704-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107580">Wisdom, truth, etc. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107590" who="A73704-eternity">
                <speaker>Eternitie.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107600">Brave spirits, whose adventurous feet</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107610">Have to the mountain's top aspired,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107620">Where fair desert, and honour meet,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107630">Here, from the toiling press retired,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107640">Secure from all disturbing evil,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107650">For ever in my temple revel. </l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107660">With wreathes of stars circled about,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107670">Guild all the spacious firmament,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107680">And smiling on the panting routs</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107690">That labour in the steep ascent,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107700">With your resistless influence guide</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107710">Of human change th' incertain tide</l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107720" who="A73704-multiple">
                <speaker>Eus. ale. Sop.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107730">But o you royal turtles, shed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107740">When you from earth remove,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107750">On the ripe fruits of your chaste bed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107760">Those sacred seeds of love. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107770" who="A73704-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107780">Which no power can but yours dispense,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107790">Since you the pattern bear from hence. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107800" who="A73704-multiple">
                <speaker>Hom dic. Eup.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107810">Then from your fruitful race shall flow</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107820">Endless succession,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107830">Sceptres shall bud, and laurels blow</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107840">About their immortal throne. </l>
              </sp>
              <pb facs="20" n="29"/>
              <sp xml:id="A73704-e107850" who="A73704-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107860">Propitious stars shall crown each birth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A73704-e107870">Whilst you rule them, and they the earth. </l>
              </sp>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <stage xml:id="A73704-e107880">
          <p xml:id="A73704-e107890">The song ended, the two clouds, with the persons sitting on them, ascend; the great cloud closeth again, and so passeth away overthwart the scene; leaving behind it no thing but a Sirene sky. After which, the masquers dance their last dance, and the curtain was let fall.</p>
        </stage>
        <div type="characters" xml:id="A73704-e107900">
          <list xml:id="A73704-e107910">
            <head>The names of the masquers.</head>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e107920">The King's majesty. </item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e107930">Duke of Lenox.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e107940">Earl of Devonshire.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e107950">Earl of Holland.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e107960">Earl of Newport.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e107970">Earl of Elgin.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e107980">Viscount Grandeson.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e107990">Lord rich.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108000">Lord Fielding.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108010">Lord Digby.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108020">Lord Dungarvin.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108030">Lord Dunluce.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108040">Lord Wharton.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108050">Lord Paget.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108060">Lord Saltine.</item>
          </list>
          <list xml:id="A73704-e108070">
            <head>The names of the young lords and noblemen's sons.</head>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108080">Lord Walden.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108090">Lord Craborne,</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108100">Lord Brackley.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108110">Lord Shandos.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108120">Mr. William Herbert.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108130">Mr. Thomas Howard.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108140">Mr. Thomas Egerton,</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108150">Mr. Charles Cavendish.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108160">Mr. Robert Howard.</item>
            <item xml:id="A73704-e108170">Mr. Henry Spencer.</item>
          </list>
          <pb facs="21"/>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A73704"><item xml:id="A73704-momus" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-momus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-mercury" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-mercury</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-chorus" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-chorus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-genius" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-genius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-kingdoms" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-kingdoms</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-aletheia" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-aletheia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-eternity" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-eternity</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-sophia" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-sophia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-homonoia" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-homonoia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-euphemia" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-euphemia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-multiple" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-multiple</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-eusebeia" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-eusebeia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-dicaearche" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-dicaearche</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-pleasure" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-pleasure</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-fortuna" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-fortuna</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-poverty" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-poverty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A73704-plutus" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A73704-plutus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

