<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Comedies and Tragedies<date type="creation_date">1647</date></title>
        <author>Beaumont, Francis</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A27177_00.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Comedies and tragedies written by Francis Beaumont and Iohn Fletcher ...</title>
            <author>Beaumont, Francis, 1584-1616.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>473 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno type="marc">12491932</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing B1581.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">52257</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27177</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Comedies and tragedies written by Francis Beaumont and Iohn Fletcher ...</title>
            <author>Beaumont, Francis, 1584-1616.</author>
            <author>Fletcher, John, 1579-1625.</author>
            <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
            <author>Lowin, John, 1576-1659.</author>
            <author>Taylor, Joseph, 1586?-1653?</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[53], 75, 143, [1], 165, [3], 71, [1], 172, 92, 50 [i.e. 52], 28, 25-48 p. : port.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Robinson ... and for Humphrey Moseley ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1647.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>"Never printed before, and now published by the authours originall copies"</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>First folio; includes the plays not hitherto printed, except the Wild-goose chase, which was missing, but recovered and printed in 1652. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>"The Epistle dedicatorie" is signed by John Lowin, Joseph Taylor, and eight others; "To the reader" signed by Ja. Shirley, who is usually regarded as the editor.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Portrait of Fletcher by Marshall.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>For complete contents of this edition, see NUC pre-1956 imprints.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A27177_00-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A27177_00-e100020">
      <div type="frontispiece" xml:id="A27177_00-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100040">
          <figure xml:id="A27177_00-e100050">
            <figDesc xml:id="A27177_00-e100060">engraved bust of Fletcher</figDesc>
            <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100070">Poetarjm jngenjosjssjmvs Joannes Fletcherus anglvs, epjscopj lond: fjljus</p>
            <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100080">Tragoedia comoedia</p>
            <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100090">Obyt 1625 aetat: 49</p>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100100">Felicis avi ac praesulis natus; comes</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100110">Beaumontio; sic, quip Parnassus, biceps;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100120">Fletcherus unam in Pyramida furcas agens. </l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100130">Struxit chorum plùs simplicem vates duplex;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100140">Plùs duplicem plus: nec ullum transtulit;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100150">Nec transferendus: dramatum aeterni sales,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100160">Anglo theatro, oebi, sibi, superstites. </l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100170">Fletchere, fancies absque vultu pingitur;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100180">Quantus! vel umbram circuit nemo tuam. </l>
            <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e100190">J. Berkenhead</signed>
            <ab type="byline" xml:id="A27177_00-e100200">Guliel 'marshal fecit</ab>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A27177_00-e100210">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100220">Comedies and tragedies</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100230">Written by Francis Beaumont and John Fletcher gentlemen.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100240">Never printed before, and now published by the authors original copies.</p>
        <quote xml:id="A27177_00-e100250">Si quid habent veri vatum praesagia, vivam.</quote>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100260">London, printed for Humphrey Robinson, at the three pigeons, and for Humphrey Moseley at the prince's arms in stPaul's churchyard. 1647.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A27177_00-e100270">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To the right honourable Philip Earl of Pembroke and Mountgomery: baron Herbert of Cardiff and Sherland, lord Parr and Ross of Kendall; lord Fitz-hugh, Marmyon, and saint Quintin; knight of the most noble order of the garter; and one of his majesty's most honourable privy council: and our singular good lord.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A27177_00-e100280">
          <salute xml:id="A27177_00-e100290">My lord,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100300">There is none among all the names of honour, that hath more encouraged the legitimate muses of this latter age, then that which is owing to your family; whose coronet shines bright with the native luster of its own jewels, which with the access of some beams of Sidney, twisted with their flame presents a constellation, from whose influence all good may be still expected upon wit and learning.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100310">At this truth we rejoice, but yet aloof, and in our own valley, for we dare not approach with any capacity in ourselves to apply your smile, since we have only preserved as trustees to the ashes of the authors, what we exhibit to your honour, it being no more our own, than those imperial crowns and garlands were the soldiers, who were honourably designed for their conveyance before the triumpher to the capitol. </p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100320">But directed by the example of some, who once steered in our quality, and so fortunately aspired to choose your honour, joined with your (Now glorified) brother, patrons to the flowing compositions of the then expired sweet swan of Avon Shakespeare; and since, more particularly bound to your lordship's<pb facs="3"/> most constant and diffusive goodness, from which, we did for many calm years derive a subsistence to ourselves, and protection to the scene (Now withered, and condemned, as we fear, to a long winter and sterility) we have presumed to offer to your self, what before was never printed of these authors. </p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100330">Had they been less than all the treasure we had contracted in the whole age of poesy (Some few poems of their own excepted, which already published, command their entertainment, with all lovers of art and language) or were they not, the most justly admired, and beloved pieces of wit and the world, we should have taught ourselves a less ambition.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100340">Be pleased to accept this humble tender of our duties, and till we fail in our obedience to all your commands, vouchsafe, we may be known by the cognizance and character of</p>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e100350">
          <salute xml:id="A27177_00-e100360">My lord,</salute>
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e100370">Your honour's most bounden</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A27177_00-e100380">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>To the reader.</head>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100390">Poetry is the child of nature, which regulated and made beautiful by art, presenteth the most harmonious of all other compositions; among which (If we rightly consider) the dramatical is the most absolute, in regard of those transcendent abilities, which should wait upon the composer; who must have more than the instruction of libraries which of itself is but a cold contemplative knowledge) there being required in him a soul miraculously knowing, and conversing with all mankind, enabling him to express not only the phlegm and folly of thick-skinned men, but the strength and maturity of the wise, the air and insinuations of the court, the discipline and resolution of the soldier, the virtues and passions of every noble condition, nay the counsels and characters of the greatest princes.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100400">This you will say is a vast comprehension, and hath not happened in many ages. Be it then remembered to the glory of our own, that all these are demonstrative and met in Beaumont and Fletcher, whom but to mention is to throw a cloud upon all former names and benight posterity; this book being, without flattery, the greatest monument of the scene that time and humanity have produced, and must live, not only the crown and sole reputation of our own, but the stain of all other nations and languages, for it may be boldly averred, not one indiscretion hath branded this paper in all the lines, this being the authentic wit that made Blackfriars an academy, where the three hours spectacle while Beaumont and Fletcher were presented, were usually of more advantage to the hopeful young heir, than a costly, dangerous, foreign travel, with the assistance of a governing monsieur, or signior to boot; and it cannot be denied but that the young spirits of the time, whose birth and quality made them impatient of the sourer ways of education, have from the attentive hearing these pieces, got ground in point of wit and carriage of the most severely employed students, while these recreations were digested into rules, and the very pleasure did edify. How many passable discoursing dining wits stand yet in good credit upon the bare stock of two or three of these single scenes.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100410">And now reader in this tragical age where the theater hath been so much out-acted, congratulate thy own happiness that in this silence of the stage, thou hast a liberty to read these inimitable plays, to dwell and converse in these immortal groves, which were only showed our fathers in a conjuring glass, as suddenly removed as represented, the landscrap is now brought home by this optic, and the press thought too pregnant before shall be now looked upon as greatest<pb facs="4"/> benefactor to Englishmen, that must acknowledge all the felicity of wit and words to this derivation.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100420">You may here find passions raised to that excellent pitch and by such insinuating degrees that you shall not choose but consent, and go along with them, finding yourself at last grown insensibly the very same person you read, and then stand admiring the subtle tracks of your engagement. Fall on a scene of love and you will never believe the writers could have the least room left in their souls for another passion, peruse a scene of manly rage, and you would swear they cannot be expressed by the same hands, but both are so excellently wrought, you must confess none, but the same hands, could work them.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100430">Would thy melancholy have a cure? thou shalt laugh at Democritus himself, and but reading one piece of this comic variety, find thy exalted fancy in Elysium; and when thou art sick of this cure, (For the excess of delight may too much dilate thy soul) thou shalt meet almost in every leaf a soft purling passion or spring of sorrow so powerfully wrought high by the tears of innocence, and wronged lovers, it shall persuade thy eyes to weep into the stream, and yet smile when they contribute to their own ruins.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100440">Infinitely more might be said of these rare copies, but let the ingenuous reader peruse them and he will find them so able to speak their own worth, that they need not come into the world with a trumpet, since any one of these incomparable pieces well understood will prove a preface to the rest, and if the reader can taste the best wit ever trod our English stage, he will be forced himself to become a breathing panegerick to them all.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100450">Not to detain or prepare thee longer, be as capricious and sick-brained, as ignorance and malice can make thee, here thou art rectified, or be as healthful as the inward calm of an honest heart, learning, and temper can state thy disposition, yet this book may be thy fortunate concernment and companion.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100460">It is not so remote in time, but very many gentlemen may remember these authors and some familiar in their conversation deliver them upon every pleasant occasion so fluent, to talk a comedy. He must be a bold man that dares undertake to write their lives. What I have to say is, we have the precious remains, and as the wisest contemporaries acknowledge they lived a miracle, I am very confident this volume cannot die without one.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100470">What more specially concern these authors and their works is told thee by another hand in the following epistle of the stationer to the readers. </p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100480">Farewell, read, and fear not thine own understanding, this book will create a clear one in thee, and when thou hast considered thy purchase, thou wilt call the price of it a charity to thyself, and at the same time forgive thy friend, and these authors humble admirer,</p>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e100490">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e100500">Ja. Shirley.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="stationer_to_the_reader" xml:id="A27177_00-e100510">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <head>The stationer to the readers.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A27177_00-e100520">
          <salute xml:id="A27177_00-e100530">Gentlemen,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100540">Before you engage farther, be pleased to take notice of these particulars. You have here a new book; I can speak it clearly; for of all this large volume of comedies and tragedies, not one, till now, was ever printed before. A collection of plays is commonly but a new impression, the scattered pieces which were printed single, being then only republished together: 'tis otherwise here.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100550">Next, as it is all new, so here is not any thing spurious or imposed; I had the originals from such as received them from the authors themselves; by those, and none other, I publish this edition.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100560">And as here's nothing but what is genuine and theirs, so you will find here are no omissions; you have not only all I could get, but all that you must ever expect. For (Besides those which were formerly printed) there is not any piece written by these authors, either jointly or severally, but what are now published to the world in this volume. One only play I must except (For I mean to deal openly) 'tis a comedy called the wild-goose chase, which hath been long lost, and I fear irrecoverable; for a person of quality borrowed it from the actors many years since, and (By the negligence of a servant) it was never returned; therefore now I put up this si quis, that whosoever hereafter happily meets with it, shall be thankfully satisfied if he please to send it home.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100570">Some plays (You know) written by these authors were heretofore printed: I thought not convenient to mix them with this volume, which of itself is entirely new. And indeed it would have rendered the book so voluminous, that ladies and gentlewomen would have found it scarce manageable, who in works of this nature must first be remembered. Besides, I considered those former pieces had been so long printed and reprinted, that many gentlemen were already furnished; and I would have none say, they pay twice for the same book.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100580">One thing I must answer before it be objected; 'tis this: when these comedies and tragedies were presented on the stage, the actors omitted some scenes and passages (With the author's consent) as occasion led them; and when private friends desired a copy, they then (And justly too) transcribed what they acted. But now you have both all that was acted, and all that was not; even the perfect full originals without the least mutilation; so that were the authors living, (And sure they can never die) they themselves would challenge neither more nor less than what is here published; this volume being now so complete and finished, that the reader must expect no future alterations.</p>
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100590">For literal errors committed by the printer, 'tis the fashion to ask pardon, and as much in fashion to take no notice of him that asks it; but in this also I have done my endeavour. 't were vain to mention the chargeableness of this work; for those who owned the manuscripts, too well known their value to make a cheap estimate of any of these pieces, and though another joined with me in the purchase and printing, yet the care and pains was wholly mine, which I found to be more than you'll easily imagine, unless you knew into how many hands the originals were dispersed. They are all now happily met in this book, having escaped these public troubles, free and unmangled. Heretofore when gentlemen desired but a copy of any of these plays, the meanest piece here (If any may be called mean where every one is best) cost them more than four times the price you pay for the whole volume. </p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100600">I should scarce have adventured in these slippery times on such a work as this, if knowing persons had not generally assured me that these authors were the most unquestionable wits this kingdom hath afforded. Mr. Beaumont was ever acknowledged a man of a most strong and searching brain; and (His years considered) the most judicious wit these later ages have produced; he died young, for (Which was an invaluable loss to this nation) he left the world when he was not full thirty years old. Mr. Fletcher survived, and lived till almost fifty; whereof the world now enjoys the benefit. It was once in my thoughts to have printed Mr. fletcher's works by themselves, because single and alone he would make a just volume: but since never parted while they lived, I conceived it not equitable to separate their ashes.</p>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e100610">It becomes not me to say (Though it be a known truth) that these authors had not only high unexpressible gifts of nature, but also excellent acquired parts, being furnished with arts and sciences by that liberal education they had at the university, which sure is the best place to make a great wit understand itself; this their works will soon make evident. I was very ambitious to have got Mr. Beaumont's picture; but could not possibly, though I spared no enquiry in those noble families whence he was descended, as also among those gentlemen that were his acquaintance when he was of the inner temple: the best pictures and those most like him you'll find in this volume. This figure of Mr. Fletcher was out by several original pieces, which his friends lent me, but withal they tell me, that his unimitable soul did shine through his countenance in such air and spirit, that the painters confessed it, was not easy to express him: as much as could be, you have here, and the graver hath done his part. Whatever I have seen of Mr. Fletcher's own hand, is free from interlining; and his friends affirm he never writ any one thing twice: it seems he had that rare felicity to prepare and perfect all first in his own brain; to shape and attire his notions, to add or lop off, before he committed one word to writing, and never touched pen till all was to stand as firm and immutable as if engraven in brass or marble. But I keep you too long from those friends of his whom 'tis fitter for you to read; only accept of the honest endeavours of</p>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e100620">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e100630">One that is a servant to you all Humphrey Moseley. </signed>
          <dateline xml:id="A27177_00-e100640">at the prince's arms in saint Paul's churchyard. <date xml:id="A27177_00-e100650">Feb. 14th 1646.</date></dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="poem_to_the_stationer" xml:id="A27177_00-e100660">
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <head>To the stationer.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100670">Tell the sad world that now the labouring press</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100680">Has brought forth safe a child of happiness,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100690">The frontispiece will satisfy the wise</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100700">And good so well, they will not grudge the price. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100710">'Tis not all kingdoms joined in one could buy</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100720">(If prized aright) so true a library</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100730">Of man: where we the characters may find</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100740">Of every nobler and each baser mind. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100750">Desert has here reward in one good line</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100760">For all it lost, for all it might repine:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100770">Vile and ignobler things are open laid,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100780">The truth of their false colours are displayed:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100790">You'll say the poet's both best judge and priest,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100800">No guilty soul abides so sharp a test</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100810">As their smooth pen; for what these rare men writ</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100820">Commands the world, both honesty and wit. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e100830">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e100840">Grandison</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e100850">
        <pb facs="6"/>
        <head>In memory of Mr. John Fletcher.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100860">Methought our Fletcher weary of this crowd,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100870">Wherein so few have wit, yet all are loud,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100880">Unto Elysium fled, where he alone</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100890">Might his own wit admire and ours bemoan;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100900">But soon upon those flowery banks, a throng</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100910">Worthy of those even numbers which he sung,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100920">Appeared, and though those ancient laureates strive</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100930">When dead themselves, whose raptures should survive,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100940">For his temples all their own bays allows,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100950">Not shamed to see him crowned with naked brows;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100960">Homer his beautiful Achilles named,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100970">Urging his brain with Jove's might well be famed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100980">Since it brought forth one full of beauty's charms,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e100990">As was his Pallas, and as bold in arms;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101000"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A27177_00-e101010">King and no King.</note> but when he the brave Arbases saw, one</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101020">That saved his people's dangers by his own,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101030">And saw Tigranes by his hand undone</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101040">Without the help of any Myrmidon,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101050">He then confessed when next he'd Hector slay,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101060">That he must borrow him from Fletcher's play;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101070">This might have been the shame, for which he bid</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101080">His Iliades in a nutshell should be hid:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101090">Virgil of his Aeneas next begun,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101100">Whose godlike form and tongue so soon had won;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101110">That Queen of Carthage and of beauty too,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101120">Two powers the whole world else were slaves unto,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101130">Urging that prince for to repair his fault</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101140">On earth, boldly in hell his mistress sought;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101150"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A27177_00-e101160">the maids tragedy.</note> but when he Amintor saw revenge that wrong,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101170">For which the sad Aspasia sighed so long,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101180">Upon himself, to shades hasting away,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101190">Not for to make a visit but to stay;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101200">He then did modestly confess how far</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101210">Fletcher outdid him in a character. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101220">Now lastly for a refuge, Virgil shows</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101230">The lines where Corydon Alexis woes;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101240">But those in opposition quickly met</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101250"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A27177_00-e101260">the faithful shepherdess.</note> the smooth tongued Perigot and Amoret:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101270">A pair whom doubtless had the others seen,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101280">They from their own loves had apostates been;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101290">Thus Fletcher did the famed laureate exceed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101300">Both when his trumpet sounded and his reed;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101310">Now if the ancients yield that heretofore,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101320">None worthier than those ere laurel wore;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101330">The least our age can say now thou art gone,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101340">Is that there never will be such a one:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101350">And since t'express thy worth, our rhymes too narrow be,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101360">To help it we'll be ample in our pprophecy. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e101370">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e101380">H. Howard.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e101390">
        <pb facs="6"/>
        <head>On Mr. John Fletcher, and his works, never before published.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101400">To flatter living fools is easy slight:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101410">But hard, to do the living-dead men right. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101420">To praise a landed lord, is gainful art:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101430">But thankless to pay tribute to desert. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101440">This should have been my task: I had intent</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101450">To bring my rubbish to thy monument,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101460">To stop some crannies there, but that I found</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101470">No need of least repair; all firm and sound. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101480">Thy well-built fame doth still itself advance</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101490">Above the world's mad zeal and ignorance,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101500">Though thou died'st not possessed of that same pelf</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101510">(Which nobler souls call dirt,) the city wealth:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101520">Yet thou hast left unto the times so great</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101530">A legacy, a treasure so complete,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101540">That 'twill be hard I fear to prove thy will:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101550">Men will be wrangling, and in doubting still</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101560">How so vast sums of wit were left behind,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101570">And yet nor debts nor sharers they can find. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101580">'Twas the kind providence of fate, to lock</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101590">Some of this treasure up; and keep a stock</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101600">For a reserve until these sullen days:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101610">When scorn, and want, and danger, are the bays</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101620">That crown the head of merit. But now he</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101630">Who in thy will hath part, is rich and free. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101640">But there's a caveat entered by command,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101650">None should pretend, but those can understand. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e101660">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e101670">Henry Mody, baronet.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e101680">
        <pb facs="7"/>
        <head>On Mr. Fletcher's works.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e101690">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101700">Though poets have a licence which they use</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101710">As th'ancient privilege of their free muse;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101720">Yet whether this be leave enough for me</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101730">To write, great bard, an eulogy for thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101740">Or whether to commend thy work, will stand</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101750">Both with the laws of verse and of the land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101760">Were to put doubts might raise a discontent</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101770">Between the Muses and the —</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101780">I'll none of that. There's desperate wits that be</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101790">(As their immortal laurel) thunder-free;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101800">Whose personal virtues, above the laws of fate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101810">Supply the room of personal estate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101820">And thus enfranchised, safely may rehearse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101830">Rapt in a lofty strain, theirs own neck-verse. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101840">For he that gives the bays to thee, must then</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101850">First take it from the military men;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101860">He must untriumph conquests, bid 'emstand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101870">Question the strength of their victorious hand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101880">He must act new things, or go near the sin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101890">Reader, as near as you and I have been:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101900">He must be that, which he that tries will swear</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101910">Ii is not good being so another year. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e101920">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101930">And now that thy great name I've brought to this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101940">To do it honour is to do amiss,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101950">What's to be done to those, that shall refuse</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101960">To celebrate, great soul, thy noble muse? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101970">Shall the poor state of all those wand'ring things,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101980">Thy stage once raised to emperors and Kings? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e101990">Shall rigid forfeitures (That reach our heirs)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102000">Of things that only fill with cares and fears? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102010">Shall the privation of a friendless life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102020">Made up of contradictions and strife? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102030">Shall he be entity, would antedate</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102040">His own poor name, and thine annihilate? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102050">Shall these be judgements great enough for one</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102060">That dares not write thee an encomion? </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e102070">
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102080">Then where am i? but now I've thought upon't,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102090">I'll praise thee more than all have ventured on't. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102100">I'll take thy noble work (And like the trade</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102110">Where for a heap of salt pure gold is laid)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102120">I'll lay thy volume, that huge tome of wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102130">About in ladies' closets, where they sit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102140">Enthroned in their own wills; and if she be</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102150">A laic sister, she'll straight fly to thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102160">But if a holy habit she have on,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102170">Or be some novice, she'll scarce look upon</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102180">Thy lines at first; but watch her then a while,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102190">And you shall see her steal a gentle smile</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102200">Upon thy title, put thee nearer yet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102210">Breath on thy lines a whisper, and then set</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102220">Her voice up to the measures; then begin</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102230">To bless the hour, and happy state she's in. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102240">Now she lays by her characters, and looks</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102250">With a stern eye on all her pretty books. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102260">She's now thy votaress, and the just crown</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102270">She brings thee with it, is worth half the town. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e102280">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102290">I'll send thee to the army, they that fight</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102300">Will read thy tragedies with some delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102310">Be all thy reformadoes, fancy scars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102320">And pay too, in thy speculative wars. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e102330">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102340">I'll send thy comic scenes to some of those</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102350">That for a great while have played fast and loose;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102360">New universalists, by changing shapes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102370">Have made with wit and fortune fair escapes. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e102380">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102390">Then shall the country that poor tennis-ball</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102400">Of angry fate, receive thy pastoral,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102410">And from it learn those melancholy strains</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102420">Fed the afflicted souls of primitive swains. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102430">Thus the whole world to reverence will flock</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102440">Thy tragic buskin and thy comic stock:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102450">And winged fame unto posterity</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102460">Transmit but only two, this age, and thee. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e102470">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e102480">Thomas Peyton. Agricola anglo-cantianus.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e102490">
        <pb facs="8"/>
        <head>On the deceased author, Mr. John Fletcher, his plays; and especially, the mad lover. </head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102500">While his well organed body doth retreat,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102510">To its first matter, and the formal heat</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102520">Triumphant sits in judgement to approve</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102530">Pieces above our candour and our love:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102540">Such as dare boldly venture to appear</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102550">Unto the curious eye, and critic ear:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102560">Lo the mad lover in these various times</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102570">Is pressed to life, t'accuse us of our crimes. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102580">While Fletcher lived, who equal to him writ</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102590">Such lasting monuments of natural wit? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102600">Others might draw their lines with sweat, like those</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102610">That (With much pains) a garrison enclose;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102620">Whilst his sweet fluent vein did gently run</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102630">As uncontrolled, and smoothly as the sun. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102640">After his death our theatres did make</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102650">Him in his own unequalled language speak:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102660">And now when all the muses out of their</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102670">Approved modesty silent appear,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102680">This play of Fletcher's braves the envious light</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102690">As wonder of our ears once, now our sight. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102700">Three and fourfold blessed poet, who the lives</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102710">Of poets, and of theatres survives! </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102720">A groom, or ostler of some wit may bring</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102730">His Pegasus to the Castalian spring;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102740">Boast he a race o'er the Pharsalian plain,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102750">Or happy Tempe valley dares maintain:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102760">Brag at one leap upon the double cliff</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102770">(Were it as high as monstrous Tennariffe)</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102780">Of far-renowned Parnassus he will get,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102790">And there (To amaze the world) confirm his seat:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102800">When our admired Fletcher vaunts not ought,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102810">And slighted every thing he writ as naught:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102820">While all our English wondering world (In's cause)</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102830">Made this great city echo with applause. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102840">Read him therefore all that can read, and those</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102850">That cannot learn, if you're not learning's foes,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102860">And wilfully resolved to refuse</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102870">The gentle raptures of this happy muse. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102880">From thy great constellation (Noble soul)</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102890">Look on this kingdom, suffer not the whole</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102900">Spirit of poesy retire to heaven,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102910">But make us entertain what thou hast given. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102920">Earthquakes and thunder diapasons make</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102930">The sea's vast roar, and irrestistless shake</l>
        <pb facs="8"/>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102940">Of horrid winds, a sympathy compose;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102950">So in these things there's music in the close:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102960">And though they seem great discords in our ears,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102970">They are not so to them above the spheres. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102980">Granting these music, how much sweeter's that</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e102990">Mnemosyne's daughter's voices do create? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103000">Since heaven, and earth, and seas, and air consent</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103010">To make an harmony (The instrument,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103020">Their own agreeing selves) shall we refuse</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103030">The music which the deities do use? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103040">Troy's ravished Ganymed doth sing to Jove,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103050">And Phoebus self plays on his lyre above. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103060">The Cretan gods, or glorious men, who will</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103070">Imitate right, must wonder at thy skill,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103080">Best poet of thy times, or he will prove</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103090">As mad as thy brave Memnon was with love. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e103100">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e103110">Aston Cokaine, baronet.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e103120">
        <head>Upon the works of Beaumont, and Fletcher.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103130">How angels (Cloistered in our humane cells)</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103140">Maintain their parley, Beaumount-fletcher tells;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103150">Whose strange unimitable intercourse</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103160">Transcends all rules, and flies beyond the force</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103170">Of the most forward souls; all must submit</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103180">Until they reach these mysteries of wit. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103190">The intellectual language here's expressed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103200">Admired in better times, and dares the test</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103210">Of ours; for from wit, sweetness, mirth, and sense,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103220">This volume springs a new true quintessence. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e103230">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e103240">Jo. Pettus, knight.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e103250">
        <pb facs="9"/>
        <head>On the works of the most excellent dramatic poet, Mr. John Fletcher, never before printed.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e103260">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103270">Hail Fletcher, welcome to the world's great stage;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103280">For our two hours, we have thee here an age</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103290">In thy whole works, and may th'impression call</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103300">The praetor that presents thy plays to all:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103310">Both to the people, and the lords that sway</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103320">That herd, and ladies whom those lords obey. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103330">And what's the loadstone can such guests invite</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103340">But moves on two poles, profit, and delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103350">Which will be soon, as on the rack, confessed</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103360">When every one is tickled with a jest:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103370">And that pure Fletcher, able to subdue</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103380">A melancholy more than Burton knew. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103390">And though upon the by, to his designs</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103400">The native may learn English from his lines,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103410">And th' alien if he can but construe it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103420">May here be made free denizen of wit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103430">But his main end does drooping virtue raise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103440">And crowns her beauty with eternal bays;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103450">In scenes where she inflames the frozen soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103460">While vice (Her paint washed off) appears so foul;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103470">She must this blessed isle and Europe leave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103480">And some new quadrant of the globe deceive:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103490">Or hide her blushes on the Afrique shore</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103500">Like Marius, but never rise to triumph more;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103510">That honour is resigned to Fletcher's fame;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103520">Add to his trophies, that a poet's name</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103530">(Late grown as odious to our modern states</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103540">As that of King to Rome) he vindicates</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103550">From black aspersions, cast upon't by those</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103560">Which only are inspired to lie in prose. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e103570">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103580">And, by the court of Muses be't decreed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103590">What graces spring from Poesy's richer seed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103600">When we name Fletcher shall be so proclaimed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103610">As all that's royal is when caesar's named. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e103620">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e103630">Robert Stapylton knight.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e103640">
        <pb facs="9"/>
        <head>To the memory of my most honoured kinsman, Mr. Francis Beaumont. </head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e103650">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103660">I'll not pronounce how strong and clean thou writes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103670">Nor by what new hard rules thou tookest thy flights,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103680">Nor how much Greek and Latin some refine</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103690">Before they can make up six words of thine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103700">But this I'll say, thou strikest our sense so deep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103710">At once thou mak'st us blush, rejoice, and weep. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103720">Great father Johnson bowed himself when he</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103730">(Thou writest so nobly) vowed he envied thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103740">Were thy Mardonius armed, there would be more</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103750">Strife for his sword then all Achilles wore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103760">Such wise just rage, had he been lately tried</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103770">My life on't he had been o'th' better side,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103780">And where he found false odds (Through gold or sloth)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103790">There brave Mardonius would have be at them both. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e103800">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103810">Behold, here's Fletcher too! the world never knew</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103820">Two potent wits cooperate till you;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103830">For still your fancies are so woven and knit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103840">'Twas Francis-fletcher, or John Beaumont writ. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103850">Yet neither borrowed, nor were so put to't</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103860">To call poor gods and goddesses to do't;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103870">Nor made nine girls your muses (You suppose</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103880">Women never write, save love-letters in prose)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103890">But are your own inspirers, and have made</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103900">Such powerful scenes, as when they please, invade. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103910">Your plot, sense, language, all's so pure and fit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103920">He's bold, not valiant, dare dispute your wit. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e103930">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e103940">George Lisle knight.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e103950">
        <pb facs="10"/>
        <head>On Mr. John Fletcher's works.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e103960">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103970">So shall we joy, when all whom beasts and worms</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103980">Had turned to their own substances and forms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e103990">Whom earth to earth, or fire hath changed to fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104000">We shall behold more than at first entire</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104010">As now we do, to see all thine, thine own</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104020">In this thy muse's resurrection,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104030">Whose scattered parts, from thy own race, more wounds</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104040">Hath suffered, than Actaeon from his hounds;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104050">Which first their brains, and then their bellies fed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104060">And from their excrements new poets bred. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104070">But now thy muse enraged from her urn</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104080">Like ghosts of murdered bodies doth return</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104090">To accuse the murderers, to right the stage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104100">And undeceive the long abused age,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104110">Which casts thy praise on them, to whom thy wit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104120">Gives not more gold than they give dross to it:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104130">Who not content like felons to purloin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104140">Add treason to it, and debase thy coin. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e104150">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104160">But whither am I strayed? I need not raise</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104170">Trophies to thee from other men's dispraise;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104180">Nor is thy fame on lesser ruins built,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104190">Nor needs thy juster title the foul guilt</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104200">Of Eastern Kings, who to secure their reign,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104210">Must have their brothers, sons, and kindred slain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104220">Then was wit's empire at the fatal height,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104230">When labouring and sinking with its weight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104240">From thence a thousand lesser poets sprung</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104250">Like petty princes from the fall of Rome. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104260">When Johnson, Shakespeare, and thyself did sit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104270">And swayed in the triumvirate of wit —</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104280">Yet what from Jonson's oil and sweat did flow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104290">Or what more easy nature did bestow</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104300">On Shakespeare's gentler muse, in thee full grown</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104310">Their graces both appear, yet so, that none</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104320">Can say here nature ends, and art begins</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104330">But mixed like th'elements, and born like twins,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104340">So interweaved, so like, so much the same,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104350">None this mere nature, that mere art can name:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104360">'Twas this the ancients meant, nature and skill</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104370">Are the two tops of their Parnassus hill. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e104380">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e104390">I. Denham.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e104400">
        <pb facs="10"/>
        <head>Upon Mr. John fletcher's plays.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104410">Fletcher, to thee, we do not only owe</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104420">All these good plays, but those of others too:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104430">Thy wit repeated, does support the stage,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104440">Credits the last, and entertains this age. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104450">No worthies formed by any muse but thine</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104460">Could purchase robes to make themselves so fine:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104470">What brave commander is not proud to see</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104480">Thy brave Melantius in his gallantry,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104490">Our greatest ladies love to see their scorn</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104500">Out done by thine in what themselves have worn:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104510">Th'impatient widow ere the year be done</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104520">Sees thy Aspasia weeping in her gown:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104530">I never yet the tragic strain assayed</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104540">Deterred by that inimitable maid:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104550">And when I venture at the comic style</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104560">Thy scornful lady seems to mock my toil:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104570">Thus has thy muse, at once, improved and marred</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104580">Our sport in plays, by rendering it too hard. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104590">So when a sort of lusty shepherds throw</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104600">The bar by turns, and none the rest outgo</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104610">So far, but that the best are measuring casts,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104620">Their emulation and their pastime lasts;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104630">But if some brawny yeoman, of the guard</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104640">Step in and toss the axletree a yard</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104650">Or more beyond the farthest mark, the rest</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104660">Despairing stand, their sport is at the best. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e104670">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e104680">Edw. Waller.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e104690">
        <pb facs="11"/>
        <head>To Fletcher revived.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e104700">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104710">How have I been religious? what strange good</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104720">Has 'scaped me that I never understood? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104730">Have I hell guarded heresy o'erthrown? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104740">Healed wounded states? made Kings and kingdoms one? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104750">That fate should be so merciful to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104760">To let me live t'have said I have read thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104770">Fair star ascend! the joy! the life! the light</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104780">Of this tempestuous age, this dark world's sight! </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104790">O from thy crown of glory dart one flame</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104800">May strike a sacred reverence, whilst thy name</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104810">(Like holy flamens to their god of day)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104820">We bowing, sing; and whilst we praise, we pray. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e104830">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104840">Bright spirit! whose eternal motion</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104850">Of wit, like time, still in itself did run;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104860">Binding all others in it, and did give</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104870">Commission, how far this, or that shall live:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104880">Like destiny of poems, who, as she</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104890">Signs death to all, herself can never die. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e104900">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104910">And now thy purple-robbed tragedy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104920">In her embroidered buskins, calls mine eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104930"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A27177_00-e104940">Valentinian</note> where brave Aëtius we see betrayed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104950">T'obey his death, whom thousand lives obeyed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104960">Whilst that the mighty fool his sceptre breaks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104970">And through his generals wounds his own doom speaks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104980">Weaving thus richly Valentinian</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e104990">The costliest monarch with the cheapest man. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e105000">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105010"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A27177_00-e105020">the mad lover.</note>soldier's may here to their old glories add,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105030">The lover love, and be with reason mad:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105040">Not as of old, Alcides' furious,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105050">Who wilder than his bull did tear the house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105060">(Hurling his language with the canvas stone)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105070">'Twas thought the monster roared the sob'rer tone. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e105080">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105090"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A27177_00-e105100">tragi-comedies.</note>but ah, when thou thy sorrow didst inspire</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105110">With passions, black as is her dark attire,</l>
          <pb facs="11"/>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105120">Virgins as sufferers have wept to see</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105130">So white a soul, so red a cruelty;<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A27177_00-e105140">Arcas. Bellario.</note></l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105150">That thou hast grieved, and with unthought redress,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105160">Dried their wet eyes who now thy mercy bless;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105170">Yet loath to lose thy watery jewel, when</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105180">Joy wiped it off, laughter straight sprang again. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e105190">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105200">Now ruddy cheeked mirth with rosy wings,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A27177_00-e105210">comedies. The Spanish curate. The humorous lieutenant. The tamer tamed. The little French lawyer.</note></l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105220">Fans every brow with gladness, whilst she sings</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105230">Delight to all, and the whole theatre</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105240">A festival in heaven doth appear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105250">Nothing but pleasure, love, and (Like the morn)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105260">Each face a general smiling doth adorn. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e105270">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105280">Hear ye foul speakers, that pronounce the air</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105290">Of stews and shores, I will inform you where</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105300">And how to clothe aright your wanton wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105310">Without her nasty bawd attending it. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105320">View here a loose thought said with such a grace,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A27177_00-e105330">the custom of the country.</note></l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105340">Minerva might have spoke in Venus' face;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105350">So well disguised, that was conceived by none</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105360">But Cupid had Diana's linen on;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105370">And all his naked parts so veiled, th' express</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105380">The shape with clouding the uncomeliness;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105390">That if this reformation which we</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105400">Received, had not been buried with thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105410">The stage (As this work) might have lived and loved;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105420">Her lines; the austere scarlet had approved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105430">And th' actors wisely been from that offence</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105440">As clear, as they are now from audience. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e105450">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105460">Thus with thy genius did the scene expire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105470">Wanting thy active and inliv'ning fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105480">That now (To spread a darkness over all,)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105490">Nothing remains but poesy to fall. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105500">And though from these thy embers we receive</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105510">Some warmth, so much as may be said, we live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105520">That we dare praise thee, blushless, in the head</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105530">Of the best piece Hermes to love e'er read,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105540">That we rejoice and glory in thy wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105550">And feast each other with remembering it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105560">That we dare speak thy thought, thy acts recite</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105570">Yet all men henceforth be afraid to write. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e105580">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e105590">Rich. Lovelace.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e105600">
        <pb facs="12"/>
        <head>On master John Fletcher's dramatical poems.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105610">Great tutelary spirit of the stage! </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105620">Fletcher! I can fix nothing but my rage</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105630">Before thy works, 'gainst their officious crime</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105640">Who print thee now, in the worst scene of time. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105650">For me, uninterrupted hadst thou slept</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105660">Among the holly shades and close hadst kept</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105670">The mystery of thy lines, till men might be</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105680">Taught how to read, and then, how to read thee. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105690">But now thou art exposed to th'common fate,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105700">Revive then (Mighty soul!) and vindicate</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105710">From th' ages rude affronts thy injured fame,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105720">Instruct the envious, with how chaste a flame</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105730">Thou warmest the lover; how severely just</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105740">Thou wert to punish, if he burned to lust. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105750">With what a blush thou didst the maid adorn,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105760">But tempted, with how innocent a scorn. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105770">How epidemic errors by thy play</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105780">Were laughed out of esteem, so purged away. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105790">How to each sense thou so didst virtue fit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105800">That all grew virtuous to be thought t'have wit. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105810">But this was much too narrow for thy art,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105820">Thou didst frame governments, give Kings their part,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105830">Teach them how near to God, while just they be;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105840">But how dissolved, stretched forth to tyranny. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105850">How kingdoms, in their channel, safely run,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105860">But rudely overflowing are undone. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105870">Though vulgar spirits poets scorn or hate:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105880">Man may beget, a poet can create. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e105890">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e105900">Will. Habington.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e105910">
        <pb facs="12"/>
        <head>Upon master Fletcher's dramatical works.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105920">What? now the stage is down, dar'st thou appear</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105930">Bold Fletcher in this tottering hemisphere? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105940">Yes; poets are like palms which, the more weight</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105950">You cast upon them grow more strong and straight,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105960">'Tis not love's thunderbolt, nor Mars his spear,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105970">Or Neptune's angry trident, poet's fear. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105980">Had now grim Ben been breathing, with what rage,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e105990">And high-swollen fury had he lashed this age,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106000">Shakespeare with Chapman had grown mad, and torn</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106010">Their gentle sock, and lofty buskins worn,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106020">To make their muse welter up to the chin</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106030">In blood; of feigned scenes no need had been,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106040">England like Lucian's eagle with an arrow</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106050">Of her own plumes piercing her heart quite thorough,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106060">Had been a theater and subject fit</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106070">To exercise in real truth's their wit:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106080">Yet none like high-winged Fletcher had been found</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106090">This eagle's tragic-destiny to sound,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106100">Rare Fletcher's quill had soared up to the sky,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106110">And drawn down gods to see the tragedy:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106120">Live famous dramatist, let every spring</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106130">Make thy bay flourish, and fresh burgeons bring:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106140">And since we cannot have thee trod o'th' stage,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106150">We will applaud thee in this silent page. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e106160">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e106170">Ja. Howell. P.c.c.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e106180">
        <pb facs="13"/>
        <head>On the edition.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e106190">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106200">Fletcher (Whose fame no age can ever waste;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106210">Envy of ours, and glory of the last)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106220">Is now alive again; and with his name</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106230">His sacred ashes waked into a flame;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106240">Such as before did by a secret charm</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106250">The wildest heart subdue, the coldest warm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106260">And lend the lady's eyes a power more bright,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106270">Dispensing thus to either, heat and light. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e106280">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106290">He to a sympathy those souls betrayed</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106300">Whom love or beauty never could persuade;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106310">And in each moved spectator could beget</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106320">A real passion by a counterfeit:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106330">When first Bellario bled, what lady there</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106340">Did not for every drop let fall a tear? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106350">And when Aspasia wept, not any eye</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106360">But seemed to wear the same sad livery;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106370">By him inspired the feigned Lucina drew</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106380">More streams of melting sorrow than the true;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106390">But then the scornful lady did beguile</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106400">Their easy griefs, and teach them all to smile. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e106410">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106420">Thus he affections could, or raise or lay;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106430">Love, Grief and mirth thus did his charms obey:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106440">He nature taught her passions to outdo,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106450">How to refine the old, and create new;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106460">Which such a happy likeness seemed to bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106470">As if that nature art, art nature were. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e106480">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106490">Yet all had nothing been, obscurely kept</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106500">In the same urn wherein his dust hath slept,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106510">Nor had he ris 'The Delphic wreath to claim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106520">Had not the dying scene expired his name;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106530">Despair our joy hath doubled, he is come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106540">Thrice welcome by this post-liminium. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106550">His loss preserved him; they that silenced wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106560">Are now the authors to eternize it;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106570">Thus poets are in spite of fate revived,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106580">And plays by intermission longer lived. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e106590">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e106600">Tho. Stanley.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e106610">
        <pb facs="13"/>
        <head>On the edition of Mr. Francis Beaumont's, and Mr. John Fletcher's plays never printed before.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e106620">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106630">I am amazed; and this same ecstasy</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106640">Is both my glory and apology. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106650">Sober joys are dull passions; they must bear</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106660">Proportion to the subject: if so; where</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106670">Beaumont and Fletcher shall vouchsafe to be</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106680">That subject; that joy must be ecstasy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106690">Fury is the complexion of great wits;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106700">The fool's distemper: he, that's mad by fits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106710">Is wise so too. It is the poet's muse;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106720">The prophet's god: the fools, and my excuse. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106730">For (In me) nothing less than Fletcher's name</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106740">Could have begotten, or justified this flame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106750">Beaumont returned? methinks it should not be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106760">Fletcher returned? methinks it should not be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106770">No, not in's works: plays are as dead as he. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106780">The palate of this age gusts nothing high;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106790">That has not custard in't or bawdry. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106800">Folly and madness fill the stage: the scane</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106810">Is Athens; where, the guilty, and the mean,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106820">The fool 'scapes well enough; learned and great,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106830">Suffer an ostracism; stand exulate. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e106840">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106850">Mankind is fallen again, shrunk a degree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106860">A step below his very apostasy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106870">Nature her self is out of tune; and sick</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106880">Of tumult and disorder, lunatic. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106890">Yet what world would not cheerfully endure</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106900">The torture, or disease, to enjoy the cure? </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e106910">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106920">This book's the balsam, and the hellebore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106930">Must preserve bleeding nature, and restore</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106940">Our crazy stupor to a just quick sense</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106950">Both of ingratitude, and providence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106960">That teaches us (At once) to feel, and know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106970">Two deep points: what we want, and what we owe. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106980">Yet great goods have their ills: should we transmit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e106990">To future times, the power of love and wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107000">In this example: would they not combine</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107010">To make our imperfections their design? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107020">They'd study our corruptions; and take more</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107030">Care to be ill, than to be good, before. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e107040">
          <pb facs="14"/>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107050">For nothing but so great infirmity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107060">Could make them worthy of such remedy. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e107070">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107080">Have you not seen the sun's almighty ray</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107090">Rescue th' affrighted world, and redeem day</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107100">From black despair: how his victorious beam</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107110">Scatters the storm, and drowns the petty flame</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107120">Of lightning, in the glory of his eye:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107130">How full of power, how full of majesty? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107140">When to us mortals, nothing else was known,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107150">But the sad doubt, whether to burn, or drown. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e107160">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107170">Choler, and phlegm, heat, and dull ignorance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107180">Have cast the people into such a trance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107190">That fears and danger seem great equally,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107200">And no dispute left now, but how to die. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107210">Just in this nick, Fletcher sets the world clear</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107220">Of all disorder and reforms us here. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e107230">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107240">The formal youth, that knew no other grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107250">Or value, but his title, and his lace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107260">Glasses himself: and in this faithful mirror,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107270">Views, disapproves, reforms, repents his error. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e107280">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107290">The credulous, bright girl, that believes all</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107300">Language, (In oaths) if good, canonical,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107310">Is fortified, and taught, here, to beware</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107320">Of every specious bait, of every snare</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107330">Save one: and that same caution takes her more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107340">Than all the flattery she felt before. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107350">She finds her boxes, and her thoughts betrayed</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107360">By the corruption of the chambermaid:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107370">Then throws her washes and dissemblings by;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107380">And vows nothing but ingenuity. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e107390">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107400">The severe statesman quits his sullen form</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107410">Of gravity and business; the lukewarm</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107420">Religious his neutrality; the hot</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107430">Brainsick illuminate his zeal; the sot</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107440">Stupidity; the soldier his arrears;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107450">The court its confidence; the plebs their fears;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107460">Gallants their apishness and perjury,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107470">Women their pleasure and inconstancy;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107480">Poets their wine; the usurer his pelf;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107490">The world its vanity; and I my self. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e107500">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e107510">Roger l' estrange.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e107520">
        <pb facs="14"/>
        <head>On the dramatic poems of Mr. John Fletcher.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107530">Wonder! who's here? Fletcher, long buried</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107540">Revived? 'tis he! he's risen from the dead,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107550">His winding sheet put off, walks above ground,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107560">Shakes off his fetters, and is better bound. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107570">And may he not, if rightly understood,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107580">Prove plays are lawful? he hath made them good. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107590">Is any lover mad? see here loves cure;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107600">Unmarried? to a wife he may be sure</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107610">A rare one, for a month; if she displease,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107620">The Spanish curate gives a writ of ease. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107630">Inquire the custom of the country, then</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107640">Shall the French lawyer set you free again. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107650">If the two fair maids take it wondrous ill,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107660">(One of the inn, the other of the mill,)</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107670">That th' lover's progress stopped, and they defamed;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107680">Here's that makes women pleased, and tamer tamed. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107690">But who then plays the coxcomb, or will try</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107700">His wit at several weapons, or else die? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107710">Nice valour and he doubts not to engage</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107720">The noble gentleman, in love's pilgrimage,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107730">To take revenge on the false one, and run</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107740">The honest man's fortune, to be undone</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107750">Like knight of Malta, or else captain be</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107760">Or th' humorous lieutenant: go to sea</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107770">(A voyage for to starve) he's very loath,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107780">Till we are all at peace, to swear an oath,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107790">That than the loyal subject may have leave</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107800">To lie from beggar's bush, and undeceive</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107810">The creditor, discharge his debts; why so,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107820">Since we can't pay to Fletcher what we owe. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107830">O could his prophetess but tell one chance,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107840">When that the pilgrims shall return from France. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107850">And once more make this kingdom, as of late,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107860">The island Princess, and we celebrate</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107870">A double marriage; every one to bring</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107880">To Fletcher's memory his offering. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107890">That thus at last unsequesters the stage,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107900">Brings back the silver, and the golden age. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e107910">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e107920">Robert Gardiner.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e107930">
        <pb facs="15"/>
        <head>To the manes of the celebrated poets and fellow-writers, Francis Beaumont and John Fletcher, upon the printing of their excellent dramatic poems.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107940">Disdain not gentle shades, the lowly praise</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107950">Which here I tender your immortal bays. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107960">Call it not folly, but my zeal, that I</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107970">Strive to eternize you that cannot die. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107980">And though no language rightly can commend</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e107990">What you have writ, save what yourselves have penned</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108000">Yet let me wonder at those curious strains</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108010">(The rich conceptions of your twinlike brains)</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108020">Which drew the god's attention; who admired</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108030">To see our English stage by you inspired. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108040">Whose chiming muses never failed to sing</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108050">A soul-affecting music; ravishing</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108060">Both ear and intellect, while you do each</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108070">Contend with other who shall highest reach</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108080">In rare invention; conflicts that beget</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108090">New strange delight, to see two fancies met,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108100">That could receive no foil: two wits in growth</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108110">So just, as had one soul informed both. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108120">Thence (Learned Fletcher) sung the muse alone,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108130">As both had done before, thy Beaumont gone. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108140">In whom, as thou, had he outlived, so he</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108150">(Snatched first away) survived still in thee. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108160">What though distempers of the present age</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108170">Have banished your smooth numbers from the stage ▪</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108180">You shall be gainers by't; it shall confer</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108190">To th' making the vast world your theater. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108200">The press shall give to every man his part,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108210">And we will all be actors; learn by heart</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108220">Those tragic scenes and comic strains you wrote,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108230">Unimitable both for art and wit;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108240">And at each exit, as your fancies rise,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108250">Our hands shall clap deserved plaudities. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e108260">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e108270">John web.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e108280">
        <pb facs="15"/>
        <head>To the desert of the author in his most ingenious pieces.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108290">Thou art above their censure, whose dark spirits</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108300">Respects but shades of things, and seeming merits;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108310">That have no soul, nor reason to their will,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108320">But rhyme as ragged, as a gander's quill:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108330">Where pride blows up the error, and transfers</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108340">Their zeal in tempests, that so widely errs. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108350">Like heat and air compressed, their blind desires</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108360">Mix with their ends, as raging winds with fires. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108370">Whose ignorance and passions, wear an eye</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108380">Squint to all parts of true humanity. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108390">All is apocrypha suits not their vain:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108400">For wit, o fie! and learning too; profane! </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108410">But Fletcher hath done miracles by wit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108420">And one line of his may convert them yet. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108430">Tempt them into the state of knowledge, and</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108440">Happiness to read and understand. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108450">The way is strowed with laurel, and every muse</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108460">Brings incense to our Fletcher: whose scenes infuse</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108470">Such noble kindlings from her pregnant fire,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108480">As charms her critic poets in desire,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108490">And who doth read him, that parts less endued,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108500">Then with some heat of wit or gratitude. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108510">Some crowd to touch the relic of his bays,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108520">Some to cry up their own wit in his praise,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108530">And think they engage it by comparatives,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108540">When from himself, himself he best derives. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108550">Let Shakespeare, Chapman, and applauded Ben,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108560">We are the eternal merit of their pen,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108570">Here I am lovesick: and were I to choose,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108580">A mistress corrival 'tis fletcher's muse. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e108590">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e108600">George buck.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e108610">
        <pb facs="16"/>
        <head>On Mr. Beaumont. (Written thirty years since, presently after his death.)</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108620">Beaumont lies here; and where now shall we have</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108630">A muse like his to sigh upon his grave? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108640">Ah! none to weep this with a worthy tear,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108650">But he that cannot, Beaumont, that lies here. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108660">Who now shall pay thy tomb with such a verse</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108670">As thou that ladies didst, fair Rutland's hearse? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108680">A monument that will then lasting be,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108690">When all her marble is more dust than she. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108700">In thee all's lost: a sudden dearth and want</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108710">Hath seized on wit, good epitaphs are scant;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108720">We dare not write thy elegy, whilst each fears</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108730">He ne'er shall match that copy of thy tears. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108740">Scarce in an age a poet, and yet he</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108750">Scarce lives the third part of his age to see,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108760">But quickly taken off and only known,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108770">Is in a minute shut as soon as shown. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108780">Why should weak nature tire herself in vain</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108790">In such a piece, to dash it straight again? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108800">Why should she take such work beyond her skill,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108810">Which when she cannot perfect, she must kill? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108820">Alas, what is't to temper slime or mire? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108830">But nature's puzzled when she works in fire:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108840">Great brains (Like brightest glass) crack straight, while those</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108850">Of stone or wood hold out, and fear not blows. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108860">And we their ancient hoary heads can see</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108870">Whose wit was never their mortality:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108880">Beaumont dies young, so Sidney did before,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108890">There was not poetry he could live to more,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108900">He could not grow up higher, I scarce know</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108910">If thou'rt itself unto that pitch could grow,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108920">Were't not in thee that hadst arrived the height</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108930">Of all that wit could reach, or nature might. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108940">O when I read those excellent things of thine,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108950">Such strength, such sweetness couched in every line,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108960">Such life of fancy, such high choice of brain,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108970">Naught of the vulgar wit or borrowed strain,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108980">Such passion, such expressions meet my eye,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e108990">Such wit untainted with obscenity,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109000">And these so unaffectedly expressed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109010">All in a language purely flowing dressed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109020">And all so born within thyself, thine own,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109030">So new, so fresh, so nothing trod upon. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109040">I grieve not now that old Menander's vein</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109050">Is ruined to survive in thee again;</l>
        <pb facs="16"/>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109060">Such in his time was he of the same piece,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109070">The smooth, even natural wit, and love of Greece. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109080">Those few sententious fragments show more worth,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109090">Than all the poets Athens e'er brought forth;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109100">And I am sorry we have lost those hours</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109110">On them, whose quickness comes far short of ours,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109120">And dwell not more on thee, whose every page</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109130">May be a pattern for their scene and stage. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109140">I will not yield thy works so mean a praise;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109150">More pure, more chaste, more sainted then are plays,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109160">Nor with that dull supineness to be read,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109170">To pass a fire, or laugh an hour in bed. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109180">How do the muses suffer everywhere ,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109190">Taken in such mouths censure, in such ears,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109200">That twixt a whiff, a line or two rehearse,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109210">And with their rheum together spawl a verse? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109220">This all a poem's leisure after play,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109230">Drink or tobacco, it may keep the day. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109240">Whilst even their very idleness they think</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109250">Is lost in these, that lose their time in drink. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109260">Pity then dull we, we that better know,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109270">Will a more serious hour on thee bestow,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109280">Why should not Beaumont in the morning please,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109290">As well as Plautus, Aristophanes? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109300">Who if my pen may as my thoughts be free,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109310">Were scurrile wits and buffoons both to thee;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109320">Yet these our learned of severest brow</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109330">Will deign to look on, and to note them too,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109340">That will defy our own, 'tis English stuff,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109350">And th' author is not rotten long enough. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109360">Alas what phlegm are they, compared to thee,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109370">In thy Philaster, and maids-tragedy? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109380">Where's such an humour as thy Bessus? pray</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109390">Let them put all their Thrasoes in one play,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109400">He shall outbid them; their conceit was poor,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109410">All in a circle of a bawd or whore;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109420">A cozening dance, take the fool away,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109430">And not a good jest extant in a play. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109440">Yet these are wits, because they're old, and now</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109450">Being greek and Latin, they are learning too:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109460">But those their own times were content to allow</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109470">A thirsty fame, and thine is lowest now. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109480">But thou shalt live, and when thy name is grown</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109490">Six ages older, shall be better known,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109500">When th' art of Chaucer's standing in the tomb,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109510">Thou shalt not share, but take up all his room. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e109520">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e109530">Joh. Earl.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e109540">
        <pb facs="17"/>
        <head>Upon Mr. Fletcher's incomparable plays.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109550">The poet lives; wonder not how or why</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109560">Fletcher revives, but that he e'er could die:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109570">Safe mirth, full language, flow in every page,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109580">At once he doth both heighten and assuage;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109590">All innocence and wit, pleasant and clear,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109600">Nor church nor laws were ever libelled here;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109610">But fair deductions drawn from his great brain,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109620">Enough to conquer all that's false or vain;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109630">He scatters wit, and sense so freely flings</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109640">That very citizens speak handsome things,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109650">Teaching their wives such unaffected grace,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109660">Their looks are now as handsome as their face. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109670">Nor is this violent, he steals upon</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109680">The yielding soul until the frenzy's gone;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109690">His very launcings do the patient please,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109700">As when good music cures a mad disease. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109710">Small poets rifle him, yet think it fair,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109720">Because they rob a man that well can spare;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109730">They feed upon him, owe him every bit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109740">They're all but sub-exciseman of his wit. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e109750">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e109760">I. m.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e109770">
        <pb facs="17"/>
        <head>On the works of Beaumont and Fletcher, now at length printed.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109780">Great pair of authors, whom one equal star</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109790">Begotten so like in genius, that you are</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109800">In fame, as well as writings, both so knit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109810">That no man knows where to divide your wit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109820">Much less your praise; you, who had equal fire,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109830">And did each other mutually inspire;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109840">Whether one did contrive, the other write,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109850">Or one framed the plot, the other did indite;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109860">Whether one found the matter, th'other dress,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109870">Or the one disposed what th'other did express;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109880">Where'er your parts between yourselves lay, we,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109890">In all things which you did but one thread see,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109900">So evenly drawn out, so gently spun,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109910">That art with nature ne'er did smoother run. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109920">Where shall I fix my praise then? or what part</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109930">Of all your numerous labours hath desert</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109940">More to be famed then other? shall I say,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109950">I've met a lover so drawn in your play,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109960">So passionately written, so inflamed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109970">So jealously enraged, then gently tamed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109980">That I in reading have the person seen,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e109990">And your pen hath part stage and Actor been? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110000">Or shall I say, that I can scarce forbear</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110010">To clap, when I a captain do meet there,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110020">So lively in his own vain humour dressed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110030">So braggingly, and like himself expressed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110040">That modern cowards, when they saw him played,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110050">Saw, blushed, departed guilty, and betrayed? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110060">You wrote all parts right; whatsoever the stage</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110070">Had from you, was seen there as in the age,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110080">And had their equal life: vices which were</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110090">Manners abroad, did grow corrected there:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110100">They who possessed a box, and half crown spent</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110110">To learn obsceneness, returned innocent,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110120">And thanked you for this cozenage, whose chaste scene</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110130">Taught loves so noble, so reformed, so clean,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110140">That they who brought foul fires, and thither came</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110150">To bargain, went thence with a holy flame. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110160">Be't to your praise too, that your stock and vein</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110170">Held both to tragic and to comic strain;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110180">Where'er you listed to be high and grave,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110190">No buskin showed more solemn, no quill gave</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110200">Such feeling objects to draw tears from eyes,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110210">Spectators sat part in your tragedies. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110220">And where you listed to be low, and free,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110230">Mirth turned the whole house into comedy;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110240">So piercing (Where you pleased) hitting a fault,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110250">That humours from your pen issued all salt. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110260">Nor were you thus in works and poems knit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110270">As to be but two halves, and make one wit;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110280">But as some things we see, have double cause,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110290">And yet the effect itself from both whole draws;</l>
        <pb facs="18"/>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110300">So though you were thus twisted and combined</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110310">As two bodies, to have but one fair mind</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110320">Yet if we praise you rightly, we must say</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110330">Both joined, and both did wholly make the play,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110340">For that you could write singly, we may guess</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110350">By the divided pieces which the press</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110360">Hath severally sent forth; nor were gone so</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110370">(Like some our modern authors) made to go</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110380">On merely by the help of th'other, who</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110390">To purchase same do come forth one of two;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110400">Nor wrote you so, that ones part was to lick</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110410">The other into shape, nor did one stick</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110420">The others cold inventions with such wit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110430">As served like spice, to make them quick and fit;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110440">Nor out of mutual want, or emptiness,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110450">Did you conspire to go still twins to th' press:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110460">But what thus joined you wrote, might have come forth</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110470">As good from each, and stored with the same worth</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110480">That thus united them, you did join sense,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110490">In you 'twas league, in others impotence;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110500">And the press which both thus amongst us sends,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110510">Sends us one poet in a pair of friends. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e110520">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e110530">Jasper main.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomia" xml:id="A27177_00-e110540">
        <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e110550">
          <head>Upon the report of the printing of the dramatical poems of master John Fletcher, collected before, and now set forth in one volume.</head>
          <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e110560">
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110570">Though when all Fletcher writ, and the entire</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110580">Man was indulged unto that sacred fire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110590">His thoughts, and his thoughts dress, appeared both such,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110600">That 'twas his happy fault to do too much;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110610">Who therefore wisely did submit each birth</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110620">To knowing Beaumont ere it did come forth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110630">Working again until he said 'twas fit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110640">And made him the sobriety of his wit;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110650">Though thus he called his judge into his fame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110660">And for that aid allowed him half the name,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110670">'Tis known, that sometimes he did stand alone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110680">That both the sponge and pencil were his own;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110690">That himself judged himself, could singly do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110700">And was at last Beaumont and Fletcher too;</l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e110710">
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110720">Else we had lost his shepherdess, a piece</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110730">Even and smooth, spun from a finer fleece,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110740">Where softness reigns, where passions passions greet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110750">Gentle and high, as floods of balsam meet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110760">Where dressed in white expressions, sit bright loves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110770">Drawn, like their fairest Queen, by milky doves;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110780">A piece, which Johnson in a rapture bid</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110790">Come up a glorified work, and so it did. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e110800">
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110810">Else had his muse set with his friend; the stage</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110820">Had missed those poems, which yet take the age;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110830">The world had lost those rich exemplars, where</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110840">Art, language, wit, sit ruling in one sphere,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110850">Where the fresh matters soar above old themes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110860">As prophet's raptures do above our dreams;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110870">Where in a worthy scorn he dares refuse</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110880">All other gods, and makes the thing his muse;</l>
            <pb facs="18"/>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110890">Where he calls passions up, and lays them so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110900">As spirits, awed by him to come and go;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110910">Where the free author did whate'er he would,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110920">And nothing willed, but what a poet should. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e110930">
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110940">No vast uncivil bulk swells any scene,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110950">The strength's ingenious, and the vigour clean;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110960">None can prevent the fancy, and see through</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110970">At the first opening; all stand wondering how</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110980">The thing will be until it is; which thence</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e110990">With fresh delight still cheats, still takes the sense;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111000">The whole design, the shadows, the lights such</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111010">That none can say he shows or hides too much:</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111020">Business grows up, ripened by just increase,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111030">And by as just degrees again doth cease,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111040">The heats and minutes of affairs are watched,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111050">And the nice points of time are met, and snatched:</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111060">Naught later than it should, naught comes before,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111070">Chemists, and calculators do err more:</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111080">Sex, age, degree, affections, country, place,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111090">The inward substance, and the outward face;</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111100">All kept precisely, all exactly fit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111110">What he would write, he was before he writ. </l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111120">Betwixt Jonson's grave, and Shakespeare's lighter sound</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111130">His muse so steered that something still was found,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111140">Nor this, nor that, nor both, but so his own,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111150">That 'twas his mark, and he was by it known. </l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111160">Hence did he take true judgements, hence did strike</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111170">All palates some way, though not all alike:</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111180">The god of numbers might his numbers crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111190">And listening to them wish they were his own. </l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111200">Thus welcome forth, what ease, or wine, or wit</l>
            <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111210">Durst yet produce, that is, what Fletcher writ. </l>
          </lg>
        </div>
        <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e111220">
          <head>Another.</head>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111230">Fletcher, though some call it thy fault, that wit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111240">So overflowed thy scenes, that ere 'twas fit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111250">To come upon the stage, Beaumont was fain</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111260">To bid thee be more dull, that's write again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111270">And bate some of thy fire, which from thee came</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111280">In a clear, bright, full, but too large a flame;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111290">And after all (Finding thy genius such)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111300">That blunted, and allayed, 'twas yet too much;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111310">Added his sober sponge, and did contract</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111320">Thy plenty to less wit to make't exact:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111330">Yet we through his corrections could see</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111340">Much treasure in thy superfluity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111350">Which was so filed away, as when we do</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111360">Cut jewels, that that's lost is jewel too:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111370">Or as men use to wash gold, which we know</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111380">By losing makes the stream thence wealthy grow:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111390">They who do on thy works severely sit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111400">And call thy store the over-births of wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111410">Say thy miscarriages were rare, and when</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111420">Thou wert superfluous, that thy fruitful pen</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111430">Had no fault but abundance, which did lay</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111440">Out in one scene what might well serve a play;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111450">And hence do grant, that what they call excess</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111460">Was to be reckoned at thy happiness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111470">From whom wit issued in a full springtide;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111480">Much did enrich the stage, much flowed beside. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111490">For that thou couldst thine own free fancy bind</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111500">In stricter numbers, and run so confined</l>
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111510">As to observe the rules of art, which sway</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111520">In the contrivance of a true born play:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111530">These works proclaim which thou didst write retired</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111540">From Beaumont, by none but thyself inspired;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111550">Where we see 'twas not chance that made them hit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111560">Nor were thy plays the lotteries of wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111570">But like to Durer's pencil, which first knew</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111580">The laws of faces, and then faces drew:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111590">Thou knowest the air, the colour, and the place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111600">The symmetry, which gives a poem grace:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111610">Parts are so fitted unto parts, as do</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111620">Show thou hadst wit, and mathematics too:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111630">Knewest where by line to spare, where to dispense,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111640">And didst beget just comedies from thence:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111650">Things unto which thou didst such life bequeath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111660">That they (Their own Blackfriars) unacted breath. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111670">Johnson hath writ things lasting, and divine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111680">Yet his love-scenes, Fletcher, compared to thine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111690">Are cold and frosty, and expressed love so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111700">As heat with ice, or warm fires mixed with snow;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111710">Thou, as if struck with the same generous darts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111720">Which burn, and reign in noble lovers hearts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111730">Hast clothed affections in such native tires,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111740">And so described them in their own true fires;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111750">Such moving sighs, such undissembled tears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111760">Such charms of language, such hopes mixed with fears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111770">Such grants after denials, such pursuits</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111780">After despair, such amorous recruits. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111790">That some who sat spectators have confessed</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111800">Themselves transformed to what they saw expressed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111810">And felt such shafts steak through their captived sense,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111820">As made them rise parts, and go lovers thence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111830">Nor was thy style wholly composed of groves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111840">Or the soft strains of shepherds and their loves;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111850">When thou wouldst comic be, each smiling birth</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111860">In that kind, came into the world all mirth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111870">All point, all edge, all sharpness; we did sit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111880">Sometimes five acts out in pure sprightful wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111890">Which flowed in such true salt, that we did doubt</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111900">In which scene we laughed most two shillings out. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111910">Shakespeare to thee was dull, whose best jest lies</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111920">I'th lady's questions, and the fools replies;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111930">Old fashioned wit, which walked from town to town</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111940">In turned hose, which our fathers called the clown;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111950">Whose wit our nice times would obsceneness call,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111960">And which made bawdry pass for comical:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111970">Nature was all his art, thy vein was free</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111980">As his, but without his scurility;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e111990">From whom mirth came unforced, no jest perplexed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112000">But without labour clean, chaste, and unvexed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112010">Thou wert not like some, our small poets who</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112020">Could not be poets, were not we poets too;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112030">Whose wit is pilfering, and whose vein and wealth</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112040">In poetry lies merely in their stealth;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112050">Nor didst thou feel their drought, their pangs, their qualms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112060">Their rack in writing, who do write for alms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112070">Whose wretched genius, and dependant fires,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112080">But to their benefactors dole aspires. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112090">Nor hadst thou the sly trick, thyself to praise</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112100">Under thy friends names, or to purchase Bayes</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112110">Didst write stale commendation to thy book,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112120">Which we for Beaumont's or Ben Jonson's took:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112130">That debt thou leftest to us, which none but he</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112140">Can truly pay, Fletcher, who writes like thee. </l>
        </div>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e112150">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e112160">William Cartwright.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="epigram" xml:id="A27177_00-e112170">
        <pb facs="19"/>
        <head>On Mr. Francis Beaumont (Then newly dead.)</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112180">He that hath such acuteness, and such wit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112190">As would ask ten good heads to husband it;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112200">He that can write so well that no man dare</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112210">Refuse it for the best, let him beware:</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112220">Beaumont is dead, by whose sole death appears,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112230">Wit's a disease consumes men in few years. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e112240">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e112250">Rich. Corbet. D. D.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e112260">
        <head>To Mr. Francis Beaumont (Then living.)</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112270">How I do love thee Beaumont, and thy muse,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112280">That unto me dost such religion use! </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112290">How I do fear myself, that am not worth</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112300">The least indulgent thought thy pen drops forth! </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112310">At once thou mak'st me happy, and unmakest;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112320">And giving largely to me, more thou takest. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112330">What fate is mine, that so itself bereaves? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112340">What art is thine, that so thy friend deceives? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112350">When even there where most thou praisest me,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112360">For writing better, I must envy thee. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e112370">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e112380">Ben: Johnson.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e112390">
        <head>Upon master Fletcher's incomparable plays.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112400">Apollo sings, his harp resounds; give room,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112410">For now behold the golden pomp is come,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112420">Thy pomp of plays which thousands come to see,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112430">With admiration both of them and thee,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112440">Oh volume worthy leaf, by leaf and cover</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112450">To be with juice of cedar washed all over;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112460">Here's words with lines, and lines with scenes consent,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112470">To raise an act to full astonishment;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112480">Here melting numbers, words of power to move</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112490">Young men to swoon, and maids to die for love. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112500">Love lies a bleeding here, Evadne there</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112510">Swells with brave rage, yet comely everywhere ,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112520">Here's a mad lover, there that high design</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112530">Of King and no King (And the rare plot thine)</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112540">So that when 'Ere we circumvolve our eyes,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112550">Such rich, such fresh, such sweet varieties,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112560">Ravish our spirits, that entranced we see</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112570">None writes loves passion in the world, like thee. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e112580">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e112590">Rob. Herrick.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e112600">
        <pb facs="20"/>
        <head>On the happy collection of master Fletcher's works, never before printed.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e112610">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112620">Fletcher arise, usurpers share thy bays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112630">They canton thy vast wit to build small plays:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112640">He comes! his volume breaks through clouds and dust,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112650">Down, little wits, ye must refund, ye must. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e112660">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112670">Nor comes he private, here's great Beaumont too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112680">How could one single world encompass two? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112690">For these heirs had equal power to teach</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112700">All that all wits both can and cannot reach. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112710">Shakespeare was early up, and went so dressed</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112720">As for those dawning hours he knew was best;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112730">But when the sun shone forth, you two thought fit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112740">To wear just robes, and leave off trunk-hose-wit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112750">Now, now 'twas perfect; none must look for new,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112760">Manners and scenes may alter, but not you;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112770">For yours are not mere humours, gilded strains;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112780">The fashion lost, your massy sense remains</l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e112790">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112800">Some think your wits of two complexions framed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112810">That one the sock, th'other the buskin claimed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112820">That should the stage embattle all it's force,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112830">Fletcher would lead the foot, Beaumont the horse. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112840">But, you were both for both; not semiwits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112850">Each piece is wholly two, yet never splits:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112860">You're not two faculties (And one soul still)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112870">He th'understanding, thou the quick free will;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112880">But, as two voices in one song embrace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112890">(Fletcher's keen treble, and deep Beaumont's base)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112900">Two, full, congenial souls; still both prevailed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112910">His muse and thine were quartered, not impaled:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112920">Both brought your ingots, both toiled at the mint,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112930">Beat, melted, sifted, till no dross stuck in't,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112940">Then in each others scales weighed every grain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112950">Then smoothed and burnished, then weighed all again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112960">Stamped both your names upon't at one bold hit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112970">Then, then 'twas coin, as well as bullion-wit. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e112980">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e112990">Thus twins: but as when fate one eye deprives,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113000">That other strives to double which survives:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113010">So Beaumont died: yet left in legacy</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113020">His rules and standard-wit (Fletcher) to thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113030">Still the same planet, though not filled so soon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113040">A two-horned crescent then now one Full-moon. </l>
          <pb facs="20"/>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113050">Joint love before, now honour doth provoke;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113060">So th' old twin-giants forcing a huge oak</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113070">One slipped his footing, th' other sees him fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113080">Grasped the whole tree and single held up all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113090">Imperial Fletcher! here begins thy reign,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113100">Scenes flow like sunbeams from thy glorious brain;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113110">Thy swift dispatching soul no more doth stay</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113120">Then he that built two cities in one day;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113130">Ever brim full, and sometimes running o'er</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113140">To feed poor languid wits that wait at door,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113150">Who creep and creep, yet never aboveground stood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113160">(For creatures have most feet which have least blood)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113170">But thou art still that bird of paradise</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113180">Which hath no feet and ever nobly flies:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113190">Rich, lusty sense, such as the poet ought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113200">For poems if not excellent, are naught;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113210">Low wit in scenes? in state a peasant goes;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113220">If mean and flat, let it foot yeoman prose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113230">That such may spell as are not readers grown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113240">To whom he that writes wit, shows he hath none. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e113250">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113260">Brave Shakespeare flowed, yet had his ebbings too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113270">Often above himself, sometimes below;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113280">Thou always best; if ought seemed to decline,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113290">'Twas the unjudging rout's mistake, not thine:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113300">Thus thy fair shepherdess, which the bold heap</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113310">(False to themselves and thee) did prize so cheap,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113320">Was found (When understood) fit to be crowned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113330">At worst 'twas worth two hundred thousand pound. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e113340">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113350">Some blast thy works test we should track their walk</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113360">Where they steal all those few good things they talk;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113370">Wit-burglary must chide those it feeds on,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113380">For plundered folks ought to be railed upon;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113390">But (As stolen goods go off at half their worth)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113400">Thy strong sense palls when they purloin it forth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113410">When didst thou borrow? where's the man e'er read</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113420">Ought begged by thee from those alive or dead? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113430">Or from dry goddesses, as some who when</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113440">They stuff their page with gods, write worse than men. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113450">Thou was't thine own muse, and hadst such vast odds</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113460">Thou out-writ'st him whose verse made all those gods:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113470">Surpassing those our dwarfish age up rears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113480">As much as Greeks or latins thee in years:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113490">Thy ocean fancy knew nor banks nor dams,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113500">We ebb down dry to pebble-anagrams;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113510">Dead and insipid, all despairing fit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113520">Lost to behold this great relapse of wit:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113530">What strength remains, is like that (Wild and fierce)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113540">Till Johnson made good poets and right verse. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e113550">
          <pb facs="21"/>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113560">Such boisterous trifles thy muse would not brook,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113570">Save when she'd show how scurvily they look;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113580">No savage metaphors (Things rudely great)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113590">Thou dost display, not butcher a conceit;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113600">Thy nerves have beauty, which invades and charms;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113610">Looks like a Princess harnessed in bright arms. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e113620">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113630">Nor art thou loud and cloudy; those that do</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113640">Thunder so much, do't without lightning too;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113650">Tearing themselves, and almost split their brain</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113660">To render harsh what thou speak'st free and clean;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113670">Such gloomy sense may pass for high and proud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113680">But trueborn wit still flies above the cloud;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113690">Thou knewest 'twas impotence what they call height;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113700">Who blusters strong i'th dark, but creeps it'h light. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e113710">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113720">And as thy thoughts were clear, so, innocent;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113730">Thy fancy gave no unswept language vent;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113740">Slanderst not laws, profanest no holy page,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113750">(As if thy father's crosier awed the stage;)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113760">High crimes were still arraigned, though they made shift</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113770">To prosper out four acts, were plagued i'th fifth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113780">All's safe, and wise; no stiff-affected scene,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113790">Nor swollen, nor flat, a true full natural vein;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113800">Thy sense (Like well-dressed ladies) clothed as skinned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113810">Not all unlaced, nor city-starched and pinned</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113820">Thou hadst no sloth, no rage, no sullen fit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113830">But strength and mirth, Fletcher's a sanguine wit. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e113840">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113850">Thus, two great consul-poets all things swayed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113860">Till all was English born or English made:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113870">Mitre and coif here into one piece spun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113880">Beaumont a judge's, this a prelate's son. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113890">What strange production is at last displayed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113900">(Got by two fathers, without female aid)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113910">Behold, two masculines espoused each other,</l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e113920">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113930">Wit and the world were born without a mother. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e113940">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e113950">I. Berkenhead.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e113960">
        <pb facs="21"/>
        <head>To the memory of master Fletcher. </head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e113970">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113980">There's nothing gained by being witty: fame</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e113990">Gathers but wind to blather up a name. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114000">Orpheus must leave his lyre, or if it be</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114010">In heaven, 'tis there a sign, no harmony;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114020">And stones, that followed him, may now become</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114030">Now stones again, and serve him for his tomb. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114040">The Theban Linus, that was ably skilled</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114050">In muse and music, was by Phoebus killed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114060">Though Phoebus did beget him: sure his art</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114070">Had merited his balsam, not his dart. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e114080">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114090">But here Apollo's jealousy is seen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114100">The god of physics troubled with the spleen;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114110">Like timorous Kings he puts a period</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114120">To high grown parts lest he should be no god. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114130">Hence those great master-wits of Greece that gave</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114140">Life to the world, could not avoid a grave. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e114150">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114160">Hence the inspired prophets of old Rome</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114170">Too great for earth fled to Elysium. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e114180">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114190">But the same ostracism benighted one,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114200">To whom all these were but illusion;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114210">It took our Fletcher hence, Fletcher, whose wit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114220">Was not an accident to th'soul, but it;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114230">Only diffused. (Thus we the same sun call,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114240">Moving it'h sphere, and shining on a wall.) </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114250">Wit, so high placed at first, it could not climb,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114260">Wit, that never grew, but only showed by time. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114270">No firework of sack, no seldom shown</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114280">Poetic rage, but still in motion:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114290">And with far more than spheric excellence</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114300">It moved, for 'twas its own intelligence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114310">And yet so obvious to sense, so plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114320">You'd scarcely think't allied unto the brain:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114330">So sweet, it gained more ground upon the stage</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114340">Then Johnson with his self-admiring rage</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114350">Ere lost: and then so naturally it fell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114360">That fools would think, that they could do as well. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e114370">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114380">This is our loss: yet spite of Phoebus, we</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114390">Will keep our Fletcher, for his wit is he. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e114400">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e114410">Edw. Powell.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e114420">
        <pb facs="22"/>
        <head>Upon the ever to be admired Mr. John Fletcher and his plays.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e114430">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114440">What's all this preparation for? or why</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114450">Such sudden triumphs? Fletcher the people cry! </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114460">Just so, when Kings approach, our conduits run</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114470">Claret, as here the spouts flow Helicon;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114480">See, every sprightful muse dressed trim and gay</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114490">Strews herbs and scatters roses in his way. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e114500">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114510">Thus th'outward yard set round with bays we've seen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114520">Which from the garden hath transplanted been:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114530">Thus, at the praetor's feast, with needless costs</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114540">Some must b'employed in painting of the posts:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114550">And some as dishes made for sight, not taste,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114560">Stand here as things for show to Fletcher's feast. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114570">O what an honour! what a grace 'thad been</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114580">T'have had his cook in Rollo served them in! </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e114590">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114600">Fletcher the King of poets! such was he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114610">That earned all tribute, claimed all sovereignty;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114620">And may he that denies it, learn to blush</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114630">At's loyal subject, starve at's beggar's bush:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114640">And if not drawn by example, shame, nor grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114650">Turn o'er to's coxcomb, and the wild-goose chase</l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e114660">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114670">Monarch of wit! great magazine of wealth! </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114680">From whose rich bank, by a promethean-stealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114690">Our lesser flames do blaze! His the true fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114700">When they like glowworms, being touched, expire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114710">'Twas first believed, because he always was,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114720">The ipse dixit, and Pythagoras</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114730">To our disciple-wits; his soul might run</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114740">(By the same-dreamt-of transmigration)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114750">Into their rude and indigested brain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114760">And so inform their chaos-lump again;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114770">For many specious brats of this last age</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114780">Spoke Fletcher perfectly in every page. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114790">This roused his rage to be abused thus:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114800">Made's lover mad, lieutenant humorous. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114810">Thus ends of gold and silver-men are made</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114820">(As th'use to say) goldsmiths of his own trade;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114830">Thus rag-men from the dunghill often hop,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114840">And publish forth by chance a broker's shop:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114850">But by his own light, now, we have descried</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114860">The dross, from that hath been so purely tried. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114870">Proteus of wit! who reads him doth not see</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114880">The manners of each sex of each degree! </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114890">His full stored fancy doth all humours fill</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114900">From th'queen of Corinth to the maid o'th mill;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114910">His curate, lawyer, captain, prophetess</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114920">Show he was all and every one of these;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114930">He taught (So subtly were their fancies seized)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114940">To rule a wife, and yet the women pleased. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114950">Parnassus is thine own, claim't as merit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e114960">Law makes the elder brother to inherit. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e114970">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e114980">G. hills.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e114990">
        <pb facs="22"/>
        <head>In honour of Mr. John Fletcher. </head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e115000">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115010">So Fletcher now presents to fame</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115020">His alone self and unpropped name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115030">As rivers rivers entertain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115040">But still fall single into th'main,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115050">So doth the moon in consort shine</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115060">Yet flows alone into its mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115070">And though her light be jointly thrown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115080">When she makes silver 'tis her own:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115090">Perhaps his quill flew stronger, when</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115100">'Twas woven with his Beaumont's pen;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115110">And might with deeper wonder hit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115120">It could not show more his, more wit;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115130">So Hercules came by sex and love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115140">When Pallas sprang from single Jove;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115150">He took his Beaumont for embrace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115160">Not to grow by him, and increase,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115170">Nor for support did with him twine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115180">He was his friend's friend, not his vine. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115190">His wit with wit he did not twist</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115200">To be assisted, but to assist. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115210">And who could succour him, whose quill</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115220">Did both run sense and sense distil? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115230">Had time and art in't, and the while</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115240">Slid even as theirs who're only style,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115250">Whether his chance did cast it so</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115260">Or that it did like rivers flow</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115270">Because it must, or whether 'twere</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115280">A smoothness from his file and ear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115290">Not the most strict enquiring nail</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115300">Could e'er find where his piece did fail</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115310">Of entire oneness; so the frame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115320">Was composition, yet the same. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e115330">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115340">How does he breed his brother? and</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115350">Make wealth and estate understand? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115360">Suits land to wit, makes luck match merit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115370">And makes an eldest fitly inherit:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115380">How was he been, when Ben did write</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115390">Tooth stage, not to his judge indite? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115400">How did he do what Johnson did,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115410">And earn what Johnson would have said? </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e115420">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e115430">Jos. how of Trin. Coll. Oxon.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e115440">
        <pb facs="23"/>
        <head>Master John Fletcher his dramatical works now at last printed.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e115450">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115460">I could praise Heywood now: or tell how long,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115470">Falstaff from cracking nuts hath kept the throng:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115480">But for a Fletcher, I must take an age,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115490">And scarce invent the title for one page. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115500">God's must create new spheres, that should express</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115510">The several accents, Fletcher, of thy dress:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115520">The pen of fates should only write thy praise:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115530">And all Elysium for thee turn to bays. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115540">Thou feltst no pangs of poetry, such as they,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115550">Who the heavens quarter still before a play,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115560">And search the Ephemerides to find,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115570">When the aspect for poets will be kind. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115580">Thy poems (Sacred spring) did from thee flow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115590">With as much pleasure, as we read them now. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115600">Nor need we only take them up by fits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115610">When love or physic hath diseased our wits;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115620">Or conster's English to untie a knot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115630">Hid in a line, far subtler than the plot. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115640">With thee the page may close his lady's eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115650">And yet with thee the serious student rise:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115660">The eye at several angles darting rays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115670">Makes, and then sees, new colours; so thy plays</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115680">To every understanding still appear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115690">As if thou only meant'st to take that ear;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115700">The phrase so terse and free of a just poise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115710">Where every word has weight and yet no noise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115720">The matter too so nobly fit, no less</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115730">Than such as only could deserve thy dress:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115740">Witness thy comedies, pieces of such worth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115750">All ages shall still like, but never bring forth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115760">Other in season last scarce so long time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115770">As cost the poet but to make the rhyme:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115780">Where, if a lord a new way does but spit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115790">Or change his shrug this antiquates the wit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115800">That thou didst live before, nothing would tell</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115810">Posterity, could they but write so well. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115820">Thy Cath'lick fancy will acceptance find,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115830">Not whilst an humour's living, but mankind. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115840">Thou, like thy writings, innocent and clean,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115850">Never practised a new vice, to make one scene,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115860">None of thy ink had gall, and ladies can,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115870">Securely hear thee sport without a fan. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e115880">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115890">But when thy tragic muse would please to rise</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115900">In majesty, and call tribute from our eyes;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115910">Like scenes, we shifted passions, and that so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115920">Who only came to see, turned actors too. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115930">How didst thou sway the theatre! make us feel</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115940">The player's wounds were true, and their swords, steel! </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115950">Nay, stranger yet, how often did I know</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115960">When the spectators ran to save the blow? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115970">Frozen with grief we could not stir away</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115980">Until the epilogue told us 'twas a play. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e115990">What shall I do? all commendations end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116000">In saying only thou wert Beaumont's friend? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116010">Give me thy spirit quickly, for I swell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116020">And like a raveing prophetess cannot tell</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116030">How to receive thy genius in my breast:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116040">Oh! I must sleep, and then I'll sing the rest. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e116050">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e116060">T. palmer of Ch. Ch. Oxon.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e116070">
        <pb facs="23"/>
        <head>Upon the unparalleled plays written by those renowned twins of poetry Beaumont and Fletcher.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e116080">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116090">What's here? another library of praise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116100">Met in a troop t'advance contemned plays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116110">And bring exploded wit again in fashion? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116120">I can't but wonder at this reformation. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116130">My skipping soul surfeits with so much good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116140">To see my hopes into fruition bud. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116150">A happy chemistry! blessed viper, joy! </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116160">That through thy mother's bowels gnaw'st thy way! </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e116170">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116180">Wit's flock in shoals, and club to re-erect</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116190">In spite of ignorance the architect</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116200">Of occidental poesy; and turn</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116210">Gods, to recall wits ashes from their urn. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116220">Like huge collosses they've together met</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116230">Their shoulders, to support a world of wit. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e116240">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116250">The tale of Atlas (Though of truth it miss)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116260">We plainly read mythologised in this;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116270">Orpheus and Amphion whose undying storeys</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116280">Made Athens famous, are but allegories. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116290">'Tis poetry has power to civilize</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116300">Men, worse than stones, more blockish than the trees</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116310">I cannot choose but think (Now things so fall)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116320">That wit is passed its climacterical;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116330">And though the Muses have been dead and gone</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116340">I know they'll find a resurrection. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116350">'Tis vain to praise; they're to themselves a glory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116360">And silence is our sweetest oratory. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116370">For he that names but Fletcher must needs be</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116380">Found guilty of a loud hyperbole. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116390">His fancy so transcendently aspires,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116400">He shows himself a wit, who but admires. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e116410">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116420">Here are no volumes stuffed with cheverle sense,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116430">The very anagrams of eloquence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116440">Nor long-long-winded sentences that be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116450">Being rightly spelled, but wit's stenography. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116460">Nor words, as void of reason, as of rhythm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116470">Only caesura'd to spin out the time. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116480">But here's a magazine of purest sense</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116490">Clothed in the newest garb of eloquence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116500">Scenes that are quick and sprightly, in whose veins</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116510">Bubbles the quintessence of sweet-high strains. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116520">Lines like their authors, and each word of it</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116530">Does say 'twas writ b' a gemini of wit. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e116540">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116550">How happy is our age! how blessed our men! </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116560">When such rare souls live themselves o'er again. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116570">We err, that think a poet dies; for this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116580">Shows that 'tis but a metempsychosis. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116590">Beaumont and Fletcher here at last we see</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116600">Above the reach of dull mortality,</l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e116610">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116620">Or power of fate: and thus the proverb hits</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116630">(That's so much crossed) these men live by their wits. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e116640">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e116650">Alex. Brome.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e116660">
        <pb facs="24"/>
        <head>On the death and works of Mr. John Fletcher.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e116670">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116680">My name, so far from great, that 'tis not known,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116690">Can lend no praise but what thou'dst blush to own;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116700">And no rude hand, or feeble wit should dare</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116710">To vex thy shrine with an unlearned tear. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e116720">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116730">I'd have a state of wit convoked, which hath</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116740">A power to take up on common faith;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116750">That when the stock of the whole kingdom's spent</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116760">In but preparative to thy monument,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116770">The prudent council may invent fresh ways</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116780">To get new contribution to thy praise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116790">And rear it high, and equal to thy wit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116800">Which must give life and monument to it. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e116810">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116820">So when late Essex died, the public face</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116830">Wore sorrow in't, and to add mournful grace</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116840">To the sad pomp of his lamented fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116850">The common wealth served at his funeral</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116860">And by a solemn order built his hearse. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e116870">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116880">But not like thine, built by thyself, in verse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116890">Where thy advanced image safely stands</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116900">Above the reach of sacrilegious hands. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116910">Base hands how impotently you disclose</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116920">Your rage 'gainst Camden's learned ashes, whose</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116930">Defaced statua and martyred book,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116940">Like an antiquity and fragment look. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116950">Nonnulla desunts legibly appear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116960">So truly now Camden's remains lie there. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116970">Vain malice! how he mocks thy rage, while breath</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116980">Of fame shall speak his great Elizabeth! </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e116990">'Gainst time and thee he well provided hath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117000">Brittannia is the tomb and epitaph. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117010">Thus princes honours; but wit only gives</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117020">A name which to succeeding ages lives. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e117030">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117040">Singly we now consult ourselves and fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117050">Ambitious to twist ours with thy great name. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117060">Hence we thus bold to praise. For as a vine</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117070">With subtle wreath, and close embrace doth twine</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117080">A friendly elm, by whose tall trunk it shoots</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117090">And gathers growth and moisture from its roots;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117100">About its arms the thankful clusters cling</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117110">Like bracelets, and with purple enameling</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117120">The blue-cheeked grape stuck in its vernant hair</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117130">Hangs like rich jewels in a beauteous ear. </l>
          <pb facs="24"/>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117140">So grow our praises by thy wit; we do</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117150">Borrow support and strength and lend but show. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e117160">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117170">And but thy male wit like the youthful sun</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117180">Strongly begets upon our passion. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117190">Making our sorrow teem with elegy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117200">Thou yet unwept, and yet unpraised mightst be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117210">But th' are imperfect births; and such are all</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117220">Produced by causes not univocal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117230">The scapes of nature, passives being unfit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117240">And hence our verse speaks only mother wit. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e117250">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117260">O for a fit o'th father! for a spirit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117270">That might but parcel of thy worth inherit;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117280">For but a spark of that diviner fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117290">Which thy full breast did animate and inspire;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117300">That souls could be divided, thou traduce</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117310">But a small particle of thine to us! </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117320">Of thine; which we admired when thou didst sit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117330">But as a join-commissioner in wit;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117340">When it had plummets hung on to suppress</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117350">It's too luxuriant growing mightiness:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117360">Till as that tree which scorns to be kept down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117370">Thou grew'st to govern the whole stage alone. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117380">In which orb thy thronged light did make the star,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117390">Thou wert th' intelligence did move that sphere. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117400">Thy fury was composed; rapture no fit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117410">That hung on thee; nor thou far gone in wit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117420">As men in a disease; thy fancy clear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117430">Muse chaste, as those frames whence they took their fire;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117440">No spurious composures amongst thine</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117450">Got in adultery 'twixt wit and wine. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e117460">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117470">And as th' hermetical physicians draw</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117480">From things that curse of the first-broken law,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117490">That ens venenum, which extracted thence</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117500">Leaves naught but primitive good and innocence:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117510">So was thy spirit calcined; no mixtures there</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117520">But perfect, such as next to simples are. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117530">Not like those meteor-wits which wildly fly</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117540">In storm and thunder through th'amazed sky;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117550">Speaking but th'ills and villainies in a state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117560">Which fools admire, and wise men tremble at,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117570">Full of portent and prodigy, whose gall</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117580">Oft scapes the vice, and on the man doth fall. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117590">Nature used all her skill, when thee she meant</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117600">A wit at once both great and innocent. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e117610">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117620">Yet thou hadst tooth; but 'twas thy judgement, not</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117630">For mending one word, a whole sheet to blot. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117640">Thou couldst anatomize with ready art</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117650">And skilful hand crimes locked close up i'th heart. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117660">Thou couldst unfold dark plots, and show that path</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117670">By which ambition climbed to greatness hath. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117680">Thou couldst the rises, turns, and falls of states,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117690">How near they were their periods and dates;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117700">Couldst mad the subject into popular rage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117710">And the grown seas of that great storm assuage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117720">Dethrone usurping tyrants, and place there</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117730">The lawful prince and true inheriter;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117740">Knewest all dark turnings in the labyrinth</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117750">Of policy, which who but knows he sinn'th,</l>
          <pb facs="25"/>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117760">Save thee, who uninfected didst walk in't</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117770">As the great genius of government. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117780">And when thou laidst thy tragic buskin by</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117790">To court the stage with gentle comedy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117800">How new, how proper th' humours, how expressed</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117810">In rich variety, how neatly dressed</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117820">In language, how rare plots, what strength of wit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117830">Shined in the face and every limb of it! </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117840">The stage grew narrow while thou grew'st to be</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117850">In thy whole life an excellent comedy. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e117860">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117870">To these a virgin-modesty which first met</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117880">Applause with blush and fear, as if he yet</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117890">Had not deserved; till bold with constant praise</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117900">His brows admitted the unfought for bays. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117910">Nor would he ravish fame; but left men free</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117920">To their own vote and ingenuity. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117930">When his fair shepherdess on the guilty stage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117940">Was martyred between ignorance and rage;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117950">At which the impatient virtues of those few</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117960">Could judge, grew high, cried murder: though he knew</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117970">The innocence and beauty of his child,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117980">He only, as if unconcerned, smiled. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e117990">Prince's have gathered since each scattered grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118000">Each line and beauty of that injured face;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118010">And on th'united parts breathed such a fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118020">As spite of malice she shall never expire. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e118030">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118040">Attending, not affecting, thus the crown</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118050">Till every hand did help to set it on,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118060">He came to be sole monarch, and did reign</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118070">In wits great empire, absolute sovereign. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e118080">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e118090">John Harris.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e118100">
        <head>On Mr. John fletcer's ever to be admired dramatical works.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e118110">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118120">I've thought upon't; and thus I may gain bays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118130">I will commend thee Fletcher, and thy plays. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118140">But none but wits can do't, how then can I</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118150">Come in amongst them, that could never come nigh? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118160">There is no other way, I'll throng to sit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118170">And pass it'h crowd amongst them for a wit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118180">Apollo knows me not, nor I the nine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118190">All my pretence to verse is love and wine. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e118200">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118210">By your leave gentlemen. You wits o'th' age,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118220">You that both furnished have, and judged the stage. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118230">You, who the poet and the actors fright,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118240">Lest that your censure thin the second night:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118250">Pray tell me, gallant wits, could critics think</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118260">There ere was solecism in Fletcher's ink? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118270">Or lapse of plot, or fancy in his pen? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118280">A happiness not still allowed to Ben! </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118290">After of time and Wit he'd been at cost</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118300">He of his own new-inn was but an host. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118310">Inspired, Fletcher! here's no vainglorious words:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118320">How e'en thy lines, how smooth thy sense accords. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118330">Thy language so insinuates, each one</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118340">Of thy spectators has thy passion. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118350">Men seeing, valiant; ladies amorous prove:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118360">Thus owe to thee their valour and their love:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118370">Scenes! chaste yet satisfying! Lady's can't say</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118380">Though Stephen miscarried that so did the play:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118390">Judgement could never to this opinion lean</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118400">That Lowen, tailor, ere could grace thy scene:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118410">'Tis richly good unacted, and to me</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118420">Thy very farce appears a comedy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118430">Thy drollery is design, each looser part</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118440">Stuffs not thy plays, but makes 'em up an art</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118450">The stage has seldom seen; how often vice</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118460">Is smartly scourged to check us? to entice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118470">How well encouraged virtue is? how guarded,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118480">And, that which makes us love her, how rewarded? </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e118490">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118500">Some, I dare say, that did with loose thoughts sit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118510">Reclaimed by thee, came converts from the pit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118520">And many a she that to be ta'en up came,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118530">Took up themselves, and after left the game. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e118540">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e118550">Henry Harington.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A27177_00-e118560">
        <pb facs="25"/>
        <head>To the memory of the deceased but everliving author in these his poems, Mr. John Fletcher.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e118570">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118580">On the large train of Fletcher's friends let me</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118590">(Retaining still my wonted modesty,)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118600">Become a waiter in my ragged verse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118610">As follower to the Muses followers. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118620">Many here are of noble rank and worth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118630">That have, by strength of art, set Fletcher forth</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118640">In true and lively colours, as they saw him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118650">And had the best abilities to draw him;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118660">Many more are abroad, that write, and look</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118670">To have their lines set before Fletcher's book;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118680">Some, that have known him too; some more, some less;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118690">Some only but by Hearsay, some by guess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118700">And some, for fashion-sake, would take the hint</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118710">To try how well their wits would show in print. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118720">You, that are here before me gentlemen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118730">And princes of Parnassus by the pen</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118740">And your just judgements of his worth, that have</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118750">Preserved this authors memory from the grave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118760">And made it glorious; let me, at your gate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118770">Porter it here, 'gainst those that come too late,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118780">And are unfit to enter. Something I</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118790">Will deserve here: for where you versify</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118800">In flowing numbers, lawful weight, and time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118810">I'll write, though not rich verses, honest rhyme. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118820">I am admitted. Now, have at the rout</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118830">Of those that would crowd in, but must keep out. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118840">Bear back, my masters; pray keep back; forbear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118850">You cannot, at this time have entrance here. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118860">You, that are worthy, may, by intercession,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118870">Find entertainment at the next impression. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118880">But let none then attempt it, that not know</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118890">The reverence due, which to this shrine they owe:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118900">All such must be excluded; and the sort,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118910">That only upon trust, or by report</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118920">Have taken Fletcher up, and think it trim</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118930">To have their verses planted before him:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118940">Let them read first his works, and learn to know him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118950">And offer, then, the sacrifice they owe him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118960">But far from hence he such, as would proclaim:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118970">Their knowledge of this author, not his fame;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118980">And such, as would pretend, of all the rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e118990">To be the best wits that have known him best. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119000">Depart hence all such writers, and, before</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119010">Inferior ones, thrust in, by many a score,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119020">As formerly, before Tom Coryate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119030">Whose work before his praisers had the fate</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119040">To perish: for the witty copies took</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119050">Of his encomiums made themselves a book. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119060">Here's no such subject for you to outdo,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119070">Outshine, outlive (Though well you may do too</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119080">In other spheres:) for Fletcher's flourishing bays</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119090">Must never fade while Phoebus wears his rays. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119100">Therefore forbear to press upon him thus. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119110">Why, what are you (Cry some) that prate to us? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119120">Do not we know you for a flashy meteor? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119130">And styled (At best) the muse's serving-creature? </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119140">Do you control? You've had your Jere: sirs, no;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119150">But, in an humble manner, let you know</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119160">Old serving-creatures oftentimes are fit</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119170">T'inform young masters, as in land, in wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119180">What they inherit; and how well their dads</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119190">Left one, and wished the other to their lads. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119200">And from departed poets I can guess</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119210">Who has a greater share of wit, who less. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119220">' way fool, another says. Ay, let him rail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119230">And about his own ears flourish his wits-tail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119240">Till with his swingle he his noddle break;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119250">While this of Fletcher and his works I speak:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119260">His works (Says Momus) nay, his plays you'd say:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119270">Thou hast said right, for that to him was play</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119280">Which was to others brains a toil: with ease</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119290">He played on waves which were their troubled seas. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119300">His nimble births have longer lived than theirs</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119310">That have, with strongest labour, divers years</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119320">Been sending forth the issues of their brains</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119330">Upon the stage; and shall to th' stationer's gains</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119340">Life after life take, till some after-age</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119350">Shall put down printing, as this doth the stage;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119360">Which nothing now presents unto the eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119370">But in dumb-shows her own sad tragedy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119380">Would there had been no sadder works abroad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119390">Since her decay, acted in fields of blood. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A27177_00-e119400">
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119410">But to the man again, of whom we write,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119420">The writer that made writing his delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119430">Rather than work. He did not pump, nor drudge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119440">To beget wit, or manage it; nor trudge</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119450">To wit-conventions with notebook, to glean</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119460">Or steal some jests to foist into a seen:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119470">He scorned those shifts. You, that have known him, know</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119480">The common talk that from his lips did flow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119490">And run at waste, did savour more of wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119500">Than any of his time, or since have writ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119510">(But few excepted) in the stages way:</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119520">His scenes were acts, and every act a play. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119530">I knew him in his strength; even then, when he</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119540">That was the master of his art and me</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119550">Most knowing Johnson (Proud to call him son)</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119560">In friendly envy swore, he had outdone</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119570">His very self. I knew him till he died;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119580">And, at his dissolution, what a tide</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119590">Of sorrow overwhelmed the stage; which gave</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119600">Volleys of sighs to send him to his grave. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119610">And grew distracted in most violent fits</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119620">(For she had lost the best part of her wits.) </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119630">In the first year, our famous Fletcher fell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119640">Of good King Charles who graced these poems well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119650">Being then in life of action: but they died</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119660">Since the King's absence; or were laid aside,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119670">As is their poet. Now at the report</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119680">Of the Kings second coming to his court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119690">The books creep from the press to life not action,</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119700">Crying unto the world, that no protraction</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119710">May hinder sacred majesty to give</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119720">Fletcher, in them, leave on the stage to live. </l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119730">Others may more in lofty verses move;</l>
          <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119740">I only, thus, express my truth and love. </l>
        </lg>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e119750">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e119760">Ric. Brome.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="sonnet" xml:id="A27177_00-e119770">
        <pb facs="26"/>
        <head>Upon the printing of Mr. John Fletcher's works.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119780">What means this numerous guard? or do we come</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119790">To file our names or verse upon the tomb</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119800">Of Fletcher, and by boldly making known</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119810">His wit, betray thee nothing of our own? </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119820">For if we grant him dead, it is as true</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119830">Against ourselves, no wit, no poet now;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119840">Or if he be returned from his cool shade,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119850">To us, this book his resurrection's made,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119860">We bleed ourselves to death, and but contrive</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119870">By our own epitaphs to show him alive. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119880">But let him live and let me prophesy,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119890">As I go swanlike out, our peace is nigh;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119900">A balm unto the wounded age I sing,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119910">And nothing now is wanting but the King. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e119920">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e119930">Ja. Shirley.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="poem_by_stationer" xml:id="A27177_00-e119940">
        <pb facs="26"/>
        <head>The stationer.</head>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119950">As after th' epilogue there comes some one</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119960">To tell spectators what shall next be shown;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119970">So here, am I; but though I've toiled and vexed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119980">'Cannot devise what to present ye next;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e119990">For, since ye saw no plays this cloudy weather,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e120000">Here we have brought ye our whole stock together. </l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e120010">'Tis new, and all these gentlemen attest</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e120020">Under their hands 'tis right, and of the best;</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e120030">Thirty four witnesses (Without my task)</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e120040">You've just so many plays (Besides a mask)</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e120050">All good (T'me told) as have been read or played,</l>
        <l xml:id="A27177_00-e120060">If this book fail, 'tis time to quit the trade. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A27177_00-e120070">
          <signed xml:id="A27177_00-e120080">H. Moseley.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="notice" xml:id="A27177_00-e120090">
        <head>Postcript.</head>
        <p xml:id="A27177_00-e120100">We forgotten to tell the reader, that some prologues and epilogues (Here inserted) were not written by the authors of this volume; but made by others on the revival of several plays. After the comedies and tragedies were wrought off, we were forced (For expedition) to send the gentlemen's verses to several printers, which was the occasion of their different character; but the work itself is one continued letter, which (Though very legible) is none of the biggest, because (As much as possible) we would lessen the bulk of the volume.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="list_of_plays" xml:id="A27177_00-e120110">
        <pb facs="27"/>
        <head>A catalogue of all the comedies and tragedies contained in this book.</head>
        <list xml:id="A27177_00-e120120">
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120130">The mad lover.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120140">The Spanish curate.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120150">The little French lawyer.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120160">The custom of the country.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120170">The noble gentleman.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120180">The captain.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120190">The beggar's bush.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120200">The coxcomb.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120210">The false one.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120220">The chances.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120230">The loyal subject.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120240">The laws of Candy. </item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120250">The lover's progress.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120260">The island Princess.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120270">The humorous lieutenant.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120280">The nice valour, or the passionate mad man.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120290">The maid in the mill.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120300">The prophetess.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120310">The tragedy of Bonduca. </item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120320">The sea voyage.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120330">The double marriage.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120340">The pilgrim.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120350">The knight of Malta. </item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120360">The woman's prize, or the tamer tamed.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120370">Love's cure, or the martial maid.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120380">The honest man's fortune.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120390">The Queen of Corinth. </item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120400">Women pleased.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120410">A wife for a month.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120420">Wit at several weapons.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120430">The tragedy of Valentinian. </item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120440">The fair maid of the inn.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120450">Love's pilgrimage.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120460">The mask of the gentlemen of Grays-inn, and the inner temple, at the marriage of the prince and Princess palatine of Rhine. </item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120470">Four plays (Or moral representations) in one.</item>
          <item xml:id="A27177_00-e120480">
            <add xml:id="A27177_00-e120490">the wild goose chase</add>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

