<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Courageous Turk<date type="creation_date">1619</date></title>
        <author>Goffe, Thomas </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nayoon Ahn</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A85334_02.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title>Early English books online.</title>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Three excellent tragœdies.: Viz. The raging Turk, or, Bajazet the Second. The courageous Turk, or, Amurath the First. And The tragoedie of Orestes· / Written, by Tho. Goff, Master of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford; and acted by the students of the same house.</title>
            <author>Goffe, Thomas, 1591-1629.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>137 400dpi TIFF images (displayed as GIF) and XML-encoded text (displayed as HTML).</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2011 December (TCP phase 2)</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85334</idno>
            <idno type="vid">114751</idno>
            <idno type="Aleph">5358848</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing (2nd ed.) G1006.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, III, p. 1066.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Thomason E.1591[2].</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Madan III 2290.</idno>
            <idno type="bibno">(UnM)99862588e</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>Where applicable, subject to copyright. Other restrictions on distribution may apply. Please go to http://www.umdl.umich.edu/ for more information.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Three excellent tragœdies.: Viz. The raging Turk, or, Bajazet the Second. The courageous Turk, or, Amurath the First. And The tragoedie of Orestes· / Written, by Tho. Goff, Master of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford; and acted by the students of the same house.</title>
            <author>Goffe, Thomas, 1591-1629.</author>
            <author>Meighen, Richard, fl. 1656.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>The second edition, carefully corrected by a friend of the authors.</edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <extent>[2], 263, [7] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed for G. Bedell and T. Collins, at the middle Temple gate Fleet-street,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1656.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>Editor's dedication signed: Rich. Meighen.</note>
            <note>In verse.</note>
            <note>"The raging Turk", "The courageous Turk", and "The tragedy of Orestes" each have separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
            <note>With three final advertisement leaves.</note>
            <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 8".</note>
            <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">eng</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>English drama (Tragedy)</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A85334_02-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A85334_02-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A85334_02-e100030">
        <pb facs="60"/>
        <pb facs="60"/>
        <p xml:id="A85334_02-e100040">The courageous Turk, or, Amurath the first.</p>
        <p xml:id="A85334_02-e100050">A tragedy, written by Thomas Goff master of arts, and student of christ-church in Oxford, and acted by the students of the same house.</p>
        <p xml:id="A85334_02-e100060">The second edition</p>
        <p xml:id="A85334_02-e100070">London, printed for G. Bedell and T. Collins, at the middle temple gate Fleetstreet. 1656.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A85334_02-e100080">
        <pb facs="61"/>
        <pb facs="61"/>
        <head>To the no less honoured, then deserving, sir Walter Tichborne, knight.</head>
        <opener xml:id="A85334_02-e100090">
          <salute xml:id="A85334_02-e100100">Sir,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A85334_02-e100110">This with another tragedy, entitled, the raging Turk, the issue of one man's brain; are now come forth together from the press, nearer allied, even as twins in this their second birth; they are full of glory, strength, and indeed full of what not, that beautifies? The more apt to be soiled, opposed, and disgraced; the rather, because the author has made his exit hence. The intent, and use of dedication (As I have observed) is to no other end, than that ignorance and spite, (Sworn enemies to ingenuity) should know<pb facs="62"/> upon their dull or envious dislikes, whether to repair and receive reformation. The fatherless fellow-orphan to this work resteth safe under the protection of your most noble brother, my much honoured friend, sir Richard Tichborne, knight and baronet; now for these reasons, and that I might not make them strangers by remote fosterings, but especially standing to you (Most worthy sir) equally engaged, I this to you present and dedicate: together tendering the love and unfeigned acknowledgements, of</p>
        <closer xml:id="A85334_02-e100120">
          <signed xml:id="A85334_02-e100130">Your most embounden servant, Richard Meighen.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="printer_to_author" xml:id="A85334_02-e100140">
        <pb facs="62"/>
        <head>To the author, in that, transcribing his book, without his knowledge, I was bound by promise to stand to his pleasure to keep it or burn it. </head>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100150">I will not praise this work, 'twere lost,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100160">Rich pearls best praise themselves; nor will I boast</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100170">To be possessed of more than India's wealth,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100180">That were the way to lose't, since I myself</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100190">Distrust myself in keeping it, and stand</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100200">In fear of robbing by some envious hand:</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100210">Robbed of it, said I? Alas, that fate were just,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100220">Since I am found first thief to you, who durst</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100230">Unbidden thus, ransack your precious store;</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100240">This magazine of wit, so choice; nay more,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100250">Steal from the chariot of the glorious sun,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100260">This heavenly fire. What shall I say, 'tis done;</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100270">I do confess the enditement, pity then</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100280">Must be my surest advocate 'mongst men. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100290">None can abate the rigor of the law,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100300">But the lawgiver; but methinks I saw,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100310">(Or hoped I saw) some watery beams of mercy</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100320">Break, glimpsing forth of your imperious eye. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100330">O let me beg reprieve, your pardon may</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100340">By due observance come another day. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100350">Here lo, I tender't back to bide the doom,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100360">By promise bound to him, to him with whom</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100370">I would not break for all rich Tagus sands;</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100380">Now he the prisoner at your mercy stands. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100390">— ergo ibit in ignes</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100400">Hoc opus aeternum rvet, et tot bella, tot enses</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100410">In cineres dabit hora nocens. —</l>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="A85334_02-e100420">
        <pb facs="63"/>
        <head>The prologue.</head>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100430">Were not our present subject mixed with fear,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100440">'Twould much affright us to see all you here. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100450">One would suffice us, or no auditor. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100460">Each to himself an ample theater,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100470">Let rude plebeians think so, but we know</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100480">All judgements here from the same spring do flow;</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100490">All here have but one censure, all one breast,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100500">All sons of the same mother; but the rest</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100510">We preoccupate their censure, and foretell,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100520">What after may be said not to be well. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100530">As in most decent garments you may see. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100540">Some gracious ornaments inweaved be;</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100550">Which serve for little use; but on some day</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100560">Destined to please himself, the wearer may</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100570">Without a blush put on, when his best friends</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100580">Intend to visit him. So our hope intends</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100590">The sacred muse's progeny to greet,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100600">Which under our roof, now the third time meet. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100610">We will not open the book to you, and show</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100620">A story word by word, as it doth go;</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100630">But give invention leave to undertake,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100640">Of it's own strains, some benefit to make:</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100650">For though a tragic pen may be confined</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100660">Within a study's private walls, the mind</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100670">Must be unbounded, and with inventions steel,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100680"><pb facs="63" n="121"/> strike fire from the alien flints —</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100690">So free we are from setting any price</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100700">On these our studied vanities, that advice</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100710">Almost disdained the whispers of those tongues</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100720">Which, private first, though vented, public wrongs</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100730">To the patient, patient oft. We'll here begin</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100740">To be a little peremptory. O that sin</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100750">Of wilful indiscretion; 'tis no bays</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100760">To make us garlands of our own mouths praise. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100770">Which who affect, may they so laurel lack,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100780">That slanders thunder's may behind their back</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100790">Blast them with calumny; for we vow, they dear</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100800">Pay for their pains, that give attention here. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100810">And since it's suffered with kind indulgence,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100820">We hope that kingly parent's our defence;</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100830">Who would not have his dandling love be known,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100840">But unto those had offspring of their own. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100850">And (For we are assured that here be</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100860">No brains so cursed with black sterility,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100870">But of some nature they can freely call</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100880">Births more mature, and celestial;</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100890">Their studies issue) they, like kindest mothers,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100900">With tender hands will swath the limbs of others. </l>
      </div>
      <div type="argument" xml:id="A85334_02-e100910">
        <pb facs="64"/>
        <head>The argument.</head>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100920">A suppoed victory by Amureth</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100930">Obtained in Greece, where many captives ta'en,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100940">One among the rest, Irene, conquers him,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100950">For, taken with her love, he sounds retreat</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100960">Eternally from war: but after, moved</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100970">With murmur of his nobles, in her bed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100980">Before his councils face, strikes off her head. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e100990">Then ruminating former bloody broils,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101000">He straight o'ercomes all Christian provinces,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101010">Invades the confines of his son in law,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101020">Fires Caramania, and makes Aladin</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101030">With's wife and children suppliant for their lives:</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101040">At length appointed his greatest field to fight</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101050">Upon Cassanae's plains; where having got</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101060">A wondrous conquest 'gainst the Christians,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101070">Comes the next morn to overview the dead;</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101080">'Mongst whom a Christian captain, Cobelitz,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101090">Lying wounded there, at sight of Amurath,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101100">Rising and staggering towards him, desperately</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101110">With a short dagger wounds him to the heart,</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101120">And then immediately the christian dies. </l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101130">The Turk expiring, Bajazet his heir</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101140">Strangles his younger brother: thus still springs</l>
        <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101150">The tragic sport which fortune makes with Kings. </l>
        <pb facs="64"/>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A85334_02-e101160">
        <pb facs="65"/>
        <head>The actors.</head>
        <list xml:id="A85334_02-e101170">
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101180">Amurath. </item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101190">Lala Schahin. — tutor to Amurath.</item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101200">Two Turkish captains. <list xml:id="A85334_02-e101210"><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101220">Eurenoses,</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101230">Chase Illibegge. </item></list></item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101240">Cobelitz a Christian captain.</item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101250">Lazarus the despot or governor of Servia.</item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101260">Sasmenos governor of Bulgaria.</item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101270">Aladin son in law to Amurath: and King of Caramania.</item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101280">Two lords with Aladin. </item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101290">Two ambassadors. </item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101300">Bajazet, eldest son to Amurath.</item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101310">Jacyl, youngest son to Amurath.</item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101320">Carradin Bassa a governor under the Turk.</item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101330">For the mask. <list xml:id="A85334_02-e101340"><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101350">Jupiter</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101360">Juno</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101370">Mars</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101380">Venus</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101390">Hector</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101400">Achil</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101410">Apollo</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101420">Pallas</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101430">Alexander</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101440">Philoxenus</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101450">Neptune</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101460">Cupid</item></list></item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101470">Women actors. <list xml:id="A85334_02-e101480"><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101490">Eumorphe, concubine to Amurath.</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101500">Menthe, an attendant on Eumorphe.</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101510">Hatun, daughter to the lord of Phrygia, married to Bajazet.</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101520">Aldine's wife, two little boys with her.</item></list></item>
          <item xml:id="A85334_02-e101530">Mutes. <list xml:id="A85334_02-e101540"><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101550">Men Christians taken, given to Amurath for janissaries.</item><item xml:id="A85334_02-e101560">Six Christian maidens presented to Hatun supposed to be Kings daughters. </item></list></item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A85334_02-e101570">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A85334_02-e101580">
        <pb facs="65"/>
        <head>The courageous Turk, or, Amurath the first.</head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A85334_02-e101590">
          <head>Actus 1.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e101600">
            <head>Scaena 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e101610">Enter as from war, Lala-schahin at one door, with warlike music, soldiers, a march. Enter to him at the other door, Amurath in state, with Eumorphe his concubine, attendants, lords and ladies. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e101620" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amurath.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101630">Be dumb those now harsh notes, our softer cares</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101640">Shall never be acquainted with such sounds. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101650">Peace (Our grand captain) see here Amurath,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101660">That would have once confronted Mars himself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101670">(Acknowledged for a better deity)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101680">Puts off ambitious burdens; and doth hate</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101690"><pb facs="66" n="126"/> through bloody rivers to make passages,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101700">Whereby his soul might float to Acheron. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101710">Wrinkle your brows no more (Stern fates) for we</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101720">Scorn to be made the servile ministers</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101730">To cut those threads, at which yourselves have trembled,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101740">Esteeming us the fiercer destiny. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101750">Yet must great Amurath thank those sacred powers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101760">They have enriched our souls with such a price,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101770">As had those heroes, whose revengeful arms</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101780">Served Mars a ten years prenticeship at Troy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101790">Ere dreamed succeeding times should be possessed</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101800">With such an unparalleled, unprized beauty as my saint,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101810">They would not have prevented so their bliss,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101820">But been most humble suitors to the gods</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101830">To have protracted their then fond spent life</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101840">But to behold this object; which outshines</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101850">Their Helena, as much as doth the eye</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101860">Of all the world dazzle the lesser fires. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101870">Jove, I'll outbrave thee; melt thyself in lust,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101880">Embrace at once all star-made concubines,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101890">I'll not envy thee, know I have to spare</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101900">Beauty enough, to make another Venus;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101910">And for fond gods, that have no reward in store</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101920">To make me happier, here I'll place my heaven. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101930">And for thy sake, this shall my motto be,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101940">I conquered Greece, one Grecian conquered me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e101950" who="A85334_02-eumorphe">
              <speaker>Eum.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101960">But (Gracious lord) those streams (We see) soon ebb,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101970">Which with outrageous swelling flow too fast;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101980">Forbid (Lucina) this soon kindled fire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e101990">Should ere burn out itself. 'tis a true theme,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102000">That ne'er lasts long, that seemeth most extreme. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e102010" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102020">Can this rich price of nature, precious gem,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102030">Give entertainment to suspecting guests? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102040">Come, come, these arms are curious chains of love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102050">With which thou linkest my heart eternally,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102060"><pb facs="66" n="127"/> thy cheeks the royal paper interlined,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102070">With nature's rhetoric, and loves persuasion</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102080">Stands there attracting still my gazing eye:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102090">This then I'll read, and here I now will feign,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102100">That those all antique fables of the gods</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102110">Are writ in flowing numbers; first thy lip,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102120">Was fair Europa's, which they say, made Jove</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102130">Turn a wild heifer: next, this sparkling eye</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102140">Was the Aemonian Io's: then, this hand</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102150">Leda's, fair mother to those star-made twins;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102160">Thus, thus I'll comment on this golden book:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102170">Nature nor art, have taught me how to feign;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102180">Fairest, 'twas you first brought me to this vain:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102190">In loving combats, now I valiant prove,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102200">Let others war, great Amurath shall love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e102210" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102220">Brave resolution! O the fond thoughts of man!</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102230">Awake Euno! I'll find stratagems:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102240">There shall be physic, to purge this disease:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102250">Light sores are gently used; but such a part</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102260">Must be cut off, left it infect the heart. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e102270" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amar.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102280">Schahin, our tutor, we command this night</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102290">Be solemnised with all delightful sports</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102300">Thy learned invention best can think upon. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102310">Prepare a mask, which lively represents,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102320">How once the gods did love: that shall not teach</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102330">Us by examples; but we'll smile to think,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102340">How poor and weak their idle feigning was</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102350">To our affection. Schahin, be free in wit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102360">And sudden: now come my kingdom's bride:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102370">Hymen would wed himself to such a bride. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e102380">Exeunt all but Schahin.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e102390">
            <head>Actus 1. Scaena 2.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e102400" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102410">Nature, and all those universal powers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102420">Which showed such admirable godlike skill,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102430"><pb facs="67" n="130"/> in framing this true model of ourselves,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102440">This man, this thing called man, why do you thus,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102450">Make him a spectacle of such laughter for you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102460">When in each man we see a monarchy? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102470">For, as in states, all fortunes still attend:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102480">So with a kingdom, with a complete state</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102490">Will governed, and well managed in himself:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102500">Both each man bears, when that best part of man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102510">(Reason) doth sway and rule each passion. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102520">Affections are good servants: but if will</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102530">Makes them once master, they'll prove tyrants still. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102540">No more King now, poor subject Amurath;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102550">Whom I have seen, break through a troop of men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102560">Like lightning from a cloud: and done those acts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102570">Which 'E'en the furies would have trembled at:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102580">Treading down armies, as if by them he meant</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102590">Of dead men's backs to build up stairs to heaven:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102600">And now lieth lurking in a woman's arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102610">Drenched in the Lethe of ignoble lust,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102620">Appoints me for the wanton engineer</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102630">To keep his so loose thoughts in smoothing tune. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102640">Woman, enticing woman, golden hook</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102650">To catch our thoughts, and when we once are caught</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102660">To drag's into the public view of shame;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102670">And there we lie bathed in incestuous pleasure</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102680">For all good men to laugh and scorn at once. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102690">Bane to my senses! I could either wish</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102700">Our birth were like those creatures, which we say</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102710">Are bred from putrid and corrupted matter;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102720">Then that we should acknowledge our dear being</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102730">With grass and flowers: for what else is our state</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102740">Up to the top? But then the weight shall fall</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102750">Upon their head that caused it. Work (My brain)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102760">Tush, blood, not water must wash off this stain. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e102770">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e102780">
            <pb facs="67" n="129"/>
            <head>Scaena 3. Actus 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e102790">Enter Amurath in state with nobles: Eumorphe with attendant ladies: while Amurath ascends his throne, and placeth Eumorphe by him. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e102800" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102810">Shine here (My beauty) and expel the night</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102820">More than a thousand stars that grace the heavens:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102830">Methinks , I see the gods inventing shapes</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102840">In which they mean to court thee. Jove he frowns,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102850">And is more jealous, more suspicious</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102860">Of thee, than all the painted trulls, whose eyes</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102870">Bedeck the all enamelled firmament. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e102880" who="A85334_02-eumorphe">
              <speaker>Eum.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102890">Beauty (My lord) 'tis the worst part of woman,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102900">A weak poor thing, assaulted every hour</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102910">By creeping minutes of defacing time;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102920">A superficies which each breath of care</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102930">Blasts off: and every humorous stream of grief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102940">Which flows from forth these fountains of our eyes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102950">Washeth away, as rain doth winter's snow. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102960">But those blessed guiders of all nuptial rites,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102970">Have wrought a better cement to make fast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102980">The hearts of lovers; the true name of wife</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e102990">Guilds o'er our thrones, with a more constant shape</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103000">Than can be subject or to time, or care:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103010">And in ourselves; yea in our own true breasts</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103020">We have obedience, duty, careful love;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103030">And last and best of all, we may have children,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103040">Children are Hymen's pledges, these shall be</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103050">Perpetual chains, to link my lord and me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e103060" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103070">Art thou a woman? Goddess, we adore,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103080">And idolise what we but loved before. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103090">What devils have men been, whose furious brains</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103100">Have oft abused that deity called woman:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103110"><pb facs="68" n="130"/> dipping their raven's quill in Stygian ink,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103120">To blast such heavenly paper as your faces! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103130">Were all the enticing lusts, damned policies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103140">Prodigious fascinations, unsearched thoughts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103150">Dissembled tears, broke vows, loathed appetites,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103160">Luxurious and unsatiate desires;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103170">Were all these of women equally weighed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103180">That virtue in thy breast 'twill outbalance all,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103190">And recompense the ruin of all thy sex. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e103200">Enter a servant and speaks.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e103210" who="A85334_02-servant">
              <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103220">So please your majesty, l. schahin's ready</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103230">For entrance with his masque. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e103240" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103250">Tell him, we're wholly bent for expectation. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e103260">Exit Serv.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103270">Sit, sit (My Queen) music exceed your spheres,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103280">Think I am Jove, and godlike please our ears. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e103290">
            <head>Scaena 4. Actus 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e103300">A masque.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e103310">Enter from aloft two torch-bearers, then Jupiter and Juno, and two torch-bearers more, then Mars and Venus, and two torch-bearers more, then Apollo and Pallas ▪ and two more torch-bearers, then Neptune and Diana. Whilst they are descending, Cupid hanging in the air, sings to soft music this song following. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e103320" who="A85334_02-cupid">
              <speaker>Cupid</speaker>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e103330">Sings.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103340">Gaze you mortals, gaze you still,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103350">On the gods now look your fill. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103360">Jove and Juno are descending,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103370">Yet her jealousy's not ending,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103380">Mars, stern Mars, he will not fight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103390"><pb facs="68" n="131"/> but with Venus when 'tis night. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103400">Daphne crowns Apollo's head,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103410">Whom she would embrace in bed;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103420">Neptune swells his frothy cheek,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103430">Cause Diana is not meek. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103440">Gaze you mortals, etc. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e103450" who="A85334_02-jupiter">
              <speaker>Jup.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103460">Come now my (Sister and wife) we'll begin</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103470">To court afresh! Nay, lour not (Heaven's Queen)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103480">Here on this green we'll a lavalto dance;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103490">What if our hairs grow silver, yet our strength</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103500">Is young, and vigorous. Say (Fellow gods)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103510">(Since we are full of nectar, and our cares</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103520">Lie drenched in our Nepenthe) take your Queens, and be</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103530">All jovial; Mars for our daughter Venus,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103540">Apollo join with Pallas, brother of floods</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103550">Embrace Diana; gods sometimes merry be;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103560">But in the night, when mortals may not see. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e103570">Each God as appointed by Jove, takes his goddess, they dance a masque dance, and in the dance Juno observes Jove's glances to Eumorphe, and at the end of the dance, speaketh thus. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e103580" who="A85334_02-jupiter">
              <speaker>Jup.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103590">How now (Wanton?) Can I nowhere go,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103600">For recreation, but you follow me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e103610" who="A85334_02-juno">
              <speaker>Jun.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103620">Is this your recreation? Fie! My lord,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103630">Will you be wanton still! For here you came</l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e103640">Points at Eumorphe.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103650">For some new harlot, some new Queen for you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e103660" who="A85334_02-jupiter">
              <speaker>Jup.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103670">Juno, wife. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e103680" who="A85334_02-juno">
              <speaker>Juno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103690">Your sister, (Thunderer,) and not your wife! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103700">Banished from heaven I am; and your bed:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103710">Resign them both to strumpets, concubines. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e103720">Points at Eumorphe.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103730">And now you come to see a fresh new lass,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103740"><pb facs="69" n="132"/> in which pole now, or in what part of heaven</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103750">Shall she be stellified? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e103760" who="A85334_02-jupiter">
              <speaker>Jupit.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103770">Shall still sinister thoughts wrong our intent?</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103780">Well (Juno) well, you'll ever be a woman,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103790">A very, very woman! But since she scolds,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103800">Let's hence (Ye gods) lest her infectious breath</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103810">Blast the succeeding day; and mortals curse</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103820">Her hellbred jealousy: calumnious woman,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103830">Come, scold in heaven; for if gods lived on earth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103840">Suspicious tongues would blame most innocent mirth. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e103850">Here all the gods and goddesses ascend; at the top of the ascent, Juno stops and speaks.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e103860" who="A85334_02-juno">
              <speaker>Jun.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103870">Well, Jove looked pale, I touched him to the quick;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103880">'Tis some new minion he came down to see:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103890">Hark (Jealousy) know Juno is a woman! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103900">Am I not mad yet? Mistress Bride, adieu,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103910">Jove shall not steal a kiss; my curse is past,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103920">When thou sleepest first a bride, mayst sleep thy last. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e103930">Exit.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e103940" who="A85334_02-cupid">
              <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103950">Fair bride, I sang thy epithalamy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103960">And left Elysium for thy nuptials:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103970">Juno here thundered 'Against the thunderer;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103980">Knowing how thy beauty dazzles hers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e103990">She durst not let heaven's King once glance a look,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104000">But threatened with her hellbred incantations,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104010">To metamorphize thine unparalleled</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104020">And most celestial shape into worse forms;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104030">And more prodigious than ever poisoned charms</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104040">Wrought on the fabled concubines of Jove:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104050">But know great Queen, my mother Venus vows</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104060">Her everlasting guard to save such beauty;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104070">Lest if thou perish, nature herself</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104080">Lose her only parterre of serenity. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104090">But I must haste, love, which the gods protect,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104100">Can never be endangered by neglect. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e104110">Ascend't.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104120" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <pb facs="69" n="133"/>
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104130">Schahin, thine art is excellent but say,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104140">Do gods fall out for love amongst themselves? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104150" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104160">My lord, these are but fables: yet to make</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104170">The show more pertinent, and to grace your Queen,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104180">Conceit took leave to put the frown on Juno. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104190" who="A85334_02-eumorphe">
              <speaker>Eum.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104200">My lords and friends, we shall be ever thankful</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104210">And rest a debtor to your courtesy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104220" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104230">Not so, fair Queen, but durst I now entreat</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104240">The Kings detaining from the sweets of bed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104250">There yet remains one thought upon conceit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104260">Which you would doubly grace me to behold. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104270" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104280">Our worthy tutor shall obtain a night,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104290">A night of us, in any case we can! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104300" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104310">But then let me inform your majesty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104320">That 'tis a warrior's show, which once you loved,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104330">But now are free from. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104340" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104350">'Tis best of all, with greediness we'll see it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104360">Oh how the soul doth gratulate itself</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104370">When safely it beholds the dangerous state</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104380">Of others, and itself security free! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104390">Glad are we still to stand upon the shore,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104400">And see afar off others tossed i'th' sea:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104410">Or in a gallery at a fencer's stage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104420">We laugh when mutually each one takes wounds;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104430">Sit still (Eumorphe:) Schahin, thy show in haste;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104440">'Tis best delight, to think on troubles past. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e104450">
            <head>Scaena 5. Actus 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e104460">Enter in masque the ghost of Hector and Achilles, to them Alexander the great stands gazing on 't 'em, whilst fame speaks from aloft. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104470" who="A85334_02-fame">
              <speaker>Fame.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104480">Stay you most worthy shades ▪ brave Hector, stay;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104490">And proud Achilles, know your massy tombs,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104500"><pb facs="70" n="134"/> which have so long o'erwhelmed your valiant bones,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104510">Yawns wide to let the imprisoned corses forth. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104520">I must afresh embalm your sacred trunks,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104530">And sweet your memory with most happy oil</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104540">Of just report; the gods awaked me fame</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104550">From out the oblivious sepulchre of sleep,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104560">To drop that ink into old Homer's pen,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104570">Wherewith he curiously hath lined your names,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104580">Enfolding them in everlasting cedar,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104590">And make them live to all posterity. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104600">Virtue to valour hath his gift assigned,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104610">Great men may die, yet deeds still rest in mind. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e104620">Exeunt umbrae Hectoris and Achilis, Manet Alexander looking after them, reading in Homer.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104630" who="A85334_02-alexander">
              <speaker>Alexand.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104640">
                <seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A85334_02-e104650">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>
              </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104660">Most fortunate young man, whose worth is crowned</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104670">With everlasting trophies of renown,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104680">How hath he set thee on the wings of fame</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104690">Which soar i'th middle region of high glory,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104700">Proposed to all, a never dying story! </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e104710">Enter to Alexander, Philoxenus a captain. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104720" who="A85334_02-philoxenus">
              <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104730">May it please thee (Son of Jupiter) to accept</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104740">A present, which our fight enriched us with? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104750" who="A85334_02-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104760">Is it a band of stubborn soldiers, captain? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104770" who="A85334_02-philoxenus">
              <speaker>Philox.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104780">O no (My liege) of exquisite formed ladies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104790">Darius his wife, the wonder of her sex;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104800">Besides a troop of such shaped Ganimedes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104810">That love not equals. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104820" who="A85334_02-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104830">Philoxenus, we thank thee. Yet hark,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104840">There is a secret we would know of thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104850">And you must tell us: on your faith you must. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104860" who="A85334_02-philoxenus">
              <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104870">My liege —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e104880" who="A85334_02-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104890">Nay, no court oil (By your leave) no flattery,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104900">We are but man, this very trunk of ours,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104910">Is but a vessel filled with humane blood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104920"><pb facs="70" n="135"/> and we trust not that parasite like pen,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104930"><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A85334_02-e104940"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104950">All the destroying vices of frail man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104960">I may be subject to; but what base looseness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104970">Or supple luxury, didst thou ere observe</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104980">So to benumb our sense, that thou shouldst think</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e104990">We could be pleased with such effeminate presents? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105000">Know sir, our eyes shall have that abstinence</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105010">That will not look on them, on boys, or women. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105020">Hence then, and present some coward with them. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e105030">Exit Philoxenus</stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105040">Give me a spectacle would please the gods,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105050">And make them bend their ivory brows to the earth;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105060">A man, a soldier, strong with his wounds;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105070">'Mongst fate and ruin, upright and unshaped,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105080">His mind being all his guard, his wall, and armour ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105090">And if he fall, still noble wrath remains</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105100">In his amased trunk: not all the darts</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105110">Stuck in his sides, making him all one wound,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105120">Affright his courage; but wrath lending weapons,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105130">Himself doth seem a new and horrid war. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105140">Nor are those milksops which beguile the time,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105150">With stealing minutes from their ladies' lips,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105160">Such as the gods do love; for as the wind</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105170">Loseth it's force, if it be not opposed</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105180">With woods of strong and stubborn planted trees;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105190">So virtue, if it walk in trodden paths. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105200">That breaks up honour's gap, and makes the way</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105210">Through paths of death: that flame burns strong</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105220">Which is resisted: valour shines in wrong:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105230">Of Alexander's soldiers be this said,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105240">War was as peace, when he the army led. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e105250">Exit.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e105260" who="A85334_02-fame">
              <speaker>Fame.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105270">Brave Macedon, how truly hast thou weighed</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105280">The reason of man's birth! who is equal born,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105290">For all the world, as well as for himself.</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105300">The world's a field too narrow for thy worth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105310"><pb facs="71" n="136"/> and although nature hath her enacted bounds</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105320">For sea and earth, nay for the heavens themselves,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105330">Nor sea nor earth shall coop thy valour up:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105340">Valour of nature ever this attains,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105350">That it breaks forth, far, and beyond her chains,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105360">And this I'll trumpet out; the whole world's ball,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105370">In which thou art so great, to thee is small. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105380">When men want worlds to show their virtue in,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105390">That is the crime o'th gods, and not their sin:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105400">'Tis a decree of a true soldier's mind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105410">To think naught done, when ought is left behind. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105420">On (Valiant youth) for, know I will appoint</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105430">A Grecian prince, who so shall steep his quill</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105440">To paint thy name in wells of eloquence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105450">That this thy scorn of lust shall be proposed</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105460">For King's example to posterity. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105470">Know mortals, that the men the gods most love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105480">In hard and dangerous arts they always prove</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105490">When men live brave at first, then fall to crimes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105500">Their bad is chronicle to future times:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105510">For, who begins good arts, and not proceeds</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105520">He but goeth backward in all noble deeds. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105530">Death consecrates those men whose awful end,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105540">Though most men fear, yet all men must commend. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e105550">Ascends.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e105560">Amurath seems troubled, yet collecting himself, dissembles his passion, speaks. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e105570" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105580">Scahin, the Macedon's beholding to thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105590">And history shall pay you thanks for this,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105600">Which we rest debtors for. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e105610" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105620">Great prince, such kindness of acceptance pays</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105630">For things which are but for a King's delight:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105640">In seeing them, he amply doth requite. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e105650" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105660">Eumorphe, love, Queen, wife, le'ts haste to bed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105670">And may we wish this night eternal time. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105680"><pb facs="71" n="137"/>Scahin, good night: good night, kind gentlemen. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105690">Thus when we are dead shall we revive o'th' stage:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105700">One hour can present a King's whole age. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e105710">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A85334_02-e105720">
          <head>Actus 2.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e105730">
            <head>Scaena 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e105740">Enter Schahin, Eurenoses. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e105750" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105760">Observed you not the King's looks? Grew they not pale? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e105770" who="A85334_02-eurenoses">
              <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105780">O yes (Lord Schahin) you must be his parent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105790">And snatch him out o'th' gulf he's falling in. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105800">That feigned speech of Alexander's wrought</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105810">Like to most purging physic; nights then black,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105820">When 'tis compared with day: boldness is clear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105830">When 'tis presented before bastard fear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e105840" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105850">I'll tell thee, Eurenoses, thou art a soldier,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105860">And I am both a soldier, and a scholar;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105870">And for these two professions am both most glorious,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105880">And most meritorious; Pallas is for both:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105890">Oh what Tisiphon, what snaked scourge</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105900">Can make a scholar, that should never sleep,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105910">But 'twixt the pillows of Parnassus hills,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105920">And dip his lips in springs of Helicon,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105930">Make him by snoring on a wanton breast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105940">And suck the adulterate and spiced breath</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105950">Of a lewd famed woman? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e105960" who="A85334_02-eurenoses">
              <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105970">And for a soldier (Schahin,) let me speak:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105980">We that do know, the use of swords and fire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e105990">We that do know, halters can throttle us,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106000">Shall we ere venture on a woman's cruelty? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106010">We that endure no lords, shall we endure</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106020">A woman to overcome us? Most true Demophoon,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106030">I reverence thy memory: no puling phrase</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106040"><pb facs="72" n="138"/> could so enchain thee to thy Thracian dame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106050">But thou wouldst rather perish than she save thee. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106060">I'll not declaim long on that common theme,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106070">But they have lust lie in their fingers ends,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106080">And whilst their sweethearts breath sticks in their sheets,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106090">They will admit another Lucrece in the day,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106100">To be a Thais, if the night will not gainsay. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106110" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106120">Why (Eurenoses) why should we endure</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106130">A new Queen now? this kingdom wants not heirs:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106140">We know (Should we have more) 'twere dangerous. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106150">But hark! The queen's for bed-enticing sleep</l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e106160">Soft music.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106170">With charms of music: well, even such a night</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106180">May yet prove dismal ere the following light! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106190" who="A85334_02-eurenoses">
              <speaker>Eurenos.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106200">Scahin, let's in:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106210">The first degree to purge such ills as these,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106220">Is to instruct the patient his disease:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106230">That you have done. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106240" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106250">Yea, and will yet once more</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106260">Adventure a new stratagem. Just when the King</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106270">Has rid his chamber, and with covetous haste</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106280">Thinks for to clip Elysium, and drink deep</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106290">Of his long wished delight, I having skill</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106300">And uncontrolled access, will in disguise</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106310">Seem his deceased father's apparition:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106320">And by all ties of children to their parents,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106330">Bid him forsake that vile bewitching woman. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106340" who="A85334_02-eurenoses">
              <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106350">An easy medicine doth and sure will work,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106360">To rub shrewd wounds, make them but fester more,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106370">Foul medicines we worse brook, than a foul sore. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e106380">
            <head>Scaena 2. Actus 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e106390">Enter Eumorphe as to bed in her night-robes, attended with tapers and ladies. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106400" who="A85334_02-menthe">
              <speaker>Menth.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106410">Madam make haste, the King will be impatient</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106420"><pb facs="72" n="139"/> if he be from you long. O happiness! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106430" who="A85334_02-eumorphe">
              <speaker>Emorph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106440">Why Menthe! then thou deemest us happy</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106450">Thus to command a world of services,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106460">To have a King my subject; and attended</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106470">With these harmonious sounds t'affect our ears? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106480" who="A85334_02-menthe">
              <speaker>Menthe.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106490">Yes (Truly madam) 'tis a happiness. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106500" who="A85334_02-eumorphe">
              <speaker>Eumorph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106510">'Tis, were 't eternal: but I fear a power,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106520">A woman's power, doth but make sport with us. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106530">Why, were we not once (Menthe) a captive wretch? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106540" who="A85334_02-menthe">
              <speaker>Menthe</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106550">Yes lady! now your happiness's the more:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106560">Riches please best, when there went want before. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106570" who="A85334_02-eumorphe">
              <speaker>Eum.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106580">That power which raised us from so base, so high,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106590">Can throw us down again as suddenly:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106600">Methinks my life is but a player's scene</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106610">In the last act: my part was then to play</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106620">A captive creature, and a Queen today. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106630" who="A85334_02-menthe">
              <speaker>Menthe.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106640">Your morals (Madam) are too serious;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106650">Methinks these ornaments should elevate</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106660">Your dumpish spirits. Think this bed a place,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106670">In which no icy slipping chance hath power;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106680">A King's safe bed is like a guarded tower. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106690" who="A85334_02-eumorphe">
              <speaker>Eum.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106700">No (Menthe) no, 'tis not the bed of state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106710">Nor the free smile of a well pleased King:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106720">'Tis not the embracing arms of emperors,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106730">Nor all the gems that so enwreathe the brows</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106740">Can so allure fortune unto their gaze,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106750">As she should still be constant; oh she's blind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106760">Nor doth she know herself where she is kind;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106770">Those, those are Kings, and Queens, whose breast's secure,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106780">Like brazen walls, lust's entrance not endure;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106790">Where impotent ambition not intrudes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106800">Nor the unstable talk of multitudes;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106810">Fortune serves such, they happiness command</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106820">More than all Lybia's gold, all Tagus' sand;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106830">As heaven hath given us no more conspicuous things,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106840">Than form or beauty: so like a forward spring,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106850"><pb facs="73" n="140"/> nothing more short. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106860" who="A85334_02-menthe">
              <speaker>Menthe.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106870">Madam, divine not of a change; belief</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106880">Is too too prone, in entertaining grief! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106890" who="A85334_02-eumorphe">
              <speaker>Eum.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106900">Our lord attends, to enter in,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106910">And surely sleep envieth his delight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106920">For he sits heavy on my drowsy lids,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106930">Draw all our curtains; sleep be guiles our ears. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e106940" who="A85334_02-menthe">
              <speaker>Men.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106950">Madam, good night, time helps suspicious fears! </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e106960">Exit Menthe.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e106970">This song is to be sung in the music room to soft music, now when she looks, she's dreaming scent to Elisium.</stage>
            <quote xml:id="A85334_02-e106980">
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e106990">Drop golden showers, gentle sleep,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107000">And all the angels of the night,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107010">Which do us in protection keep,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107020">Make this Queen dream of delight</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107030">Morpheus be kind a little, and be</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107040">Death's now true image, for 't will prove</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107050">To this poor Queen, that then thou art he;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107060">Her grave is made i'th bed of love. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107070">Thus with sweet sweets can heaven mix gall,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107080">And marriage turn to funeral. </l>
            </quote>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e107090">
            <head>Scaena 3. Actus. 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e107100">Enter Amurath in his night robes, a taper in his hand, seems much disturbed, speaks. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e107110" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107120">Turk, Amurath, slave, nay something baser,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107130">King! For all airy titles which the gods</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107140">Have blasted man withal, to make them swell</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107150">With puffed up honour, and ambitious wind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107160">This name of King holds greatest antipathy</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107170"><pb facs="73" n="141"/> with manly government: for if we weigh,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107180">'Tis subjects, and not Kings bear all the sway. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107190">Each whispered murmur from their idle breath</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107200">Condemns a King to infamy, to death;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107210">Were there a metempsychosis of souls,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107220">And nature should a free election grant</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107230">What things they afterwards would reinform,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107240">The vain and haughtiest minds the sun ere saw,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107250">Would choose it's cottage in some shepherd's flesh,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107260">Nay, be confined within some dog or cat,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107270">Than (Antique-like) prank in a King's gay-clothes ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107280">Were I no King, and had no majesty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107290">I had more than all Kings, blessed liberty;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107300">And without rumor might enjoy my choice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107310">Not fearing censure of each popular voice. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107320">Poor men may love, and none their wills correct:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107330">But all turn satires of a King's affect. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107340">O my base greatness! What disastrous star</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107350">Professed itself a midwife at my birth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107360">To shape me into such prodigious states? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107370">But hence regard of tongues! Were we a saint,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107380">Some envious tongue would dare our names to taint:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107390">And he from slander is at securest rest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107400">Not that hath none, but that regards it least. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107410">Open you envious curtains; here's a sight,</l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e107420">Draws the curtain.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107430">That might commend the act of love so chaste. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107440">Were now the chariot-guider of the sun</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107450">Weary o's task, and would entreat a day</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107460">Of heaven to rest in, here's a radiant look,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107470">That might be fixed ith' midst oth' axletree;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107480">And in despite of dark conspiring clouds,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107490">She would outshine sun, moon and all the stars. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107500">O, I could court thee now (My sweet) a fresh,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107510">Mixing a kiss with every period;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107520">Telling the lilies how they are but won,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107530"><pb facs="74" n="142"/> earth in the vernant spring is dull, and dark,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107540">Compared with this aspect! the Eastern air,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107550">Fanned with the wings of Mercury and Jove,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107560">Infectious, but compared with this perfume. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107570">Hence then th' ambition of that furious * youth, Alexis</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107580">Who knew not what a crime his rashness was! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107590">I might o'ercome more kingdoms, have more dominion,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107600">Enthrone myself an emperor oth' world;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107610">I might, I might; Amurath thou mightst. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107620">The Christians now will scoff at Mahomet;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107630">Perchance they sent this wretch thus to inchant me! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107640">O my perplexed thoughts! Tush, I'll to bed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107650">Should the commanding thunder of the gods</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107660">Prohibit me, or strike me in the act. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107670">Talk on (Vain rumor) fame I dare thy worst! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107680">Call me a lusty, lazy, wanton, coward!</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107690">Should I win all the world, my breath once fled,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107700">My bad would still survive all good be dead. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107710">Eumorphe, sweet, I come! you sacred powers</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107720">Who have bestowed some happiness on man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107730">To help to pass away this sinful life,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107740">Grant me a youthful vigour yet a while,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107750">Full veins, free strength, complete and manly sense,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107760">To know, and take a beauty most immense! </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e107770">
            <head>Scaena 4. Actus 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e107780">Amurath makes haste to the bed, on a sudden enter Schahin disguised like the ghost of Orchanes, father to Amurath.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e107790" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scabin.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107800">Amurath, Amurath. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e107810" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amurath.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107820">Devil, devil; what? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107830">Darest thou appear before an angel (Fiend?) </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e107840" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107850">O Amurath, why doth intemperate lust,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107860">Raging within thy furious youthful veins,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107870">Burst through thy father's tomb? Disturb his soul? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107880"><pb facs="74" n="143"/>Know, all the torments that the fabulous age</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107890">Dreamt, did afflict deceased impious ghosts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107900">Heartbiting-hunger, and soul-searching thirst,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107910">The never consumed, yet ever eaten prey</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107920">That the devouring vulture feeds upon,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107930">Are not such tortures as our offsprings crimes:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107940">They, they sit heavy on us, and no date</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107950">Makes our compassionate affection cease. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107960">O thou hereditary ulcer, hark,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107970">By the name of father, and by all those cares</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107980">Which brought me to my grave, to make thee great:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e107990">Thou that hast nothing of me but my crown:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108000">My enterprise surpassed the boundless sea,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108010">Cutting the churlish waves of Hellespont,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108020">When the flood stood which wind for to obey! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108030">Euxinum groaned beneath my burdenous ships:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108040">I was the first of all the Turkish Kings</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108050">That Europe knew, and the fond christians' plague. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108060">What coward blood ran flowing in my veins,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108070">When thou wert first begotten, who marrest all</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108080">Thy father's acts by thy untamed desires? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108090">Wherefore with Stygian curses I will lade thee:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108100">First, may she prove a strumpet to thy bed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108110">Be her lips poison, and let her loose embraces ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108120">Be venomous as scorpions: if she conceive</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108130">A generation from thee, let it be;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108140">As ominous as thou hast been to me;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108150">Rebellious to thy precepts, printing cares</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108160">Upon thy aged brows. O may they prove,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108170">As Faries for to lash thee in thy rest! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108180">But Amurath, if thou canst quench this flame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108190">If thou wilt cut this Gordian thread, and rend hence</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108200">That putrid wen which cleaves unto they flesh,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108210">Be all thine actions prosperous. Mahomet</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108220">Shall be auspicious unto each design;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108230">Fortune to show thee favour shall be proud,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108240"><pb facs="75" n="144"/> farewell. If what men do speak last before</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108250">They die take root, then dead men's should take more. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e108260">Exit Schahin.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e108270" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108280">What, art thou vanished? Know (Thou careful spright)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108290">Thou shalt no sooner pierce the wand'ring clouds</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108300">With unperceived flight, than my resolve</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108310">Shall expiate my former vanity. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108320">Look on thy son, thou airy intellect,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108330">And see him sacrifice to thy command! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108340">Now Titan turn thy breathing courser's back,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108350">Start hence bright day, a sable cloud invade</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108360">This universal globe, break every prop</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108370">And every hinge that doth sustain the heavens:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108380">For straight must die a woman, I have named</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108390">A crime, that may accuse all nature guilty. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108400">The sex wisely considered, deserves a death;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108410">For think this, Amurath, this woman may</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108420">Prostrate her delicate and ivory limbs</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108430">To some base page, or skull, or shrunk up dwarf,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108440">Or let some groom lie feeding on her lips,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108450">She may devise some mishapen trick</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108460">To satiate her goatish Amurath;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108470">And from her bent knees at meditation,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108480">Be taken by some slave toth' deep of hell! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108490">Thou'rt a brave creature, wert thou not a woman. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108500">Tutor! Come! thou shalt see my well-kept vow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108510">And know my hate, which saw me dote but now:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108520">Schahin! Eurenoses! Captains, ho! </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e108530">
            <head>Scaenae. 5. Actus. 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e108540">Enter Schahin, Eurenoses, Chase-illibegge.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108550">Our tutor, Eurenoses, captains, welcome. </l>
            <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108560">Gallants, I call you to a spectacle:</l>
            <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108570">My breast's too narrow to hoard up my joy ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108580">Nay, gaze here gentlemen! give nature thanks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108590"><pb facs="75" n="145"/> for framing such an excellent sense as sight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108600">Whereby such objects are enjoined as this ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108610">Which of you now imprison not your thoughts</l>
            <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108620">In envious and silent policy. </l>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e108630" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108640">My lord to whatsoever you shall propose,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108650">My sentence shall be free. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108660">Euren and mine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e108670" who="A85334_02-chase_illibegge">
              <speaker>Chase-il</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108680">And mine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e108690" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108700">Which of you then dare challenge to himself</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108710">Such a pathetical prerogative,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108720">So stoically severed from affection? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108730">That, had he such a creature as lieth here,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108740">One, at whom nature herself stood amazed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108750">One, whom those lofty ecstasies of poets,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108760">Should they decay, here't must nor barely dump</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108770">Their dull inventions with similitudes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108780">Taken from sun, moon, violets, roses;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108790">And, when their ruptures at a period stand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108800">A silent admiration must supply. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108810">Only name her, and she is all described. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108820">Hyperbole of women, colour itself</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108830">Is not more pure, and incontaminate!</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108840">Sleep dotes on her and grasps her eyelids close?</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108850">The sky itself hath only so much blew</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108860">As the azure in her veins lends by reflux. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108870">Here's breath that would those vapours purify,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108880">Which from Avernus chokes the flying birds:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108890">Here's heat would tempt the numbed Athenian,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108900">Though all his blood with age were congealed ye! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108910">Now, which of you all is so temperate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108920">That did he find this jewel in his bed</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108930">(Unless an eunuch) could refrain to grapple,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108940">And dally with her? come! speak freely all. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e108950" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Sch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108960">Truly (My lord) I came of mortal parents</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108970">And must confess me subject to desires;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108980">Freely enjoy your love!</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e108990">That were she mine, I surely would do no less. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e109000" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <pb facs="76" n="146"/>
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109010">What say Eurenoses? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e109020" who="A85334_02-eurenoses">
              <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109030">My lord, I say,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109040">That they may rail at light, that ne'er saw day;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109050">But had I such a creature by my side,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109060">Were the world twice enlarged, and all that world</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109070">O'ercome by me, all volumes writ,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109080">Made clean and filled up by rhetoric strains</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109090">Of my great deeds, historians should spend</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109100">Their ink and paper in my sole chronicle;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109110">A thousand such alluring idle charms</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109120">Could not conjure me from betwixt her arms. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e109130" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109140">Your sentence Chas-illebeg? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e109150" who="A85334_02-chase_illibegge">
              <speaker>Chas.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109160">What need your grace depend upon our breath? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109170">I vow (My lord,) if all those scrupulous things</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109180">Which burden us with precepts so precise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109190">Those parents, which when they are married once</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109200">And passed their strength of years, think their sons straight</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109210">Should be as old in every thing as they;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109220">I say my lord, did my head wear a crown,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109230">That Queen should be the chiefest gem t'adorn it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109240">Spite of all hate. That's an unhappy state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109250">When Kings must fear to love lest subjects' hate. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e109260" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109270">Well spoke, three milksops, Schahin. your sword,</l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e109280">Scahin gives him a sword.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109290">Now, now be valour in this manly arm</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109300">To cut off troops of thoughts that would invade me! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109310">Think you my mind is waxy to be wrought</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109320">Int' any fashion? Orchanes, thy strength! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109330">Here do I wish, as did that emperor,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109340">That all the heads of that enticing sex</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109350">Were upon hers, thus then should one full stroke</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109360">Mow them all off. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e109370">Amurath cuts off eumorphes head, shows it to the nobles. </stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109380">There kiss now (Captains) do, and clap her cheeks:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109390">This is the face that did so captive me:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109400">These were the looks that so bewitched mine eyes:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109410">Here be the lips, that I but for to touch,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109420"><pb facs="76" n="147"/> gave over fortune, victory, fame and all;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109430">These were two lying mirrors where I looked</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109440">And thought I saw a world of happiness. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109450">Now tutor, shall our swords be exercised</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109460">In ripping up the breasts of Christians? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109470">Say generals, whither is't first? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e109480" who="A85334_02-unassigned">
              <speaker>A.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109490">For Thracia. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e109500" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amurath.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109510">On then for Thracia, for he surely shall,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109520">That conquers first himself, soon conquer all. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e109530">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A85334_02-e109540">
          <head>Actus 3.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e109550">
            <head>Scaena 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e109560">Enter Cobelitz solus. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e109570" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cobelitz.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109580">Thou sacred guider of the arched heavens,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109590">Who canst collect the scattering stars, and fix</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109600">The erratic planets in the constant pole! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109610">O why shouldst thou take such solicitous care</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109620">To keep the air, and elements in course? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109630">That winter should unclothe our mother earth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109640">And wrap her in a winding sheet of snow;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109650">That then the spring duly revives her still,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109660">Unbinds her sinews, fills her clinged up veins</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109670">With living dew, and makes her young again. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109680">Next that, the Nemean terror breathes her flames,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109690">To parch her flaxy hairs with furious heat;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109700">Which to allay too, thou op'st the catacacts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109710">And water'st the world's gardens with blessed drops;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109720">Canst thou, which canst sustain the ponderous world,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109730">And keep it in true poise, securely sleep,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109740">Letting a tyrant (Which with a fillip, thus;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109750">Thou mightest sink to earth) to baffle thee? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109760">A warrior in thy fields, I long have been</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109770"><pb facs="77" n="148"/> to see if in thy sacred providence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109780">Thou meanst to arm me with thy thunderbolt,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109790">Yet, yet, it strikes not; now he giant-wise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109800">Dares thee again; pardon our earnest zeal</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109810">What e're's decreed for man, by thy behest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109820">He must perform, and in obedience rest. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109830">Thou, like spectators when they do behold</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109840">An hardy youth encountering with a bear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109850">Or something terrible ▪ then they give a shout;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109860">So dost thou even applaud they self to see</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109870">Religion striving with calamity. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109880">Which while it often bears, and still rests true,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109890">It's fence 'gainst all that after shall ensue. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109900">Turk, I'll oppose thee still; heaven has decreed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109910">That this weak hand, shall make that tyrant bleed ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109920">A man religious, firm, and strongly good</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109930">Cannot oth' sudden be, nor understood. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e109940">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e109950">
            <head>Actus 3. Scaena 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e109960">Enter Amurath in arms, Schahin, captains, soldiers. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e109970" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amurath.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109980">Rise (Soul!) enjoy the prize of thy brave worth:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e109990">Schahin, the present that thou so professed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110000">Should from the city of Orestias,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110010">Make proud our eyes! then tell me, hast thou slain</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110020">A thousand superstitious Christian souls?</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110030">Made them stoop to us: oh, I would bathe my hands</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110040">In their warm blood to make them supple (Schahin)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110050">That they may wield more spears: our hands are dull,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110060">Our fury's patient! Now will I be a Turk.</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110070">And to our prophet's altars do I vow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110080">That to his yoke I will all necks subdue,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110090">Or in their throats my bloody sword imbrue. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e110100"><pb facs="77" n="149"/>Schahin calls in his soldiers, and each of them presents to Amurath the head of a dead christian. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110110" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110120">Then King, to add fresh oil unto thy hate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110130">And make it raise itself a greater flame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110140">See here these Christians heads; thus still shall fall</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110150">Before thy fatal hand, these impious slaves:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110160">So long as numbers is wanting to the sand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110170">So long as day shall come with sun, and night</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110180">Be spangled with the twilight dawning stars,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110190">Whilst floods shall fall into the ocean,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110200">Shall Christians tremble at Turk's thundering strokes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110210" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amurat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110220">So am I Amurath, the great King of Turks,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110230">Oh how it glads me thus to pash their brains,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110240">To rend their locks, to tear these infidels! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110250">Who thundered when these heads were smitten off? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110260">Stars I could reach you with my lofty hand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110270">'Tis well, enough, enough, (Great Amurath)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110280">For now I sit in Orcanes' great throne,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110290">And sacrifice due rites to Mahomet;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110300">Yet why enough? I'll on, and dung the earth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110310">With Christians rotted trunks, that from that soil,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110320">May spring more Cadmean monsters to o'ercome them. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110330">Captains, what countries next shall we make flow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110340">With channels of their blood? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110350" who="A85334_02-eurenoses">
              <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110360">To Servia (My lord) there are troops of arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110370">Gathered to resist Mahometan. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110380" who="A85334_02-chase_illibegge">
              <speaker>Chase</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110390">At Bulgaria, there they set on fire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110400">The countries as they pass, 'twere good we haste. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110410" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110420">Why they do well! we like of their desire</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110430">To make the flame in which themselves must fry! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110440">Ruin, destruction, famine, and the sword,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110450">Shall all invade them: sun stay thou thy flight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110460">And see the sneaks in their own river drenched,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110470">Whilst with their blood our furious thirst is quenched! </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e110480">
            <pb facs="78" n="150"/>
            <head>Scaena. 3. Actus 3.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e110490">Enter in arms, Lazarus despot of Servia, Sesmenos governor of Bulgaria.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110500" who="A85334_02-lala">
              <speaker>La.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110510">Whither (Bulgaria) whither must we fly?</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110520">The butcherous turk's at hand. Blessed sanctity!</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110530">If thou didst ere guard goodness, wall our towers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110540">Bring strength into our nerves. For in thy cause</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110550">Our breasts upon their rapiers we will run;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110560">We'll with just hope confront the tyrant's rage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110570">Meet him i'the face, fury will find us arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110580">There is a power can guard us from all harms. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110590" who="A85334_02-sesmenos">
              <speaker>Ses.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110600">Let us be sudden: for we'll not find scope,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110610">To see our haps. Who most doth fear, may hope. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e110620">Enter to them Cobelitz.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110630" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110640">Governor, captains, haste unto your arms:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110650">The dangers imminent, and the turk's at hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110660" who="A85334_02-lazarus">
              <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110670">- (Cobelitz) must we still wade thus deep</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110680">In blood and terror? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110690" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110700">Yes (Servia) we must, we should, we ought,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110710">Ease and lucresse keeps baseness company. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110720">Shall we not blush to see the register</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110730">Of those great Romans, and heroic Greeks,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110740">Which did those acts, at which our hearts are struck</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110750">Beneath all credence, only to win fame?</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110760">And shall not we for that eternal name? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110770">To live without all credence, even to win fame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110780">Is not to know life's chief, and better parts:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110790">To us of future hopes: calamity</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110800">Must help to purchase immortality. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110810" who="A85334_02-sesmenos">
              <speaker>Ses.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110820">Well spoken (True christian) they who still live high,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110830">And snoare in praised applause ne'er know to bear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110840">A contumely, or check, or fate. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110850">Wisely to steer a ship, or guide an army,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110860"><pb facs="78" n="151"/> undaunted hardiness is requisite;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110870">Oh then let's to our weapons! make him yield;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110880">They which deny all right, oft give't ith' field. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e110890">Enter Christian soldiers falling out among them-fighting confusedly.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110900" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110910">Why (Gentlemen) we want no foes to fight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110920">Nor need we turn our weapons on ourselves. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e110930">One soldier speaks as drunk.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110940" who="A85334_02-xxxx_1">
              <speaker>1.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110950">You lazy rogue, what come in my cabinet? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e110960">Answer the other.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e110970" who="A85334_02-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110980">Conspiring slave, you murmured 'gainst th'allowance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e110990">And wouldst persuade upon a larger pay,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111000">To betray all garrisons, and turn Turk. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111010">Thou half can-carousing rascal, I'll tear thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111020">And those treacherous veins of thine. Will you see,</l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e111030">They all fall by the ears.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111040">Blew-jackets, will you see your corporal wronged?</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111050">Well, since I fight for victuals, for company. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111060">Use now your swords and bucklers. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111070" who="A85334_02-lala">
              <speaker>La.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111080">Treason, the next man that speaks or strikes a blow. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111090" who="A85334_02-soldier">
              <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111100">Then shall our laundresses fight for us? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111110" who="A85334_02-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111120">Why, Amazons! Baudicans, come help to scratch. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e111130">Enter some truls on both sides, they fight and scratch.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111140" who="A85334_02-sesmenos">
              <speaker>Sesm.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111150">O Cobelitz, what way shall we appease them? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e111160">Truls scold confusedly: thus</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111170" who="A85334_02-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. trul </speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111180">Out, thy corporal (Housewife) hath the itch,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111190">You now will have foul washing. Drab, I'll tear your mouth:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111200" who="A85334_02-xxxx_2">
              <speaker>2.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111210">An inch or two yet wider. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111220" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111230">What, soldiers! think you each distasteful word,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111240">Given 'mongst yourselves so strong an obloquy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111250">That revenge spurs you to each others death? </l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e111260">The general parts them with his sword.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111270">And will not seek to wash those blasphemies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111280">In seas of their foul blood, which are belched out</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111290">By our approaching foes, against the essence</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111300">Of the eternal! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111310" who="A85334_02-lazarus">
              <pb facs="79" n="152"/>
              <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111320">Leave, leave, these factions; cease these mutinies</l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e111330">A drum from the Turk's Camp.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111340">Hark, their drums take advantage of these stirs:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111350">Let us oppose our strength against our foe;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111360">And in our camp let not one soldier be,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111370">Who will not find, and strike his enemy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111380" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111390">Now (Blessed guider and great strength of arms)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111400">If in thy secret and hidden decree,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111410">Thou hast not yet appointed the full time</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111420">Wherein thou meanest to tame this tiger,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111430">Who dare murmur against thine hidden will? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111440">Be we slain now, there's victory in store,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111450">Which when thou pleasest thou 't give, and not before. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111460">Give us still strength of patience, not to wish,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111470">A funeral honour unto all the world,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111480">When we are perishing, we'll still believe,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111490">Those dangers worth our death we undergo,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111500">Whilst he, who's ours, is alike thy foe. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111510">Should fortune lose this day, when we are slain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111520">Thou canst give hands, and strength, and men again;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111530">On thee we trust then, and on thee bear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111540">Scorning for heaven's sake to shed a tear. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e111550">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e111560">
            <head>Actus 3. Scaena 4.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e111570">A march within, excursions, alarms. Enter as conquerors, Cairadin bassa, Schahin, leading young men Christians, prisoners.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111580" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111590">Bassa, we thank thy valour and discretion,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111600">In finding fit occasion to invade</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111610">The mutinous Christians! these captives here</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111620">Shall be good presents to our worthy master. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111630" who="A85334_02-bassa">
              <speaker>Bassa.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111640">General, now trust me these young slaves,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111650">Be full of valour, they have metal in them. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111660" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Schuh.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111670">Yes: and to his highness shall perform</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111680"><pb facs="79" n="153"/> a service which I long have thought upon,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111690">And when his Turkish majesty requires;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111700">They'll fit to be a near attendant guard,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111710">On all occasions to the emperor;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111720">Therefore they shall be called janissaries,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111730">By me first instituted, for our prince's safeties sake. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111740" who="A85334_02-bassa">
              <speaker>Bass.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111750">Their vigour and strong hearts becomes such service,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111760">For to o'ercome them made our soldiers sweat</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111770">Much Turkish blood: the Servians kept the fight</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111780">With stubborn hard resistance, the Bulgarians</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111790">Left the right wing; there set I forward first,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111800">And like a torrent rolled destruction on,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111810">Raising huge storms of blood, as doth the whale</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111820">Puff up the waves against a mighty ship;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111830">Methinks , I see the rivers of their gore:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111840">Their leaders trampled on by Turkish horse,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111850">The body of their army quite dispersed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111860">Themselves all floating in vermilion pools,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111870">With their own weapons hasting to their death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111880">And such a slaughter did we make of them,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111890">As nature scarce can ere repair again. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111900">One hastening tother's death, pulling to ground</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111910">Him that held up, so they each other drowned. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111920" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111930">Still are they confident upon a power,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111940">They know not what, who (As they think) can snatch</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111950">Their precise souls from out the jaws of death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e111960" who="A85334_02-bassa">
              <speaker>Bass.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111970">Yes, such a superstition doth possess them;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111980">For when they looked for nothing but their fate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e111990">And danger stood in sweat upon their brows:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112000">They yet scorned Mahomet, and profaned his rites,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112010">And naught but horror made them to believe</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112020">So many men were fighting on his side,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112030">As might have changed my seat, and part ith' world,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112040">(Though nature stood against) to a new place:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112050">Or carry Sestos whereby Abydos stands,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112060">Or pull down Atlas with so many hands. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e112070">
            <pb facs="80" n="154"/>
            <head>Actus 3. Scaena 5.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e112080">Enter Amurath with ambassadors from German Ogly, concerning Bajazet, Amurath's elder son, and the Mahometans daughter. Cairadin Bassa presents Amurath with his captives for janissaries. Etc. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e112090" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amurath.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112100">How like our captains the last victory? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112110">(If any can prophesy of future things)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112120">Methought I did dream of this blessed hap. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112130">How fortune did involve them in their ruin!</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112140">And flight from danger, brought them in their ruin.</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112150">Each one astonished with a sudden fear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112160">Knew not the danger that was then most near. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e112170">Bassa and Schahin presents Amurath with captives for janissaries</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e112180" who="A85334_02-bassa">
              <speaker>Bassa.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112190">To add more triumph, I present my liege,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112200">With these young rebels, which you may bring up</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112210">In all the precepts of our Mahomet. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e112220" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112230">And, (For great emperor, your person wants</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112240">A thing which much o'erclouds your light of state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112250">Attendant janissaries to a prince:)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112260">These may be so trained up, as to supply</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112270">The duty fit for such a majesty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e112280" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112290">Bassa, we thank thy strength, Schahin your counsel</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112300">And to that end, let them have safe protection. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112310">But we must treat now of a marriage (Lords)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112320">The German Ogly, he whose sceptre sways</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112330">The Phrygian confines in strong Asia,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112340">By embassy entreats that he may join</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112350">His daughter hatum to our Bajazet. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112360">Ambassador, here to our counsel speak</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112370">Your master's message. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e112380" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <pb facs="80" n="155"/>
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112390">Please then your maj. and these reverend heads</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112400">To be informed my master's will by me? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112410">In wedlock if your prince may be combined</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112420">To the fair Princess his sole daughter,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112430">He freely gives the Phrygian territories,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112440">And Bythinia to you for your dowry;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112450">Cutas, Simon, egregios, Sansale,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112460">Abbettingon, the Ottomans estate;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112470">Which Ottomans, because he not endures,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112480">The noble Zelzucciom family protests,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112490">To join with you in quelling their ambition</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e112500" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Sca.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112510">May't please your majesty to like mine advice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112520">It's good to have alliance with such friends;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112530">Kings that combine themselves are like to shafts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112540">The ancient sage proposed unto his sons;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112550">Which whilst together they were close compact,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112560">Arms, knees, and his whole strength, could never break;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112570">Take one by one, they with a touch were cracked:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112580">So Kings may be o'ercome that stand alone;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112590">But two such princes, knit thus hand in hand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112600">Should nations totter they would firmly stand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e112610" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112620">Yes Schahin, we'll approve what thou sayest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112630">Then from us carry the great Asia's monarch</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112640">This our kindest greeting:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112650">Tell him, the gates of Prusa shall stand ope,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112660">And the glad air shall echo notes of joy ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112670">To entertain her who shall bless our land</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112680">With hopeful issue; greedy thoughts expect</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112690">Her soon arrival; and so (Ambassador)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112700">Inform thy Princess, when she shall appear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112710">A lasting star shall shine within our sphere. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e112720">
            <pb facs="81" n="156"/>
            <head>Scen 6. Actus 3.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e112730">Enter Sasmenos, Lazarus, Cobelitz.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e112740" who="A85334_02-sasmenos">
              <speaker>Sas.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112750">O Servia, our cities are turned flames;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112760">Each strives to haste his own and others death:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112770">And as though heaven conspired destruction too,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112780">That rains down scalding sulphur on our heads,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112790">Here one that lies thick gasping for his breath</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112800">Is choked with blood that runs from's fellows wounds;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112810">Whilst others for the dead are making graves,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112820">Themselves are made the corpse that do fill them. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112830">Nobles, and base, together perish all,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112840">And a drawn sword sticks fast in every rib;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112850">Our stones are died vermilion with our blood:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112860">Old creatures that are creeping to the grave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112870">Are thrust on faster. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112880">Infants, but in the threshold of their lives,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112890">Are thus kicked off: o most disastrous times,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112900">To love our deaths, and make our life our crimes! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e112910" who="A85334_02-lazarus">
              <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112920">See, see, the ruins of our goodly walls,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112930">Our city's smoke hinder the sight of heaven:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112940">The conqueror yet amazed measures out our towns,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112950">With eyes of terror, and doth scarce believe</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112960">He hath overcome us, yet among these fires,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112970">Our dead men are denied their funeral flames:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112980">And those infectious carcases do perform,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e112990">A second murder on the rest that live;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113000">And all the hope of safety that we have,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113010">Is now to fix our flattering lips at's feet:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113020">Mercy (Perhaps) may wearied slaughter meet. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e113030" who="A85334_02-sasmenos">
              <speaker>Sas.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113040">Will you do so? speak, for I am determined —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e113050" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A85334_02-e113060">
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113070">No (Worthy general) heaven avert</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113080">And arm you with the proof of better thoughts! </l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113090">What though a tyrant strives to terrify</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113100"><pb facs="81" n="157"/> all Christendom, and would not be beloved;</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113110">Let not your fears give impious rage such scope,</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113120">As for to bring religion to profaneness:</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113130">Fortune and heaven will scorn to try a man,</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113140">That hurls his weapons hence and runs away:</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113150">How is he worthy of heaven's victory,</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113160">That, when it frowns, dares not look up and see? </l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113170">Methinks we three are now environed round,</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113180">With hosts of angels, and our powerful Mars</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113190">Is putting bows of steel into our hands:</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113200">He doth suggest our wrath, and bids us on. </l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113210">O what an army 'tis to have a cause</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113220">Holy and just; there, there's our strength indeed! </l>
              </lg>
              <quote xml:id="A85334_02-e113230">
                <lg xml:id="A85334_02-e113240">
                  <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113250">— Tu mente labantes,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113260">Direge nos, dubios, et certo robore firma. </l>
                </lg>
              </quote>
              <lg xml:id="A85334_02-e113270">
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113280">If we must die, the narrow way to bliss</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113290">Shall be made wide for us: the gate's wide ope,</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113300">And the spread palace entertains with joy. </l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113310">Mean time, let's look like men upon our grief,</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113320">Our frown fate despot, Bulgaria, come. </l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113330">Turk, once more at thee (Tyrant) mortals must</l>
                <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113340">Command heavens favour in a case so just. <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e113350">Exeunt.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A85334_02-e113360">
          <head>Actus 4.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e113370">
            <head>Scaena 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e113380">Enter Aladin King of Caramania, son in law to Amurath, with nobles, ambassadors from Amurath.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e113390" who="A85334_02-aladin">
              <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113400">Sends our proud father-in-law this greeting to us?</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113410">Was our sword sheathed so soon to hear this answer? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e113420" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113430">My lord, he bade me tell you that 'twas you</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113440">Have made him leave off this great prophet's wars,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113450"><pb facs="82" n="158"/> when he was hewing down the Christians;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113460">Therefore submission should not now appease him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113470">No, though your wife, his daughter, should herself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113480">Upon her penitent knees be suppliant. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113490">No sooner shall the Tyrian splendid sol</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113500">Open heavens casements, and enlarge the day,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113510">But his horse hooves shall beat your treacherous earth;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113520">And that you may be warned of his approach,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113530">Murder and flames shall be his Prodromo's! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e113540" who="A85334_02-aladin">
              <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113550">Confederate princes, and my kind allies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113560">Shall his proud nostril's breath those threats on us? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e113570" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113580">Moreover, my lord will, or win, or raze,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113590">Iconium and Larenda. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e113600" who="A85334_02-aladin">
              <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113610">Iconium and Larenda? I? No more?</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113620">Had best look first, how safe his Prusa stands. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113630">Lords, I am moved, and will forget my Queen</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113640">Was ere the issue of his hated blood:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113650">My spleen is tossed within, mine entrails pant,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113660">As, when the sea is raised with Southern gusts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113670">The wind allayed, yet still the waves will tremble,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113680">Princes, now bind yourselves with such strong chains,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113690">Your faith and breathes can make; swear to me all,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113700">To be as firm to me 'gainst Amurath,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113710">As is the skin and flesh unto the nerves;<stage xml:id="A85334_02-e113720">They all kneel, and swear upon his sword.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e113730" who="A85334_02-nobles">
              <speaker>Nobles.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113740">We all swear we will. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e113750" who="A85334_02-aladin">
              <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113760">Then all here kiss my sword,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113770">Which shall be steeped within the hdadman's throat:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113780">We'll make him know those will not fly in war,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113790">Which may in policy entreat a peace! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113800">Hast thy course (Time) and soon reduce the year! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113810">Lucan: — infestique obvia signis</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113820">Signa, pares aquilas, et pila minantia pilis. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113830">Ensigns may ensigns meet, Carmania's King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113840">Great Aladin, scorns to avoid a Turk. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113850">Princes, and neighbours, muster up your strength,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113860"><pb facs="82" n="159"/> that we may meet him on his full career;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113870">And let it be Carmanian's pride to say,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113880">To o'ercome him we ask no second day. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e113890">
            <head>Scaena 2. Actus 4.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e113900">Enter Amurath at one door with nobles, Bajazet; enter at th'other, Hatum, richly attended, they meet, salute in dumb shows; Amurath joins the hands of the prince and Princess; whilst this is solemnising, is sung to soft music, this song following. </stage>
            <floatingText xml:id="A85334_02-e113910">
              <body xml:id="A85334_02-e113920">
                <div type="song" xml:id="A85334_02-e113930">
                  <head>Song.</head>
                  <lg xml:id="A85334_02-e113940">
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113950">Thine oh Hymen, thine is she,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113960">Whose beauty's verse Calliope,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113970">Sing to marriage ties an Io;</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e113980">Io to Hymen. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e113990" who="A85334_02-chorus">
                    <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                    <lg xml:id="A85334_02-e114000">
                      <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114010">To thee Apollo is my suit,</l>
                      <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114020">Lend me a while thy silver lute,</l>
                      <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114030">Oh what a woe it is to bring,</l>
                      <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114040">A bride to bed and never sing,</l>
                      <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114050">Io to Hymen. </l>
                    </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e114060" who="A85334_02-ambo">
                    <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
                    <lg xml:id="A85334_02-e114070">
                      <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114080">When she's old, still seems she young,</l>
                      <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114090">When she's weak, to her be strong! </l>
                      <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114100">Be Cyprus, both, and Paphos here,</l>
                      <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114110">Love, sing with merry cheer,</l>
                      <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114120">Io to Hymen. </l>
                    </lg>
                  </sp>
                </div>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e114130" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114140">You gods of marriage, sacred protectoress</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114150">Of lawful propagations, and blessed love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114160">Be most propitious to these grafted stems;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114170">Drop dewing showers of generation on them. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114180"><pb facs="83" n="160"/>Think (Son) this day so prodigal of blessing,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114190">As, that had Juno tasked thee (Like Alcides)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114200">To grapple with Stymphallides, or cleanse</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114210">Augean stables: or like the Trojan boy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114220">Sit like a shepherd on Dardania's hills,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114230">Such a reward as this fair Queen repays. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114240">O thou hoped future offspring, spare thy parent! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114250">Hurt not this tender womb, these ivory worlds,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114260">In which a pretty people yet shall live</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114270">When you are born; oh be within your limbs</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114280">The grandsire, Amurath, and father's strength;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114290">Line their faces (Nature) with their mothers die:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114300">And let the destinies make the ensuing night</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114310">In their eternal books, with notes most white. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e114320" who="A85334_02-all">
              <speaker>All.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114330">Grant it great Mahomet. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e114340" who="A85334_02-hatun">
              <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114350">Most awful father, and my honoured prince,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114360">Although it be enacted by the heavens,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114370">That in these bonds of marriage, such curse</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114380">Attends on princes above private men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114390">That no affection, nor home-nourished love</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114400">But state and policy must elect their wives,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114410">Which must be fetched from countries far remot;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114420">Yet the protecting powers have such a care,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114430">Both of their offsprings and their kingdom's state. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114440">That to what they ordain, they work in us</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114450">A sudden willingness to make's obey;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114460">For in this breast, I do already feel</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114470">That there's a kindling a diviner heat,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114480">Which disobedience never shall extinguish. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114490">And if there be any felicity</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114500">From these united loves to be derived</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114510">From the weak sex unto the husband's soul,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114520">Then may my lord make his affection sure,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114530">To be repaid with an untainted love. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114540">With soft and yielding courtesy in all</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114550">He shall command, my willing arms shall still</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114560"><pb facs="83" n="161"/> be ope t'enfold within a wife's embrace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114570">If any comfort else there be in store,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114580">(Which modesty keeps silent to itself</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114590">Cause only husbands and the night must know't)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114600">My loyalty shall ever all perform:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114610">And though my lord should frown, I'll be the same,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114620">Green wood will burn with a continued flame:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e114630" who="A85334_02-bajazet">
              <speaker>Baja.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114640">Princess, our ardour is already fired,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114650">Yet with no violent temerity;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114660">Such as might fear it's short and soon decaying:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114670">Thy virtue seems so to exceed thy sex,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114680">And wisdom so far to outpace thy years,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114690">That, surely (Princess) soon maturity,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114700">Argues in them hidden divinity. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114710">Expected Hymen here hath bound our hands</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114720">And hearts, with everlasting ligaments:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114730">Fortunate both we are, and have one bliss,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114740">The want of which for ever doth infect</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114750">With anxious cares the sweets of marriage beds:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114760">Our parents' benediction and consent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114770">They are the truest Hymens, and should be</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114780">To children the best marriage deity. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114790">Thus then attended with such sacred charms</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114800">Our last day of content shall never come;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114810">Till we must part by th'unresisted doom,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114820">With a pleased error we will age beguile,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114830">All stars on us, an equal yoke, must smile,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e114840" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114850">Now (Lords) who'll dance</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114860">A Turkish measure? Ladies our nerves are shrunk;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114870">And you now fix the sign of age on me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114880">You, who have blood still flowing in your veins,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114890">Be nimble as an hart: caper to the spheres:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114900">Oh you are light, that want the weight of years!<stage xml:id="A85334_02-e114910">Music</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e114920">Here Amurath ascends his throne, the rest set down to dance, Bajazet with Hatum, etc. the end of the dance, all kneel, Amur. begins an health, a flourish with cornets. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e114930" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <pb facs="84" n="162"/>
              <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114940">And health to our bride and her father:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114950">Oh (Nobles) would this wine were christians blood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114960">But that it would frenetic humours breed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e114970">And so infect our brains with superstition! </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e114980">Enter Eurenoses with six Christian maidens, richly attired, their hair hanging loose, in their hands cups of gold with jewels, etc.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e114990" who="A85334_02-eurenoses">
              <speaker>Eure.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115000">Auspicious fortunes to great Amurath:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115010">To open more springs to this full-tide of joy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115020">Know (Potent emperor) I from Europe bring</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115030">Six daughters of six several Kings,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115040">Whose cities we have equalled to the ground;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115050">And of their palaces did torches make,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115060">To light their souls through the black cave of death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115070" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115080">Describe (Good captain) how the dogs were wearied. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115090" who="A85334_02-eurenoses">
              <speaker>Eure.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115100">So weary were they to endure our swords,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115110">That by impetuous mutiny themselves</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115120">Turned on each other, slew their masters;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115130">Children's own hands tore out their father's throats,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115140">And each one strove who should be slaughtered first;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115150">Here did a brother pash out a brother's brains,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115160">Some in stinking quagmires, and deep lakes</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115170">(Which they had made t'avoid their excrements)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115180">Ran quick, and in the lake lay buried. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115190" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115200">Good executioner of our most just wrath! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115210" who="A85334_02-eurenoses">
              <speaker>Eur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115220">Nor did it leave till death itself was weary,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115230">Murder grew faint, and each succeeding day</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115240">Showed us the slaughter of the day before. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115250">'Mongst carcases and funerals we stood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115260">Denying those that lived such ceremonies</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115270">As in their temples to the Indian gods,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115280">With prayers and vows they daily offered:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115290">Nor destiny, nor cruelty ere left,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115300">Till they had nothing for to work upon;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115310"><pb facs="84" n="163"/> for, of so many souls that breathed of late,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115320">These six are all remain: which as a pledge</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115330">Of my best service to your majesty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115340">I here am bold to yield an offer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115350" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115360">Nor shall this present be unrecompensed;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115370">For thy true service, on thee I'll bestow</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115380">All the rich gifts, which all these Asian lords</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115390">Brought to adorn these happy nuptials;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115400">On you fair bride, great Princess, and our daughter</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115410">Do we bestow these virgins (Daughters to Kings)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115420">For your attendance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115430" who="A85334_02-hatun">
              <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115440">We are two much bound unto our princely father</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115450" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115460">No (Daughter) no, we hope thou art the spring</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115470">From whence shall flow to all the world a King. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115480">Captains and lords, tomorrow we must meet,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115490">To think of our rebellious son in law. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115500">Be this time all for comfort and delight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115510">Short wedding days make it seem long tonight . <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e115520">Exeunt omnes.</stage></l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e115530">
            <head>Scaena 3. Actus 4.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e115540">Enter Lazartis and Cobelitz, bringing the dead body of Sasmenos.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115550" who="A85334_02-lazarus">
              <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115560">Here set we down our miserable load,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115570">Oh Cobelitz, with whom is't that we fight? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115580">With Lybian lions? Or Hyrcanian bears,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115590">Which grind us daily in their ravenous teeth? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115600">The tyrant (As it were destruction's engineer)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115610">Helps nature to destroy the world's frame quickly. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115620" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115630">Alas, my lord, that needs not, every day</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115640">Is a sufficient helper to decay:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115650">Great workman, who art sparing in thy strength</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115660">To bring things to perfection: and to o'erturn</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115670">All thy best works, thou usest sudden force.</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115680"><pb facs="85" n="164"/> when man's an embryo and first conceived,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115690">How long 'tis ere he sees his native light? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115700">Then born, with expectation for his growth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115710">Tenderly nourished, carefully brought up:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115720">Grown to perfection, what a little thing</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115730">Serves to call on his sudden ruining? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115740" who="A85334_02-lazarus">
              <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115750">Come Cobelitz, 'mongst those demolished stones</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115760">We'll sit as Hecuba, at those Trojan walls:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115770">Our tears shall be false glasses to our eyes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115780">Through these we'll look, and think we yet may see</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115790">Our stately pinnacles, and strong founded holds:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115800">That which one hour can dilapidate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115810">One age can scarce repair. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115820" who="A85334_02-unassigned">
              <speaker>Col.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115830">No sir, for nothing's hard</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115840">To nature, when she means for to consume:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115850">A thousand oaks (Which time hath fixed i'th earth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115860">As monuments of lasting memory)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115870">Are in a moment turned to ashes; all</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115880">Things that rise slowly, take a sudden fall. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115890" who="A85334_02-lazarus">
              <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115900">What course now, Cobelitz? must we still be yoked</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115910">To misery, and murder? We scarce have room</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115920">Upon our bodies to receive more wounds,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115930">And must we still oppose ourselves to more? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e115940" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115950">Yes! We are ready still; a solid mind</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115960">Must not be shaked with every blast of wind. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115970">Pollux, nor Hercules, had none other art,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115980">To get them mansions in the spangled heavens</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e115990">Then a true firm resolve; th' Adriatic sea,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116000">Shall from his currents with tempestuous blasts</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116010">Be sooner moved, than virtue from its aim. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116020">Let us but think (When we so many see</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116030">Enjoying greater quiet than our themselves)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116040">How many have endured more misery;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116050">Ilion, Ilion, what a fate hadst thou? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116060">How fruitful wert thou in matter for thy foe? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116070">Thus we'll delude our grief, make ourselves glad,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116080"><pb facs="85" n="165"/> to think of miseries that others had. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e116090" who="A85334_02-lazarus">
              <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116100">Ay, (Captain) ay; they that furnish thee</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116110">With sentences of comfort, never saw,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116120">Their cities burned, their countries desolate. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116130">'Tis easy for physicians for to tell</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116140">Advice to others, when themselves are well. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e116150" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116160">Tush, tush (My lord) there's on our side we know,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116170">One that both can, and will our weak hands guide,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116180">One that will strike and thunder; giant then,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116190">Look for a dart! we must not appoint when;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116200">Meanwhile help to convey this burden hence. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116210">Turk, though thy tyranny deny us graves,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116220">Corruption will give them spite of thee:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116230">Nor do our corpse, such tombs and caverns need:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116240">For our own flesh, still our own graves do breed:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116250">And, whom the earth receives not when they die,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116260">Heaven's vault overwhelms them, so their tomb's ith' sky. <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e116270">Exeunt with a dead trunk.</stage></l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e116280">
            <head>Actus 4. Scaena 4.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e116290">Enter Aladin as flying, an arrow through his arm, wounded in his forehead, his shield stuck with darts: with him two nobles.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e116300" who="A85334_02-aladin">
              <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116310">Besieged on every side? Iconium taken? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116320">Entrenched within my foes myself must lie</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116330">Wrapped in my city's ruin. Turks come on. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e116340" who="A85334_02-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Nob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116350">Nay but my lord, mean you to meet your death?</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116360">Let's haste our flight, and trust more to our feet</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116370">Than words, or hands —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e116380" who="A85334_02-aladin">
              <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116390">Why so much of our blood</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116400">Is already spilt, as should the glittering sun</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116410">Exhale it upward, 'twould obnubulate</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116420">It's luster, else to fiery meteors turn.</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116430">Some counsel (Lords) he that's amid the sea,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116440"><pb facs="86" n="166"/> when every curled wave doth threat his death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116450">Yet trusts upon the oars of his own arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116460">And sometime the salt foam doth pity him. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116470">A wolf, or lion, that hath filled his gorge</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116480">With bloody prey, at last will lie to sleep,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116490">And the unnatural'st creatures not forget</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116500">Their love to those whom they do know their own:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116510">My wife's his daughter; since we cannot stand</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116520">His fury longer, she shall suage his wrath. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116530">The boisterous ocean when no winds oppose,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116540">Grows calm: revenge is lost, when't hath no foes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e116550" who="A85334_02-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Nob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116560">Why then (My lord) array yourself in weeds</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116570">Of a petitioner: take the Queen along,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116580">And your two children; they may move his eyes;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116590">For, desperate sores ask desperate remedies. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e116600" who="A85334_02-aladin">
              <speaker>Ala.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116610">Go (Lords) go: fetch some straight. O heavens! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116620">O fortune, they that lean on thy cracked wheel,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116630">And trust a kingdom's power, and domineer</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116640">In a walled palace, let them look on me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116650">And thee (Carmania;) greater instances</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116660">The world affords not to demonstrate</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116670">The frail estate of proudest potentates,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116680">Of sturdiest monarchies: high pinnacles</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116690">Are still invaded with the prouder winds;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116700">They must endure the threats of every blast;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116710">The tops of Caucasus and Pindus' shake</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116720">With every crack of thunder; humble vaults</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116730">Are never touched with a bolt: ambiguous wings</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116740">Hath all the state, that hovers over Kings. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e116750">Enter the 2. Nobles with a winding sheet, Aladin puts it on. </stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116760">Ay, ay, this vesture sits my misery!</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116770">This badge of poverty must now prevail,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116780">Where all my kingdom's power and strength doth fail. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116790">Why should not a prophetic soul attend</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116800">On great men's persons, and forewarn their ills? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116810"><pb facs="86" n="167"/>Raging Bootes doth doth not so turmoil</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116820">The Lybian ford, as fortune doth great hearts. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116830">Bellona and Erynnis scourge us on;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116840">Should wars and treasons cease, why our own weight</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116850">Would send us to the earth, as spreading arms</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116860">Make the huge trees in tempest for to split. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116870">For as the slaughterman to pasture goes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116880">And drags that ox home first, whose bulk is greatest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116890">The lean he still let's feed: disease takes hold</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116900">On bodies that are pampered with best fare;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116910">So doth all ruin choose the fairest marks,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116920">At which it bends, and strikes it full of shafts;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116930">Ambition made me now that eminent butt:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116940">And I that fell by mine own strength, must rise</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116950">By professed weakness; buckets full sink down,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116960">Whilst th'empty dance i'th' air and cannot drown. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116970">Come (Lords) he out of's way can never range,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e116980">Who is at furthest; worst ne'er finds ill change. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A85334_02-e116990">
          <head>Actus 5.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e117000">
            <head>Scaena 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e117010">Enter at one door Amurath, with attendants; at the other door Aladin, his wife, two children, all in white sheets, kneel down to Amurath.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e117020" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117030">Our hate must not part thus; I'll tell thee (Prince)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117040">Thou 'Hast kindled violent Aetna in our breast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117050">And such a flame is quenched with naught but blood:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117060">His blood whose hasty and rebellious blast ▪</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117070">Gave life unto the fire; should heaven threat us;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117080">Know, we dare menace it; are we not Amurath? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117090">(Whose awful name is even trembled at)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117100">So often dared by pigmy Christians;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117110">Which we will crush to air? what haughty thought</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117120">Buzzed thy presumptuous ears with such vain blasts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117130"><pb facs="87" n="168"/> to puff thee into such impetuous acts?</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117140">Or what, durst prompt thee with a thought so frail,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117150">As made thee covetous of so brave a death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117160">As this known hand should cause it? know, that throat</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117170">Shall feel it strangled with some slave brought up</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117180">To naught but for an hangman: thy last breath,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117190">Torn from thee by a hand that's worse than death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e117200" who="A85334_02-aladin">
              <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117210">Why then, I'll (Like the Roman Pompey) hide</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117220">My dying sight, scorning imperious looks</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117230">Should grace so base a stroke with sad aspect;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117240">Thus will I muffle up and choke my groans,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117250">Lest a grieved tear should quite put out the name</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117260">Of lasting courage in Carmania's fame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e117270" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117280">What? still stiff necked? Is this the truce you beg? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117290">Sprinkled before thy face those rebel brats,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117300">Shall have their brains, and their dissected limbs,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117310">Hurled for a prey to kites; for (Lords) 'tis fit</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117320">No spark of such a mountain threatening fire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117330">Be left as unextinct, lest it devour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117340">And prove more hot unto the Turkish empire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117350">Than the Promethean blaze did trouble Jove!</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117360">First sacrifice those brats. —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e117370" who="A85334_02-multiple">
              <speaker>All. wife.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117380">(Dear father) let thy fury rush on me;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117390">Within these entrails sheath thine unsatiate sword,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117400">And let this ominous, and too fruitful womb</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117410">Be torn insunder, for from thence those babes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117420">Took all their crimes; error made them guilty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117430">'Twas nature's fault, not theirs: oh if affection</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117440">Can work, than now show a true father's love;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117450">If not, appease those murdering thoughts with me:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117460">For as Jocasta pleaded with her sons</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117470">For their dear father, so to a father I</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117480">For my dear babes and husband; husband, father,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117490">Which shall I first embrace? Victorior's father,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117500">Be blunt those now sharp thoughts, lay down those threats,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117510">Unclasp that impious helmet; fix to earth</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117520"><pb facs="87" n="169"/> that monumental spear, look on thy child</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117530">With pardoning looks, not with a warrior's eye:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117540">Else shall my breast cover my husband's breast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117550">And serve as buckler to receive thy wounds. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117560">Why dost thou doubt? Fearest thou thy daughter's faith? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e117570" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117580">I fear, for after daughter's perjury,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117590">All laws of nature shall distasteful be;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117600">Nor will I trust thy children or thyself. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e117610" who="A85334_02-wife">
              <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117620">No father, 'tis I: fear you him, he you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117630">I both, but for you both, for both you war;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117640">So that 'tis best with him that's overcome. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117650">O let me kiss (Kind father) first the earth</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117660">On which you tread, then kiss mine husband's cheek. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117670">Great King embrace these babes, you are the stock</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117680">On which these grafts were planted —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e117690" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117700">True, and when sprouts do rob the tree of sap,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117710">They must be pruned. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e117720" who="A85334_02-wife">
              <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117730">Dear father, leave such harsh similitudes:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117740">By my deceased mother, (To whose womb</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117750">I was a ten months burden:) by yourself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117760">(To whom I was a pleasing infant once)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117770">Pity my husband, and these tender infants. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e117780" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117790">Yes, to have them collect a manly strength,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117800">And their first lesson that their dad shall teach them</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117810">Shall be to read my misery. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e117820" who="A85334_02-all">
              <speaker>All.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117830">Stern conqueror: but that thy daughter shows,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117840">There once dwelled good in that obdurate breast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117850">I would not spend a tear to soften thee. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117860">Thou seest my countries turned into a grave:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117870">My cities scare the sun with fiercer flames,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117880">Which turn them into ashes, and myself</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117890">So flick and carved, that my amazed blood</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117900">Knows not through which wound first to take it's way;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117910">If not on me, have mercy on my babes, —</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117920">Which, with thy mercy thou mayst turn to love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e117930" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117940">No sir, we must root out malicious seed:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117950"><pb facs="88" n="170"/> nothing sprouts faster, than an envious weed! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117960">We see a little bullock, 'mongst an herd</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117970">(Whose horns are yet scarce crept from out his front)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117980">Grows on a sudden tall, and in the field,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e117990">Frolicks so much, he makes his father yield. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118000">A little twig left budding on an elm,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118010">Ungratefully bars his mother sight from heaven! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118020">I love not future Aladins. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e118030" who="A85334_02-aladin">
              <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118040">Threat all a conqueror can, canst threat but death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118050">And I can die: but if thou wouldst have mercy! —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e118060" who="A85334_02-wife">
              <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118070">Let's see your feet, we're proud with this hands kiss! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118080">The higher those great powers have raised you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118090">Press that which lies below with gentler weight:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118100">To pardon miseries is fortune's height:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118110">Alas, these infants, these weak sinewed hands</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118120">Can be no terror to these Hector's arms! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118130">Beg (Infants) beg, and teach these tender joints</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118140">To ask for mercy; learn your lisping tongues</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118150">To give due accent to each syllable:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118160">Nothing that fortune urgeth to, is base;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118170">Put from your thoughts all memory of descent:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118180">Forget the princely titles of your fathers:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118190">If your own misery you cannot feel,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118200">Learn thus of me to weep, of me to kneel. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e118210" who="A85334_02-aladin">
              <speaker>Al.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118220">Do (Boys) and imitate your parents tears,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118230">Which I (Like Priam) shed, when he beheld,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118240">Hector thrice dragged about the Trojan walls. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118250">He that burst open the gates of Erebus,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118260">And roused the yelling monster from his den,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118270">Was conquered with a tear. Great monarch learn,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118280">To know how dear a King doth weeping earn. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e118290" who="A85334_02-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Ch. </speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118300">Good grandsire see, see how my father cries! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e118310" who="A85334_02-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Ch. </speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118320">Good mother take my napkin for your eyes! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e118330" who="A85334_02-wife">
              <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118340">(Good father) hear, hear how thy daughter prays! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118350">Thou that knowest how to use stern warriors arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118360">Learn how to use mild warriors pity too. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118370"><pb facs="88" n="171"/>Alas? Can ere these ungrown strengths repair</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118380">Their fathers battered cities? Or can these,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118390">These o'erthrown turrets? (Iconium) what small hopes</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118400">Hast thou to lean upon? If these be all? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118410">Not half so mild hath our misfortune been</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118420">That any can ere fear us: be pleased —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e118430" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118440">Rise (My dear child) as marble against rain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118450">So I at these obedient showers, melt;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118460">Thus I do raise thy husband: thus thy babes:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118470">Freely admitting you to former state. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118480">But Aladin, wake not our wrath again;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118490">"Patience grows fury that is often stirred;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118500">When conquerors wax calm, and cease to hate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118510">The conquered should not dare to reiterate. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118520">Be thou our son and friend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e118530" who="A85334_02-aladin">
              <speaker>Alad.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118540">By all the rites of Mahomet, I vow it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e118550" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118560">Then, for to seal unto you this our love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118570">Yourself shall lead a wing in Servia,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118580">In our immediate wars; we are to meet</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118590">The Christians in Cassanoe's plains with speed:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118600">Great Amurath ne'er had time to breathe himself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118610">So much as to have warring with new foes;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118620">No day securely to his sceptre shone,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118630">But one wars end, still brought another on. <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e118640">Exeunt.</stage></l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e118650">
            <head>Actus 5. Scaena 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e118660">Enter Lazarus, Cobelitz, soldiers, all armed.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e118670" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118680">Let now victorious wreathes ingirt our brows,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118690">Let angels 'Stead of soldiers wield our arms</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118700">'Gainst him, who that our cities might be his,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118710">Strives to depopulate, and make them none! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118720">But look, look in the air ( methinks ) I see</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118730">An host of soldiers brandishing their swords;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118740">Each corner of the heaven shoots thunderbolts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118750"><pb facs="89" n="172"/> to nail these impious forces to the earth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e118760" who="A85334_02-lazarus">
              <speaker>Laz.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118770">Soldiers stand to't, though fortune bandy at's,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118780">Let's stand her shocks, like sturdy rocks ith' sea,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118790">On which the angry foaming billows beat,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118800">With frivolous rush, and break themselves, not them;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118810">Stand like the undaunted countenance oth' sky,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118820">Or, like the sun, which when the foolish King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118830">Thought to obscure with a cloud of darts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118840">Out looked them all, our lives are all enchanted,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118850">And more invulnerate than Thetis son. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118860">We shall have hands and weapons: if the stone</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118870">Of fortune glide from under our weak feet,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118880">And we must fall, yet, let all Christians say,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118890">'Tis she, and not the cause, that wins the day. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118900">We must believe heaven hath a greater care</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118910">Of them, whom fortune doth so oft out dare! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e118920" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118930">Gentlemen, brothers, friends, soldiers, Christians,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118940">We have no reason to command of heaven</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118950">A thing denied to all mortality. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118960">Nor should we be so impudently proud,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118970">As in this weak condition to repute</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118980">Ourselves above the stroke of lady chance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e118990">A caution must divine it, ever fixed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119000">That whilst her checks equally fall out,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119010">Community should ease their bitterness. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119020">I could afresh now shed those princely tears,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119030">To think such sudden ruin should attend</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119040">Heroic spirits glittering in bright arms! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119050">But if the Grecian (When he heard the dreams</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119060">Disputed subtly by philosophers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119070">To prove innumerable extant worlds)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119080">Was struck with pensiveness, and wept to think</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119090">He had not yet obtained one for himself;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119100">What terror can affright a Christian's thoughts</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119110">Who knows there is a world, at liberty</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119120">To breathe in, when this glass of life is broke?</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119130"><pb facs="89" n="173"/> our foes with circling fury are entrenched;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119140">Pelions of earth and darkness shall o'erlade them,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119150">Whilst we shall mount, and these our spirits light,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119160">Shall be yet ponderous to depress them lower. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119170">Nay, my enthusiastic soul divines,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119180">That some weak hand shall from the blazing zone</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119190">Snatch lightning, which shall strike the snarling cur</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119200">With horror and amazement to the earth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119210">Which hell cannot oppose! Turk, tyrannize,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119220">Stand, yet at length to fall my sacrifice. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119230">Super Olympic vigour will (No doubt).</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119240">Squeeze all thy supercilious rancour out! <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e119250">Exeunt in a march.</stage></l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e119260">
            <head>Scaena 3. Actus 5.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e119270">The heavens seem on fire, comets and blazing stars appear, Amurath speaks. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e119280" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119290">Who set the world on fire? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119300">How now (Ye heavens) grow you</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119310">So proud, that you must needs put on curled locks,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119320">And clothe yourselves in periwigs of fire? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119330">Mahomet (Say not but I invoke thee now!)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119340">Command the Puny-christians demigod</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119350">Put out those flashing sparks, those ignes fatui,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119360">Or I'll unseat him, or with my looks so shake</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119370">The staggering props of his weak seated throne,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119380">That he shall find he shall have more to do</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119390">To quell one Amurath, than the whole giant brood</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119400">Of those same sons of earth, than ten Lycaon's. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119410">Do the poor snacks so love their misery</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119420">That they would see it by these threatening lights? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119430">Dare ye blaze still? I'll toss up buckets full</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119440">Of Christian's blood to quench you: by those hairs</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119450">Drag you beneath the centre: there put out</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119460"><pb facs="90" n="174"/> all your presaging flames in Phlegeton. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119470">Can you outbrave me with your piddling lights? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119480">Yawn earth with casements as wide as hell itself. <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e119490">Vault opens.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119500">Burn heaven as ardent as the Lemnian flames,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119510">Wake pale Tisiphon, spend all thy snakes;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119520">Be Aeacus, and Minos, as severe</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119530">As if the goal delivery of us all</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119540">Were the next sessions. I'll pull Radamanth</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119550">By his flaming furs from out his iron chair. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e119560">Whilst he is in his fury, arise four fiends, framed like Turkish Kings, but black, his supposed predecessors dance about him; to a kind of hideous noise, sing this song following.</stage>
            <floatingText xml:id="A85334_02-e119570">
              <body xml:id="A85334_02-e119580">
                <div type="song" xml:id="A85334_02-e119590">
                  <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e119600" who="A85334_02-1_fiend">
                    <speaker>1. Fiend.</speaker>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119610">Horror, dismal cries, and yells</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119620">Of these thy grandsires thee foretells,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119630">Furies sent of thee to learn</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119640">Crimes, which they could ne'er discern. </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e119650" who="A85334_02-all">
                    <speaker>All.</speaker>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119660">Furies sent, etc. </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e119670" who="A85334_02-2_fiend">
                    <speaker>2. Fiend.</speaker>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119680">O Amurath thy father's come,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119690">To warn thee of a sudden doom,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119700">Which in Cassanoe's fields attends</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119710">To bring thee to thy hellish friends. </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e119720" who="A85334_02-all">
                    <speaker>All.</speaker>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119730">Which in Cassanoes, etc. </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e119740" who="A85334_02-3_fiend">
                    <speaker>3. Fiend.</speaker>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119750">Megaera and Enyo both do stand</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119760">Trembling lest when thou art damned,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119770">Chief of furies thou shouldst be,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119780">And they their snakes resign to thee. </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e119790" who="A85334_02-all">
                    <speaker>All.</speaker>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119800">Chief of furies, etc. </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e119810" who="A85334_02-4_fiend">
                    <pb facs="90" n="175"/>
                    <speaker>4. Fiend.</speaker>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119820">Terror, we a while will leave thee,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119830">Till Cocytus' lake receive thee. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119840">Cerberus will quake for fear</l>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119850">Where he a new Turk's fate shall hear. </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e119860" who="A85334_02-all">
                    <speaker>All.</speaker>
                    <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119870">Cerberus will, etc. </l>
                  </sp>
                </div>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e119880" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119890">Now who the devil sent my grandsires hither? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119900">Had Pluto no task else to set them too? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119910">He should have bound them to Ixion's wheel,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119920">Or bid them roll the stone of Sisyphus:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119930">Beshrew me, but their singing did not please me! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119940">Have they not been so drunk with Lethe yet,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119950">As to forget me? They can portend no ill;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119960">For, should the fates be twining my last thread,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119970">Yet none durst come from hell to tell me so. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119980">Shall I be scared with a nightwalking ghost;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e119990">Or what my working fancy shall present? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120000">Why, I can look more terrible than night,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120010">And command darkness in the unwilling day:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120020">Make Hecate start, and draw back her head</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120030">To wrap it in a swarthy veil of clouds. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120040">Drop sheets of sulphur, you prodigious skies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120050">Cyclops, run all thy bullets into Aetna,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120060">Then vomit them at once; should Christians</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120070">Couch to the bottomless abyss of Styx,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120080">Or hide themselves under Avernus' shade,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120090">This arm should fetch them out. Day must perform</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120100">What I intend, wrath rains a bloody storm:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120110">And now, begins rise the sun, which yet not knows</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120120">The misery it shall see on Amurath's foes! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120130">Lords, leaders, captains —<stage xml:id="A85334_02-e120140">Enter Schahin and others.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e120150" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120160">Your highness up so soon? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e120170" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120180">He small rest takes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120190">That dreams on naught but bloody broils and death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e120200" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <pb facs="91" n="176"/>
              <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120210">Your grace seems much distempered: beds of sweat</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120220">Bedew your brows with never-wonted paleness</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e120230" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120240">Why; see you not? The heavens are turned court ladies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120250">And put on other hair besides their own:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120260">Canst guess (Learned Schahin) what these flames portend? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e120270" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120280">My lord, such things as these, we men must see,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120290">And wonder at, and yet not search the reason;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120300">Perchance unwholesome fogs exhaled by th' sun</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120310">Are set a blazing by his too near heat:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120320">But 'tis not lawful that a mortal eye</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120330">Should dare to penetrate heaven's secrecy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e120340" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120350">Doth it not bode a conquest? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e120360" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120370">Yes, 'gainst the Christians:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120380">For, unto them it bends sinister looks,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120390">And frowns upon their army more than ours. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e120400" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120410">So, so: come on, ere Phosphorus appear</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120420">Let's to't, and so prevent that sluggard sol. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120430">If we want light, we'll from our whinyards</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120440">Strike fire enough to scorch the universe;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120450">Mine armour there! <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e120460">Some go for his armour.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120470">Now (Mahomet) I implore</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120480">Thy promised aid for this auspicious day:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120490">Toss me aloft, and make me ride on clouds:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120500">If my horse fail me, those fire breathing jades,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120510">(Which the boy Phaëthon knew not how to guide)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120520">Will I pluck out from out the flaming team,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120530">And hurl myself against those condense spheres,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120540">On which I'll sit, and stay their turning orbs;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120550">The whole vertigious circle shall stand still,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120560">But to behold me: mine armour, ho! <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e120570">They bring his armour.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120580">So, help on here; now like Alcides do I girt myself</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120590">With well knit sinews, able to stagger earth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120600">And threaten nature with a second chaos:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120610">If one impetuous broil remain to come</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120620"><pb facs="91" n="177"/> in future ages, set on foot this hour. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120630">How well this weight of steel bends my strength! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120640">Methinks the gods stand quivering, and do fear</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120650">(When I am armed) another phlege●'ss near. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120660">Chiron shall see his Piadus at my feet;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120670">And I'll climb up to heaven, and pull it down</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120680">And kick the weighty burden of the world,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120690">From off the babies shoulders that supports it.</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120700">For I am safer buckled 'gainst my foe,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120710">Then sturdy Jason, who by th' enchanted charms</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120720">Medea gave, encountered unicorns,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120730">Quelled lions, struggled with fire-belching bulls,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120740">Obtained a glorious prize, a fleece. A fleece</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120750">Dipped deep in tincture of the Christ'ans blood</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120760">Shall be my spoil; nay should they hide their heads</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120770">In their god's bosom, here's a sword shall reach them. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120780">Come they shall know no place is free from wrath,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120790">When boiling blood is stirred in Amurath. <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e120800">Exeunt.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e120810">An alarm, excursions: fight within. Enter at one door a christian, at another a Turk; fight, both killed, so a new charge, the Turks kill most. Enter Lazarus, Schahin kills him. Enter Eurenoses, Cobelitz, they fight, Cobelitz faints, falls for dead. A shout within, a token of victory on the Turks side, a retreat sounded. </stage>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A85334_02-e120820">
            <head>Scaena 4. Actus 5.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e120830">Enter above Amurath, Bajazet, nobles, to see the spoil. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e120840" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120850">Here, mighty prince, take view of victory,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120860">And see the field too narrow for thy spoils. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120870">Erynnus hides her head as if afraid,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120880"><pb facs="92" n="178"/> to see a slaughter she durst never hope for. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120890">Earth hath the carcases: and denies them graves,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120900">And lets them lie and rot, and fat her womb,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120910">Scorning to be unto the slaves a tomb. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e120920" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120930">Where are become those ominous comets now? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120940">What? are those pissing candles quite extinct?</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120950">Leave their disastrous snuffs no stench behind them? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120960">'Tis something yet, that their god seeth their slaughter,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120970">Lending sulphurous meteors to behold</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120980">The blessed destruction of these parasites. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e120990">I knew the elements would first untie</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121000">The nerves of th' universe, then let me die. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e121010">Here Cobelitz riseth as awaked, amazed, leaning on his sword, stumbling o'er the dead bodies, looks towards Amurath.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121020" who="A85334_02-eurenoses">
              <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121030">See (King) here's one worm yet that dare confess</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121040">He breathes and lives, which once this hand crushed down. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121050" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121060">Ha, ha, by Mahomet, and we are weary now:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121070">Some mercy shall lay victory asleep. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121080">It will a laureate prove to this great strife,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121090">'Mongst all these murdered to give one his life,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121100">So we'll descend. <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e121110">He goeth from aloft.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121120" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121130">From what a dismal grave am I awaked,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121140">Entombed within a Golgatha of men! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121150">Have all these souls prevented me in bless,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121160">And left me in a dream of happiness? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121170">But soft! methinks he said he would descend! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121180">Then, heavens, one minutes breath, that's all I ask,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121190">And then I shall perform my life's true task. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e121200">Amurath descends on the stage, Cobelitz staggers towards him.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121210" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121220">Poor slave, wouldst live? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e121230">Here Cobelitz is come to him, seeming to kneel, stabs him with a pocket dagger.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121240" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <pb facs="92" n="179"/>
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121250">Yes Turk to see thee die. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121260">Howle, howl, grim tartar, yell (Thou grisly wolf)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121270">Force forth the blood from out thy gaping wound! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121280">Dii tibi non mortem, quae cunctis poena paratur,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121290">Said sensum post fata, tuae dent (Impie) morti. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121300" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121310">My spirit makes me not to feel thy weapon! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121320">Hold, you cracked organs, of my shattered life,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121330">I 'em not touched yet; can I not mock my death,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121340">And think 'tis but a dream tells me I 'em hurt? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121350">Darest thou then leave me (Blood?) Canst be so bold</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121360">As to forsake these veins to flow on earth? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121370">And must I, like th'unhappy roman, die</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121380">By a slave's hand? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121390" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121400">Tyrant, 'tis known</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121410">He's lord of others lives that scorns his own. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121420" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121430">I that could scarce ere sleep, can I ere die? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121440">And will none fear my life when I am dead;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121450">Tortures and torments for the murderer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121460" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121470">Ha, ha, ha! <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e121480">Leaning on his sword.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121490">I thank thee (Great omnipotent) that I</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121500">Shall here laugh out the lag end of my life! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121510" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121520">Villain, thy laugh wounds worse than did thy dagger. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121530">Are you lethargic (Lords) in cruelty? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121540" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121550">Nay, hear me (Turk) now will I prompt their rage:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121560">Lock me up in the bull of Phalaris,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121570">Cut off these eyelids, bid me then outgaze</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121580">The parching sunbeams; flea this tender skin,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121590">Set nests of hornets on my rawest flesh,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121600">Let the Siconian clouds drop brimstone on me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121610">Power boiling Lemnos on my greenest wounds,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121620">Put on my shoulder Nessus poisoned shirt,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121630">Bind all these bloody faces to my face,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121640">Rack me, Procrustes like —<stage xml:id="A85334_02-e121650">The lord that holds up Amurath offers to touch his wounds. </stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121660" who="A85334_02-amurath">
              <speaker>Amur.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121670">Hell, o! I cannot brook your smallest touch. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121680" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <pb facs="93" n="180"/>
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121690">Ha, ha! each groan is balsam to my wounds:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121700">I am perfect well. <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e121710">Bajazet offers to kill Gobelitz; a nobleman holds his hand. </stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121720" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121730">Rascal, dar'st deride us? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121740" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121750">Yea? and while your witty furies shall invent</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121760">For me some never heard of punishment;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121770">I see a guard of saints ready to take me hence. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121780">Take then free flight my new rewarded soul,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121790">And seat thee on the winged Seraphims,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121800">Hast to the empyreum, where thy welcome</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121810">Shall be an halelvia, anthemed forth</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121820">By the chorus of the angel-hierarchy. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121830">Pierce with swift plumes, the concave paths oth' moon</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121840">Where the black air enlightened is with stars. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121850">Stay not to wonder there at wand'ring signs,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121860">At bi-horned gemini, or Amphion's harp,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121870">At Arctos, or Bootes, or the bear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121880">(Which are to please wizard astrologers:)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121890">Soar higher with thy pitch, and then look down</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121900">To laugh at the hard trifles of the world;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121910">Perchance some oft have known a better life,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121920">Never did one ere leave 'It more willingly. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121930" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121940">Fear your death (Gods!) for I have lost my life,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121950">And what, I most complain, my tyranny. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e121960" who="A85334_02-cobelitz">
              <speaker>Cob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121970">Soul, to detain thee from thy wished rest!</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121980">Were but an envious part! arise, farewell:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e121990">To stay thee to accuse or fate or man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122000">Would show I were unwilling yet to leave thee. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122010">But dear companion hence: cut through the air</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122020">Let not the grossness of my earth o'er-lime</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122030">Thy speedy wings, fly without weight of crime. <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e122040">He dies.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e122050" who="A85334_02-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122060">O, now have I and fortune tried it out. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122070">With all her best of favours was I crowned</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122080">And suffered her worst threats, when most she frowned. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122090">Stay (Soul! A King, a Turk, commands thee stay. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122100"><pb facs="93" n="181"/>Sure I am but an actor, and must strive</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122110">To personate the tragic ends of Kings. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122120">And so (To win applause unto the scene)</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122130">With feigned passion thus must grasp at death. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122140">O but I see pale Nemesis at hand:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122150">Art thou dull, fate, and dost not overspread</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122160">Cimmerian wings of death throughout the world;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122170">What? Not one earthquake? One blazing comet</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122180">T'accompany my soul to his funeral? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122190">Is not this hour the general period</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122200">To never returning time! Last breath command</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122210">A new Deacalion's deluge, that with me</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122220">The world may swim to his eternal grave. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122230">Crack hinge that holds this globe, and welcome death. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122240">Wilt thou not stay soul? Friend, not stay with Kings? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122250">Sink then, and sink beneath the Thracian mount. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122260">Sink beneath Athos, be the brackish waves</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122270">Of Acheron thy tomb; I'll want a grave;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122280">So all parts fear, which first my corpse shall have;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122290">For in my grave, I'll be the Christians foe,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122300">Here like a massy pyramid I'll fall,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122310">I'll strive to sink all the whole fabric with me:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122320">Quake Pluto, for 'tis I that come</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122330">A Turk, tyrant, and a conqueror.</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122340">And with this groan, like thunder will I cleave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122350">The timorous earth, whilst thus my last I breath. <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e122360">He dies.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e122370" who="A85334_02-bajazet">
              <speaker>Bajaz.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122380">O easy powers, to give us all at first,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122390">But in their loss, they make us most accursed. <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e122400">Here all the nobles kneel to Bajazet.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e122410" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Schah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122420">The taper of your father's life is spent;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122430">We must have light still and adore a sun.</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122440">That next is rising; therefore mighty prince,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122450">Upon your shoulders must the ponderous load</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122460">Of empire rest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e122470" who="A85334_02-bajazet">
              <pb facs="94" n="182"/>
              <speaker>Bajaz.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122480">Why (Lords) we have a brother,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122490">Who, as in the same blood he took a share,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122500">So let him bear his part in government. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e122510" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Sch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122520">My lord, within the selfsame hemisphere</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122530">It's most prodigious when two suns appear. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122540">One body by one soul must be informed. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122550">Kingdom's like (Marriage beds) must not endure</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122560">Any corrival. Rome was ne'er secure</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122570">Whilst she contained a Pompey; and a Caesar. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122580">Like as one prophet we acknowledge now,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122590">So of one King in state we must allow. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122600">You know the Turkish laws, prince be not nice</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122610">To purchase kingdoms, whatsoe'er the price. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122620">He must be lopped, send for him he must die. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e122630" who="A85334_02-bajazet">
              <speaker>Bajazet.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122640">O happy Bajazet, that he was born</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122650">To be a King when thou wast counsellor. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122660">Call in our brother Jacup. <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e122670">Some go for him.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e122680">Here six men take up Amurath's trunk on their shoulders.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e122690" who="A85334_02-bajazet">
              <speaker>Baj.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122700">Why (Lords!) is Amurath so light a weight? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122710">Is this the trunk oth' Turkish emperor? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122720">O what a heap of thoughts are come to naught? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122730">What a light weight is he unto six men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122740">Who durst stand under Ossa, and sustain 't? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e122750" who="A85334_02-eurenoses">
              <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122760">My lord, these meditations fit not you:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122770">You are to take the honour he hath left,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122780">And think you of his rising, not his fall! <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e122790">Enter Jacup.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122800">Let your decree be sudden, here's your brother. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e122810" who="A85334_02-bajazet">
              <speaker>Baj.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122820">Brother, I could have wished we might have met</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122830">At times of better greeting! Our father hath</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122840">Bequeathed to the grave these ashes, to us his state. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122850">Nor have we leisure (Yet) to mourn for him. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122860">Brother, you know our state hath made a law,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122870">That, he that sits in a majestic chair,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122880"><pb facs="94" n="183"/> must not endure the next succeeding heir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e122890" who="A85334_02-jacyl">
              <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122900">Yes, we do:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122910">And, brother, do you think 'tis crime enough</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122920">To die, because I am son to an emperor? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e122930" who="A85334_02-schahin">
              <speaker>Scah.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122940">My lord, we know there breathes in him that air</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122950">Of true affection, that he doth much desire</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122960">You should be equal in his kingdom with him:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122970">But still when two great evils are proposed;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e122980">The less is to be chosen. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e122990" who="A85334_02-eurenoses">
              <speaker>Euren.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123000">My lord, your life is but one:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123010">Kings are the threads whereto there are inweaved</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123020">Millions of lives, and he that must rule all</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123030">Must still be one that is select from all. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123040">Although we speak, yet think them not our words,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123050">But what the land speaks in us! Kings are free;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123060">And must be impatient of equality. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e123070" who="A85334_02-jacyl">
              <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123080">And is't e'en so? </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123090">How have these dogs fawned on me, licked my feet</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123100">When Amurath yet lived! Felt all my thoughts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123110">And soothed them to the sight of empire! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123120">And now the first would set their politic hands</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123130">To strangle up that breath, a blast of which</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123140">Their nostrils have sucked up like perfumed air. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123150">Well brother well, by all men this is spoke,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123160">That heart that cannot bow, may yet be broke. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e123170" who="A85334_02-bajazet">
              <speaker>Bajazet.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123180">Brother, you must not now stand to upbraid;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123190">They which do fear the vulgars' murmuring tongue,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123200">Must also fear th' authority of a King;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123210">For rulers must esteem it happiness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123220">That with their government they can hate suppress:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123230">They with too faint a hand the sceptres sway,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123240">Who regard love, or what the people say:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123250">To kindred we must quite put off respect,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123260">When 't is so near it may our crown affect. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e123270" who="A85334_02-jacyl">
              <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123280">Then name of brother do I thus shake off,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123290">For 't is in vain their mercy to implore,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123300"><pb facs="95" n="184"/> when impious statists have decreed before. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123310">Yet King, although thou take my life away</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123320">See how I'll die in better state than thou! </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123330">Who like (My father) after his greatest glory</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123340">May fall by some base hand: the minister. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123350">To take my breath, shall be thyself a King. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e123360">Here Jacup takes a scarf from his arm, and putting it about his neck gives one end to Bajazet.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123370">Yet give me leave a while to prophesy. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123380">You that so puppetlike delude your hopes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123390">And wire-draw the ancestry from Kings,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123400">Thinking, that fates dare not approach your blood</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123410">Till they do seize you, than you leave this earth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123420">Not as you went, but by compulsion dragged;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123430">Still begging for a morrow from your grave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123440">And with such shifts you do deceive yourselves,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123450">As if you could deceive mortality,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123460">No (Brother King) not all the glow-worm state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123470">Which makes thee be a horseleech to thy blood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123480">Not all the parasitest 'Minions thou maintainst,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123490">Nor the restorative dishes that are found out. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123500">Not all thy shifts and tricks can cheat mortality,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123510">Or keep thee from a death that's worse than mine. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123520">Should all this fail, age would profess itself</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123530">A slow, but a sure executioner. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123540">O 'tis a hard thing well to temperate</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123550">Decaying happiness in great estate. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123560">But this example by me may you gain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123570">That at my death! not of heaven complain. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123580">Pull then, and with my fall pull on thyself</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123590">Mountains of burdenous honour, which shall curse thee. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123600">Death leads the willing by the hand</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123610">But spurs them headlong on, that dare command. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e123620">Here himself pulls one end, Bajazet the other, Jacup. dies. </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A85334_02-e123630" who="A85334_02-bajazet">
              <pb facs="95" n="185"/>
              <speaker>Bajazet.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123640">Take up this trunk; and let us first appoint</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123650">Our fathers, and our brothers funerals.</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123660">The sense less body of that caitiff slave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123670">Hurl to a ditch. Posterity shall hear</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123680">Our less ill chronicled, but time shall hear</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123690">These minutes rather, then repeat their woe. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123700">Now primacy, on thee I'll mediate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123710">Which who enjoy thee, are in blessed estate. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123720">Whose age in secure silence fleets away,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123730">Without disturbance to his funeral day;</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123740">Nor ponderous nor unquiet honours can</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123750">Vex him, but dies a primare ancient man. </l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123760">What greater powers threaten inferior men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123770">A greater power threatens him again:</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123780">And like to wasted tapers Kings must spend</l>
              <l xml:id="A85334_02-e123790">Their lives to light up others: so all end. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A85334_02-e123800">Exeunt bearing out solemnly the bodies of Amurath and Jacup.</stage>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A85334_02-e123810">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A85334_02"><item xml:id="A85334_02-amurath" n="34">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-amurath</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">34</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-schahin" n="29">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-schahin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">29</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-ambassador" n="24">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-ambassador</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">24</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A85334_02-cobelitz" n="20">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-cobelitz</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">20</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-eurenoses" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-eurenoses</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-aladin" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-aladin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-lazarus" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-lazarus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-bajazet" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-bajazet</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-eumorphe" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-eumorphe</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-all" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-menthe" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-menthe</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-jupiter" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-jupiter</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-wife" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-wife</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-alexander" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-alexander</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-bassa" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-bassa</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-juno" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-juno</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-chase_illibegge" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-chase_illibegge</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-jacyl" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-jacyl</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-xxxx_2" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-xxxx_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-yyyy_1" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-philoxenus" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-philoxenus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-sesmenos" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-sesmenos</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-cupid" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-cupid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-unassigned" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-yyyy_2" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-yyyy_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-fame" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-fame</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-lala" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-lala</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-hatun" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-hatun</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-sasmenos" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-sasmenos</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-4_fiend" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-4_fiend</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-3_fiend" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-3_fiend</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-multiple" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-multiple</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-ambo" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-ambo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-1_fiend" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-1_fiend</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-chorus" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-chorus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-xxxx_1" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-xxxx_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-2_fiend" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-2_fiend</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-soldier" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-soldier</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-servant" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-servant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A85334_02-nobles" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A85334_02-nobles</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

