<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A68114">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Tragical Reign of Selimus<date type="creation_date">1591</date></title>
        <author>Greene, Robert</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Hannah Bredar</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A68114.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The tragedy of Selimus Emperour of the Turkes. Written T.G.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2007 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">AUA3579</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 12310b</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 130(AII)</idno>
            <idno type="vid">3571</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68114</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The tragedy of Selimus Emperour of the Turkes. Written T.G.</title>
            <author>T. G., fl. 1638.</author>
            <author>Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592,</author>
            <author>Goffe, Thomas, 1591-1629.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[76] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed [by Thomas Creede, and Nicholas Okes] for Iohn Crooke and Richard Serger and are to be sold at their shop in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Grey-hound,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1638.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Selimus.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Sometimes attributed to Robert Greene. "The initials T.G. were presumably intended to suggest Thomas Goffe" (Greg), who, however, was not born until 1591.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>A reissue, with cancel title page printed by Nicholas Okes, of: The first part of the tragicall raigne of Selimus: London, 1594.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-KÛp4Ûs (-A1,K4).</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The last leaf was blank, and the first leaf blank except for signature-mark in the original issue, but they are not recorded in any extant copy of this reissue.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: The first part of the tragicall raigne of Selimus, Emperour of the Turkes.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Identified as STC 12310a on UMI microfilm reel 298.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and the Bodleian Library.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Appears at reel 298 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy) and at reel 1574 (Bodleian Library copy).</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A68114-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A68114-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A68114-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A68114-e100040"><pb facs="1"/>The tragedy of Selimus emperor of the Turks. </p>
        <p xml:id="A68114-e100050">Written T. G.</p>
        <p xml:id="A68114-e100060">London: printed for John Crooke and Richard Serger and are to be sold at their shop in Paul's churchyard at the sign of the greyhound. 1638.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A68114-e100070">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A68114-e100080">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>The first part of the most tyrannical tragedy and reign of Selimus, emperor of the Turks, and grandfather to him that now raigneth.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e100090">Enter Bajazet emperor of Turkey, Mustaffa, Cherseoly, and the janissaries. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e100100" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Bajazet.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e100110">Leave me my lords until I call you forth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e100120">For I am heavy and disconsolate. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e100130">Exeunt all but Bajazet. </stage>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e100140">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100150">So Bajazet, now thou remainest alone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100160">Unrip the thoughts that harbour in thy breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100170">And eat thee up, for arbiter here's none,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100180">That may descry the cause of thy unrest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100190">Unless these walls thy secret thoughts declare,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100200">And prince's walls they say, unfaithful are●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100210">Why that's the profit of great regiment,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100220">That all of us are subject unto fears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100230">And this vain show and glorious intent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100240">Privy suspicion on each scruple rears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100250">Ay, though on all the world we make extent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100260">From the south-pole unto the Northern bears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100270">And stretch our reign from east to western shore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100280">Yet doubt and care are with us evermore. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100290">Look how the earth clad in her summer's pride,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100300">Embroidereth her mantle gorgeously,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100310">With fragrant herbs, and flowers gaily died,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100320"><pb facs="3"/> spreading abroad her spangled tapestry:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100330">Yet under all a loathsome snake doth hide. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100340">Such is our life, under crowns, cares do lie,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100350">And fear the sceptre still attends upon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100360">O who can take delight in kingly throne</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100370">Public disorders joined with private cark,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100380">Care of our friends, and of our children dear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100390">Do toss our lives, as waves a silly bark. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100400">Though we be fearless, 'tis not without fear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100410">For hidden mischief lurketh in the dark:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100420">And storms may fall, be the day ne'er so clear. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100430">He knows not what it is to be a King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100440">That thinks a sceptre is a pleasant thing. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100450">Twice fifteen times hath fair Latona's son</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100460">Walked about the world with his great light:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100470">Since I began, would I had ne'er begun</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100480">To sway this sceptre. Many a careful night</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100490">When Cynthia in haste to bed did run. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100500">Have I with watching vexed my aged spright? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100510">Since when what dangers I have overpassed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100520">Would make a heart of adamant aghast. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100530">The Persian sophy mighty Ismaell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100540">Took the Levant clean away from me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100550">And caraguis bassa sent his force to quell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100560">Was killed himself the while his men did flee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100570">Poor Hali Bassa having once sped well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100580">And gained of him a bloody victory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100590">Was at the last slain fighting in the field,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100600">Charactering honour in his battered shield. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100610">Ramirchan the Tartarian emperor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100620">Gathering to him a number numberless,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100630">Of big-boned Tartars in a hapless hour</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100640">Encountered me, and there my chiefest bliss</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100650">Good Alemshae (Ah this remembrance sour)</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100660">Was slain the more t'augment my sad distress,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100670">In losing Alemshae poor, I lost more</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100680"><pb facs="3"/> than ever I had gained theretofore. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100690">Well may thy soul rest in her latest grave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100700">Sweet Alemshae the comfort of my days,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100710">That thou mightst live, how often did I crave? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100720">How often did I bootless prayers raise</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100730">To that high power that life first to thee gave? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100740">Trusty wast thou to me at all assays,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100750">And dearest child thy father oft hath cried,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100760">That thou hadst lived, so he himself had died. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100770">The Christian armies, oftentimes defeated</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100780">By my victorious father's valiance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100790">Have all my captains famously confronted,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100800">And cracked in two our uncontrolled lance. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100810">My strongest garrisons they have supplanted,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100820">And overwhelmed me in sad mischance:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100830">And my decrease so long wrought their increase,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100840">Till I was forced conclude a friendly peace. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100850">Now all these are but foreign damages,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100860">Taken in war whose die uncertain is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100870">But I shall have more home-born outrages,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100880">Unless my divination aims amiss:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100890">I have three sons all of unequal ages,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100900">And all in divers studies set their bliss. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100910">Corcut my eldest a philosopher,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100920">Acomat pompous, Selmi a warrior. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100930">Corcut in fair Magnesia leads his life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100940">In learning arts and Mahound's dreaded laws:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100950">Acomat loves to court it with his wife,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100960">And in a pleasant quiet ●●yes to pause:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100970">But Selmi follows wars in dismal strife,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100980">And snatcheth at my crown with greedy claws:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e100990">But he shall miss of that he aimeth at,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101000">For I reserve it for my Acomat. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101010">For Acomat? Alas it cannot be,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101020">Stern Selimus hath won my people's heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101030">The janissaries love him more than me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101040"><pb facs="4"/> and for his cause will suffer any smart. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101050">They see he is a friend to chivalry,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101060">And sooner will they from my faith depart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101070">And by strong hand Bajazet pull thee down,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101080">Then let their Selmi hop without the crown. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101090">Ah, if the soldiers overrule thy state,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101100">And nothing must be done without their will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101110">If every base and upstart runagate</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101120">Shall cross a prince and overthwart him still. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101130">If Corcut, Selimus, and Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101140">With crowns and kingdoms shall their hungers fill? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101150">Poor Bajazet what then remains to thee? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101160">But the bare title of thy dignity. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101170">Ay, and unless thou do dissemble all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101180">And wink at Selimus aspiring thought:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101190">The bassas cruelly shall work thy fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101200">And then thy empire is but dear bought. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101210">Ah that our sons thus to ambition thrall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101220">Should set the law of nature all at naught. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101230">But what must be, cannot choose but be done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101240">Come bassas enter, Bajazet hath done. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e101250">Enters again.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e101260" who="A68114-cherseoli">
          <speaker>Cherseoli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e101270">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101280">Dread emperor, long may you happy live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101290">Loved of your subjects, and feared of your foes:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101300">We wonder much what doth your highness grieve,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101310">That you will not unto your lords disclose. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101320">Perhaps you fear lest we your loyal peers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101330">Would prove disloyal to your majesty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101340">And be rebellious in your dying years. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101350">But mighty prince the heavens can testify,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101360">How dear we esteem your safety. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e101370" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Mustaf.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e101380">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101390">Perhaps you think Mustaffa will revoke</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101400">And leave your grace, and cleave to Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101410">But sooner shall th'almighty's thunderbolt</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101420">Strike me down to the cau● tenebrious</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101430">The lowest land, and damned spirits ho●t</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101440"><pb facs="4"/> then true Mustaffa prove so treacherous:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101450">Your majesty then needs not much to fear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101460">Since you are loved of subject, prince, and peer. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101470">First shall the sun rise from the occident,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101480">And lose his steeds benighted in the East,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101490">First shall the sea become the continent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101500">Ere we forsake our sovereign's behest:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101510">We fought not for you 'gainst persians' tent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101520">Breaking our lances on his sturdy crest. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101530">We fought not for you 'gainst the Christian host,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101540">To become traitors after all our cost. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e101550" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Ba●a.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e101560">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101570">Hear me Mustaffa and Cherseoli,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101580">I am a father of a headstrong brood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101590">Which if I look not closely to myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101600">Will seek to ruinate their father's state,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101610">Even as the vipers in great Nero's fen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101620">Eat up the belly that first nourished them. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101630">You see the harvest of my life is past,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101640">And aged winter hath besprent my head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101650">With a hoar frost of silver coloured hairs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101660">The harbingers of honourable eld,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101670">These branchlike veins which once did guide my arms</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101680">To toss the spear in battailous array,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101690">Now withered up● have lost their former strength:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101700">My sons whom now ambition begins to prick,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101710">May take occasion of my weakened age,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101720">And rise in rebel arms against my state. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101730">But stay, here comes a messenger to us. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e101740">Sound within. Enters a messenger.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e101750" who="A68114-messenger">
          <speaker>Messe●.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e101760">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101770">Health and good hap to Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101780">The great commander of all Asia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101790">Selmi the soldan of great Trebizond,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101800">Sends me unto your grace, to signify</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101810">His alliance with the King of Tartary. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e101820" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Ba●a.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e101830">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101840">Said I not lords as much to you before,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101850">That mine own sons would seek my overthrow? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101860"><pb facs="5"/>And see here comes a luckless messenger</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101870">To prove that true which my mind did foretell. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101880">Does Selim make so small account of us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101890">That he dare marry without our consent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101900">And to that devil too of Tartary? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101910">And could he then unkind, so soon forget</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101920">The injuries that Ramir did to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101930">Thus to consort himself with him 'gainst me? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e101940" who="A68114-cherseoli">
          <speaker>Cher e</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e101950">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101960">Your majesty misconstrues Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101970">It cannot be, that he in whose high thoughts</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101980">A map of many valures is enshrined,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e101990">Should seek his father's ruin and decay. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102000">Selimus is a prince of forward hope,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102010">Whose only name affrights your enemies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102020">It cannot be he should prove false to you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e102030" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e102040">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102050">Can it not be? O yes Cherseoli,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102060">For Selimus hands do itch to have the crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102070">And he will have it, or else pull me down. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102080">Is he a prince? ah no he is a sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102090">Into which run naught but ambitious reaches,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102100">Seditious complots, murder, fraud and hate. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102110">Could he not let his father know his mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102120">But match himself when I least thought on it▪</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e102130" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e102140">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102150">Perhaps my lord Selimus loved the dame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102160">And feared to certify you of his love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102170">Because her father was your enemy. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e102180" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e102190">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102200">In love Mustaffa, Selimus in love? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102210">If he be, lording 'tis not lady's love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102220">But love of rule, and kingly sovereignty. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102230">For wherefore should he fear t'ask my consent</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102240">True Mustaffa, if he had feared me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102250">He never would have loved mine enemy. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102260">But this his marriage with the Tartars daughter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102270">Is but the prologue to his cruelty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102280">And quickly shall we have the tragedy. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102290">Which though he act with meditated bravery,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102300"><pb facs="5"/> the world will never give him plaudite. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102310">What yet more news? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e102320">Sound within. Enters another messenger.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e102330" who="A68114-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e102340">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102350">Dread emperor, Selimus is at hand. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102360">Two hundreth thousand strong Tartarians</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102370">Armed at all points does he lead with him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102380">Besides his followers from Trebisond. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e102390" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e102400">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102410">I thought so much of wicked Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102420">O forlorn hopes and hapless Bajazet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102430">Is duty then exiled from his breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102440">Which nature hath inscribed with golden pen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102450">Deep in the hearts of honourable men? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102460">Ah Selim, Selim , wert thou not my son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102470">But some strange unacquainted foreigner,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102480">Whom I should honour as I honoured thee:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102490">Yet would it grieve me even unto the death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102500">If he should deal as thou hast dealt with me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102510">And thou my son to whom I freely gave</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102520">The mighty empire of great Trebisond,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102530">Art too unnatural to requite me thus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102540">Good alemshae hadst thou lived till this day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102550">Thou wouldst have blushed at thy brother's mind</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102560">Come sweet Mustaffa, come Cherseoli</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102570">And with some good advice recomfort me. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e102580">Exeunt. All.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e102590">Enter Selimus, Sinam bassa, Otrante, Cochialie, and the soldiers. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e102600" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e102610">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102620">Now Selimus consider who thou art,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102630">Long hast thou marched in disguised attire</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102640">But now unmask thyself and play thy part,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102650">And manifest the heat of thy desire:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102660">Nourish the coals of thine ambitious fire●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102670">And think that then thy empire is most sure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102680">When men for fear thy tyranny endure</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102690">Think that to thee there is no worse Reproach,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102700"><pb facs="6"/> then filial duty in so high a place,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102710">Thou oughtst to set barrels of blood abroach,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102720">And seek with sword whole kingdoms to displace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102730">Let Mahound's laws be locked up in their case. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102740">And meaner men and of a base spirit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102750">In virtuous actions seek for glorious merit. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102760">I count it sacrilege for to be holy</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102770">Or reverence this threadbare name of good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102780">Leave to old men and babes that kind of folly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102790">Count it of equal value with the mud:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102800">Make thou a passage for thy gushing flood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102810">By slaughter, treason, or what else thou can,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102820">And scorn religion, it disgraces man. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102830">My father Bajazet is weak and old,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102840">And hath not much above two years to live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102850">The Turkish crown of pearl and Ophir gold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102860">He means to his dear Acomat to give. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102870">But ere his ship can to her haven drive,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102880">I'll send abroad my tempests in such sort,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102890">That she shall sink before she get the port. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102900">Alas, alas, his highness aged head</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102910">Is not sufficient to support a crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102920">Than Selimus take thou it in his lead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102930">And if at this thy boldness he dare frown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102940">Or but resist thy will, then pull him down:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102950">For since he hath so short a time t'enjoy it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102960">I'll make it shorter, or I will destroy him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102970">Nor pass I what our holy votaries</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102980">Shall here object against my forward mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e102990">I wreak not of their foolish ceremonies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103000">But mean to take my fortune as I find,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103010">Wisdom commands to follow tide and wind:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103020">And catch the front of swift occasion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103030">Before she be too quickly overgone:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103040">Some man will say I am too impious,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103050">Thus to lay siege against my father's life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103060"><pb facs="6"/> and that I ought to follow virtuous</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103070">And godly sons that virtue is a glass</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103080">Wherein I may my errant life behold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103090">And frame myself by it in ancient mould. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103100">Good sir, your wisdoms overflowing wit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103110">Digs deepe with learning's wonder-working spade</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103120">Perhaps you think that now forsooth you sit</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103130">With some grave wizard in a prattling shade. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103140">Avant such glasses: let them view in me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103150">The perfect picture of right tyranny. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103160">I like a lion's look not worth a leek,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103170">When every dog deprives him of his prey:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103180">These honest terms are far enough to seek. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103190">When angry fortune menaceth decay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103200">My resolution treads a nearer way. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103210">Give me the heart conspiring with the hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103220">In such a cause my father to withstand. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103230">Is he my father? why I am his son▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103240">I owe no more to him then he to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103250">I● he proceed as he hath now begun,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103260">And pass from me the Turkish signiory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103270">To acomat, than Selimus is free:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103280">And if he injure me that am his son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103290">Faith all the love twixt him and me is done. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103300">But for I see the schoolmen are prepared,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103310">To plant 'gainst me their bookish ordinance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103320">I mean to stand on a sententious guard:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103330">And without any far fetched circumstance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103340">Quickly unfold mine own opinion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103350">To arm my heart with irreligion. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103360">When first this circled round● this building fair,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103370">Some God took out of the confused ma●●e,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103380">(What God I do not know, nor greatly care)</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103390">Then every man of his own dition was,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103400">And every one his life in peace did pass. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103410">War was not then, and riches were not known,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103420"><pb facs="7"/> and no man said this● or this is mine own,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103430">The ploughman with a furrow did not mark</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103440">How far his great possessions did reach:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103450">The earth knew not the share, nor seas the bark. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103460">The soldiers entered not the battered breach,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103470">Nor trumpets the tantara loud did teach●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103480">There needed them no judge nor yet no law,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103490">Nor any King of whom to stand in awe. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103500">But after Ninus, warlike ●●lus son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103510">The earth with unknown armour did warray,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103520">Then first the sacred name of King begun:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103530">And things that were as common as the day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103540">Did then to set possessors first obey. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103550">Then they established laws and holy rites</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103560">To maintain peace, and govern bloody fights. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103570">Then some sage man, above the vulgar wise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103580">Knowing that laws could not in quiet dwell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103590">Unless they were observed did first devise</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103600">The names of gods, religion heaven and hell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103610">And 'gan of pains, and feigned rewards to tell. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103620">Pains for those men which did neglect the law,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103630">Rewards, for those that lived in quiet awe. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103640">Whereas indeed they were mere fictions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103650">And if they were not Selim thinks they were:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103660">And these religions observations,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103670">Only bugbears to keep the world in fear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103680">And make men quietly a yoke to bear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103690">So that religion of itself a babble,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103700">Was only found to make us peaceable</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103710">Hence in especial come the foolish namest</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103720">Of father, mother, brother and such like:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103730">For who so well his cogitation frames,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103740">Shall find they serve but only for to strike</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103750">Into our minds a certain kind of love. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103760">For these names too 〈…〉 policy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103770">To keepe the quiet of society</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103780"><pb facs="7"/> indeed I must confess they are not bad,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103790">Because they keep the baser sort in fear? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103800">But we, whose mind in heavenly thoughts is clad,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103810">Whose body doth a glorious spirit bear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103820">That hath no bounds, but flieth everywhere . </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103830">Why should we seek to make that soul a slave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103840">To which dame nature so large freedom gave. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103850">Amongst us men, there is some difference,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103860">Of actions termed by us good or ill:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103870">As he that doth his father recompense,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103880">Differs from him that doth his father kill. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103890">And yet I think think other what they will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103900">That parricides, when death hath given them rest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103910">Shall have as good a part as the rest. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103920">And that's just nothing, for as I suppose</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103930">In deaths void kingdom reigns eternal night:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103940">Secure of evil, and secure of foes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103950">Where nothing doth the wicked man affright,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103960">No more than him that dies in doing right. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103970">Then since in death nothing shall to us fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103980">Here while I live, I'll have a snatch at all. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e103990">And that can never, never be attained,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104000">Unless old Bajazet do die the death:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104010">For long enough the graybeard now hath reigned,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104020">And lived at ease, while others lived uneath. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104030">And now its time he should resign his breath. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104040">'Twere good for him if he were pressed out,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104050">'Twould bring him rest, and rid him of his gout. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104060">Resolved to do it, cast to compass it</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104070">Without delay or long procrastination:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104080">It argueth an unmanured wit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104090">When all is ready for so strong invasion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104100">To draw out time, an unlooked for mutation</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104110">May soon prevent us if we do delay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104120">Quick speed is good, where wisdom leads the way. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e104130" who="A68114-occhiali">
          <pb facs="8"/>
          <speaker>Occhi.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e104140">My lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e104150" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e104160">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104170">Lo fly boy to my father Bajazet</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104180">And tell him Selim his obedient son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104190">Desires to speak with him and kiss his hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104200">Tell him I long to see his gracious face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104210">And that I come with all my chivalry,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104220">To chase the Christians from his signory</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104230">In any wise say I must speak with him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104240">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e104250">Exit Occhiali.</stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104260">Now Sinam if I speed. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e104270" who="A68114-sinam">
          <speaker>Sinam.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e104280">What then my lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e104290" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>S●l.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e104300">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104310">What then? why Sinam thou art nothing worth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104320">I will endeavour to persuade him man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104330">To give the empire over unto me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104340">Perhaps I shall attain it at his hands:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104350">If I cannot, this right hand is resolved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104360">To end the period with a fatal stab. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e104370" who="A68114-sinam">
          <speaker>Sin.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e104380">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104390">My gracious lord give Sinam leave to speak,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104400">If you resolve to work your father's death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104410">You venture life: think you the janissaries</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104420">Will suffer you to kill him in their sight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104430">And let you pass free without punishment? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e104440" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e104450">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104460">If I resolve? as sure as heaven is heaven,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104470">I mean to see him dead, or myself King:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104480">As for the bassas they are all my friends,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104490">And I am sure would pawn their dearest blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104500">That Selim might be emperor of Turks. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e104510" who="A68114-sinam">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e104520">Yet Acomat and Corcut both survive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e104530">To be revenged for their father's death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e104540" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e104550">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104560">Sinam if they or twenty such as they,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104570">Had twenty several armies in the field,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104580">If Selimus were once your emperor</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104590">I'd dart abroad the thunderbolts of war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104600">And mow their heartless squadrons to the ground. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e104610" who="A68114-sinam">
          <speaker>Sin.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e104620">O yet my lord after your highness' death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e104630">There is a hell and a revenging God. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e104640" who="A68114-selimus">
          <pb facs="8"/>
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e104650">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104660">Tush Sinam these are school conditions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104670">To fear the devil or his cursed dam:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104680">Thinkst thou I care for apparitions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104690">Of Sisyphus and of his backward stone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104700">And poor Ixion's lamentable moan? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104710">Now I think the cave of damned ghosts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104720">Is but a tale to terrify young babes:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104730">Like devils faces scored on painted posts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104740">Or feigned circles in our astrolabes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104750">Why theirs no difference when we are dead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104760">And death once come, than all alike are sped. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104770">Or if there were, as I can scarce believe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104780">A heaven of joy, and hell of endless pain:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104790">Yet by my soul it never should me grieve:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104800">So I might on the Turkish empire reign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104810">To enter hell, and lean on fair heaven's gain. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104820">An empire Sinam, is so sweet a thing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104830">As I could be a devil to be a King. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104840">But go we lords and solace in our camp,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104850">Till the return of young Occhiali,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104860">And if his answer be to thy desire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104870">Selim thy mind in kingly thoughts attire. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e104880">Exeunt. All.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e104890">Enter Bajazet, Mustaffa, Cherseoli, Occhiali, and the janissaries.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e104900" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e104910">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104920">Even as the great Egyptian crocodile,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104930">Wanting his prey, with artificial tears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104940">And ●ained plaints his subtle tongue doth file,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104950">T'entrap the silly wand'ring traveller,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104960">And move him to advance his footing near,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104970">That when he is in danger of his claws,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104980">He may devour him with his famished jaws,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e104990">So playeth crafty Selimus with me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105000">His haughty thoughts still wait on diadems,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105010">And not a step but treads to majesty. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105020"><pb facs="9"/>The phoenix gazeth on the sun's bright beams,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105030">The echinaeis swims against the streams. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105040">Naught but the Turkish scepter can him please,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105050">And there I know lieth his chief disease. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105060">He sends his messenger to crave access,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105070">And says he longs to kiss my aged hands▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105080">But howsoever he in show profess,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105090">His meaning with his words but weakly stands. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105100">And sooner will the Syrteis boiling sands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105110">Become a quiet road for fleeting ships,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105120">Than Selimus' heart agree with Selim's lips</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105130">Too well I know the crocodiles feigned tears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105140">Are but nets wherein to catch his prey:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105150">Which who so moved with foolish pity hears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105160">Will be the author of his own decay</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105170">Then hie thee Bajazet from hence away:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105180">A fawning monster is false Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105190">Whose fairest words are most pernicious. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105200">Young man, would Selim come and speak with us▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105210">What is his message to us, canst thou tell? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e105220" who="A68114-occhiali">
          <speaker>Occhi.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e105230">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105240">He craves my lord, another signiory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105250">Nearer to you and to the Christians,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105260">That he may make them know, that Selimus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105270">Is born to be a scourge unto them all. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e105280" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e105290">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105300">He's born to be a scourge to me and mine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105310">He never would have come with such an host,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105320">Unless he meant my state to undermine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105330">What though in word he bravely seem to boast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105340">The foraging of all the Christian coast? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105350">Yet we have cause to fear when burning brands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105360">Are vainly given into a mad man's hands. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105370">Well I must seem to wink at his desire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105380">Although I see it plainer than the light,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105390">My lenity adds fuel to his fire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105400">Which now begins to break in flashing brights</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105410">Then Bajazet chastise his stubborn spright. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105420"><pb facs="9"/>Lest these small sparkles grow to such a flame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105430">As shall consume thee and thy house's name. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105440">A lass I spare when all my store is gone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105450">And thrust my sickle where the corn is reaped,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105460">In vain I send for the physician,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105470">When on the patient is his grave dust heaped. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105480">In vain, now all his veins in venom steeped</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105490">Break out in blisters that will poison us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105500">We seek to give him an Antidotus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105510">He that will stop the brook, must then begin</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105520">When summer's heat hath dried up his spring,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105530">And when his pittering streams are low and thin●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105540">For let the winter aid unto him bring,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105550">He grows to be of watery floods the King. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105560">And though you dam him up with lofty ranks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105570">Yet will he quickly overflow his banks. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105580">Messenger, go and tell young Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105590">We give to him all great Samandria,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105600">Bordering on Belgrade of Hungaria,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105610">Where he may plague those Christian runnages,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105620">And salve the wounds that they have given our states,</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e105630" who="A68114-cherseoli">
          <speaker>Cherseo.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e105640">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105650">Go and provide a gift,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105660">A royal present for my Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105670">And tell him messenger another time</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105680">He shall have talk enough with Bajazet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105690">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e105700">Exeunt Cherseoli and Occhiali.</stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105710">And now what counsel gives Mustaffa to us? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105720">I fear this hasty reckoning will undo us. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e105730" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e105740">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105750">Make haste my lord from Andrinople walls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105760">And let us fly to fair Byzantium,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105770">Lest if your son before you take the town,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105780">He may with little labour win the crown. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e105790" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e105800">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105810">Then do so good Mustaffa, call our guard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105820">And gather all our warlike janissaries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105830">Our chiefest aid is swift celerity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105840">Then let our winged coursers tread the wind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105850"><pb facs="10"/> and leave rebellious Selimus behind. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e105860">Exeunt. A●●.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e105870">Enter Selimus, Sinam, Occhiali, Ottrante, and their soldiers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e105880" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Selim.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e105890">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105900">And is his answer so Occhiali? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105910">Is Selim such a corrosive to his heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105920">That he cannot endure the sight of him? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105930">Forsooth he gives thee all Samandria,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105940">From whence our mighty emperor Mahomet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105950">Was driven to his country back with shame. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105960">No doubt thy father loves thee Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105970">To make thee regent of so great a land,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105980">Which is not yet his own: or if it were,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e105990">What dangers wait on him that should it steer. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106000">Here the Polonian he comes hurtling in,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106010">Under the conduct of some foreign prince,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106020">To fight in honour of his crucifix! </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106030">Here the Hungarian with his bloody cross,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106040">Deals blows about to win Belgrade again. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106050">And after all, forsooth Basilius</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106060">The mighty emperor of Russia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106070">Sends in his troops of slave-born Muscovites,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106080">And he will share with us, or else take all. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106090">In giving such a land so full of strife,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106100">His meaning is to rid me of my life. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106110">Now by the dreaded name of termagant,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106120">And by the blackest brook in loathsome hell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106130">Since he is so unnatural to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106140">I will prove as unnatural as he. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106150">Thinks he to stop my mouth with gold or pearl? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106160">Or rusty jades ●et from Barbaria? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106170">No let his minion his philosopher,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106180">Corcut and Acomat be enriched with them. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106190">I will not take my rest, till this right hand</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106200">Hath pulled the crown from off his coward's head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106210"><pb facs="10"/> and on the ground his bastard's gore-blood shed:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106220">Nor shall his flight to old Byzantium,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106230">Dismay my thoughts which never learned to stoop. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106240">March Sinam, march in order after him:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106250">Were his light steeds as swift as Pegasus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106260">And trodden the airy pavement with their heels,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106270">Yet Selimus would overtake them soon. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106280">And though the heavens do ne'er so crossly frown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106290">In spite of heaven shall Selim wear the crown. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e106300">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e106310">Alarum within. Enter Bajazet, Mustaffa, Cherseoli and the janissaries, at one door. Selimus, Sinam, Ottrante, Occhiali, and their soldiers at another.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e106320" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e106330">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106340">Is this thy duty son unto thy father,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106350">So impiously to level at his life? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106360">Can thy soul wallowing in ambitious mire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106370">Seek for to reave that breast with bloody knife,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106380">From whence thou hadst thy being Selimus? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106390">Was this the end for which thou joind'st thyself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106400">With that mischievous traitor Ramirchan? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106410">Was this thy drift to speak with Bajazet? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106420">Well hoped I (But hope I see is vain)</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106430">Thou wouldst have been a comfort to mine age,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106440">A scourge and terror to mine enemies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106450">That this thy coming with so great an host,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106460">Was for no other purpose and intent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106470">Then for to chastise those base Christians</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106480">Which spoil my subjects wealth with fire and sword</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106490">Well hoped I the rule of Trebisond,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106500">Would have increased the valour of thy mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106510">To turn thy strength upon thy Persians. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106520">But thou like to a crafty Polipus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106530">Dost turn thy hungry jaws upon thyself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106540">For what am I Selimus but thyself? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106550"><pb facs="11"/>When courage first crept in thy manly breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106560">And thou beganst to rule the martial sword,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106570">How oft said thou the sun should change his course,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106580">Water should turn to earth, and earth to heaven</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106590">Ere thou wouldst prove disloyal to thy father. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106600">O Titan turn thy breathless courser's back,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106610">And enterprise thy journey from the East</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106620">Blush Selim that the world should say of thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106630">That by my death thou gain'st the empery. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e106640" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e106650">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106660">Now let my cause be pleaded Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106670">For father I disdain to call thee now:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106680">I took not arms to seize upon thy crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106690">For that if once thou hadst been laid in grave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106700">Should sit upon the head of Selimus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106710">In spite of Corcut and Acomat. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106720">I took not arms to take away thy life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106730">The remnant of thy days is but a span,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106740">And foolish had I been to enterprise</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106750">That which the gout and death would do for me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106760">I took not arms to shed my brother's blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106770">Because they stop my passage to the crown. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106780">For while thou liv'st Selimus is content</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106790">That they should live, but when thou once art dead</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106800">Which of them both dares Selimus withstand? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106810">I soon should hew their bodies in piecemeal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106820">As easy as a man would kill a gnat. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106830">But I took arms unkind to honour thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106840">And win again the fame that thou hast lost. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106850">And thou thoughtst scorn Selim should speak with thee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106860">But had it been your darling Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106870">You would have met him half the way yourself . </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106880">I am a prince, and though your younger son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106890">Yet are my merits better than both theirs:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106900">But you do seek to disinherit me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106910">And mean t'invest Acomat with your crown. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106920">So he shall have a prince's due reward,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106930"><pb facs="11"/> that cannot show a scar received in field,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106940">We that have fought with mighty Prester John,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106950">And stripped th' Egyptian soldan of his camp,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106960">Venturing life and living to honor thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106970">For that same cause shall now dishonoured be. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106980">Art thou a father? Nay ●al●e Bajazet</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e106990">Disclaim the title which thou dost not merit. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107000">A father would not thus flee from his son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107010">As thou dost fly from loyal Selimus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107020">A father would not injure thus his son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107030">As thou dost injure loyal Selimus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107040">Then Bajazet prepare thee to the fight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107050">Selimus once thy son, but now thy foe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107060">Will make his fortunes by the sword,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107070">And since thou fearest as long as I do live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107080">I'll also fear, as long as thou dost live. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e107090">Exeunt Selim and his company.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e107100" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e107110">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107120">My heart is overwhelmed with fear and grief,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107130">What dismal comet blazed at my birth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107140">Whose influence makes my strong unbridled sons</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107150">In steed of love to render hate to me? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107160">Ah bassas if that ever heretofore</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107170">Your emperor ought his safety unto you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107180">Defend me now 'gainst my unnatural son:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107190">Non timeo mortem: mortis mihi displicet author. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e107200">Exit Bajazet and his company. </stage>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e107210">Alarum, Mustaffa beat Selimus in, then Ottrante and Cherseoli enter at divers doors.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e107220" who="A68114-cherseoli">
          <speaker>Cherse.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e107230">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107240">Yield thee Tartarian or thou shalt die,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107250">Upon my sword's sharp point standeth pale death</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107260">Ready to rive in two thy caitiff breast. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e107270" who="A68114-ottrante">
          <speaker>Ott.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e107280">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107290">Art thou that knight that like a lion fierce,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107300">Tiring his stomach on a flock of lambs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107310">Hast broke our ranks and put them clean to flight? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e107320" who="A68114-cherseoli">
          <pb facs="12"/>
          <speaker>Cherse.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e107330">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107340">I and unless thou look unto thyself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107350">This sword never drunk in the Tartarian blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107360">Shall make thy carcase as the outcast dung. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e107370" who="A68114-ottrante">
          <speaker>Ottran.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e107380">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107390">Nay I have matched a braver knight than you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107400">Strong Alemshae thy master's eldest son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107410">Leaving his body naked on the plains,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107420">And Turk, the selfsame end for thee remains. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107430">They fight. He killeth Cherseoli, and flieth. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e107440">Alarum, enter Selimus. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e107450" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Selim.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e107460">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107470">Shall Selim's hope be buried in the dust? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107480">And Bajazet triumph over his fall? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107490">Then o thou blindful mistress of mishap,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107500">Chief patroness of Rhamus' golden gates,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107510">I will advance my strong revenging hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107520">And pluck thee from thy everturning wheel. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107530">Mars, or Minerva, Mahound, termagant,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107540">Or whosoe'er you are that fight 'gainst me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107550">Come and but show yourselves before my face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107560">And I will rend you all like trembling reeds. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107570">Well Bajazet though fortune smile on thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107580">And deck thy camp with glorious victory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107590">Though Selimus now conquered by thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107600">Is fain to put his safety in swift flight:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107610">Yet so he flies, that like an angry ram,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107620">He'll turn more fiercely than before he came. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e107630">Exit Selimus.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e107640">Enter Bajazet, Mustaffa, the sould●er with the body of Cherseoli, and Ottrante prisoner.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e107650" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e107660">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107670">Thus have we gained a bloody victory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107680">And though we are the masters of the field,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107690">Yet have we ●o●t more than our enemies:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107700">Ah luckless fault of my Cherseoli,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107710">As dear and dearer wert thou unto me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107720">Than any of my sons, then mine own self. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107730">When I was glad, thy heart was full of joy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107740"><pb facs="12"/> and bravely hast thou died for Bajazet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107750">And though thy bloodless body here do lie,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107760">Yet thy sweet soul in heaven for ever blessed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107770">Among the stars enjoys eternal rest. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107780">What art thou warlike man of Tartary,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107790">Whose hap it is to be our prisoner? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e107800" who="A68114-ottrante">
          <speaker>Ottran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e107810">I am a prince, Ottrante is my name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e107820">Chief captain of the Tartars mighty host. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e107830" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e107840">Ottrante? Wast not thou that slew my son? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e107850" who="A68114-ottrante">
          <speaker>Ottran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e107860">Ay, and if fortune had but favoured me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e107870">Had sent the ●ire to keep him company. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e107880" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e107890">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107900">Off with his head and spoil him of his arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107910">And leave his body for the airy birds. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107920">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e107930">Exit one with Ottrante. </stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107940">The unrevenged ghost of Alemshae,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107950">Shall now no more wander on Stygian banks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107960">But rest in quiet in th' Elysian fields. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107970">Mustaffa, and you worthy men at arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107980">That left not Bajazet in greatest need,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e107990">When we arrive at Constantine's great Tour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108000">You shall be honoured of your emperor. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e108010">Exeunt all.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e108020">Enter Acomat visir, Regan, and a band of soldiers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e108030" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e108040">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108050">Perhaps you wonder why prince Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108060">Delighting heretofore in foolish love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108070">Hath changed his quiet to a soldier's state:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108080">And turned the dulcet tunes of Hymen's song,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108090">Into Bellona's horrible outcries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108100">You think it strange, that whereas I have lived,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108110">Almost a votary to wantonness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108120">To see me low lay off effeminate robes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108130">And arm my body in an iron wall. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108140">I have enjoyed quiet long enough,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108150">And surfeited with pleasures suq●●d●●e</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108160">A field of dainties I have passed through,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108170"><pb facs="13"/> and been a champion to fair Cytheree. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108180">Now since this idle peace hath wearied me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108190">I'll follow Mars and war another while,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108200">And die my shield in dolorous vermeil. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108210">My brother Selim through his manly deeds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108220">Hath lifted up his fame unto the skies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108230">While we like earth worms lurking in the weeds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108240">Do live inglorious in all men's eyes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108250">What lets me then from this vain slumber rise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108260">And by strong hand achieve eternal glory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108270">That may be talked of in all memory? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108280">And see how fortune favours mine intent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108290">Heard you not lordings, how prince Selimus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108300">Against our royal father armed went,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108310">And how the janissaries made him flee</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108320">To Ramir emperor of Tartary? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108330">This his rebellion greatly profits me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108340">For I shall sooner win my father's mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108350">To yield me up the Turkish empire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108360">Which if I have, I am sure I shall find</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108370">Strong enemies to pull me down again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108380">That fain would have prince Selimus to reign. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108390">Then civil discord, and contentious war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108400">Will follow Acomat's coronation. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108410">Selim no doubt will broach seditious jar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108420">And Corcut too will seek for alteration,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108430">Now to prevent all sudden perturbation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108440">We thought it good to muster up our powers</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108450">That danger may not take it unprovided. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e108460" who="A68114-visir">
          <speaker>Visir.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e108470">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108480">I like your highness' resolution well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108490">For these should be the chief arts of a King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108500">To punish those that furiously rebel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108510">And honour those that sacred counsel bring,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108520">To make good laws, ill customs to expel:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108530">To nourish peace from whence your riches spring,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108540">And when good quarrels call you to the field,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108550"><pb facs="13"/> t'excel your men in handling spear and shield. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108560">Thus shall the glory of your matchless name,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108570">Be registered up in immortal lines:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108580">Whereas that prince that follows lustful game</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108590">And to fond toys his captive mind inclines,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108600">Shall never pass the temple of true fame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108610">Whose worth is greater than the Indian mines. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108620">But is your grace assured certainly</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108630">That Bajazet doth favour your request? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108640">Perhaps you may make him your enemy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108650">You know how much your father doth detest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108660">Stout obedience and obstinacy. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108670">I speak not this as if I thought it best:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108680">Your highness should your right in it neglect,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108690">But that you might be close and circumspect. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e108700" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e108710">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108720">We thank thee visir for thy loving care,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108730">As for my father Baiazet's affection,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108740">Unless his holy vows forgotten are,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108750">I shall be sure of it by his election. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108760">By after Acomat's erection,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108770">We must forecast what things be necessary,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108780">Lest that our kingdom be too momentary. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e108790" who="A68114-regan">
          <speaker>Reg.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e108800">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108810">First let my lord be seated in his throne,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108820">Installed by great Bajazet's consent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108830">As yet your harvest is not fully grown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108840">But in the green and unripe blade is pent:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108850">But when you once have got the regiment,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108860">Then may your lords more easily provide,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108870">Against all accidents that may betide. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e108880" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Acomat.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e108890">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108900">Then set we forward to Byzantium,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108910">That we may know what Bajazet intends. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108920">Advise thee Acomat, what's best to do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108930">The janissaries favour Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108940">And they are strong undaunted enemies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108950">Which will in arms 'gainst thy election rise. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108960">Then will them to thy will with precious gifts</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108970"><pb facs="14"/> and store of gold: timely largition</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108980">The stedfast persons from their purpose lifts:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e108990">But then beware lest Bajazet's affection</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109000">Change into hatred by such premonition. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109010">For than he think that I am factious,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109020">And imitate my brother Selimus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109030">Besides, a prince his honour doth debase,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109040">That begs the common soldiers suffrages,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109050">And if the bassas knew I ●ought their grace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109060">It would the more increase their insolentness. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109070">To resist them were overhardiness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109080">And worse it were to leave my enterprise. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109090">Well howsoe'er , resolve to venture it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109100">Fortune doth favour every bold assay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109110">And 'twere a trick of an unsettled wit</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109120">Because the bees have stings with them always,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109130">To fare our mouths in honey to embay. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109140">Then resolution for me leads the dance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109150">And thus resolved, I mean to try my chance. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e109160">Exeunt all.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e109170">Enter Bajazet, Mustaffa, Calibassa, Halibassa, and the janissaries.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e109180" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e109190">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109200">What prince soe'er , trusts to his mighty power,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109210">Ruling the reins of many nations,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109220">And feareth not lest fickle fortune lour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109230">Are thinks his kingdom free from alterations,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109240">If he were in the place of Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109250">He would but little by his sceptre set. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109260">For what hath rule that makes it acceptable,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109270">Rather what hath it not worthy of hate:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109280">First of all is our state still mutable,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109290">And our continuance at the people's rate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109300">So that it is a slender thread, whereon</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109310">Depends the honour of a prince's throne. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109320">Then do we fear, more than the child new born,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109330"><pb facs="14"/> our friends, our lords, our subjects, and our sons. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109340">Thus is our mind in sundry pieces torn</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109350">By care, by fear, suspicion, and distrust,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109360">In wine, in meat we fear pernicious poison,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109370">At home, abroad, we fear seditious treason. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109380">Too true that tyrant Dionysius</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109390">Did picture out the image of a King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109400">When Daniocles was placed in his throne,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109410">And o'er his head a threatening sword did hang,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109420">Fastened up only by a horse's hair. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109430">Our chiefest trust is secretly distrust,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109440">For whom have we whom we may safely trust,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109450">If our own sons, neglecting awful duty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109460">Rise up in arms against their loving fathers. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109470">Their heart is all of hardest marble wrought,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109480">That can lay wait to take away their breath,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109490">From whom they first sucked this vital air. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109500">My heart is heavy, and I needs must sleep. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109510">Bassas withdraw yourselves from me awhile,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109520">That I may rest my ouerburdned soul. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e109530">They stand aside while the curtains are drawn.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e109540">Eunuchs play me some music while I sleep. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e109550">Music within.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e109560" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e109570">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109580">Good Bajazet, who would not pity thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109590">Whom thine own son so vildly persecutes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109600">More mildly do th'unreasonable beasts</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109610">Deal with their dams, than Selimus with thee. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e109620" who="A68114-unassigned">
          <speaker>Halibas.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e109630">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109640">Mustaffa we are princes of the land,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109650">And love our emperor as well as thou:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109660">Yet will we not for pitying his estate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109670">Suffer our foes our wealth to ruinate. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109680">If Selim have played false with Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109690">And overslipped the duty of a son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109700">Why he was moved by just occasion. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109710">Did he not humbly send his messenger</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109720">To crave access unto his majesty? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109730"><pb facs="15"/>And yet he could not get permission</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109740">To kiss his hands, and speak his mind to him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109750">Perhaps he thought his aged father's love</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109760">Was clean estranged from him: and Acomat</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109770">Should reap the fruit that he had laboured for. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109780">'Tis lawful for the father to take arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109790">I and by death chastise his rebel son. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109800">Why should it be unlawful for the son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109810">To levy arms 'gainst his injurious sire? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e109820" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e109830">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109840">You reason Hali like a sophister. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109850">As if 'twere lawful for a subject prince</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109860">To rise in arms 'gainst his sovereign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109870">Because he will not let him have his will:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109880">Much less is't lawful for a man's own son. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109890">If Bajazet had injured Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109900">Or sought his death, or done him some abuse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109910">Than Selimus' cause had been more tolerable. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109920">But Bajazet did never injure him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109930">Nor sought his death, nor once abused him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109940">Unless because he gives him not the crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109950">Being the youngest of his highness' sons. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109960">Gave he not him an empire for his part,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109970">The mighty empire of great Trebisond? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109980">So that if all things rightly be observed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e109990">Selim had more than ever he deserved. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110000">I speak not this because I hate the prince,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110010">For by the heavens I love young Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110020">Better than either of his brothers. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110030">But for I owe allegiance to my King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110040">And love him much that favours me so much. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110050">Mustaffa, while old Bajazet doth live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110060">Will be as true to him as to himself. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e110070" who="A68114-cali">
          <speaker>Cali.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e110080">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110090">Why brave Mustaffa, Hali and myself</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110100">Were never false unto his majesty</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110110">Our father Hali died in the field,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110120">Against the sophi, in his highness' wars. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110130"><pb facs="15"/>And we will never be degenerate. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110140">Nor do we take part with prince Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110150">Because we would depose old Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110160">But for because we would not acomat</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110170">That leads his life still in lascivious pomp,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110180">Nor Corcut, though he be a man of worth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110190">Should be commander of our empire. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110200">For he that never saw his foe man's face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110210">But always slept upon a lady's lap,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110220">Will scant endure to lead a soldier's life. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110230">And he that never handled but his pen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110240">Will be unskilful at the warlike lance. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110250">Indeed his wisdom well may guide the crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110260">And keep that safe his predecessors got▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110270">But being given to peace as Corcut is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110280">He never will enlarge the empire:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110290">So that the rule and power over us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110300">Is only fit for valiant Selimus. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e110310" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e110320">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110330">Princes, you know how mighty Bajazet</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110340">Hath honoured Mustaffa with his love. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110350">He gave his daughter beauteous Solima,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110360">To be the sovereign mistress of my thoughts. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110370">He made me captain of the janissaries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110380">And too unnatural should Mustaffa be,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110390">To rise against him in his dying age. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110400">Yet know, you warlike peer, Mustaffa is</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110410">A loyal friend unto prince Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110420">And ere his other brothers get the crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110430">For his sake, I myself will pull them down. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110440">I love, I love them dear, but the love</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110450">Which I do bear unto my country's good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110460">Makes me a friend to noble Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110470">Only let Bajazet while he doth live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110480">Enjoy in peace the Turkish diadem. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110490">When he is dead, and la●d in quiet grave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110500">Then none but Selimus our help shall have. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e110510"><pb facs="16"/>Sound within. A messenger enters, Bajazet awaketh.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e110520" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e110530">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110540">How now Mustaffa, what news have we there▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110550">Is Selim up in arms 'gainst me again? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110560">Or is the sophi entered our confines? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110570">Hath the Egyptian snatched his crown again? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110580">Or have the uncontrolled Christians</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110590">Unsheathed their swords to make more war on us? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110600">Such news, or none will come to Bajazet. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e110610" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e110620">My gracious lord, here's an ambassador</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e110630">Come from your son the soldan Acomat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e110640" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e110650">From Acomat? o let him enter in. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e110660">Enter Regian. </stage>
        <l xml:id="A68114-e110670">Ambassador, how fares our loving son? </l>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e110680" who="A68114-regan">
          <speaker>Reg.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e110690">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110700">Mighty commander of the warlike Turks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110710">Acomat soldan of Amasia;</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110720">Greeteth your grace by me his messenger. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110730">He gives him a letter. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110740">And gratulates your highness' good success,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110750">Wishing good fortune may befall you still. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e110760" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e110770">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110780">Mustaffa read. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110790">He gives the letter to Mustaffa, and speaks the rest to himselfs</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110800">Acomat craves thy promise Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110810">To give the empire up into his hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110820">And make it sure to him in thy life time. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110830">And thou shalt have it lovely Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110840">For I have been encumbered long enough,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110850">And vexed with the cares of kingly rule,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110860">Now let the trouble of the empiry</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110870">Be buried in the bosom of thy son. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110880">Ah Acomat, if thou have such a reign</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110890">So full of sorrow as thy father's was,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110900">Thou wilt accurse the time, the day and hour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110910">In which thou was established emperor. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110920">Sound. A messenger from Corcut. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110930"><pb facs="16"/>Yet more news? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e110940" who="A68114-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e110950">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110960">Long live the mighty emperor Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110970">Corcut the soldan of Magnesia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110980">Hearing of Selim's worthy overthrow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e110990">And of the coming of young Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111000">Doth certify your majesty by me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111010">How joyful he is of your victory. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111020">And there withal he humbly doth require</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111030">Your grace would do him justice in his cause●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111040">His brothers both, unworthy such a father,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111050">Do seek the empire while your grace doth live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111060">And that by indirect sinister means. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111070">But Corcut's mind free from ambitious thoughts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111080">And trusting to the goodness of his cause,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111090">Joined unto yours highness tender love</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111100">Only desires your grace should not invest </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111110">Selim nor Acomat, in the diadem,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111120">Which appertaineth unto him by right,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111130">But keep it to yourself the while you live:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111140">And when it shall the great creator please,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111150">Who hath the spirits of all men in his hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111160">Shall call your highness to your latest home,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111170">Then will he also sue to have his right. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e111180" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e111190">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111200">Like to a ship sailing without stars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111210">Whom waves do toss one way and winds another,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111220">Both without ceasing: even so my poor heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111230">Endures a combat betwixt love and right. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111240">The love I bear to my dear Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111250">Commands me give my suffrage unto him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111260">But Corcut's title, being my eldest son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111270">Bids me recall my hand, and give it him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111280">Acomat, he would have it in my life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111290">But gentle Corcut like a loving son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111300">Desires me live and die an emperor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111310">And at my death bequeath my crown to him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111320">Ah Corcut thou I see lovest me indeed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111330"><pb facs="17"/> Selimus sought to thrust me down by force,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111340">And Acomat seeks the kingdom in my life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111350">And both of them are grieved thou liv'st so long. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111360">But Corcut numbereth not my days as they,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111370">Oh how much dearer loves he me than they. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111380">Bassas, how counsel you your emperor? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e111390" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e111400">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111410">My gracious lord, myself will speak for all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111420">For all I know are minded as I am. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111430">Your highness knows the janissaries love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111440">How firm they mean to cleave to your behest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111450">As well you might perceive in that sad fight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111460">When Selim set upon you in your flight. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111470">Then we do all desire you on our knees,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111480">To keep the crown and sceptre to yourself. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111490">How grievous will it be unto your thoughts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111500">If you should give the crown to Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111510">To see the brothers disinherited,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111520">To flesh their anger one upon another,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111530">And rend the bowels of this mighty reign. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111540">Suppose that Corcut would be well content,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111550">Yet thinks your grace if Acomat were King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111560">That Selim ere long would join league with him? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111570">Nay he would break from forth his Trebisond,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111580">And waste the empire all with fire and sword. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111590">Ah then too weak would be poor Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111600">To stand against his brother's puissance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111610">Or save himself from his enhanced hand. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111620">While Ismael and the cruel Persians,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111630">And the great soldan of th' Egyptians,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111640">Would smile to see our force dismembered so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111650">I and perchance the neighbour Christians</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111660">Would take occasion to thrust out their heads. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111670">All this may be prevented by your grace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111680">If you will yield to Corcuts just request,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111690">And keep the kingdom to you while you live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111700">Mean time we that your graces subjects are,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111710"><pb facs="17"/> may make us strong, to fortify the man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111720">Whom at your death your grace shall choose as King. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e111730" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e111740">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111750">O how thou speakest ever like thyself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111760">Loyal Mustaffa: well were Bajazet</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111770">If all his sons, did bear such love to him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111780">Though loath I am longer to wear the crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111790">Yet for I see it is my subjects' will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111800">Once more will Bajazet be emperor. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111810">But we must send to pacific our son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111820">Or he will storm, as erst did Selimus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111830">Come let us go unto our council lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111840">And there consider what is to be done. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e111850">Exeunt all.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e111860">Enter Acomat, Regan, visir, and his soldiers. Acomat must read a letter, and then renting it say:</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e111870" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e111880">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111890">Thus will I rend the crown from off thy head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111900">False hearted and injurious Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111910">To mock thy son that loved thee so dear. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111920">What? for because the headstrong janissaries</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111930">Would not consent to honour Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111940">And their base bassas vowed to Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111950">Thought me unworthy of the Turkish crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111960">Should he be ruled and overruled by them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111970">Under pretence of keeping it himself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111980">To wipe me clean for ever being King? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e111990">Doth he esteem so much the bassas words,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112000">And prize their favour at so high a rate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112010">That for to gratify their stubborn minds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112020">He casts away all care, and all respects</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112030">Of duty, promise, and religious oaths? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112040">Now by the holy prophet Mahomet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112050">Chief president and patron of the Turks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112060">I mean to challenge now my right by arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112070">And win by sword that glorious dignity</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112080">Which he injuriously detains from me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112090"><pb facs="18"/>Haply he thinks because that Selimus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112100">Rebutted by his warlike janissaries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112110">Was ●●ine to she in haste from whence he came:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112120">That Acomat by his example moved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112130">Will fear to manage arms against his sire. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112140">Or that my life forepast in pleasure's court,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112150">Promises weak resistance in the fights</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112160">But he shall know that I can use my sword,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112170">And like a lion seize upon my prey. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112180">If ever Selim moved him heretofore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112190">Acomat means to move him ten times more▪</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e112200" who="A68114-visir">
          <speaker>Visir.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e112210">'Twere good your grace would to Amasia,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e112220">And there increase your camp with fresh supply. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e112230" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e112240">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112250">Visir, I am impatient of delay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112260">And since my father hath incensed me thus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112270">I'll quench those kindled flames with his heart blood. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112280">Not like a son, but a most cruel foe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112290">Will acomat henceforth be unto him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112300">March to Natolia, there we will begin</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112310">And make a preface to our massacres. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112320">My nephew Mahomet son to Alemshae,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112330">Departed lately from Iconium,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112340">Is lodged there, and he shall be the first</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112350">Whom I will sacrifice unto my wrath. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e112360">Exeunt all.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e112370">Enter the young prince Mahomet, the Belierbey of Natolia, and one or two soldiers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e112380" who="A68114-mahomet">
          <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e112390">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112400">Lord governor, what think you best to do? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112410">If we receive the soldan Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112420">Who knoweth not but his bloodthirsty sword</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112430">Shall be embowelled in our countrymen. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112440">You know he is displeased with Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112450">And will rebel, as Selim did to fore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112460">And would to God with Selim's overthrow. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112470">You know his angry heart hath vowed revenge</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112480">On all the subjects of his father's land. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e112490" who="A68114-belierbey">
          <pb facs="18"/>
          <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e112500">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112510">Young prince, thy uncle seeks to have thy life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112520">Because by right the Turkish crown is thine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112530">Save thou thyself by flight or otherwise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112540">And we will make resistance as we can. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112550">Like an Armenian tiger, that hath lost</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112560">Her loved whelps, so raveth Acomat:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112570">And we must be subject to his rage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112580">But you may live to venge your citizens. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112590">Then fly good prince before your uncle come. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e112600" who="A68114-mahomet">
          <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e112610">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112620">Nay good my lord, never shall it be said</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112630">That Mahomet the son of Alemshae,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112640">Fled from his citizens for fear of death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112650">But I will stay, and help to fight for you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112660">And if you needs must die, I'll die with you. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112670">And I among the rest with forward hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112680">Will help to kill a common enemy. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e112690">Exeunt all.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e112700">Enter Acomat, visir, Regan, and the soldiers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e112710" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e112720">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112730">Now fair Natolia, shall thy stately walls</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112740">Be overthrown and beaten to the ground. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112750">My heart within me for revenge still calls. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112760">Why Bajazet, thoughtest thou that Acomat</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112770">Would put up such a monstrous injury? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112780">Then had I brought my chivalry in vaine●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112790">And to no purpose drawn my conquering blade,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112800">Which now unsheathed, shall not be sheathed again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112810">Till it a world of bleeding souls hath made. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112820">Poor Mahomet, thou thoughtest thyself too sure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112830">In thy strong city of Iconium,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112840">To plant thy forces in Natolia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112850">Weakened so much before by Selim's sword. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112860">Summon a parley to the citizens,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112870">That they may hear the dreadful words I speak,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112880">And die in thought before they come to blows. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112890">All. A parley Mahomet, Belierbey, and soldiers on the walls. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e112900" who="A68114-mahomet">
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e112910">What craves our uncle Acomat of us? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e112920" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e112930">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112940">That thou and all the city yield themselves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112950">Or by the holy rites of Mahomet</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112960">His wondrous tomb, and sacred Alcoran,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112970">You all shall die: and not a common death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e112980">But even as monstrous as I can devise. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e112990" who="A68114-mahomet">
          <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e113000">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113010">Uncle, if I may call you by that name,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113020">Which cruelly hunt for your nephews blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113030">You do us wrong thus to besiege our town,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113040">That ne'er deserved such hatred at your hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113050">Being your friends and kinsmen as we are. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113060" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113070">In that thou wrongest me that thou art my kinsman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113080" who="A68114-mahomet">
          <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113090">Why for I am thy nephew dost thou frown? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113100" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113110">I that thou art so near unto the crown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113120" who="A68114-mahomet">
          <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113130">Why uncle I resign my right to thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113140">And all my title were it ne'er so good. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113150" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e113160">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113170">Wilt thou? then know assuredly from me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113180">I'll seal the resignation with thy blood:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113190">Though Alemshae thy father loved me well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113200">Yet Mahomet thy son shall down to hell. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113210" who="A68114-mahomet">
          <speaker>Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113220">Why uncle doth my life put you in fear? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113230" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113240">It shall not nephew, since I have you here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113250" who="A68114-mahomet">
          <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113260">When I am dead mote hinderers shalt thou find. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113270" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Acom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113280">When ones cut off, the fewer are behind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113290" who="A68114-mahomet">
          <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113300">Yet think the gods do bear an equal eye. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113310" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113320">Faith if they all were squint-eyed, what care I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113330" who="A68114-mahomet">
          <speaker>Maho.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113340">Then Mahomet know we will rather die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113350">Then yield us up into a tyrant's hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113360" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e113370">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113380">Beshrew me but you be the wiser Mahomet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113390">For if I do but catch you boy alive,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113400">'Twere better for you run through Phlegethon. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113410">Sirs scale the walls, and pull the caitive's down,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113420">I give to you the spoil of all the town. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113430">Alarum. Scale the walls. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e113440">Enter Acomat, visir and Regan, with Mahomet.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113450" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Acom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e113460">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113470">Now youngster, you that bravedst us on the walls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113480"><pb facs="19"/> and shook your plumed crest against our shield,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113490">What wouldst thou give, or what wouldst thou not give,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113500">That thou wert far enough from Acomat? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113510">How like the villain is to Bajazet? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113520">Well nephew for thy father loved me well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113530">I will not deal extremely with his son:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113540">Then hear a brief compendium of thy death. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113550">Regan go cause a grove of steelhead spears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113560">Be pitched thick under the castle wall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113570">And on them let this youthful captain fall. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113580" who="A68114-mahomet">
          <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e113590">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113600">Thou shalt not fear me acomat with death▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113610">Nor will I beg my pardon at thy hands. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113620">But as thou givest me such a monstrous death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113630">So do I freely leave to thee my curse:</l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e113640">Exit Regan with Mahomet.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113650" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113660">O, that will serve to fill my father's purse. </l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113670">Alarum. Enter a soldier with Zonara, sister to Mahomet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113680" who="A68114-zonara">
          <speaker>Zon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113690">Ah pardon me dear uncle, pardon me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113700" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113710">No minion, you are too near a kin to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113720" who="A68114-zonara">
          <speaker>Zon.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e113730">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113740">If ever pity entered thy breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113750">Or ever thou wast touched with woman's love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113760">Sweet uncle spare wretched Zonara's life. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113770">Thou once wast noted for a quiet prince,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113780">Soft-hearted, mild, and gentle as a lamb,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113790">Ah do not prove a lion unto me. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113800" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113810">Why wouldst thou live, when Mahomet is dead? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113820" who="A68114-zonara">
          <speaker>Ron.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113830">Ah who slew Mahomet? Uncle did you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113840" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113850">He that's prepared to do as much for you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113860" who="A68114-zonara">
          <speaker>Zon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113870">Dost thou not pity Alemshae in me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113880" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e113890">Yes that he wants so long thy company. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113900" who="A68114-zonara">
          <speaker>Zon.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e113910">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113920">Thou art not false groom son to Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113930">He would relent to hear a woman weep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113940">But thou wast born in desert Caucasus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113950">And the Hyrcanian tigers gave thee suck,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113960">Knowing thou wert a monster like themselves. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e113970" who="A68114-acomat">
          <pb facs="20"/>
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e113980">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e113990">Let you her thus to rate us? Strangle her. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114000">They strangle her. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114010">Now scour the streets, and leave not one alive</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114020">To carry these sad news to Bajazet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114030">That all the citizens may dear say,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114040">This day was fatal to Natolia. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e114050">Exeunt all.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e114060">Enter Bajazet, Mustaffa, and the janissaries.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e114070" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e114080">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114090">Mustaffa, if my mind deceive me not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114100">Some strange misfortune is not far from me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114110">I was not wont to tremble in this sort. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114120">Methinks I feel a cold run through my bones,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114130">As if it hastened to surprise my heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114140">Methinks some voice still whispereth in my ears</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114150">And bids me to take heed of Acomat. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e114160" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e114170">'Tis but your highness overcharged mind</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e114180">Which feareth most the things it least desires. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e114190">Enter two soldiers with the Belierbey of Natolia in a chair, and the body of Mahomet and Zonara, in two coffins.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e114200" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e114210">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114220">Ah sweet Mustaffa, thou art much deceived,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114230">My mind presages me some future harm,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114240">And lo what doleful exequy is here. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114250">Our chief commander of Natolia? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114260">What caitiff hand is it hath wounded thee? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114270">And who are these covered in tomb-black hearse? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e114280" who="A68114-belierbey">
          <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e114290">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114300">These are thy nephews mighty Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114310">The son and daughter of good Alemshae,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114320">Whom cruel Acomat hath murdered thus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114330">These eyes beheld, when from an airy tower,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114340">They hurled the body of young Mahomet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114350">Whereas a band of armed soldiers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114360">Received him falling on their spears sharp points. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114370">His sister poor Zonara,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114380">Entreating life and not obtaining it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114390">Was strangled by his barbarous soldiers. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114400">Bajazet falls in a sound, and being recovered say▪</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e114410" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <pb facs="20"/>
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e114420">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114430">O you dispensers of our hapless breath,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114440">Why do you glut your eyes, and take delight</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114450">To see sad pageants of men's miseries? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114460">Wherefore have you prolonged my wretched life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114470">To see my son my dearest Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114480">To lift his hands against his father's life? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114490">Ah Selimus, now do I pardon thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114500">For thou didst set upon me manfully,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114510">And moved by an occasion, though unjust. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114520">But Acomat, injurious Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114530">Is ten-times more unnatural to me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114540">Hapless Zonara, hapless Mahomet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114550">The poor remainder of my Alemshae,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114560">Which of you both shall Bajazet most wail? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114570">Ah both of you are worthy to be wailed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114580">Happily dealt the froward fates with thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114590">Good Alemshae, for thou didst die in field,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114600">And so preventedst this sad spectacle,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114610">Pitiful spectacle of sad dreariment,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114620">Pitiful spectacle of dismal death. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114630">But I have lived to see thee Alemshae,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114640">By tartar pirates all in pieces torn. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114650">To see young Selim's disobedience. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114660">To see the death of Alemsha's poor seed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114670">And last of all to see my Acomat</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114680">Prove a rebellious enemy to me. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e114690" who="A68114-belierbey">
          <speaker>Beli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e114700">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114710">Ah cease your tears unhappy emperor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114720">And shed not all for your poor nephew's death. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114730">Six thousand of true-hearted citizens</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114740">In fair Natolia, Acomat hath slain:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114750">The channels run like riverets of blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114760">And I escaped with this poor company,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114770">Bemangled and dismembered as you see,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114780">To be the messenger of these sad news. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114790">And now mine eyes fast swimming in pale death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114800">Bids me resign my breath unto the heavens,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114810"><pb facs="21"/> death stands before ready for to strike. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114820">Farewell dear emperor and revenge our loss,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114830">As ever thou dost hope for happiness. He dies. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e114840" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e114850">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114860">Avernus' jaws and loathsome Taenarus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114870">From whence the damned ghosts do often creep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114880">Back to the world to punish wicked men. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114890">Black Demogorgon, grandfather of night,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114900">Send out thy furies from thy fiery hall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114910">The pitiless erymnys armed with whips,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114920">And all the damned monsters of black hell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114930">To pour their plagues on cursed Acomat. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114940">How shall I mourn, or which way shall I turn</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114950">To pour my tears upon my dearest friends? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114960">Couldst thou endue false-hearted Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114970">To kill thy nephew and thy sister thus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114980">And wound to death so valiant a lord? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e114990">And will you not you all beholding heavens,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115000">Dart down on him your piercing lightning brand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115010">Enrolled in sulphur, and consuming flames? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115020">Ah do not Jove, Acomat is my son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115030">And may perhaps by counsel be reclaimed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115040">And brought to filial obedience. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115050">Aga thou art a man of perceant wit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115060">Go thou and talk with my son Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115070">And see if he will any way relent</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115080">Speak him fair Aga, lest he kill thee too. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115090">And we my lords will in, and mourn a while,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115100">Over these princes lamentable tombs. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e115110">Exeunt all.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e115120">Enter Acomat, visir, Regan, and their soldiers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115130" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e115140">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115150">As Tityus in the country of the dead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115160">With restless cries doth call, upon high jove</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115170">The while the vulture tireth on his heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115180">So Acomat, revenge still gnaws thy soul. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115190"><pb facs="21"/>In shedding blood, and murdering innocents. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115200">I think my wrath hath been too patient,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115210">Since civil blood quencheth not out the flames</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115220">Which Bajazet hath kindled in my heart. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115230" who="A68114-visir">
          <speaker>Visir.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e115240">My gracious lord, here is a messenger</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e115250">Sent from your father the emperor. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e115260">Enter Aga, and one with him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115270" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e115280">Let him come in: Aga what news with you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115290" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e115300">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115310">Great prince, thy father mighty Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115320">Wonders your grace whom he did love so much,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115330">And thought to leave possessor of the crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115340">Would thus requite his love with mortal hate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115350">To kill thy nephews with revenging sword,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115360">And massacre his subjects in such sort. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115370" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e115380">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115390">Aga, my father traitorous Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115400">Detains the crown injuriously from me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115410">Which I will have if all the world say nay. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115420">I am not like the unmanured land,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115430">Which answers not his honours greedy mind:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115440">I sow not seeds upon the barren sand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115450">A thousand ways can acomat soon find,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115460">To gain my will, which if I cannot gain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115470">Then purple blood my angry hands shall stain. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115480" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e115490">Acomat, yet learn by Selimus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e115500">That hasty purposes have hated ends. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115510" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e115520">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115530">Tush Aga, Selim was not wise enough</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115540">To set upon the head at the first brunt:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115550">He should have done as I do mean to do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115560">Fill all the confines, with fire, sword, and blood ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115570">Burn up the fields, and overthrow whole towns,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115580">And when he had endamaged that way,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115590">Then tear the old man piecemeal with my teeth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115600">And colour my strong hands with his gore-blood. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115610" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e115620">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115630">O see my lord, how fell ambition</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115640">Deceives your senses and bewitches you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115650">Could you unkind perform so foul a deed ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115660"><pb facs="22"/> 〈…〉 the man that first gave life to you? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115670">Do you not fear the people's adverse fame? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115680" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e115690">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115700">It is the greatest glory of a King</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115710">When, though his subjects hate his wicked deeds</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115720">Yet are they forced to bear them all with praise. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115730" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e115740">Whom fear constrains to praise their princes deeds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e115750">That fear, eternal hatred in them feeds. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115760" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e115770">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115780">He knows not how to sway the kingly mace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115790">That loves to be great in his people's grace:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115800">The surest ground for Kings to build upon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115810">Is to be feared and cursed of every one. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115820">What though the world of nations me hate? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115830">Hate is peculiar to a prince's state. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115840" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e115850">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115860">Where there's no shame, no care of holy law,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115870">No faith, no justice, no integrity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115880">That state is full of mutability. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115890" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e115900">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115910">Bare faith, pure virtue, poor integrity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115920">Are ornaments fit for a private man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115930">Beseems a prince for to do all he can. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115940" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e115950">Yet know it is a sacrilegious will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e115960">To slay thy father were he ne'er so ill. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e115970" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e115980">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e115990">'Tis lawful graybeard for to do to him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116000">What ought not to be done unto a father. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116010">Hath he not wiped me from the Turkish crown? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116020">Preferred he not the stubborn janissaries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116030">And heard the bassas stout petitions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116040">Before he would give ear to my request? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116050">As sure as day, mine eyes shall ne'er taste sleep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116060">Before my sword have riven his perjured breast. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e116070" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e116080">Ah let me never live to see that day●</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e116090" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e116100">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116110">Yes thou shalt live, but never see that day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116120">Wanting the tapers that should give thee light:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116130">Pulls out his eyes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116140">Thou shalt not see so great felicity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116150">When I shall rend out Bajazet's dim eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116160">And by his death install myself a King. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e116170" who="A68114-aga">
          <pb facs="22"/>
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e116180">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116190">Ah cruel tyrant and unmerciful,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116200">More bloody than the anthropophagi,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116210">That fill their hungry stomachs with man's flesh. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116220">Thou shouldst have slain me barbarous Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116230">Not leave me in so comfortless a life</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116240">To live on earth, and never see the sun. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e116250" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e116260">Nay let him die that liveth at his ease,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e116270">Death would a wretched caitiff greatly please. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e116280" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e116290">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116300">And thinkst thou then to scape unpunished,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116310">No Acomat, though both mine eyes be gone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116320">Yet are my hands left on to murder thee. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e116330" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e116340">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116350">Was well remembered: Regan cut them off. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116360">They cur of his hands and give them acomat. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116370">Now in that sort go tell thy emperor</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116380">That if himself had but bene in thy place,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116390">I would have used him crueler than thee:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116400">Here take thy hands: I know thou lovest them well. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116410">Opens his bosom, and puts them in. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116420">Which hand is this? right? or left? canst thou tell? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e116430" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e116440">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116450">I know not which it is, but 'tis my hand. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116460">But o thou supreme architect of all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116470">First mover of those tenfold crystal orbs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116480">Where all those moving, and unmoving eyes</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116490">Behold thy goodness everlastingly:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116500">See, unto thee I lift these bloody arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116510">For hands I have not for to lift to thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116520">And in thy justice dart thy smouldering flame</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116530">Upon the head of cursed Acomat. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116540">O cruel heavens and injurious fates,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116550">Even the last refuge of a wretched man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116560">Is taken from me: for how can Aga weep? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116570">Or ruin a brinish shower of pearled tears? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116580">Wanting the watery cisterns of his eyes? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116590">Come lead me back again to Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116600">The woefullest, and saddest ambassador</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116610">That ever was dispatched to any King. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e116620" who="A68114-acomat">
          <pb facs="23"/>
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e116630">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116640">Why so, this music pleases Acomat. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116650">And would I had my doting father here,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116660">I would rip up his breast, and rend his heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116670">Into his bowels thrust my angry hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116680">As willingly, and with as good a mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116690">As I could be the Turkish emperor. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116700">And by the clear declining vault of heaven,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116710">Whither the souls of dying men do flee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116720">Either I mean to die the death myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116730">Or make that old false faitour bleed his last. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116740">For death no sorrow could unto me bring,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116750">So Acomat might die the Turkish King. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e116760">Exeunt all.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e116770">Enter Bajazet, Mustaffa, Cali, Hali, and Aga led by a souldier, who keeling before Bajazet, and holding his legs shall say:</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e116780" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e116790">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116800">Is this the body of my sovereign? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116810">Are these the sacred pillars that support</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116820">The image of true magnanimity? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116830">Ah Bajazet, thy son false Acomat</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116840">Is full resolved to take thy life from thee:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116850">'Tis true, 'tis true, witness these handless arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116860">Witness these empty lodges of mine eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116870">Witness the gods that from the highest heaven</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116880">Beheld the tyrant with remorceless heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116890">Pulled out mine eyes, and cut off my weak hands. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116900">Witness that sun whose golden coloured beams</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116910">Your eyes do see, but mine can ne'er behold:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116920">Witness the earth that sucked up my blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116930">Streaming in rivers from my tronked arms. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116940">Witness the present that he sends to thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116950">Open my bosom, there you shall it see. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116960">Mustaffa opens his bosom and takes out his hands. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116970">Those are the hands, which Aga once did use,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116980">To toss the spear, and in a warlike gyre</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e116990"><pb facs="23"/> to hurtle my sharp sword about my head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117000">Those sends he to the woeful emperor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117010">With purpose so cut thy hands from thee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117020">Why is my sovereign silent all this while? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e117030" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e117040">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117050">Ah Aga, Bajazet fain would speak to thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117060">But sudden sorrow eateth up my words. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117070">Bajazet Aga, fain would weep for thee▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117080">But cruel sorrow drieth up my tears. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117090">Bajazet Aga, fain would die for thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117100">But grief hath weakened my poor aged hands. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117110">How can he speak, whose tongue sorrow hath tide? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117120">How can he mourn, that cannot shed a tear? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117130">How shall he live, that full of misery</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117140">Calleth for death, which will not let him die? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e117150" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e117160">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117170">Let women weep, let children pour ●oo●●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117180">And cowards spend the time in bootless moan. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117190">We'll load the earth with such a mighty host</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117200">Of janissaries, stern-born sons of Mars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117210">That Phaeb shall fly and hide him in the clouds</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117220">For fear our javelins thrust him from his wain. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117230">Old Aga was a prince among your lords,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117240">His counsels always were true oracles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117250">And shall he thus unmanly be misused,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117260">And he unpunished that did the deed? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117270">Shall Mahomet and poor Zonara's ghosts</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117280">And the good governor of Natalia</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117290">Wander in Stygian meadows unrevenged</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117300">Good emperor stir up thy manly heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117310">And send forth all thy warlike janissaries</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117320">To chastise that rebellious Acomat</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117330">Thou knowest we cannot fight without a guide,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117340">And he must be one of the royal blood</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117350">Sprung from the loins of mighty Ottoman,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117360">And who remains now, but young Selimus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117370">So please your grace to pardon his offence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117380">And 〈…〉</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e117390" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <pb facs="24"/>
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e117400">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117410">I good Mustaffa, send for Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117420">So I may be revenged I care not how,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117430">The worst that can befall me is but death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117440">That would end my woeful misery. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117450">Selimus he must work me this good turn,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117460">I cannot kill myself, he'll do't for me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117470">Come Aga, thou and I will weep the while:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117480">Thou for thy eyes and loss of both thy hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117490">I for th'unkindnes of my Acomat. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e117500">Exeunt all.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e117510">Enter Selimus, and a messenger with a letter from Bajazet. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e117520" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Selim.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e117530">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117540">Will fortune favour me yet once again? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117550">And will she thrust the cards into my hands? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117560">Well if I chance but once to get the deck,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117570">To deal about and shuffle as I would:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117580">Let Selim never see the daylight spring,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117590">Unless I shuffle out myself a King. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117600">Friend let me see thy letter once again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117610">That I may read these reconciling lines. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117620">Reads the letter. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117630">Thou hast a pardon Selim granted thee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117640">Mustaffa and the forward janissaries</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117650">Have sued to thy father Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117660">That thou mayst be their captain general</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117670">Against th'attempts of soldan Acomat. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117680">Why that's the thing that I requested most,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117690">That I might once th'imperial army lead:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117700">And since it's offered me so willingly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117710">Beshrew me but I'll take their courtesy. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117720">Soft let me see is there no policy</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117730">T'entrap poor Selimus in this device? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117740">It may be that my father fears me yet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117750">Lest I should once again rise up in arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117760">And like Antaeus' quelled by Hercules,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117770">Gather new forces by my overthrow:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117780"><pb facs="24"/> and therefore sends for me under pretence</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117790">Of this, and that: but when he hath me there▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117800">He'll make me sure for putting him in fear</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117810">Distrust is good, when theirs cau●e or distrust</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117820">Read it again, perchance thou dost mistake. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117830">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e117840">Read.</stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117850">O, here's Mustaffa signet ●et thereto</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117860">Than Selim cast all foolish fear aside,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117870">For he's a prince that favours thy estate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117880">And hateth treason worse than death it ●el●e. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117890">And hardly can I think he could be brought</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117900">If there were treason, to subscribe his name▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117910">Come friend, the cause requires we should be gone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117920">Now once again have at the Turkish throne</l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e117930">Exeunt both.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e117940">Enter Bajazet leading Aga, Mustaffa, Hali, Cali, Selimus, the janissaries. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e117950" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e117960">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117970">Come mournful Aga, come and sit by me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117980">Thou hast been sorely grieved for Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e117990">Good reason then that he should grieve for thee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118000">Give me thy arm, though thou hast lost thy hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118010">And liv'st as a poor exile in this light,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118020">Yet hast thou won the heart of Bajazet,</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e118030" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e118040">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118050">Your grace's words are very comfortable,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118060">And well can Aga bear his grievous loss,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118070">Since it was for so good a prince's sake. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e118080" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e118090">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118100">Father, if I may call thee by that name,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118110">Whose life I aimed at with rebellious sword:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118120">In all humility thy reformed son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118130">Offers himself into your grace's hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118140">And at your feet layeth his bloody sword,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118150">Which he advanced against your majesty. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118160">If my offence do seem so odious</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118170">That I deserve not longer time to live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118180">Behold I open unto you my breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118190">Ready prepared to die at your command. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118200"><pb facs="25"/>But if repentance in unfeigned heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118210">And sorrow for my grievous crime forepast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118220">May merit pardon at your princely hands▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118230">Behold where poor inglorious Selimus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118240">Upon his knees begs pardon of your grace. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e118250" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e118260">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118270">Stand up my son, I joy to hear thee speak,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118280">But more to hear thou art so well reclaimed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118290">Thy crime was ne'er so odious unto me●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118300">But thy reformed life and humble thoughts</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118310">Are thrice as pleasing to my aged spirit. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118320">Selim we here pronounce thee by our will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118330">Chief general of the warlike janissaries</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118340">Go lead them out against false Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118350">Which hath so grievously rebelled 'gainst me●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118360">Spare him not Selim, though he be my son▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118370">Yet do I now clean disinherit him▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118380">As common enemy to me and mine. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e118390" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e118400">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118410">May Selim live to show how dutiful</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118420">And loving he will be to Bajazet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118430">So now doth fortune smile on me again</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118440">And in regard of former injuries</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118450">Offer me millions of diadems:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118460">I smile to see how that the good old man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118470">Thinks Selim's thoughts are brought to such an ebb</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118480">As he hath cast off all ambitious hope.</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118490">But soon shall that opinion be removed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118500">For if I once get amongst the janissaries</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118510">Then on my head the golden crown shall sit.</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118520">Well Bajazet, I fear me thou wilt grieve,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118530">That ere thou didst thy faining son believe,</l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e118540">Exit Selim, with all the rest save Bajazet and Aga</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e118550" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e118560">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118570">Now Aga, all the thoughts that troubled me●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118580">Do rest within the centre of my heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118590">And thou shalt shortly joy as much with me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118600">Than Acomat by Selim's consuming sword,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118610"><pb facs="25"/> shall lose that ghost which made thee lose thy sight. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e118620" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e118630">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118640">Ah Bajazet, Aga looks not for revenge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118650">But will pour out his prayers to the heavens,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118660">That Acomat may learn by Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118670">To yield himself up to his father's grace. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118680">Sound within, long live Selimus emperor of Turks. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e118690" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e118700">How now, what sudden triumph have we here? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e118710" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e118720">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118730">Ah gracious lord, the captains of the host,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118740">With one assent have crowned prince Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118750">And here he comes with all the janissaries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118760">To crave his confirmation at thy hands. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e118770">Enter Cali bassa, Selimus, Hali bassa, Sinam, and the janissaries. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e118780" who="A68114-sinam">
          <speaker>Sinam.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e118790">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118800">Bajazet, we the captains of thy host,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118810">Knowing thy weak and too unwieldy age,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118820">Unable is longer to govern us▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118830">Have chosen Selimus thy younger son</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118840">That he may be our leader and our guide,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118850">Against the sophi and his Persians,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118860">'Gainst the victorious soldan Tonumbey. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118870">Their wants but thy consent, which we will have,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118880">Or hew thy body piecemeal with our swords. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e118890" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e118900">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118910">Needs must I give, what is already gone. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118920">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e118930">He takes of his crown.</stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118940">Here Selimus, thy father Bajazet</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118950">Wearied with cares that wait upon a King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118960">Resigns the crown as willingly to thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118970">As ere my father gave it unto me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e118980">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e118990">Sets it on his head.</stage>
            </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e119000" who="A68114-all">
          <speaker>All.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e119010">Long live Selimus emperor of Turks. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e119020" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e119030">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119040">Live thou a long and a victorious reign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119050">And be triumpher of thine enemies</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119060">Aga and I will to dimoticum</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119070">And live in peace the remnant of our days. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e119080">Exit Bajazet and Aga.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e119090" who="A68114-selimus">
          <pb facs="26"/>
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e119100">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119110">Now ●it I like ●he arm strong son of love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119120">When after he had all his monsters quelled</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119130">He was received in heaven amongst the gods,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119140">And had fair Hebe for his lovely bride. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119150">As many labours Selimus hath had,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119160">And now at length attained to the crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119170">This is my Hebe, and this is my heaven</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119180">Bajazet goeth to Dimeticum,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119190">And there he purposes to live at ease,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119200">But Selimus, as long as he is on earth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119210">Thou shalt not sleep in rest without some broil</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119220">For Bajazet is unconstant as the winde●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119230">To make that sure I have a platform laid. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119240">Bajazet hath with him a cunning Jew,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119250">Professing physic, and so skilled therein,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119260">As if he had power over life and death. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119270">Withal, a man so stout and resolute,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119280">That he will venture any thing for gold</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119290">This Jew with some intoxicated drink,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119300">Shall poison Bajazet and that blind lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119310">Than one of Hydra's heads is clean cut off. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119320">Go some and fetch Abraham the Jew</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119330">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e119340">Exit one for Abraham. </stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119350">Corcut, thy pageant next is to be played. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119360">For though he be a grave philosopher,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119370">Given to read Mahomet's dread jews,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119380">And Razin's toys, and Avicenna's drugs</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119390">Yet he may have a longing for the crown. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119400">Besides, he may by devilish negromancie</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119410">Procure my death or work my overthrow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119420">The devil still is ready to do harm. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119430">Hali, you and your brother presently. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119440">Shall with an army to Magnesia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119450">There you shall find the scholar at his book,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119460">And hearest thou Hali? strangle him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119470">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e119480">Exeunt Hali, and Cali.</stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119490"><pb facs="26"/>Corcut once dead, than Acomat remains,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119500">Whose death will make me certain of the crown. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119510">These heads of Hydra are the principal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119520">When these are off, some other will arise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119530">As Amurath and Aladin, sons to Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119540">My sister Solyma, Mustaffa's wife,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119550">All these shall suffer shipwreck on a shelf,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119560">Rather than Selim will be drowned himself. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119570">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e119580">Enter Abraham the Jew.</stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119590">Jew thou art welcome unto Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119600">I have a piece of service for you sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119610">But on your life be secret in the deed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119620">Get a strong poison, whose envenomed taste</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119630">May take away the life of Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119640">Before he pass forth of Byzantium. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e119650" who="A68114-abraham">
          <speaker>Abra.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e119660">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119670">I warrant you my gracious sovereign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119680">He shall be quickly sent unto his grave</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119690">For I have potions of so strong a force,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119700">That whosoever touches them shall die▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119710">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e119720">Speaks aside.</stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119730">And would your grace would once but taste of them</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119740">I could as willingly afford them you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119750">As your aged father Bajazet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119760">My lord, I am resolved to do the deed. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e119770">Exit Abraham</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e119780" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e119790">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119800">So this is well▪ for I am none of those</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119810">That make a conscience for to kill a man. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119820">For nothing is more hurtful to a prince,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119830">Then to be scrupulous and religious. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119840">I like Lysander's counsel passing well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119850">If that I cannot speed with lion's force,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119860">To clothe my complots in a fox's skin. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119870">For th'only things that wrought our empiry,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119880">Were open wrongs, and hidden treachery. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119890">O, they're two wings wherewith I use to flie●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119900">And soar above the common fort</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119910"><pb facs="27"/> if any seek our wrongs to remedy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119920">With these I take his 〈…〉</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119930">And one of these shall still maintain in● cause,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119940">Or fox's skin, or lions rending paws. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e119950">Exeunt all.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e119960">Enter Bajazet, Aga, in mourning cloaks, Abraham the Jew with a cup.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e119970" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e119980">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e119990">Come Aga let sit us and mourn a while,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120000">For fortune never showed herself so cross,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120010">To any prince as to poor Bajazet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120020">That woeful emperor first of my name,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120030">Whom the Tartarians locked in ●age,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120040">To be a spectacle to all the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120050">Was ten times happier than I am. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120060">For Tamberlaine the scourge of nations,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120070">Was he that pulled him from his kingdom so. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120080">But mine own sons, expel me from the throne,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120090">Ah where shall I begin to make my moan. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120100">Or what shall I first reckon in my plaint,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120110">From my youth up I have been drowned in woe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120120">And to my latest hour I shall be so. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120130">You swelling seas of never ceasing care,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120140">Whose waves my weather-beaten ship do toss,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120150">Your boisterous billows too unruly are</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120160">And threaten still my ruin and my loss:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120170">Like hugy mountains do your waters rear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120180">Their lofty tops, and my weak vessel cross. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120190">Alas at length allay your stormy strife,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120200">And cruel wrath within me rages rise. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120210">Or else my feeble bark cannot endure</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120220">Your slashing buffets and outrageous blows,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120230">But while thy foamy flood doth it immure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120240">Shall soon be wrecked upon the sandy shallows</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120250">Grief my lewd boatswain stirreth nothing sure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120260">But without stars 'gainst tide and wind he rows,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120270">And cares not though upon some rock we split</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120280"><pb facs="27"/> a restless pilot for the charge unfit. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120290">But out alas, the god that vales the sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120300">And can alone this raging tempest slent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120310">Will never blow a gentle gale of case,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120320">But suffer my poor vessel to be rent. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120330">Then o thou blind procurer of mischance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120340">That stayest thyself upon turning wheel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120350">Thy cruel hand even when thou wilt enhance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120360">And pierce my poor heart with thy chrillant steel</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e120370" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e120380">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120390">Cease Bajazet, now it is agas turn,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120400">Rest thou a while and gather up more tears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120410">The while poor Aga tell his tragedy. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120420">When first my mother brought me to the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120430">Some blazing comet ruled in the sky,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120440">Portending miserable chance to me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120450">My parents were but men of poor estate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120460">And happy yet had wretched Aga been,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120470">If Bajazet had not exalted him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120480">Poor Aga, had it not been much more fair,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120490">T'have died among the cruel Persians</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120500">Then thus at home by barbarous tyranny</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120510">To live and never see the cheerful day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120520">And to want hands wherewith to feel the way. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e120530" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e120540">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120550">Leave weeping Aga, we have wept enough,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120560">Now Bajazet will ban another while,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120570">And utter curses to the concave sky,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120580">Which may infect the regions of the air,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120590">And bring a general plague on all the world▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120600">Night thou most ancient grandmother of all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120610">First made by Jove, for rest and quiet sleep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120620">When cheerful day is gone from th'earth's wide hall. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120630">Henceforth thy mantle in black Lethe sleep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120640">And clothe the world in darkness infernal</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120650">Suffer not once the joyful daylight peep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120660">But let thy pitchy steeds aye draw thy wain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120670">And coal-black silence in the world still raigne●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120680"><pb facs="28"/> curse on my parents that first brought me u●●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120690">And on the cradle wherein I was rocked,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120700">Curse on the day when ●●●st I was created</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120710">The chief commander of all Asia. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120720">Curse on my sons that drive ●ne to this grief,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120730">Curse on myself that can find no relief. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120740">And curse on him, an everlasting curse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120750">That quenched those lamps of ever-burning light,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120760">And took away my agas warlike hands▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120770">And curse on all things under the wide sky,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120780">Ah Aga, I have cursed my stomach dry. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e120790" who="A68114-abraham">
          <speaker>Abra.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e120800">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120810">I have a drink my lords of noble worth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120820">Which soon will calm your stormy passions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120830">And glad your hearts if so you please to taste it. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e120840" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e120850">For who art thou that thus doest pity us? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e120860" who="A68114-abraham">
          <speaker>Abra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e120870">Your highness' humble servant Abraham. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e120880" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e120890">Abraham sit down and drink to Bajazet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e120900" who="A68114-abraham">
          <speaker>Abra.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e120910">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120920">Faith I am old as well as Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120930">And have not many months to live on earth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120940">I care not much to end my life with him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e120950">Here's to you lordings with a full carouse. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e120960">He drinks.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e120970" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e120980">Here Aga, woeful Bajazet drinks to thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e120990">Abraham, hold the cup to him while he drinks. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e121000" who="A68114-abraham">
          <speaker>Abra.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e121010">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121020">Now know old lords, that you have drunk your last:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121030">This was a potion which I did prepare</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121040">To poison you, by Selimus' instigation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121050">And now it is dispersed through my bones,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121060">And glad I am that such companions</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121070">Shall go with me down to Proserpina. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e121080">He dies.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e121090" who="A68114-bajazet">
          <speaker>Baia.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e121100">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121110">Ah wicked Jew, ah cursed Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121120">How have the destins dealt with Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121130">That none should cause my death but mine own son? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121140">Had Ismael and his warlike Persians</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121150">Pierced my body with their iron spears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121160"><pb facs="28"/> or had the strong unconquered Tonumbey</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121170">With his Egyptians took me prisoner,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121180">And sent me with his valiant Mammalukes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121190">To be pray unto the Crocodilus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121200">It never would have grieved me half so much. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121210">But welcome death into whose calmy port,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121220">My sorrow-beaten soul joys to arrive. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121230">And now farewell my disobedient sons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121240">Unnatural sons unworthy of that name. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121250">Farewell sweet life, and Aga now farewell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121260">Till we shall meet in the Elysian fields. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e121270">He dies.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e121280" who="A68114-aga">
          <speaker>Aga.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e121290">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121300">What greater grief had mournful Priamus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121310">Then that he lived to see his Hector die,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121320">His city burned down by revenging flames,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121330">And poor Polites slain before his face? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121340">Aga, thy grief is matchable to his,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121350">For I have lived to see my sovereign's death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121360">Yet glad that I must breathe my last with him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121370">And now farewell sweet light, which my poor eyes</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121380">These twice six months never did behold:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121390">Aga will follow noble Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121400">And beg a boon of lovely Proserpine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121410">That he and I may in the mournful fields,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121420">Still weep and wail our strange calamities. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e121430">He dies</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e121440">Enter Bullithrumble, the shepherd running in haste, and laughing to himself.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e121450" who="A68114-bullithrumble">
          <speaker>Bulli.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e121460">Ha, ha, ha, married quoth you? Marry and Bullithrumble were to begin the world again, I would set a tap abroach, and not live in daily fear of the breach of my wife's ten-commandments. I'll tell you what, I thought myself as proper a fellow at wasters, as any in all our village, and yet when my wife begins to play clubs trump with me, I am fain to sing:</p>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e121470">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121480">What hap had I to marry a shrew,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121490">For she hath given me many a blow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121500"><pb facs="29"/> and how to please her alas I do not know. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121510">From morn to even her tongue ne'er lies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121520">Sometime she laughs, sometime she cries:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121530">And I can scarce keep her talents from my eyes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121540">When from abroad I do come in,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121550">Sir knave she cries, where have you been? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121560">Thus please, or displease, she lays it on my skin</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121570">Then do I crouch, then do I kneel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121580">And wish my cap were furred with steel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121590">To bear the blows that my poor head doth feel. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121600">But our sir John beshrew thy heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121610">For thou hast joined us we cannot part,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121620">And I poor fool, must ever bear the smart. </l>
          </lg>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e121630">I'll tell you what, this morning while I was making me ready, she came with a holly wand, and so blessed my shoulders that I was fain to run through a whole alphabet of faces: now at the last seeing she was so cramuk with me, I began to swear all the criss-cross row over, beginning at great a, li●le a, till I came to W, x, y. And snatching up my sheephook, and my bottle and my bag, like a desperate fellow ran away, and here now I'll sit down and eat my meat.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e121640">While he is eating, enter Corcut and his page, disguised like mourners.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e121650" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e121660">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121670">O hateful hellish snake of Tartary,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121680">That feedest on the soul of noblest men,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121690">Damned ambition, cause of all misery,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121700">Why dost thou creep from out thy loathsome fen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121710">And with thy poison animatest friends,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121720">And gape and long one for the others ends. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121730">Selimus, couldst thou not content thy mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121740">With the possession of the sacred throne,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121750">Which thou didst get by father's death unkind:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121760">Whose poisoned ghost before high God doth groan. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121770">But thou must seek poor Corcut's overthrow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121780">That never injured thee, so, nor so? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121790"><pb facs="29"/>Old Halie's sons with two great company</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121800">Of barded horse, were sent from Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121810">To take me prisoner in Magnesia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121820">And death I am sure should have befallen to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121830">If they had once but set their eyes on me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121840">So thus disguised my poor page and ●,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121850">Fled fast to Smirna, where in a dark cave</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121860">We meant t'await th'arrival of some ship</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121870">That might trans●●eit us safely unto Rhodes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121880">But see how fortune crossed my enterprise. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121890">Bostang● bassa, Selim's son in law,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121900">Kept all the sea coasts with his brigandines,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121910">That if we had but ventured on the sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121920">I presently had been his prisoner. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121930">These two days have we kept us in the cave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121940">Eating such herbs as the ground did afford:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121950">And now through hunger are we both constrained</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121960">Like fearful snakes to creep out step by step,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121970">And see if we may get us any food. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121980">And in good time, see yonder sits a man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e121990">Spreading a hungry dinner on the grass. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122000">Bullithrumble spies them, and puts up his meat. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122010" who="A68114-bullithrumble">
          <speaker>Bull.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e122020">These are some felonians, that seek to rob me, well, I'll make myself a good deal valianter than I am indeed, and if they will needs creep into kindred with me, I'll betake me to my old occupation, and run away.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122030" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Corcut.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e122040">Haile groom. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122050" who="A68114-bullithrumble">
          <speaker>Bull.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e122060">Good lord sir, you are deceived, my name's master Bullithrumble: this is some cozening coney-catching crossbiter, that would fain persuade me he knows me, and so under a tense of familiarity and acquaintance, uncle me of victuals.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122070" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Corcut.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e122080">Then Bullithrumble, if that be thy name:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122090" who="A68114-bullithrumble">
          <speaker>Bull.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e122100">My name sir o lord yes, and if you will not believe me, I will bring my godfathers and godmothers, and they shall swear it upon the font-stone, and upon the church book too, where it is written.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122110" who="A68114-bullithrumble">
          <pb facs="30"/>
          <speaker>Bull.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e122120">Mass, I think he be some justice of peace, ad quorum, and omnium populorum, how he famines me: a christian, yes marry am I sir, yes verily and do believe: and it please you I'll go forward in my catechism.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122130" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Corcut.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e122140">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122150">Then bullithrumble, by that blessed Christ,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122160">And by the tomb where he was buried,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122170">By sovereign hope which thou conceivest in him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122180">Whom dead, as everliving thou adorest. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122190" who="A68114-bullithrumble">
          <speaker>Bull.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e122200">O lord help me, I shall be torn in pieces with devils and goblins.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122210" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Corcut.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e122220">By all the joys thou hopest to have in heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e122230">Give some meat to poor hunger-starved men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122240" who="A68114-bullithrumble">
          <speaker>Bulli.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e122250">O, these are as a man should say beggars: now will I be as stately to them as if I were master pigwiggen our constable: well sirs come before me, tell me if I should entertain you, would you not steal?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122260" who="A68114-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e122270">If we did mean so sir, we would not make your worship acquainted with it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122280" who="A68114-bullithrumble">
          <speaker>Bulli.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e122290">A good well nutrimented lad: well if you will keep my sheep truly and honestly, keeping your hands from lying and slandering, and your tongues from picking and stealing, you shall be master Bullithrumble's servitures.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122300" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Corcut.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e122310">With all our hearts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122320" who="A68114-bullithrumble">
          <speaker>Bulli.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e122330">Then come on and follow me, we will have a hog's cheek, and a dish of tripes, and a society of puddings, and to field: a society of puddings, did you mark that well used metaphor? Another would have said, a company of puddings: if you dwell with me long sirs, I shall make you as eloquent as our parson himself.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e122340">Exeunt Corcut, and Bullithrumble.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122350" who="A68114-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e122360">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122370">Now is the time when I may be enriched. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122380">The brothers that were sent by Selimus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122390">To take my lord, prince Corcut prisoner,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122400">Finding him fled, proposed large rewards</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122410">To them that could declare where he remains. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122420">Faith I'll to them and get the portuguese,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122430"><pb facs="30"/> though by the bargain Corcut lose his head. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e122440">Exit page.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e122450">Enter Selimus, Sinam-bassa, the courses of Mustaffa and Aga, with funeral pomp, Mustaffa, and the janissaries.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122460" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e122470">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122480">Why thus must Selim blind his subject eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122490">And strain his own to weep for Bajazet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122500">They will not dream I made him away,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122510">When thus they see me with religious pomp,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122520">To celebrate his tomb-black mortuary. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122530">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e122540">(To himself.</stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122550">And though my heart cast in an iron mould,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122560">Cannot admit the smallest dram of grief. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122570">Yet that I may be thought to love him well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122580">I'll mourn in show, though I rejoice indeed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122590">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e122600">To the courses.</stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122610">Thus after he hath five long ages lived,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122620">The sacred phoenix of Arabia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122630">Loadeth his wings with precious perfumes</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122640">And on the altar of the golden sun,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122650">Offers himself a grateful sacrifice. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122660">Long didst thou live triumphant Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122670">A fear unto thy greatest enemies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122680">And now that death the conqueror of Kings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122690">Dislodged hath thy never dying soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122700">To flee unto the heavens from whence she came</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122710">And leave her frail, earth pavilion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122720">Thy body in this ancient monument,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122730">Where our great predecessors sleep in rest:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122740">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e122750">Suppose the temple of Mahomet. </stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122760">Thy woeful son Selimus thus doth place. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122770">Thou wert the phoenix of this age of ours,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122780">And diedst wrapped in the sweet perfumes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122790">Of thy magnific deeds, whose lasting praise</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122800">Mounteth to highest heaven with golden wings. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122810">Princes come bear your emperor company</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122820">In, till the days of mourning be o'er past,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122830">And then we mean to rouse false Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122840"><pb facs="31"/> and cast him forth of Macedonia. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e122850">Exeunt all.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e122860">Enter Hali, Cali, Corcuts page, and one or two sould●erss.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122870" who="A68114-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e122880">My lords, if I bring you not where Corcut is, then let me be hanged, but if I deliver him up into your hands, then let me have the reward due to so good a deed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122890" who="A68114-hali">
          <speaker>Hali.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e122900">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122910">Page, if thou show us where thy master is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122920">Be sure thou shalt be honoured for the deed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e122930">And high exalted above other men. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e122940">Enter Corcut, and Bullithrumble. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122950" who="A68114-page">
          <speaker>Page.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e122960">That same is he, that in disguised robes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e122970">Accompanies yond shepherd to the fields. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e122980" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e122990">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123000">The sweet content that country life affords,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123010">Passeth the royal pleasures of a King:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123020">For there our joys are interlaced with fears:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123030">But here no fear nor care is harboured,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123040">But a sweet calm of a most quiet state. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123050">Ah Corcut, would thy brother Selimus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123060">But let thee live▪ here shouldst thou spend thy life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123070">Feeding thy sheep among these grassy lands. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123080">But sure I wonder where my page is gone. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123090" who="A68114-hali">
          <speaker>Hali.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e123100">Corcut. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123110" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Corcut.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e123120">A y-me, who nameth me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123130" who="A68114-hali">
          <speaker>Hal●.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e123140">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123150">Hali, the governor of Magnesia. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123160">Poor prince, thou thoughtst in these disguised weeds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123170">To mask unseen: and happily thou mightst,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123180">But that thy page betrayed thee to us.</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123190">And be not wrath with us unhappy prince,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123200">If we do what our sovereign commands. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123210">'Tis for thy death that Selim sends for thee. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123220" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e123230">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123240">Thus I like poor Amphiaraus, sought</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123250">By hiding my estate in shepherd's coat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123260">T escape the angry wrath of Selimus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123270">But as his wife false Eriphyle did</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123280">Betray his safety for a chain of gold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123290"><pb facs="31"/> so my false page hath vilely dealt with me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123300">Pray God that thou mayst prosper so as she. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123310">Hali, I know thou sorrowest for my case,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123320">But it is bootless, come and let us go,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123330">Corcut is ready, since it is must be so. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123340" who="A68114-cali">
          <speaker>Cali.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e123350">Shepheard. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123360" who="A68114-bullithrumble">
          <speaker>Bull●.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e123370">That's my profession sir. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123380" who="A68114-cali">
          <speaker>Cali.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e123390">Come, you must go with us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123400" who="A68114-bullithrumble">
          <speaker>Bull●.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e123410">Who I? Alas sir, I have a wife and seventeen cradles rocking, two ploughs going, two barns filling, and a great heard of beasts feeding, and you should utterly undo me to take me to such a great charge.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123420" who="A68114-cali">
          <speaker>Cal●.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e123430">Well there is no remedy. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e123440">Exeunt all, but bullithrumble stealing from them closely away.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123450" who="A68114-bullithrumble">
          <speaker>Bull●.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A68114-e123460">The moors the pity go with you quoth he, marry that had been the way to preferment, down Holborn up Tyburn: well I'll keep my best joint from the strappado as well as I can hereafter, I'll have no more servants.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e123470">Exit running away.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e123480">Enter Selimus, Sinam-bassa, Mustaffa, and the janissaries.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123490" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e123500">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123510">Sinam, we hear our brother Acomat</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123520">Is fled away from Macedonia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123530">To ask for aid of Persian Ismael,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123540">And the Egyptian soldan our chief foes. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123550" who="A68114-sinam">
          <speaker>Sinam.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e123560">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123570">Herein my lord I like his enterprise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123580">For if they give him aid as sure they will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123590">Being your highness vowed enemies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123600">You shall have just cause for to war on them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123610">For giving succour 'gainst you, to your foe. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123620">You know they are two mighty potentates,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123630">And may be hurtful neighbours to your grace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123640">And to enrich the Turkish diadem. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123650"><pb facs="32"/>With two so worthy kingdoms as they are,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123660">Would be eternal glory to your name. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123670" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e123680">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123690">By heaven's Sinam, thou'rt a warrior,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123700">And worthy counsellor unto a King. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123710">Sound within. <stage xml:id="A68114-e123720">Enter Calihali and Hal●, with Corcut and his page.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123730">How now, what news? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123740" who="A68114-cali">
          <speaker>Cal●.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e123750">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123760">My gracious lord, we here present to you</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123770">Your brother corcut, whom in Smirna coasts</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123780">Feeding a flock of sheep upon a down,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123790">His traitorous page betrayed to our hands. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123800" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e123810">Thanks ye bold brothers, but for that false part,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e123820">Let the vile page be famished to death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123830" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Corcut.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e123840">Selim, in this I see thou art a prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e123850">To punish treason with condign reward. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123860" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e123870">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123880">O sir, I love the fruit that treason brings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123890">But those that are the traitors, them I hate. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123900">But Corcut, could not your philosophy</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123910">Keep you safe from my janissaries hands. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123920">We thought you had old Gyges' wondrous ring,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123930">That so you were invisible to us. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e123940" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e123950">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123960">Selim, thou dealest unkindly with thy brother,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123970">To seek my death, and make a jest of me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123980">Upbraid'st thou me with my philosophy? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e123990">Why this I learned by studying learned arts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124000">That I can bear my fortune as it falls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124010">And that I fear no whit thy cruelty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124020">Since thou wilt deal no otherwise with me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124030">Than thou hast dealt with aged Bajazet. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e124040" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e124050">By heaven's Corcut, thou shalt surely die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e124060">For slandering Selim with my father's death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e124070" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e124080">Then let me freely speak my mind this once,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e124090">For thou shalt never hear me speak again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e124100" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e124110">Nay we can give such losers' leave to speak. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e124120" who="A68114-corcut">
          <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e124130">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124140">Then Selim, hear thy brother's dying words,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124150">And mark them well, for ere thou die thyself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124160"><pb facs="32"/> thou shalt perceive all things will come to pass,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124170">That Corcut doth divine before his death. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124180">Since my vain flight from fair magnesia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124190">Selim I have conversed with Christians,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124200">And learned of them the way to save my soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124210">And please the anger of the highest god. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124220">'Tis he that made this pure crystalline vault</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124230">Which hangeth over our unhappy heads,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124240">From thence he doth behold each sinner's fault:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124250">And though our sins under our feet he treads,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124260">And for a while seem for to wink at us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124270">But is to recall us from our ways. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124280">But if we do like headstrong sons neglect</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124290">To hearken to our loving father's voice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124300">Then in his anger will he us reject,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124310">And give us over to our wicked choice. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124320">Selim before his dreadful majesty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124330">There lies a book written with bloody lines,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124340">Where our offences all are registered. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124350">Which if we do not hastily repent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124360">We are reserved to lasting punishment. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124370">Thou wretched Selimus haste greatest need</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124380">To ponder these things in thy secret thoughts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124390">If thou consider what strange massacres</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124400">And cruel murders thou hast caused be done. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124410">Think on the death of woeful Bajazet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124420">Doth not his ghost still haunt thee for revenge? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124430">Selim in Chiurlu didst thou set upon</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124440">Our aged father in his sudden flight:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124450">In Chiurlu shalt thou die a grievous death. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124460">And if thou wilt not change thy greedy mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124470">Thy soul shall be tormented in dark hell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124480">Where woe, and woe, and never ceasing woe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124490">Shall sound about thy ever-damned soul. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124500">Now Selim I have spoken, let me die:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124510">I never will entreat thee for my life. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124520"><pb facs="33"/>Selim farewell: thou god of Christians,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124530">Receive my dying soul into thy hands. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e124540">(Strangles him.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e124550" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Sel●.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e124560">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124570">What is he dead? then Selimus is safe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124580">And hath no more corrivals in the crown. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124590">For as for Acomat he soon shall see,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124600">His Persian aid cannot save him from me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124610">Now Sinam march to fair Amasia walls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124620">Where Acomat's stout Queen immures herself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124630">And girt the city with a warlike siege,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124640">For since her husband is my enemy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124650">I see no cau●e why she should be my friend. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124660">They say young Amurath and Aladin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124670">Her bastard brood, are come to succour her. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124680">But ●●e prevent this their officiousness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124690">And send their soul down to their grandfather. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124700">Mustaffa you shall keep Byzantium,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124710">While I and Sinam girt Amasia. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e124720">Exit Selimus, Sinam, janissaries all save one▪</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e124730" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e124740">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124750">It grieve my soul that Baiazet's fair line,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124760">Should be eclipsed thus by Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124770">Whose cruel soul will never be at rest</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124780">Till none remain of Ottomans fair race</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124790">But he himself: yet for old Bajazet</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124800">Loved Mustaffa de●●e unto his death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124810">I will show mercy to his family. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124820">Go sirrah, post to Acomat's young sons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124830">And bid them as they mean to save their lives,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124840">To fly in haste from fair Amasia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124850">Lest cruel Selim put them to the sword. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124860">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e124870">Exit one to Amurath and Aladin. </stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124880">And now Mustaffa, prepare thou thy neck,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124890">For thou art next to die by Selim's hands. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124900">Stern Sinam bassa grudgeth still at thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124910">And crabbed Hali stormeth at thy life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124920">All repine that thou art honoured so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124930">To be the brother of their emperor. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124940">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e124950"><pb facs="33"/>Enter Solyma. </stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124960">But wherefore comes my lovely Solyma? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e124970" who="A68114-solima">
          <speaker>Soly.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e124980">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e124990">Mustaffa I am come to seek thee out,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125000">If ever thy distressed Solyma,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125010">Found grace and favour in thy manly heart:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125020">Fly hence with me unto some desert land,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125030">For if we tarry here we are but dead. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125040">This night when fair Lucina's shining wain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125050">Was passed the chair of bright Cassiopey,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125060">A fearful vision appeared to me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125070">Methought Mustaffa, I beheld thy neck</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125080">So often folded in my loving arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125090">In foul disgrace of bassas fair degree,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125100">With a vile halter basely compassed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125110">And while I poured my tears on thy dead corpses,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125120">A greedy lion with wide gaping throat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125130">Seized on my trembling body with his feet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125140">And in a moment rent me all to naught. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125150">Fly sweet Mustaffa, or we be but dead. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e125160" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e125170">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125180">Why should we fly beauteous Solyma,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125190">Moved by a vain and a fantastic dream? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125200">Or if we did fly whither should we fly? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125210">I● to the farthest part of Asia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125220">Know'st thou not Solyma, Kings have long hands? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125230">Come, come, my joy, return again with me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125240">And banish hence these melancholy thoughts. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e125250">(Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e125260">Enter Aladin, Murath, the messenger.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e125270" who="A68114-aladin">
          <speaker>Aladin.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e125280">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125290">Messenger is it true that Selimus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125300">Is not far hence encamped with his host? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125310">And means he to disjoin the hapless sons</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125320">From helping our distressed mother's town? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e125330" who="A68114-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e125340">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125350">'Tis true my lord, and if you love your lives</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125360">Fly from the bounds of his dominions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125370">For he you know is most unmerciful. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e125380" who="A68114-amurath">
          <speaker>Amu.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e125390">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125400">Here messenger take this for thy reward. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125410">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e125420">Exit mess.</stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125430">But we sweet Aladin, let us depart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125440">Now in the quiet silence of the night</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125450"><pb facs="34"/> that ere the windows of the morn be ope,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125460">We may be far enough from Selimus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125470">I'll to Aegyptus. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e125480" who="A68114-alinda">
          <speaker>Alinda.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e125490">I to Persia. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e125500">(Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e125510">Enter Selimus, Sinam, Hali, Cali, janissaries. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e125520" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e125530">But is it certain Hali they are gone? </l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e125540">And that Mustaffa moved them to fly? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e125550" who="A68114-hali">
          <speaker>Hali.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e125560">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125570">Certain my lord, I met the messenger</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125580">As he returned from young Alinda:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125590">And learned of them, Mustaffa, was the man</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125600">That certified the princes of your will. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e125610" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e125620">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125630">It is enough: Mustaffa shall aby</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125640">At a dear price his pitiful intent. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125650">Hali go fetch Mustaffa and his wife. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125660">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e125670">(Exit Hali.</stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125680">For though she be sister to Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125690">Yet loves she him better than Selimus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125700">So that if he do die at our command,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125710">And she should live: soon would she work a mean</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125720">To work revenge for her mustaffas death. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125730">
              <stage xml:id="A68114-e125740">Enter Hali, Mustaffa, and Solima.</stage>
            </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125750">False of thy faith, and traitor to thy King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125760">Did we so highly always honour thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125770">And dost thou thus requite our love with treason,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125780">For why shouldst thou send to young Alinda,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125790">And Amurath, the sons of Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125800">To give them notice of our secrecies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125810">Knowing they were my vowed enemies? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e125820" who="A68114-mustaffa">
          <speaker>Must.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e125830">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125840">I do not seek to lesson my offence</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125850">Great Selimus, but truly do protest</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125860">I did it not for hatred of your grace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125870">So help me God and holy Mahomet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125880">But for I grieved to see the famous stock</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125890">Of worthy Bajazet fall to decay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125900">Therefore I sent the princes both away. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125910">Your highness knows Mustaffa was the man</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125920">That saved you in the battle of Churlu,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125930"><pb facs="34"/> when I and all the warlike janissaries</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125940">Had hedged your person in a dangerous ring. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125950">Yet I took pity on your danger there,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125960">And made a way for you to scape by flight. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125970">But those your bassas have incensed you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125980">Repining at Mustaffa's dignity. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e125990">Stern Sinam grinds his angry teeth at me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126000">Old Halie's sons do bend their brows at me●</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126010">And are aggrieved that Mustaffa hath</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126020">Shown himself a better man than they. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126030">And yet the janisars mourn for me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126040">They know Mustaffa never proved false. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126050">Ay, I have been as true to Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126060">As ever subject to his sovereign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126070">So help me God and holy Mahomet. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e126080" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e126090">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126100">You did it not because you hated us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126110">But for you loved the sons of Acomat. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126120">Sinam, I charge thee quickly strangle him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126130">He loves not me that love's mine enemies. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126140">As for your holy protestation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126150">It cannot enter into Selim's ears:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126160">For why Mustaffa? every merchant man</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126170">Will praise his own ware be it ne'er so bad. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e126180" who="A68114-solima">
          <speaker>Solima.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e126190">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126200">For Solima's sake mighty Selimus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126210">Spare my mustaffas life, and let me die:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126220">Or if thou wilt not be so gracious,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126230">Yet let me die before I see his death. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e126240" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e126250">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126260">Nay Selima, yourself shall also die,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126270">Because you may be in the selfsame fault. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126280">Why stayest thou Sinam? strangle him I say.</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126290">Sinam<stage xml:id="A68114-e126300">Strangles him.</stage></l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e126310" who="A68114-solima">
          <speaker>Soli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e126320">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126330">Ah Selimus, he made thee emperor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126340">And wilt thou thus requite his benefits? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126350">Thou art a cruel tiger and no man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126360">That coul'st endure to see before thy face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126370">So brave a man as my Mustaffa was,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126380"><pb facs="35"/> cruelly strangled for so small a fault. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e126390" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e126400">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126410">Thou shalt not after live him Solima. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126420">'Twere pity thou shouldst want the company</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126430">Of thy dear husband: Sinam strangle her. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126440">And now to fair Amasia let us march. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126450">Acomat's wife, and her unmanly host,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126460">Will not be able to endure our sight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126470">Much less make strong resistance in hard fight. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e126480">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e126490">Enter Acomat, Tonombeius, visir, Regan, and their soldiers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e126500" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e126510">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126520">Welcome my lords into my native soil,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126530">The crown whereof by right is due to me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126540">Though Selim by the janissaries choice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126550">Through usurpation keep the same from me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126560">You know contrary to my father's mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126570">He was enthronised by the bassas will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126580">And after his enstalling, wickedly</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126590">By poison made good Bajazet to die. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126600">And strangled Corcut, and exiled me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126610">These injuries we come for to revenge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126620">And raise his siege from fair Amasia walls. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e126630" who="A68114-tonombey">
          <speaker>Tonom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e126640">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126650">Prince of Amasia, and the rightful heir</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126660">Unto the mighty Turkish diadem:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126670">With willing heart great Tonombey hath left</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126680">Egyptian Nilus and my father's court,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126690">To aid thee in thy undertaken war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126700">And by the great Usan-cassano's ghost,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126710">Companion unto mighty Tamberlaine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126720">From whom my father lineally descends,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126730">Fortune shall show herself too cross to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126740">But we will thrust Selimus from his throne,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126750">And revest Acomat in the empery. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e126760" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e126770">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126780">Thanks to the uncontrolled Tonombey. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126790">But let us haste us to Amasia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126800">To secure my besieged citizens. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126810"><pb facs="35"/>None but my Queen is overseer there,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126820">And too too weak is all her policy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126830">Against so great a foe as Selimus. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e126840">Exeunt all</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e126850">Enter Selimus, Sinam, hali, Cali, and the janissaries.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e126860" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e126870">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126880">Summon a parley sirs that we may know</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126890">Whether these mushrooms here will yield or no. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126900">A parley: Queen of Amasia, and her soldiers on the walls. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e126910" who="A68114-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e126920">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126930">What cravest thou bloodthirsty parricide? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126940">Is't not enough that thou hast foully slain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126950">Thy loving father noble Bajazet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126960">And strangled Corcut thine unhappy brother</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126970">Slain brave Mustaffa, and fair Selima? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126980">Because they favoured my unhappy sons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e126990">But thou must yet seek for more massacres ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127000">Go, wash thy guilty hands in lukewarm blood. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127010">Enrich thy soldiers with robberies:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127020">Yet do the heavens still bear an equal eye,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127030">And vengeance follows thee even at the heels. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e127040" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e127050">Queen of Amasia, wilt thou yield thyself? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e127060" who="A68114-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e127070">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127080">First shall the overflowing Euripus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127090">Of swift Euboea stop his restless course</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127100">And Phaeb's bright globe bring the day from the West,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127110">And quench his hot flames in the Eastern sea. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127120">Thy bloody sword ungracious Selimus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127130">Sheathed in the bowels of thy dearest friends:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127140">Thy wicked guard which still attends on thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127150">Fleshing themselves in murder, lust, and rape:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127160">What hope of favour ▪ what security? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127170">Rather what death do they not promise me? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127180">Then think not Selimus that we will yield,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127190">But look for strong resistance at our hands. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e127200" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli,</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e127210">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127220">Why then you never daunted janissaries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127230">Advance your shields and uncontrolled spears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127240"><pb facs="36"/> your conquering hands in foemen's blood embay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127250">For Selimus himself will lead the way. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127260">Alarum, beats them off the walls. Alarum. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e127270">Enter Selimus, Sinam, Hali, Cali, janissaries, with Acomat's Queen prisoner.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e127280" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Se.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e127290">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127300">Now sturdy dame, where are your men of war</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127310">To guard your person from my angry sword? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127320">What? though braved us on your city walls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127330">Like to that amanonian Menalip,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127340">Leaving the banks of swift-streamed Thermodon</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127350">To challenge combat with great Hercules:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127360">Yet Selimus hath plucked your haughty plumes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127370">Nor can your spouse rebellious Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127380">Nor Alinda, or Amurath your sons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127390">Deliver you from our victorious hands. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e127400" who="A68114-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e127410">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127420">Selim I scorn thy threatenings as thyself. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127430">And though ill hap hath given me to thy hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127440">Yet will I never beg my life of thee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127450">Fortune may chance to frown as much on thee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127460">And Acomat whom thou dost scorn so much,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127470">May take thy base Tartarian concubine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127480">As well as thou hast taken his loyal Queen. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127490">Thou hast not fortune tied in a chain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127500">Nor dost thou like a wary pilot sit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127510">And wisely stir this all containing barge. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127520">Thou art a man as those whom thou hast slain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127530">And some of them were better far than thou. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e127540" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e127550">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127560">Strangle her Hali, let her scold no more. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127570">Now let us march to meet with Acomat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127580">He brings with him that great Egyptian bug,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127590">Strong Tonombey, Usan-cassano's son. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127600">But we shall soon with our fine tempered swords,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127610">Engrave our prowess on their bugane●s,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127620">Were they as mighty and as fell of force,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127630">As those old earth-bred brothers, which once</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127640"><pb facs="36"/> heap hill on hill to scale the starry sky,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127650">When Briareus armed with a hundreth hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127660">Flung forth a hundreth mountains at great Jove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127670">And when the monstrous giant monichus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127680">Hurled mount Olimpus at great Mars his targe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127690">And darted cedars at Minerva's shield. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e127700">Exeunt all.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e127710">Alarms enter Selimus, Sinam, Cali, Hali, and the janissaries, at one door, and Acomat, Tonombey, Regan, Vissr, and their soldiers at another.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e127720" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e127730">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127740">What are the urchins crept out of their dens,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127750">Under the conduct of this porcupine? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127760">Dost thou not tremble Acomat at us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127770">To see how courage masketh in our looks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127780">And white-winged victory sits on our swords? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127790">Captain of Egypt, thou that vantest thyself</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127800">Sprung from great Tamberlaine the Scythia thief,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127810">Who bade the enterprise this bold attempt,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127820">To set thy feet within the Turkish confines</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127830">Or lift thy hands against our majesty? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e127840" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e127850">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127860">Brother of Trebisond, your squared words,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127870">And broad-mouthed terms, can never conquer us.</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127880">We come resolved to pull the Turkish crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127890">Which thou dost wrongfully detain from me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127900">By conquering sword from of thy coward crest. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e127910" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e127920">Acomat, sith the quarrel toucheth none</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e127930">But thee and me: I dare, and challenge thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e127940" who="A68114-tonombey">
          <speaker>Tonum.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e127950">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127960">Should he accept the combat of a boy? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127970">Whose unripe years and far unripe wit</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127980">Like to the bold foolhardy Phaeton</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e127990">That sought to rule the chariot of the sun,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128000">Hath moved thee t'undertake an empiry. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e128010" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e128020">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128030">Thou that resolvest in peremptory terms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128040">To call him boy that scorns to cope with thee:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128050">But thou canst better use thy bragging blade,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128060">Then ●●ou canst rule thy overflowing tongue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128070">Soon shalt thou know that Selim's mighty arm</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128080"><pb facs="37"/> is able to overthrow poor Tonombey. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e128090">Alarum, Tonombey beats Hali and Cali in. Selim beats Tonombey in● alarum, exit Tonombey. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e128100" who="A68114-tonombey">
          <speaker>Tonom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e128110">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128120">The field is lost, and Acomat is taken. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128130">Ah Tonombey, how canst thou show thy face</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128140">To thy victorious sire, thus conquered. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128150">A matchless knight is warlike Selimus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128160">And like a shepherd amongst a swarm of gnats,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128170">Dings down the flying Persians with their swords. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128180">Twice I encountered with him hand to hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128190">And twice returned foiled and ashamed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128200">For never yet since I could manage arms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128210">Could any match with mighty Tonombey,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128220">But this heroic emperor Selimus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128230">Why stand I still, and rather do not fly</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128240">The great occision which the victors make? </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e128250">Exit Tonombey.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A68114-e128260">Alarum. Enter Selimus, Sinam bassa, with Acomat prisoner, Hali, Cali, janissaries. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e128270" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e128280">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128290">Thus when the coward Greeks fled to their ships,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128300">The noble Hector all besmeared in blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128310">Returned in triumph to the walls of Troy. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128320">A gallant trophy, bassas have we won,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128330">Beating the never-foiled Tonombey,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128340">And hewing passage through the Persians. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128350">As when a lion raving for his prey,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128360">Falleth upon a drove of horned balls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128370">And rends them strongly in his kingly paws. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128380">Or Mars armed in his adamantive coat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128390">Mounted upon his fiery-shining wain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128400">Scatters the troops of warlike Thracians,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128410">And warms cold Hebras with hot streams of blood. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128420">Brave Sinam, for thy noble prisoner,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128430">Thou shalt be general of my janissaries. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128440"><pb facs="37"/>And Belierbey of fair Natalia. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128450">Now Acomat, thou monster of the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128460">Why stoop'st thou not with reverence to thy King? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e128470" who="A68114-acomat">
          <speaker>Aco.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e128480">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128490">Selim if thou have gotten victory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128500">Then use it to thy contentation. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128510">If I had conquered, know assuredly</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128520">I would have said as much and more to thee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128530">Know I disdain them as I do thyself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128540">And scorn to stoop or bend my lordly knee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128550">To such a tyrant as is Selimus. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128560">Thou slewest my Queen without regard or care,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128570">Of love or duty, or thine own good name. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128580">Then Selim take that which thy hap doth give,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128590">Disgraced, displaced, I longer loath to live. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A68114-e128600" who="A68114-selimus">
          <speaker>Seli.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A68114-e128610">
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128620">Then Sinam strangle him: now he is dead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128630">Who doth remain to trouble Selimus? </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128640">Now am I King alone and none but I. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128650">For since my father's death until this time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128660">I never wanted some competitors. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128670">Now as the weary wand'ring traveller</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128680">That hath his steps guided through many lands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128690">Through boiling soil of Africa and Ind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128700">When he returns unto his native home:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128710">Sits down among his friends, and with delight</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128720">Declares the travels he hath overpast. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128730">So mayst thou Selimus, for thou hast trodden</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128740">The monster-garden paths, that lead to crowns. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128750">Ha, ha, I smile to think how Selimus</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128760">Like the Egyptian Ibis hath expelled</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128770">Those swarming armies of swift-winged snakes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128780">That sought to overrun my territories,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128790">When sultering heat the earth's green children spoils</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128800">From forth the fens of venomous Africa,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128810">The generation of those flying snakes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128820">Do band themselves in troops, and take their way</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128830">To Nilus' bounds: but those industrious birds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128840"><pb facs="38"/> those ibides meet them in set array,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128850">And eat them up like to a swarm of gnats,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128860">Preventing such a mischief from the land. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128870">But see how unkind nature deals with them:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128880">From out their eggs rises the basilisk,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128890">Whose only sight kills millions of men. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128900">When Acomat lifted his ungracious hands</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128910">Against my aged father Bajazet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128920">They sent for me, and I like Egypt's bird</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128930">Have rid that monster, and his fellow mates. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128940">But as from Ibis springs the basilisk. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128950">Whose only touch burneth up stones and trees. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128960">So Selimus hath proved a cockatrice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128970">And clean consumed all the family</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128980">Of noble Ottoman, except himself. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e128990">And now to you my neighbour emperors,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e129000">That durst lend aid to Selim's enemies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e129010">Sinam those soldanes of the orient,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e129020">Egypt and Persia, Selimus will quell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e129030">Or he himself will sink to lowest hell. </l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e129040">This winter will we rest and breathe ourselves:</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e129050">But soon as Zephyrus sweet smelling blast</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e129060">Shall greatly creep over the floury meads,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e129070">We'll have a fling at the Egyptian crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A68114-e129080">And join it unto ours, or lose our own. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A68114-e129090">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div type="conclusion" xml:id="A68114-e129100">
        <pb facs="38"/>
        <head>Conclusion.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A68114-e129110">
          <l xml:id="A68114-e129120">Thus have we brought victorious Selimus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e129130">Unto the crown of great Arabia:</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e129140">Next shall you see him with triumphant sword</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e129150">Dividing kingdoms into equal shares,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e129160">And give them to their warlike followers. </l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e129170">If this first part gentles, do like you well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A68114-e129180">The second part, shall greater murders tell. </l>
        </lg>
        <trailer xml:id="A68114-e129190">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A68114"><item xml:id="A68114-bajazet" n="38">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-bajazet</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">38</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-acomat" n="37">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-acomat</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">37</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-selimus" n="37">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-selimus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">37</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-aga" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-aga</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-mustaffa" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-mustaffa</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-corcut" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-corcut</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-bullithrumble" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-bullithrumble</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-mahomet" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-mahomet</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-sinam" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-sinam</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-cherseoli" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-cherseoli</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-abraham" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-abraham</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-cali" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-cali</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-zonara" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-zonara</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-hali" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-hali</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-ottrante" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-ottrante</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-page" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-page</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-messenger" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-tonombey" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-tonombey</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-solima" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-solima</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-visir" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-visir</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-queen" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-queen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-belierbey" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-belierbey</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-occhiali" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-occhiali</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-regan" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-regan</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-all" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-aladin" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-aladin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-alinda" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-alinda</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-unassigned" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A68114-amurath" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A68114-amurath</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

