<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1 Beauty Love and Wit<date type="creation_date">1662</date></title>
        <author>Cavendish, Margaret</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nicole Sheriko</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A53060_14.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>356 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">11861873</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing N868.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">50022</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53060</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
            <author>Newcastle, William Cavendish, 1592-1676.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[24], 679 [i.e. 675], [4] p. : ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by A. Warren, for John Martyn, James Allestry, and Tho. Dicas ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1662.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>First edition.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Errata: p. [4] at end.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A53060_14-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A53060_14-e100020">
      <div n="1" type="play" xml:id="A53060_14-e100030">
        <pb facs="256" n="489"/>
        <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A53060_14-e100040">
          <list xml:id="A53060_14-e100050">
            <head>The actors names.</head>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100060">Monsieur Nobilissimo. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100070">Monsieur esperance. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100080">Monsieur fantasy. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100090">Monsieur poverty. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100100">Monsieur adviser, and several other gentlemen.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100110">Admiration. Mademoiselle la bells wooers.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100120">Vainglory. Mademoiselle la bells wooers.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100130">Pride. Mademoiselle la bells wooers.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100140">Ambition. Mademoiselle la bells wooers.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100150">Mademoiselle esperance, wife to monsieur esperance. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100160">Mademoiselle la belle. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100170">Mademoiselle Amour. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100180">Mademoiselle grand esprit. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100190">Mademoiselle bon. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100200">Mademoiselle Tell-truth. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100210">Mademoiselle spiteful. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100220">Mademoiselle detractor. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_14-e100230">Mademoiselle malicious. </item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A53060_14-e100240">
          <pb facs="257"/>
          <pb facs="257" n="491"/>
          <head>The first part of natures three daughters, beauty, love, and wit. </head>
          <head type="sub">Act i.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e100250">
            <head>Scene 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e100260">Enter mademoiselle detractor, mademoiselle spightfull, mademoiselle malicious, and mademoiselle Tell-truth. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100270" who="A53060_14-tell-truth">
              <speaker>Tell-truth.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100280">The lady nature's daughters are the only ladies that are admired, praised, adored, worshipped, and sued to; all other women are despised.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100290" who="A53060_14-spightfull">
              <speaker>Spightfull.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100300">We may go into a nunnery; for we shall never get servants, nor husbands, as long as they live.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100310" who="A53060_14-tell-truth">
              <speaker>Tell-truth.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100320">Why there are but three of them, and three women cannot serve and content all the men in the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100330" who="A53060_14-detractor">
              <speaker>Detractor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100340">No, but they may discontent all the men so much, as to make them all to be malcontented lovers, who will reject all, because they cannot have what they desire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100350" who="A53060_14-malicious">
              <speaker>Malicious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100360">Let us make a faction against them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100370" who="A53060_14-spightfull">
              <speaker>Spightfull.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100380">Alas what faction against them, can hurt and destroy love, wit, and beauty?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100390" who="A53060_14-detractor">
              <speaker>Detractor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100400">Jealousy will weaken love, dispraise will disgrace wit, and beauty, time will soon bring that to decay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100410" who="A53060_14-tell-truth">
              <speaker>Tell-truth.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100420">But jealousy cannot weaken true and virtuous love, nor dispraise cannot disgrace pure wit, nor time cannot decay the beauty of the mind; wherefore all the faction you can make against them, will do them no hurt; besides, you will be condemned by all the masculine sex, if not punished with infamy, for your treachery; and since you cannot do them harm, your best way will be to imitate them for your own good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100430" who="A53060_14-spightfull">
              <speaker>Spightfull.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100440">So we shall be laughed at, and stared on as monkeys, and scorned; forasmuch as we offer at that which is beyond our abilities, and whatsoever is forced, and constrained, appeareth ridiculous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100450" who="A53060_14-malicious">
              <speaker>Malicious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100460">Come let us leave speaking of them, and thinking of them, if we can.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e100470">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e100480">
            <pb facs="258" n="492"/>
            <head>Scene 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e100490">Enter monsieur esperance, and his wife mademoiselle esperance. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100500" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100510">Surely wife you do not love me, you are not any way kind to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100520" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100530">True love husband, is not so fond as serviceable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100540" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100550">But true love will express itself sometimes: for if you did truly love me, you would hang about my neck, as if you meant to dwell there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100560" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100570">If I thought my kindness might not surfeit your affection, I would hang about your neck, as the earth to the centre, and as you move should bear me still about you; but I am afraid if overfond, you should be weary of me, and account me a trouble, and I had rather starve all my delights, than make you loathe my company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100580" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100590">This is but an excuse wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100600" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100610">Why are you jealous, that you think my words speak not my thoughts? have I behaved myself so indiscreetly, or have my actions been so light, as you believe I shall be wanton?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100620" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100630">No, I do not fear your virtue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100640" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100650">Do you fear my indiscretion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100660" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100670">I hope you will give me no cause to fear, although husbands are oftener dishonoured by their wives indiscretions, than their inconstant affections.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100680" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100690">Pray be confident, that I shall have a greater care of your honour, than of my own life.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e100700">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e100710">
            <head>Scene 3.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e100720">Enter two gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100730" who="A53060_14-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100740">The lady nature's three daughters, namely wit, beauty, and love, are the sweetest, and most virtuous ladies in the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100750" who="A53060_14-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100760">I have heard so much of their fame, as I have a great desire to see them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100770" who="A53060_14-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100780">You may see the lady wit, for she doth discourse often in public; but for the other two sisters, they are somewhat more retired.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100790" who="A53060_14-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100800">How shall we know the time, that the lady wit discourses in public?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100810" who="A53060_14-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100820">I am now going to see if I can get a place, where I may</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100830" who="A53060_14-yyyy_2">
              <pb facs="258" n="493"/>
              <speaker>2 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100840">I will go with you, if you will give me leave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100850" who="A53060_14-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100860">With all my heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e100870">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e100880">
            <head>Scene 4.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e100890">Enter monsieur nobilissimo, and monsieur Poverty. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100900" who="A53060_14-poverty">
              <speaker>Monsieur poverty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100910">My noble lord, I am a gentleman, one that is ruined by fortune's spite, and not by my own carelessness, vanity, luxury, or prodigality; for my poverty is honest: but though my poverty hath an honest face, yet it is ashamed to appear in the open sight of public knowledge, which makes me whisper my wants to your lordship's private ear.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100920" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Monsieur nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100930">Sir, if your necessities can conceal themselves, they shall never be divulged by me; and what I can honestly give you out of my estate, and not very imprudently from myself, I shall freely, and secretly, distribute to you, and such as are in your condition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100940" who="A53060_14-poverty">
              <speaker>Monsieur poverty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e100950">Your lordship's servant.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e100960">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e100970">
            <head>Scene 5.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e100980">Enter mademoiselle amor alone.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e100990" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101000">The mind is the best tutor, and ought to instruct the senses how to choose; for the senses are but as the working labourers, to bring life's materials in; but oh my senses have betrayed my mind, in bringing through my ears, and eyes, beauty, and wit, which like as creeping serpents, got passage to my heart, and winding round about with flattering embraces, yet sting the peace, and quiet of my mind, raising therein blisters of discontent, causing an anguish of restless thoughts, which work, and beat like pulsive pain.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101010">But oh had I been born both deaf and blind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101020">Then might I scape this hell tormenting mind;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101030">His wit like various music pierced my ear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101040">Some being solemn, and some pleasant were</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101050">And when he spoke, his person did appear</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101060">Like to the sun, when no dark clouds were near;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101070">Fame of his valour, like a trumpet sound,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101080">Through ears from heart, unto the eyes rebound;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101090">And than his person, like Mars did appear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101100">Yet so, as when fair Venus' Queen was near. </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101110">O love forbear, use not this cruelty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101120">Either bind him, or give me liberty. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e101130"><pb facs="259" n="494"/>Enter monsieur addresser. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101140" who="A53060_14-adresser">
              <speaker>Monsieur Adresser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101150">What are you all alone sweet mistress?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101160" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101170">No sir, I have the company of thoughts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101180" who="A53060_14-adresser">
              <speaker>Adresser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101190">Those are melancholy companions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101200" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101210">Indeed mine are so at this time; yet thoughts with thoughts may discourse wittily, and converse pleasantly together, without articulate words.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101220" who="A53060_14-adresser">
              <speaker>Adresser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101230">Certainly your thoughts must needs be pleasant, your words are so witty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101240" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101250">No truly, for my thoughts lie in my brain like a chaos in a confused heap, and my brain being young, hath not enough natural heat to digest them into a methodical order; neither hath time cooked them ready for the mind to dish out, or the tongue to carry to the ears of the hearers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101260" who="A53060_14-adresser">
              <speaker>Adresser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101270">The oftener I hear, and see you, the more I wonder at you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101280" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101290">Why, I hope sir I am no monster?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101300" who="A53060_14-adresser">
              <speaker>Adresser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101310">No, for you seem to me something divine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101320" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101330">Then you should rather admire me: for admiration proceeds from things excellent, wonder from things strange and unusual.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101340" who="A53060_14-adresser">
              <speaker>Adresser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101350">So you are strange, and unusual: for things divine are not common; and certainly you are a thing illuminated beyond nature's art, and are the only delight of mankind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101360" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101370">Men take no worldly delight in celestial creatures, but with earthly; wherefore the most refined and illuminated, is oftenest rejected.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101380" who="A53060_14-adresser">
              <speaker>Adresser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101390">No lady, they are not rejected, but as angels, they will not reside with us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101400" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101410">Sir, for fear I should lose the angelical opinion you have of me, I will depart soon as angels do.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e101420">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A53060_14-e101430">
          <head>Act ii.</head>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e101440">
            <head>Scene 6.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e101450">Enter mademoiselle detractor, mademoiselle spightfull, mademoiselle malicious, and mademoiselle Tell-truth. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101460" who="A53060_14-tell-truth">
              <speaker>Tell-truth.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101470">Come, will you go to hear the lady wit discourse?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101480" who="A53060_14-spightfull">
              <speaker>Spightfull.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101490">Not I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101500" who="A53060_14-tell-truth">
              <speaker>Tell-truth.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101510">Will you go?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101520" who="A53060_14-detractor">
              <speaker>Detractor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101530">I will not go to hear a prating preaching woman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101540" who="A53060_14-malicious">
              <speaker>Malicious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101550">O that all the masculine sex would say as much.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101560" who="A53060_14-tell-truth">
              <speaker>Tell-truth.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101570">Let us go to learn wit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101580" who="A53060_14-spightfull">
              <speaker>Spightfull.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101590">I had rather be a dunce all my life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101600" who="A53060_14-detractor">
              <pb facs="259" n="495"/>
              <speaker>Detractor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101610">So had I, if I must have none but a woman instructor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101620" who="A53060_14-malicious">
              <speaker>Malicious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101630">Indeed women should learn, not teach.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101640" who="A53060_14-detractor">
              <speaker>Detractor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101650">It's a sign men want wit, when they go to hear a woman preach.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101660" who="A53060_14-spightfull">
              <speaker>Spightfull.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101670">But let us go, if it be but to censure; for an hundred to one, but she will say something which may be contradicted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101680" who="A53060_14-malicious">
              <speaker>Malicious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101690">Then let us agree to be her contradictors: for whatsoever she saith we will confute.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101700" who="A53060_14-tell-truth">
              <speaker>Tell-truth.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101710">Nay by your favour, that you cannot do; for though you may contradict any argument, yet not confute it: for though envy and spite have bred sophistry, yet envy and spite cannot confute the truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101720" who="A53060_14-spightfull">
              <speaker>Spightfull.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101730">Well, let us go howsoever, if it be but to see, and be seen of those men as will be there to hear her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101740" who="A53060_14-all">
              <speaker>All.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101750">Content.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e101760">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e101770">
            <head>Scene 7.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e101780">Enter mademoiselle grand esprit, and her audience. She takes her place, and then speaks.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e101790" who="A53060_14-grand_esprit">
              <speaker>Grand esprit.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101800">Great fortune, I at this time do implore,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101810">That thou wilt open every hearing door,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101820">Which are the ears: let not my wit be lost,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101830">For want of bearing, nor my words be crossed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101840">Nor yet destructed by a bustling noise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101850">Or gazing, or observing some light toys:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101860">But let their ears be sixth, as if their sight</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e101870">Did view my words, till on their ears they light. </l>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101880">Noble and right honourable,</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101890">I shall take my discourse at this time out of ignorance, which discourse, I shall divide into five parts, the gods, fates, nature, the world, and man; for although ignorance be obscure, and hard to be discovered, yet it is printed in a general language, being spread and communicated over all the world. I begin with the first, and prime creature, ignorant man. Man takes himself to be the most knowing creature, for which he hath placed himself next to the gods; yet man is ignorant: for what man is, or ever was created, that knows what the gods are, or how many there are? Or what power they have, or where they reside? What man did ever know the mansions of glory, the bowers of bliss, or the fields of pleasure? What man ever knew whether the gods were eternal, or bred out of infinite, or rule, or govern, infinite eternally?</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101900">Secondly the fates. What man is, or ever was, that knows the fates? As whether they are gods or creatures, or whether the fates are limited, or decree as they please? Or what man is, or ever was, that knows the decrees of fate, the links of destiny, or the chance of fortune, or the lots of chance.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101910"><pb facs="260" n="496"/>Thirdly. What man is, or ever was, that knows what nature is, or from whence her power proceeds? As whether from the gods, or eternity, or infinite, or from the fates? Or whether the gods, or fates, proceed from her? Or what at first set her to work? Or whether her work is prescribed, or limited? Or of what she works on? Or what instruments she worketh with? Or to what end she works for? Or whether she shall desist from working, or shall work eternally? Or whether she worked from all eternity? Or whether her work had a beginning, or shall have an ending? What man knows the beginning of motion, or the fountain of knowledge, or the spring of life, or gulf of death? Or what life is? Or what death is? Or whether life, motion, and death, had a beginning, or shall have an ending?</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101920">Fourthly the world. What man is, or ever was, that knows how the world was made? Or for what it is made? Or by whom it was made? Or whether it had beginning, or shall have end?</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101930">The fifth and last is man. What man is, or ever was, that knows how he was formed, or of what composition, or what is that he calls a rational soul? Whether it is embodied, or not embodied? Whether it is divine, or mortal? Whether it proceeds from the gods, or was created by nature? Whether it shall live for ever, or shall have a period? Whether it shall live in knowledge, or lie in ignorance? Whether it be capable of pain, or pleasure? Whether it shall have a residing place, or no certain place assigned? Or if it have none, where it shall wander? Or if it have, where that residing place is.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101940">As for the body, who knows the perfect sense of each sense, or what mistake, or illusions, each sense is apt to make, or give, or take? What man knows how the body dissolves, or to what it shall dissolve? What man knows whether there be sense in death, or not? What man knows the motion of the thoughts, or whether the thoughts belong only to the soul, or only to the body, or partly to both, or of neither? What man is there that knows strength of passion? As what faith may beget? Or what doubts may dissolve? Or what hopes may unite? Or what fears may disorder? Or what love can suffer? Or what hate can act?</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e101950">What man is there that knows the circumference of admiration, the rigour of adoration, the height of ambition, or the bottom of covetousness? Or what man knows the end of sorrow, or beginning of joy? And as for the appetites, what man knows the length and breadth of desire? As for the senses, what man is there, that knows the true sense of pleasure, or the uttermost bounds of pain? Who can number the varieties of taste, sent, touch, sound, and sight? What man knows the perfect effects of each sense? Or what man is there that knows any thing, truly as it is? Yet certainly there cannot be an atheist; for though men may be so irrelligious, as to be of no religion; yet their can be none so wilful, and utterly void of all sense, and reason, as not to believe there is a god; for though we have not the true light of knowledge, yet we have as it were a perpetual twilight; man lives as at the poles of knowledge; for though we cannot say it is truly day, yet it is not night. Man may perceive an infinite power, by the perfect distinctions of all particular varieties, by the orderly production of several creatures, and by the fit, and proper shapes of every several kind of creature; by their orderly births, by the times and seasons, to produce, flourish, and decay; by the distinct degrees, qualities, properties, places and<pb facs="260" n="497"/> motions of all things, and to, and in every thing, by the exact form of this world; by the prudent separations, and situations of the heavens and earth; by the circumferent lines, and poyzing centres; by their bounds and limits; by their orderly, and timely motions; by their assigned tracts, constant journeys, convenient distances; by their intermixing, and well tempering of the elements; by the profitable commerce, betwixt the heavens and the earth; by the different kinds, several sorts, various natures, numerous numbers of creatures; by their passions, humours, appetites; by their sympathies, and antipathies; by their wars and parties; by the harmony that is made out of discord, shows that there is only one absolute power, and wise disposer, that cannot be opposed, having no copartners, produces all things, being not produced by any thing, wherefore must be eternal, and consequently infinite; this absolute, wise, and eternal power man calls God; but this absolute power, being infinite, he must of necessity be incomprehensible, and being incomprehensible, must of necessity be unknown, yet glimpses of his power is, or may be seen; yet not so, but that man is forced to set up candles of faith, to light them, or direct them to that they cannot perfectly know, and for want of the clear light of knowledge, man calls all creations of this mighty power nature; his wise decrees, man calls fates; his pointed will, man calls destiny; his several changes, man calls fortune; his intermixing man calls life; his separating, man calls death; the sympathetical, and antipathetical motions of the senses, and their objects, humours, and their subjects, man calls pleasure, and pain; the interchanging motions in man, men call sense, and knowledge; the separating motions, man calls ignorance, stupidity, and insensibility; my application is, that this absolute power, wise disposer, and decreeing creator, hath created himself worship, in making creatures to worship him; and it is probable, truth decreed judgement, punishment, and bliss, to such of his creatures as shall omit, or submit thereunto: my exhortation to you is, to bough humbly, to pray constantly, to implore fervently, to love truly, to live awfully to the worship of this incomprehensible power; that you may enjoy bliss and avoid torment.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e101960">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A53060_14-e101970">
          <head>Act iii.</head>
          <div n="8" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e101980">
            <head>Scene 8.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e101990">Enter monsieur Nobilissimo, and three or four gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102000" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102010">I wonder who brought up that careless fashion, to go without their swords; and I wonder more, how gallant valiant men, came to follow that fashion; for a sword is a valiant man's trusty friend, to whose protection, he delivers his honour, his safety, and his peace; for a sword is a man's guardian, to maintain his right, to revenge his wrongs, or disgraces, and his mistress, for whose service he wears his life, and studies the worth and use thereof, and takes delight in the honourable, and allowable practises therein.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102020" who="A53060_14-gentleman_1">
              <pb facs="261" n="498"/>
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102030">Faith my lord I believe it was some lover that brought up that fashion, who was loath to affright his mistress, with so dangerous a weapon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102040" who="A53060_14-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102050">Some carpet knight upon my life my lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102060" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102070">It was no true lover; for certainly he would be sure to provide a safeguard, lest his mistress might be taken from him, or lest he should be affronted in her sight, which a man of honour, and a true lover, will rather die than part or suffer; and as for my part, I commend the man that would neither eat, drink, nor sleep, without his sword were by him, and made it his bedfellow, and board companion; as a friend that held to his side, and would sight in his quarrel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102080" who="A53060_14-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102090">My lord, if a man should do so in these times, his neighbours would say it was out of fear, not courage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102100" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102110">O no, for a coward is afraid to use a sword, and a valiant man is afraid to be without the use, otherwise a strong sturdy clown, might cuff him down, and kick him like a football on the ground, which a sword, and skill to use it, will prevent; for a clown hath not skill to defend, or assault a sword, having no practice therewith, nor ought they to have; for the use of this kind of arms makes a clown a gentleman, and the want of skill makes a gentleman a clown; for a right bred gentleman, is to know the use of the sword, and it is more manly to assault, than to defend; also to know how to manage horses, whereby we know how to assault our enemy as well as to defend ourselves; for it is not playing with a fiddle, and dancing a measure, makes a gentleman; for then princes should dub knighthood with a fiddle, and give the stick, and a pair of pumps, instead of a sword, and a pair of spurs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102120" who="A53060_14-gentleman_1">
              <speaker>1 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102130">My lord, we are so far from wearing our swords ourselves nowadays , as we give them our footmen to carry, as if it were a disgrace to carry a sword ourselves.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102140" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102150">'Tis true, and we are well beaten for our follies, for disarming ourselves, and arming our slaves; for now a groom is made a gentleman's equal, nay his superior sometimes; for if a groom kills a gentleman, the gentleman dies in disgrace, and the groom lives with honour, and gets the fame of a gallant person; for that is the phrase to all those that have fought, although they were forced thereto as slaves, not distinguishing true valour, which is voluntary, temperate and just.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102160" who="A53060_14-gentleman_2">
              <speaker>2 gent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102170">Why then there should be a decree, of law, that none should wear swords but gentlemen, nor arms allowed, but to those of approved merit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102180" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102190">You say right, unless in time of foreign wars, and then there should be a difference in their arms; for if there be no difference of arms, no difference of persons, and if there be no difference of persons, there will be no supremacy of power, if no supremacy, no royal government; for as the sword maintains the prerogative of the crown, so it doth the honour of a gentleman; and as the sword keeps up the dignity of the crown, so a sword keeps up the heraldry of a gentleman; and no man ought to be accounted a gentleman, that knows not how to use his sword, and manage his horse; for the one defends himself, and kills his enemies; the other, doth front and charge his enemy, and pursues him if need require.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e102200">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="9" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e102210">
            <pb facs="261" n="499"/>
            <head>Scene 9.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e102220">Enter monsieur esperance, and mademoiselle esperance his wife.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102230" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102240">Lord wife you are very brave today.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102250" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102260">I strive to be so every day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102270" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102280">For whose sake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102290" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102300">For yours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102310" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102320">For mine? why sure that is not so, for certainly you would not take that pains, and bestow so much cost, for one you do enjoy already, for a husband that is tied to you for life, and cannot quit on honourable terms; wherefore it is for one is loose and free, which you do strive by setting forth yourself with garments rich, for to attract, and draw to your desires.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102330" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102340">The circumference of my desires is only your delight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102350" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102360">Why, my delight is in your virtue, youth, and beauty, not in your clothes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102370" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102380">But virtue is best acceptable, when beauty doth present it; and beauty finds most favour, when well attired; but were I sure you would like me better in mean garments, and careless dresses, I then should clothe myself in freeze, and like a hermit my loose course garments tie with single cord about my waste; but I will go and pull these clothes off, since they are thought a crime, and I thought false for wearing them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102390" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102400">No, I like them very well, if I were sure they were worn only for love to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102410" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102420">I never gave you cause to think I wear them for the love of any other.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e102430">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="10" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e102440">
            <head>Scene 10.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e102450">Enter mademoiselle spightfull, mademoiselle detractor, mademoiselle malicious, and mademoiselle Tell-truth. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102460" who="A53060_14-spightfull">
              <speaker>Spightfull</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102470">Mademoiselle la belle is cried up to be the only beauty in the kingdom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102480" who="A53060_14-malicious">
              <speaker>Malicious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102490">Lord that is nothing, for sometimes opinion will carry a black blouse up to fame's high tower.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102500" who="A53060_14-spightfull">
              <speaker>Spightfull.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102510">Yes faith, and most commonly they are cast down in disgrace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102520" who="A53060_14-detractor">
              <speaker>Detractor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102530">Why should she be cried up so? for she is neither well featured, nor well shaped, nor well fashioned, nor well dressed, nor well bred, nor good natured; for she is of a brown complexion, a heavy eye, a sad countenance, a lazy garb; she dresses fantastically, speaks childishly,<pb facs="262" n="500"/> looks shamefastly; she is proud, reserved, coy, disdainful, and self-conceited.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102540" who="A53060_14-tell-truth">
              <speaker>Tell-truth.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102550">Let me tell you, it is reported that she hath most lovely features, a clear complexion, a modest countenance, a bashful eye, a pleasing speech, a winning behaviour, a majestical presence; besides it is reported that her disposition is civil, courteous, and obliging, her nature sweet and gentle, her education virtuous, her life temperate and chaste, her actions noble and wise, her discourse witty and delightful.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102560" who="A53060_14-spightfull">
              <speaker>Spightfull.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102570">Hey day, heigh day, good mistress Tell-truth run not so fast in the ways of vain reports, lest your judgement fail into a quagmire.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e102580">Enter monsieur fantasy. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102590" who="A53060_14-malicious">
              <speaker>Malicious.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102600">Monsieur fantasy, 'tis said you are one of mademoiselle la bells admirers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102610" who="A53060_14-phantasie">
              <speaker>Phantasie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102620">All the world would admire her, if they saw her, she is so heavenly a creature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102630" who="A53060_14-spightfull">
              <speaker>Spightfull.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102640">If she be so heavenly a creature, she would be known to the whole world by the splendour of her beams.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102650" who="A53060_14-phantasie">
              <speaker>Phantasie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102660">Heaven is not made known to all; neither can the glories be suddenly comprehended, by weak mortals.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102670" who="A53060_14-detractor">
              <speaker>Detractor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102680">Good lord, if she hath such an infinite beauty, that it cannot be comprehended, it is obscure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102690" who="A53060_14-phantasie">
              <speaker>Phantasie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102700">But those that comprehend least will be astonished, and struck with deep amaze.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102710" who="A53060_14-detractor">
              <speaker>Detractor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102720">I believe you are struck with love, which makes you blind, or mad, that makes you think you see your own imaginations: wherefore fare you well, until you are sober.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e102730">The ladies go out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e102740">Monsieur fantasy alone.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102750" who="A53060_14-phantasie">
              <speaker>Phantasie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102760">I am struck indeed, for I am wounded deeper than swords can pierce, or bullets shoot at.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e102770">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="11" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e102780">
            <head>Scene 11.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e102790">Enter monsieur nobilissimo, and many gentlemen with him.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102800" who="A53060_14-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102810">Your lordship rid today beyond Perseus on his Pegasus.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102820" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102830">No monsieur, he went (If poets speak truth) in higher capreols than ever I shall make my horse go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102840" who="A53060_14-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102850">He might go higher my lord, but never keep so just a time, and place, as to pitch from whence he rose, his feet in the same circle, his legs in the same lines, and your lordship in the same centre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102860" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102870">The truth is, my horses went well today; they were like musical instruments, fitly strung, and justly tuned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102880" who="A53060_14-yyyy_3">
              <speaker>3 gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102890">And your lordship, like a skilful musician, played rarely thereon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102900" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <pb facs="262" n="501"/>
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102910">Come gentlemen, let us to dinner, for I have uncivilly tired your stomachs with a long fast.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e102920">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A53060_14-e102930">
          <head>Act iv.</head>
          <div n="12" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e102940">
            <head>Scene 12.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e102950">Enter monsieur fantasy as in a muse, sometimes sighing, sometimes strikes his breast, and sometimes turns up his eyes; and at these postures enters mademoiselle Bon, at her approach he starts.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102960" who="A53060_14-bon">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle Bon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102970">Sir, you may very well start to see me here, I do not use modesty, pardon me to be so bold to visit men; it is the first visit I ever made your sex, and hope it will be the last, but I am come, since neither letter, nor messenger, could have access to be resolved by your own confession, whether you have forsaken me or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e102980" who="A53060_14-phantasie">
              <speaker>Phantasie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e102990">No, I have not forsaken you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103000" who="A53060_14-bon">
              <speaker>Bon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103010">But your affection prefers another before me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103020" who="A53060_14-phantasie">
              <speaker>Phantasie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103030">If I should say I did not, I should belie truth, which baseness I abhor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103040" who="A53060_14-bon">
              <speaker>Bon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103050">I am glad for your own sake you keep so much honour, though sorry, that you are no constanter, and more sorry for the oaths you took, and vows you made to me, since they became the witnesses of your perjury. I was not suddenly, nor easily brought to draw a supreme love to one; for before such time my love was placed on you, my affections run equally in purling brooks of pity, and compassion, and clear fresh rivulets of charity and humanity, from the pure springs of good nature and religion; and hard it will be for me to turn this river to each stream again, if not, yet I shall be a rest, 'twill overflow my heart and drown me.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103060">The lady goes out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103070">Monsieur fantasy alone.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103080" who="A53060_14-phantasie">
              <speaker>Monsieur Phantasie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103090">O I must curse my fortune, and my fate; lament my own condition to love without return, and only pity what I loved most.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103100">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="13" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e103110">
            <pb facs="263" n="502"/>
            <head>Scene 13.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103120">Enter mademoiselle grand esprit, and her audience.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103130" who="A53060_14-grand_esprit">
              <speaker>Grand esprit.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103140">Great Mercury to thee I now address,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103150">Employ thy favour, help me in distress;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103160">Thou god of eloquence, so guide my tongue,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103170">Let all my words on even sense be strung,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103180">And let my speech be tuned to every ear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103190">That every ear each several word may hear:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103200">That every passion may in measure move,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103210">And let the figure of the dance be love. </l>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103220">Noble and right honourable,</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103230">I will discourse at this time of love, not of the superfluous branches, or withered leaves, or rotten fruits, but of the root of love, which is self-love; it is the root and original love in nature; it is the foundation of nature, it is the fountain from whence issues all the several springs; self-love was the cause of the world's creation; for the gods out of love to themselves, caused creatures to be created, to worship them: thus all creatures being created out of self-love, and their chief being proceeding out of self-love, is the cause that every particular creature loves themselves in the first place, and what love is placed on any other, or to any other, from any particular, is derived from self-love; for we love the gods but out of self-love, as believing the gods love us; we adore the gods but out of self-love, because we think we proceed from them, or were produced by their commands; we pray to the gods but out of self-love, because we hope the gods will help us in distress; we bless the gods but out of self-love, because we do verily believe the gods will exalt, and crown us with everlasting glory; and to show that we love the gods, not as they are gods, but for our own sakes, as believing they will or can do us good, is, that we are apt to murmur at the gods, when we have not our own desires; we are apt to accuse the gods, when any worldly thing crosses us; we are apt to curse the gods at ill accidents, misfortunes, or natural losses; we are apt to forget the gods in the midst of pleasure; we are apt to think ourselves gods in the pride of prosperity; we strive to make ourselves gods in the height of worldly power; and we do not only strive to make ourselves equal with the gods, but to raise ourselves above the gods, taking, or commanding to ourselves more worship than we give unto the gods; nay, those that are accounted the most holy and devout servants of the gods, belie the gods, taking the name of the gods to cover their own follies; as for example, whensoever any eminent person hath had ill success, either in, or after their foolish, ambitious, and vainglorious actions, they charge the god's decrees and pleasure, as it was the god's will it should be so; like as she that vaingloriously had her two and only sons to draw her chariot, like two horses, or dogs, or slaves, and being both found dead the next day, she had prayed to the gods to reward them with that which was best for them, and being both dead, she said the gods accounted death as the best reward, when they no doubt died with over heating themselves, striving beyond<pb facs="263" n="503"/> their natural power and strength; yet these two sons that drew the vain mother in a chariot, drew and died out of self-love; either like as vain sons like their vain mother, vaingloriously to get a fame, or believing the gods would reward them for their act, either with extraordinary prosperity, power, or blessedness in the life to come; and many the like examples may be given; for how ordinary is it in these our times, and in former times, for the politics to persuade the people, with promises from the gods, or to tell them it is the god's commands they should do such and such acts, even such acts as are unnatural, wicked, and most horrid? thus men bely the gods to abuse their fellow creatures. But most noble and right honourable, my explanation of this discourse is, that since self-love is the fountain of and in nature from whence issue out several springs to every several creature, wherein mankind being her chiefest and supreme work, is filled with the fullest springs from that fountain, which is the cause that mankind is more industrious, cruel, and unsatiable, to and for his self ends, than any other creature, he spares nothing that he hath power to destroy, if he fears any hurt, or hopes for any gain, or finds any pleasure, or can make any sport, or to employ his idle time; he melts metals, distils and dissolves plants, dissects animals, substracts and extracts elements, he digs up the bowels of the earth, cuts through the ocean of the sea, gathers the winds into sails, fresh waters into mills, and imprisons the thinner air; he hunts, he fowls, he fishes for sport, with guns, nets, and hooks; he cruelly causeth one creature to destroy another, the whilst he looks on with delight; he kills not only for to live, but lives for to kill, and takes pleasure in torturing the life of other creatures, in prolonging their pains, and lengthening their deaths; and when man makes friendship of love, it is for his own sake, either in humouring his passion, or feeding his humour, or to strengthen his party, or for trust, or counsel, or company, or the like causes; if he dies for his friend, it is either for fame, or that he cannot live himself happy without his friend, his passion, and grief, making him restless; if man loves his children, wife, or parents, 'tis for his own sake; he loves his parents, for the honour he receives by them, or for the life he received of them; if he loves his wife, or the wife the husband, it is for their own sakes, as their own pleasure, as either for their beauties, wits, humours, or other graces, or for their company, or friendships, or because they think they love them; if they love their children, it is for their own sakes, as to keep alive their memory, and to have their duty, and obedience, to bow and do homage to them; if masters love their servants, it is for their own sakes, because they are trusty, faithful and industrious in their affairs, employments, or for their own profit, or ease; and if servants love their masters, it is for their own sakes, as either for their power to protect them, or for the regard they have to them, or for the gain they get from them, or for their lives that are nourished, and maintained by them; if amorous lovers love, it is for their own sakes, as to please the appetite, and to satisfy their desires; if subjects love their sovereigns, it is for their own sakes, as that they may have law and justice, peace and unity; if sovereign's love their subjects, it is for their own sakes, because they bear up his throne with their wealth and industry, and fight to maintain, or get him power. My application, most noble and right honourable, is, that since we do all, and in every act for our own sakes, we should endeavour, and study, for that which is best for ourselves, and the ground of our endeavour is to learn, and know<pb facs="264" n="504"/> ourselves, every particular person must learn and know himself, not by comparative, as observing others, for every man is not alike; but by self study, reading our own natures and dispositions, marking our own passions, mours, and appetites, with the pen of thought, and ink of examination; and let the truth be the tutor to instruct you in the school of reason, in which you may commence master of art, and go out doctor of judgement, to practise temperance; for temperance keeps in its full strength, prolongs beauty, quickens wit, ripens youth, refreshes age, restores decays, keeps health, maintains life, and hinders times ruins; but temperance is not only a doctor of physic; a physician to the body, but a doctor of divinity, a divine for the soul; it preaches and teaches good life, it instructs with the doctrine of tranquillity, and guides to the heaven of happiness; also temperance is the doctor of music, it tunes the senses, composes the thoughts, it notes the passions, it measures the appetites, and plays a harmonious mind. Thus most noble and right honourable, I have proved that self-love is the fountain of nature, and the original springs of her creatures, and that temperance is the strongest foundation of self-love, although few build thereupon, but upon intemperance, which is a huge bulk of excess, the substance of riot, worm eaten with surfers, rotten with pain, and sinks down to death with sickness and grief, not being able to bear and uphold life; wherefore build your lives upon temperance, which is a strong and sure foundation, which will never fail; but will uphold your lives as long as time and nature permits them, and your souls will dwell peaceably, and happily therein.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103240">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A53060_14-e103250">
          <head>Act v.</head>
          <div n="14" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e103260">
            <head>Scene 14.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103270">Enter mademoiselle amor alone as musing to herself alone, then speaks.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103280" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103290">I will confess to him my love, since my designs are noble; but oh for a woman to woo a man is against nature, and seems too bold, nay impudent, only by a contrary custom; but why should not a woman confess she loves before she is wooed, when after a seeming coyness gives consent, as being won more by a treaty than by love, when her obscure thoughts know well her heart was his at first, bound as his prisoner, and only counterfeits a freedom; besides, it were unjust although an ancient custom, if dissembling should be preferred before a modern truth, for length of time and often practises makes not falsehood truth, nor wrong right, nor evil good; then I will break down customs walls, and honest truth shall lead me on.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103300">Love plead my suit, and if I be denied,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103310">My heart will break, and death my face will hide. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103320">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="15" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e103330">
            <pb facs="264" n="505"/>
            <head>Scene 15.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103340">Enter monsieur esperance, and his wife mademoiselle esperance. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103350" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103360">Wife, whither do you go? when I come near you, you always turn to go from me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103370" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103380">I saw you not; for I had rather be fixed as a statue, than move to your dislike.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103390" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103400">Why do you blush? surely you are guilty of some crime.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103410" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103420">'Tis said blushing comes unsent for, and departs without leave; and that it oftener visits innocency than guilt.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103430">Mademoiselle esperance weeps.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103440" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103450">What do you weep?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103460" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103470">How can I otherwise choose, when my innocent life, and true love is suspected, and all my pure affections are cast away like dross, and the best of all my actions condemned as traitors, and my unspotted chastity blemished with soul jealousy, and defamed with slandering words?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103480" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103490">Prithee wife do not weep, for every tear wounds me to death, and know it is my extreme love, which creates my fears; but you might have had a husband with more faults.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103500" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103510">'Tis true, but not so many noble qualities as you have, which makes me weep, doubting you love me not, you are so jealous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103520" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103530">By heaven I love thee beyond my soul, wherefore forbear to weep if thou canst stop thy tears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103540" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103550">Tears may be stopped, unless they flow from an unrecoverable loss, which heaven forbid mine should: yet sorrow oft doth stop the spring from whence tears rise, or else the eyes do weep themselves quite blind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103560" who="A53060_14-esperance">
              <speaker>Monsieur esperance.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103570">Pray dry yours.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103580">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="16" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e103590">
            <head>Scene 16.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103600">Enter mademoiselle bon alone.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103610" who="A53060_14-bon">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle Bon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103620">O man! O man! How various and inconstant are you all, how cruel to betray our faint and unexperienced sex, bribing our judgements with flattering words, obscure our reasons with clouds of sighs, drawing us into belief with protestations, bind us with promises and vows, forcing us to yield up our affections; then murder us with scorn, and bury us in forgetfulness? but oh how happy was I, before I was betrayed by love? my heart was free, my thoughts were pleasant, and my<pb facs="265" n="506"/> humour gay; but now my mind is a garrison of cares, my thoughts like runaways are wanderers.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103630">Grief on my heart his heavy taxes lays;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103640">Which through my eyes, my heart those taxes pays. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103650">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="17" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e103660">
            <head>Scene 17.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103670">Enter mademoiselle amor, and at a distance seeth Monsieur nobilissimo, she speaks first, as to herself.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103680" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Mademoiselle amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103690">Love and discretion sight dvels in my mind, one makes me mute, the other doth persuade me to prefer my suit; but why should I be nice to speak, or be ashamed to woo with words, when all our sex doth woo with several dresses and smiles? each civil courtesy doth plead loves suit; then I will on, love give me courage, and Mercury guide my tongue.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103700">She goeth as towards the lord nobilissimo. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103710" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103720">Noble sir, impute it rather as a folly to my sex and youth, and not any impudence of nature, if that my innocency discovers my passion and affection, not having craft, or subtlety to conceal them; but I must plainly tell you, no sooner did I see you, and hear you speak, but loved: but yet mistake me not, I dote not on your person, but your mind; for sure your noble soul shot fire through my eyes into my heart, there flames with pure affection, but for this confession, perchance you will set me as a mark of scorn, for all to shoot their scoffs at, and in derision pointing, will laugh and say, there is the maid that wooed a man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103730" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103740">Is this to me lady?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103750" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103760">It cannot be to any other, nature could make but one, and that was you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103770" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103780">If this be real you do profess, the gods, should they have sent an angel down to offer me their heavenly mansion, it had not been so great a gift as your affection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103790" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103800">Do you not hate me then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103810" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103820">Nothing I love so well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103830" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103840">And will you love me ever?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103850" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103860">Yes ever; for when my body is dissolved, love shall live in my dust in spite of death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103870" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103880">And will you love none but me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103890" who="A53060_14-nobilissimo">
              <speaker>Nobilissimo.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103900">An entire and undivided affection, can be placed but upon one, and that is you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103910" who="A53060_14-amor">
              <speaker>Amor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_14-e103920">May your constancy be as firm, as my love pure.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103930">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="18" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_14-e103940">
            <pb facs="265" n="507"/>
            <head>Scene 18.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_14-e103950">Enter mademoiselle la belle and her four suitors, admiration, ambition, vainglory and pride. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e103960" who="A53060_14-admirat">
              <speaker>Admirat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103970">Dear mistress stay, that I may gaze upon you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103980">Then bow my knee, as to the rising sun;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e103990">Heave up my hands, as when to heaven I pray,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104000">But being amazed, know not one word I say:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104010">Yet superstitiously, I shall adore,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104020">As my chief goddess, shall thy love implore;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104030">And being worshipped, you are deified,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104040">Your godhead in your beauty doth reside. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e104050" who="A53060_14-vainglory">
              <speaker>Vainglory.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104060">Thou absolute beauty, for thy dear sake,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104070">Of lovers hearts, a footstool shall be made;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104080">A cushion soft, with hopes filled full, then laid,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104090">For thee to stand, and triumph on, fair maid;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104100">And lovers souls shall from their bodies fly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104110">For thee a couch, when weary on to lie. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e104120" who="A53060_14-pride">
              <speaker>Pride.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104130">Thy lovers tears for to invite thy rest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104140">In murmuring streams, fall on thy marble breast;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104150">And gentle sighs, like whispering winds shall blow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104160">And fan thy cheeks, that poet's fire may glow:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104170">Loves melancholy thoughts, like clouds of night,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104180">Like as thy curtains, drawn before thy sight;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104190">For fear the sun should trouble out of spite,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104200">Thy eyes repose, being the greater light. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e104210" who="A53060_14-ambition">
              <speaker>Ambition.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104220">Sweet beauty, thou in a glorious throne shall set,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104230">The spangled heaven, seems but thy counterfeit;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104240">Thy chariot shall be stuck with eyes all gazing,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104250">And oiled with eloquent tongues, that runs with praising:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104260">Drawn by large strong well shaped commendations,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104270">Guided by fame, about two several nations. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_14-e104280" who="A53060_14-la_belle">
              <speaker>La belle.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104290">Admiration, vainglory, pride, and ambition,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104300">Why do you woo beauty, that is deaf and dumb,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104310">That hears no praise, nor adoration;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104320">It seeth no hands heaved up, nor tears that fall,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104330">It hath no tongue to answer love withal;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104340">It hath no life, no soul where passion lies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104350">It neither gives, nor takes instructions wise:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104360">It is no solid body you admire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_14-e104370">No substance, but a shadow you desire. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A53060_14-e104380">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A53060_14"><item xml:id="A53060_14-esperance" n="31">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-esperance</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">31</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-amor" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-amor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-nobilissimo" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-nobilissimo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-spightfull" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-spightfull</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-detractor" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-detractor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-tell-truth" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-tell-truth</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-phantasie" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-phantasie</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-adresser" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-adresser</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-malicious" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-malicious</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-yyyy_1" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-yyyy_2" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-yyyy_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-bon" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-bon</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-gentleman_2" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-gentleman_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-gentleman_1" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-gentleman_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-poverty" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-poverty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-grand_esprit" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-grand_esprit</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A53060_14-pride" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-pride</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-vainglory" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-vainglory</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-yyyy_3" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-yyyy_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-la_belle" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-la_belle</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-admirat" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-admirat</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-ambition" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-ambition</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_14-all" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_14-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

