<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A41993">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Mucedorus (and Amadine) <date type="creation_date">1591</date></title>
        <author>anon.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Madeline Burg</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A41993.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A most pleasant comedy of Mucedorus the kings son of Valentia, and Amadine the kings daughter of Aragon with the merry conceits of Mouse : amplified with new additions, as it was acted before the Kings Majesty at Whitehall, on Shrove Sunday night by His Highness servants usually playing at the Globe.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>24 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2007 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">12152227</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing G1829.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">55074</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41993</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A most pleasant comedy of Mucedorus the kings son of Valentia, and Amadine the kings daughter of Aragon with the merry conceits of Mouse : amplified with new additions, as it was acted before the Kings Majesty at Whitehall, on Shrove Sunday night by His Highness servants usually playing at the Globe.</title>
            <author>Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592.</author>
            <author>Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[46] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed for Francis Coles ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>[1650?]</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Mucedorus.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Attributed to Robert Greene. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing, 1926, v. 4, p. 121.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>"Assigned to Shakespeare by some late 17th cent. booksellers but ... entirely, rejected by modern scholarship" Cf. Bartlett: Mr. William Shakespeare, p. 60.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A41993-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A41993-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A41993-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A41993-e100040">A most pleasant comedy of Mucedorus the King's son of Valentia, and Amadine the King's daughter of Aragon. With the merry conceits of mouse. Amplified with new additions, as it was acted before the King's majesty at Whitehall, on Shrove-sunday night. By his highness' servants usually playing at the globe. </p>
        <p xml:id="A41993-e100050">Very delectable and full of conceited mirth.</p>
        <p xml:id="A41993-e100060">London, printed for Francis coals, and are to be sold at his shop, at the half bowl in the old baily.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="A41993-e100070">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>The prologue.</head>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100080">Most sacred majesty, whose great deserts,</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100090">Thy subject England; nay, the world admires:</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100100">Which heaven grant still increase: oh may your praise,</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100110">Multiplying with your hours, your fame still raise. </l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100120">Embrace your council: love, with faith them guide,</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100130">That both as one bench by the others side;</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100140">So may your life pass on, and run so even,</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100150">That your firm zeal plant you a throne in heaven:</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100160">Where smiling angels shall your guardians be,</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100170">From blemished traitors, stained with perjury. </l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100180">And as the night's inferior to the day,</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100190">So be all earthly regions to your sway. </l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100200">Be as the sun today, the day tonight ,</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100210">For from your beams Europe shall borrow light:</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100220">Mirth drown your bosom, fair delight your mind,</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100230">And may our pastime your contentment find. </l>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e100240">Exit.</stage>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A41993-e100250">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>Ten persons may easily play it.</head>
        <list xml:id="A41993-e100260">
          <item xml:id="A41993-e100270">The King and Romelo, for one.</item>
          <item xml:id="A41993-e100280">King Valentia, for one.</item>
          <item xml:id="A41993-e100290">Mucedorus the prince of Valentia, for one.</item>
          <item xml:id="A41993-e100300">Anselmo. for one.</item>
          <item xml:id="A41993-e100310">Amadine the King's daughter of Aragon, for one.</item>
          <item xml:id="A41993-e100320">Segasto a nobleman, for one.</item>
          <item xml:id="A41993-e100330">Envy, Tremelio a captain, Bremo, a wild man, for one.</item>
          <item xml:id="A41993-e100340">Comedy, a boy, an old woman, Ariena, Amadine's maid, for one.</item>
          <item xml:id="A41993-e100350">Collina counsellor, a messenger, for one.</item>
          <item xml:id="A41993-e100360">Mouse the clown, for one.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A41993-e100370">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A41993-e100380">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>A most pleasant comedy of Mucedorus the King's son of Valentia, and Amadine the King's daughter of Aragon.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e100390">Enter comedy joyfully, with a garland of bays on her head.</stage>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100400">Why so thus do I hope to please;</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100410">Music revives, and mirth is tolerable:</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100420">Comedy play thy part and please;</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100430">Make merry them that come to joy with thee:</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100440">Joy then good gentiles, I hope to make you laugh;</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100450">Sound forth Bellona's silver tuned strings;</l>
        <l xml:id="A41993-e100460">Time fits us well, the day and place is ours. </l>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e100470">Enter envy, his arms naked, besmeared with blood.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e100480" who="A41993-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100490">Nay stay minion, stay, there lies a block;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100500">What all on mirth? I'll interrupt your tale,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100510">And mix your music with a tragic end. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e100520" who="A41993-comedy">
          <speaker>Comedy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100530">What monstruous ugly nag is this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100540">That dares control the pleasures of our will? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100550">Vaunt churlish cur, besmeared with gory blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100560">That seemest to check the blossom of delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100570">And still the sound of sweet Bellona's breath:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100580">Blush monster, blush, and post away with shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100590">That seekst disturbance of a goddess name. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e100600" who="A41993-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100610">Post hence thyself thou counterchecking trull,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100620">I will possess this habit spite of thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100630">And gain the glory of this wished port. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100640">I'll thunder music shall appall the nymphs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100650">And make them shiver their clattering strings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100660">Flying for succour to their Danish caves. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e100670">Sound drums within, and cry, stab, stab.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100680">Harken, thou shalt hear noise</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100690">Shall fill the air with shrilling sound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100700"><pb facs="4"/> and thunder music to the gods above:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100710">Mars shall himself breathe down</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100720">A peerless crown upon brave envies head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100730">And raise his chival with a lasting fame:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100740">In this brave music envy takes delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100750">Where I may see them wallow in their blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100760">To spurn at arms and legs quite shivered off,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100770">And hear the cries of many thousands slain:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100780">How likest thou this my trull? 'tis sport alone for me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e100790" who="A41993-comedy">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100800">Vaunt bloody cur, nursed up with tiger's sap,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100810">That so dost quail a woman's mind:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100820">Comedy is mild, gentle, willing for to please,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100830">And seeks to gain the love of all estates;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100840">Delighting in mirth, mixed all with lovely tales,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100850">And bringeth things with treble joy to pass. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100860">Thou bloody, envious, disdainer of men's joys;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100870">Whose name is fraught with bloody stratagems. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100880">Delights in nothing but in spoil and death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100890">Where thou mayst trample in their lukewarm blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100900">And grasp their hearts within thy cursed paws:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100910">Yet vail thy mind, revenge thee not on me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100920">A silly woman begs it at thy hands;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100930">Give me the leave to utter out my play. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100940">Forbear this place, I humbly crave thee hence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100950">And mix not death 'mongst pleasing comedies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100960">That treats naught else but pleasure and delight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100970">If any spark of humane rests in thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e100980">Forbear, be gone, tender the suit of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e100990" who="A41993-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101000">Why so I will; forbearance shall be such,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101010">As treble death shall cross thee with despite,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101020">And make thee mourn where most thou joyest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101030">Turning thy mirth into a deadly dole,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101040">Whirling thy pleasures with a peal of death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101050">And drench thy methods in a sea of blood;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101060">Thus will I do: thus shall I bear with thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101070">And more, to vex thee with a deeper spite,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101080">I will with threats of blood begin the play,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101090">Favouring thee with envy and with hate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101100" who="A41993-comedy">
          <pb facs="4"/>
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101110">Then ugly monster do thy worst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101120">I will defend them in despite of thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101130">And though thou thinkest with tragic fame</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101140">To prove my play unto my great disgrace ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101150">I force it not, I scorn what thou canst do ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101160">I'll grace it so, thyself shall it confess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101170">From tragic stuff, to be a pleasant comedy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101180" who="A41993-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101190">Why then comedy send the actors forth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101200">And I will cross the first step of their trade,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101210">Making them fear the very dart of death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101220" who="A41993-comedy">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101230">And I'll defend them maugre all thy spite;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101240">So ugly fiend farewell till time shall serve,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101250">That we may meet to parley for the best. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101260" who="A41993-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101270">Content comedy, I'll go spread my branch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101280">And scattered blossoms from mine envious tree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101290">Shall prove two monsters spoiling of their joys. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e101300">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e101310">Sound.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e101320">Enter, Mucedorus, and Anselmo his friend.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101330" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e101340">Anselmo?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101350" who="A41993-anselmo">
          <speaker>Ansel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101360">My lord and friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101370">Whose dear affections bosom with my heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101380">And keep their domination in one orb;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101390">Whence near disloyalty shall root it forth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101400">But faith plant firmer in your choice respect. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101410" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101420">Much blame were mine if I should other deem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101430">Nor can coy fortune contrary allow:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101440">But my Anselmo, loath I am to say I must enstrange that friendship:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101450">Misconstrue not, 'tis from the realm, not thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101460">Though lands part bodies, hearts keep company:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101470">Thou knowest that I imparted often have</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101480">Private relations with my royal sire</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101490">Had, as concerning beauteous Amadine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101500">Rich Aragon's bright jewel: whose face (Some say)</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101510">That blooming lilies never shone so gay:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101520">Excelling not excelled; yet lest report</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101530">Does mangle verity, boasting of what is not</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101540">Winged with desire, thither I'll straight repair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101550">And be my fortunes at my thoughts are, fair. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101560" who="A41993-anselmo">
          <speaker>Ansel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101570">Will you forsake Valentia? leave the court? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101580"><pb facs="5"/>Absent you from the eye of sovereignty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101590">Do not sweet prince, adventure on that task,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101600">Since danger lurks each where, he won from it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101610" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101620">Desist dissuasion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101630">My resolution brooks no battery,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101640">Therefore if thou retain thy wonted form,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101650">Assist what I intend ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101660" who="A41993-anselmo">
          <speaker>Ansel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101670">Your miss will breed a blemish in the court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101680">And throw a frosty dew upon that beard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101690">Whose front Valentia stoops to. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101700" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101710">If thou my welfare tender, then no more;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101720">Let love's strong magic charm thy trivial phrase,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101730">Wasted as vainly as to gripe the sun:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101740">Augment not then more answer; lock thy lips,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101750">Unless thy wisdom s●re me with disguise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101760">According to my purpose. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101770" who="A41993-anselmo">
          <speaker>Ansel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101780">That action craves no counsels,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101790">Since what you rightly are, will more commend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101800">Th●● best usurped shape. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101810" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101820">Thou still art opposite in disposition. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101830">A more obscure servile habiliment</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101840">Beseems this enterprise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101850" who="A41993-anselmo">
          <speaker>Ansel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101860">Then like a Florentine or mountebank. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101870" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101880">'Tis much too tedious, I dislike thy judgement,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101890">My mind is grafted on an humbler stock. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101900" who="A41993-anselmo">
          <speaker>Ansel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101910">Within my closet does there hang a cassock,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101920">Though base the weed is, 'twas a shepherd's,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101930">Which I presented in lord Julius' mask. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e101940" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101950">That my Anselmo, and none else but that,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101960">Mask Mucedorus from the vulgar view:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101970">That habit suits my mind, fetch me that weed. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e101980">Exit Anselmo.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e101990">Better then Kings have not disdained that state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102000">And much inferior, to obtain their mate. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e102010">Enter Anselmo with a shepherd's coat.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102020">So, let our respect command thy secrecy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102030">At once a brief farewell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102040">Delay to lovers is a second hell. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e102050">Exit. Mucedorus.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102060" who="A41993-anselmo">
          <pb facs="5"/>
          <speaker>Ansel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102070">Prosperity forerun thee: awkward chance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102080">Never be neighbour to thy wishes venture,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102090">Content and fame advance thee. Ever thrive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102100">And glory thy mortality survive. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e102110">Enter mouse, with a bottle of hay.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102120" who="A41993-mouse">
          <speaker>Mouse.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e102130">O horrible terrible! Was ever poor gentleman so scared out of his seven senses? A bear? Nay sure it cannot be a bear, but some devil in a bear's doublet: for a bear could never have had that agility to have frighted me. Well, I'll see my father hanged before I'll serve his horse any more: well, I'll carry home my bottle of hay, and for once make my father's horse turn Puritan, and observe fasting days, for he gets not a bit. But soft, this way she followed me, therefore I'll take the other path, and because I'll be sure to have an eye to her, I will shake hands with some foolish creditor, and make every step backward.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e102140">As he goes backward, the bear comes in, and he tumbles over her, and runs away, and leaves his bottle of hay behind him.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e102150">Enter Segasto running, and Amadine after him, being pursued with a bear.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102160" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e102170">O fly madam, fly, or else we are but dead.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102180" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e102190">Help Segasto, help, help sweet Segasto, or else I die.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e102200">Segasto runs away.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102210" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102220">Alas madam there is no way but flight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102230">Then haste and save yourself. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102240" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e102250">Why then I die. Ah help me in distress.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e102260">Enter Mucedorus like a shepherd, with a sword drawn, and a bear's head in his hand.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102270" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102280">Stay lady, stay, and be no more dismayed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102290">That cruel beast most merciless and fell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102300">Affrighted many with his hard pursues,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102310">Prying from place to place to find his prey,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102320">Prolonging thus his life by others death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102330">His carcase now lies headless void of breath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102340" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e102350">That foul deformed monster, is he dead?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102360" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102370">Assure yourself thereof, behold his head. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102380"><pb facs="6"/>Which if it please you lady to accept,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102390">With willing heart I yield it to your majesty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102400" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102410">Thanks worthy shepherd, thanks a thousand times. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102420">This gift assure thyself contents me more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102430">Than greatest bounty of a mighty prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102440">Although he were the monarch of the world. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102450" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102460">Most gracious goddess, more than mortal wight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102470">Your heavenly hue of right imports no less,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102480">Most glad am I, in that it was my chance</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102490">To undertake this enterprise in hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102500">Which doth so greatly glad our princely mind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102510" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102520">No goddess (Shepherd) but a mortal wight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102530">A mortal wight distressed as thou seest;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102540">My father here is King of Aragon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102550">I Amadine his only daughter am,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102560">And after him sole air unto the crown:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102570">Now whereas it is my father's will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102580">To marry me unto Segasto,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102590">One whose wealth through father's former usury,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102600">Is known to be no less than wonderful;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102610">We both of custom oftentimes did use,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102620">(Leaving the court) to walk within the fields</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102630">For recreation, especially the spring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102640">In that it yields great store of rare delights:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102650">And passing further than our wonted walks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102660">Scarce entered within these luckless woods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102670">But right before us down a steepfall hill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102680">A monstrous ugly bear did hie him fast</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102690">To meet us both: I faint to tell the rest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102700">Good shepherd but suppose the ghastly looks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102710">The hideous fears, the hundred thousand woes</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102720">Which at this instant Amadine sustained. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102730" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102740">Yet worthy Princess let thy sorrow cease,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102750">And let this sight your former joys revive. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102760" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e102770">Believe me shepherd, so it doth no less.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102780" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102790">Long may they last unto your hearts content,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102800">But tell me lady, what is become of him? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102810">Segasto called; what is become of him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102820" who="A41993-amadine">
          <pb facs="6"/>
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102830">I know not I, that know the powers divine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102840">But God grant this, that sweet Segasto live. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102850" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102860">Yet hard hearted he in such a case,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102870">So cowardly to save him 〈◊〉 by flight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102880">And leave so brave a Princess to the spoil. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e102890" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102900">Well shepherd, for thy worthy valour tried,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102910">Endangering thyself to set me free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102920">Unrecompensed sure thou shalt not be:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102930">In court thy courage shall be plainly known,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102940">Throughout the kingdom will I spread thy name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102950">To thy renown and never dying fame:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102960">And that thy courage may be better known,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102970">Bear thou the head of this most monstrous beast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102980">In open sight to every courtier's view:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e102990">So will the King my father thee reward. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103000">Come let's away, and guard me to the court. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103010" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103020">With all my heart.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e103030">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e103040">Enter Segasto solus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103050" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103060">When heaps of harms do hover over head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103070">'Tis time as then (Some say) to look about,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103080">And of ensuing harms to choose the least,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103090">But hard, yea hapless is that wretch's chance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103100">Luckless his lot, and caitiff-like accursed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103110">At whose proceedings fortune ever frowns:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103120">Myself I mean most subject unto thrall:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103130">For I, the more I seek to shun the worst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103140">The more by proof I find myself accursed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103150">Ere whiles assaulted with an ugly bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103160">Fair Amadine in company all alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103170">Forthwith by flight I thought to save myself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103180">Leaving my Amadine unto her shifts:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103190">For death it was for to resist the bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103200">And death no less of Amadine's harms to hear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103210">Accursed I, in lingering life thus long:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103220">In living thus, each minute of an hour</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103230">Doth pierce my heart with darts of thousand deaths:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103240">If she by flight her fury doth escape,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103250">What will she think? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103260"><pb facs="7"/>Will she not say, yea flatly to my face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103270">Accusing me of mere disloyalty. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103280">A trusty friend is tried in time of need</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103290">But I, when she in danger was of death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103300">And needed me, and cried, Segasto help,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103310">I turned my back and quickly ran away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103320">Unworthy I to bear this vital breath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103330">But what, what need those plaints? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103340">If Amadine do live, then happy I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103350">She will in time forgive and so forget:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103360">Amadine is merciful, not Juno like,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103370">In harmful hearts to harbour hatred long. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e103380">Enter mouse the clown running, crying clubs.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103390" who="A41993-mouse">
          <speaker>Mou.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103400">Clubs, prongs; pitchforks, bills: oh help,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103410">A bear, a bear, a bear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103420" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103430">Still bears, and nothing but bears. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103440">Tell me sirrah where she is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103450" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103460">O sir, she is run down the woods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103470">I saw her white head, and her white belly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103480" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103490">Thou talkest of wonders, to tell me of white bears. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103500">But sirrah, didst thou ever see any such? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103510" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103520">No faith, I never saw any such:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103530">But I remember my father's words,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103540">He bade me take heed I was not caught with the white bear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103550" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103560">A lamentable tale no doubt.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103570" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103580">I'll tell you what sir, as I was going a field to serve my father's great horse, and carried a bottle of hay upon my head: now do you see sir, I fast hoodwinked that I should see nothing, I perceiving the bear coming, I threw my hay into the hedge, and ran away.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103590" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103600">What from nothing?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103610" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103620">I warrant you yes, I saw something: for there was two load of thorns besides my bottle of hay, and that made three.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103630" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103640">But tell me sirrah: the bear that thou didst see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103650">Did she not bear a bucket on her arm? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103660" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103670">Ha, ha, ha, I never saw a bear go a milking in all my life. But hark you sir, I did not look so high as her arm, I saw nothing but her white head, and her white belly.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103680" who="A41993-segasto">
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103690">But tell me sirrah: where dost thou dwell?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103700" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103710">Why do you not know me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103720" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103730">Why no, how should I know thee?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103740" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103750">Why then you know nobody , and you know not me; I tell you sir, I am goodman rats son of the next parish over the hill.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103760" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103770">Goodman rat's son, what's thy name?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103780" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103790">Why I am very near kin unto him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103800" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103810">I think so, but what's thy name?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103820" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103830">My name? I have a very pretty name. I'll tell you what my name is, my name is mouse. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103840" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103850">What plain mouse? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103860" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103870">I plain mouse, without either wale or guard. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103880">But do you hear sir, I am a very young mouse, for my tail is scarce grown out yet; look here else. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103890" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103900">But I pray you who gave you that name?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103910" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e103920">Faith sir, I know not that, but if you would fain know ask my father's great horse, for he hath been half a year longer with my father than I have been.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103930" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103940">This seems to be a merry fellow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103950">I care not if I take him home with me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103960">Mirth is a comfort to a troubled mind. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103970">A merry man a merry master makes. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e103980">How sayest thou sirrah, wilt thou dwell with me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e103990" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104000">Nay soft sir, two words to a bargain. Pray what occupation are you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104010" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104020">No occupation, I live upon my lands.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104030" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104040">Your lands? away, yea are no master for me. Why, do you think that I am so mad to go to seek my living in the lands among the stones, briers, and bushes, and tear my holy day apparel? not I by your leave.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104050" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104060">Why, I do not mean thou shalt.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104070" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104080">How then?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104090" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104100">Why thou shalt be my man and wait on me at court:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104110" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104120">What's that?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104130" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104140">Where the King lies.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104150" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104160">What is that King, a man or a woman?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104170" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104180">A man as thou art.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104190" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104200">As I am: hark you sir, pray you what kin is he to goodman King of our parish the church warden?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104210" who="A41993-segasto">
          <pb facs="8"/>
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104220">No kin to him, he is the King of the whole land.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104230" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104240">King of the whole land! I never saw him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104250" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104260">If thou wilt dwell with me thou shalt see him every day.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104270" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104280">Shall I go home again to be torn in pieces with bears? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104290">No not I, I will go home and put on a clean shirt, and then go drown myself. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104300" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104310">Thou shalt not need, if thou wilt dwell with me, thou shalt want nothing.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104320" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104330">Shall I not? then here's my hand, I'll dwell with you: and harkee on sir, now you have entertained me, I'll tell you what I can do, I can keep my tongue from picking and stealing, and my hands from lying and slandering I warrant you as well as ever you had any man in your life.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104340" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104350">Now will I to court with sorrowful heart, rounded with doubts: if Amadine do live, then happy I; yea happy I if Amadine do live.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e104360">Enter the King with a young prisoner, Amadine, Tremelio, with Collin and counsellors.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104370" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104380">Now brave lords, our wars are brought to end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104390">Our foes the foil, and we in safety rest:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104400">It us behooves to use such clemency in peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104410">As valour in the wars;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104420">'Tis as great honour to be bountiful at home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104430">As conquerors in the field. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104440">Therefore my lords, the more to my content,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104450">Your liking, and our country's safeguard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104460">We are disposed in marriage for to give</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104470">Our daughter unto lord Segasto here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104480">Who shall succeed the diadem after me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104490">And reign hereafter as I tofore have done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104500">Your sole and lawful King of Aragon. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104510">What say you lordlings like you of my advice? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104520" who="A41993-collen">
          <speaker>Col.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104530">An't please your majesty, we do not only allow of your highness' pleasure, but also vow faithfully in what we may, to further it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104540" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104550">Thanks good my lords, if long Adrastus live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104560">He will it ●●l● require your courtesies. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104570">Tremelio, in recompense of thy late valour done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104580"><pb facs="8"/> take unto thee the Catelone a prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104590">Lately our prisoner taken in the wars:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104600">Be thou his keeper, his ransom shall be thine:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104610">We'll think of it when leisure shall afford:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104620">Meanwhile do use him well, his father is a King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104630" who="A41993-tremelio">
          <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104640">Thanks to your majesty, his usage shall be such,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104650">As he thereat shall have no cause to grutch. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e104660">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104670" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104680">Then march we on to court, and rest our wearied limbs. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104690">But Collin, I have a tale in secret fit for thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104700">When thou shalt hear a watchword from thy King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104710">Think then some weighty matter is at hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104720">That highly shall concern our state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104730">Than Collin look thou be not far from me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104740">And for thy service thou to fore hast done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104750">Thy truth and valour proved in every point,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104760">I shall with bounties thee enlarge therefore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104770">So guard us to the court. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104780" who="A41993-collen">
          <speaker>Col.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104790">What so my sovereign doth command me do,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104800">With willing mind I gladly yield consent. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e104810">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e104820">Enter Segasto, and the clown, with weapons about him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104830" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104840">Tell me sirrah, how do you like your weapons?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104850" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104860">O very well, very well, they keep my sides warm.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104870" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104880">They keep the dogs from your shins well, do they not?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104890" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104900">How, keep the dogs from my shins? I would scorn but my shins should keep the dogs from them.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104910" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104920">Well sirrah, leaving idle talk, tell me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104930">Dost thou know captain Tremelio's chamber? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104940" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e104950">I very well, it hath a door.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104960" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104970">I think so, for so hath every chamber:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e104980">But dost thou know the man? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e104990" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105000">I forsooth, he hath a nose on his face.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105010" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105020">Why :so hath every one.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105030" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105040">That's more than I know.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105050" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105060">But dost thou remember the captain that was here with the King that brought the young prince prisoner?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105070" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105080">O very well.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105090" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105100">Go to him, and bid him come unto me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105110">Tell him I have a matter in secret to impart to him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105120" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105130">I will master, what's his name?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105140" who="A41993-segasto">
          <pb facs="9"/>
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105150">Why captain Tremelio. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105160" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105170">O, the mealman; I know him very well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105180">He brings meal every Saturday; but hark you master,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105190">Must I bid him come to you, or must you come to him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105200" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105210">No sirrah, he must come to me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105220" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105230">Hark you master, if he be not at home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105240">What shall I do then? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105250" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105260">Why then leave word with some of his folks.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105270" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105280">O master if there be nobody within,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105290">I will leave word with his dog. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105300" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105310">Why can his dog speak?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105320" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105330">I cannot tell, wherefore doth he keep his chamber else?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105340" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105350">To keep out such knaves as thou art.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105360" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105370">Nay by lady then go yourself.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105380" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105390">You will go sir, will you not?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105400" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105410">Yes marry will I ▪ oh 'tis come to my head:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105420">And he be not within, I'll bring his chamber to you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105430" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105440">What, will you pluck down the King's house?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105450" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105460">No by lady, I'll know the price of it first. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105470">Master, it is such a hard name I have forgotten it again:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105480">I pray you tell me his name. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105490" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105500">I tell thee captain Tremelio. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105510" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105520">O captain treble knave, captain treble knave.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e105530">Enter Tremelio.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105540" who="A41993-tremelio">
          <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105550">How now sirrah, dost thou call me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105560" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105570">You must come to my master. Captain treble knave.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105580" who="A41993-tremelio">
          <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105590">My lord Segast. did you send for me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105600" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105610">I did Tremelio, sirrah, about your business.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105620" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105630">I marry, what's that, can you tell?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105640" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105650">No not well.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105660" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105670">Marry then I can, straight to the kitchen-dresser to John the cook, and get me a good piece of beef and brews, and then to the buttery hatch to Thomas the butler for a Jack of beer: and there for an hour I'll so belabour myself, and therefore I pray you call me not till you think I have done, I pray you good master.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e105680">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105690" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e105700">Well sir, away.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105710" who="A41993-tremelio">
          <speaker>Tremelio.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105720">This it is, thou knowest the valour of Segasto. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105730"><pb facs="9"/>Spread through all the kingdom of Aragon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105740">And such as have found triumph and favours,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105750">Never daunted at any time: but now a shepherd,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105760">Admired in court for worthiness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105770">And Segasto's honour laid aside:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105780">My will therefore is this, that thou dost find some means to work the shepherd's death: I know thy strength sufficient to perform my desire, and to love no otherwise than to revenge my injuries. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105790" who="A41993-tremelio">
          <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105800">It is not the frowns of a shepherd that Tremelio fears:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105810">Therefore account it accomplished what I take in hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105820" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105830">Thanks good Tremelio, and assure thyself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105840">What I promise, that I will perform. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105850" who="A41993-tremelio">
          <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105860">Thanks good my lord: and in good time:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105870">See where he cometh; stand by awhile,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105880">And you shall see me put in practise your intended drift. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105890">Have at thee swain, if that I hit thee right. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e105900">Enter Mucedorus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105910" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105920">Vild coward, so without cause to strike a man:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105930">Turn coward, turn: now strike and do thy worst. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e105940">Mucedorus killeth him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e105950" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105960">Hold shepherd, hold, spare him, kill him not:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105970">Accursed villain, tell me, what hast thou done? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105980">Ah Tremelio, trusty Tremelio, I sorrow for thy death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e105990">And since that thou living didst prove faithful to Segasto,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106000">So Segasto now living will honour the dead</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106010">Corpse of Tremelio with revenge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106020">Bloodthirsty villain, born and bred in merciless murder,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106030">Tell me, how durst thou be so bold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106040">As once to lay thy hands upon the least of mine? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106050">Assure thyself, thou shalt be used according to the law. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106060" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106070">Segasto cease, these threats are needless,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106080">Accuse me not of murder, that have done nothing</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106090">But in mine own defence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106100" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106110">Nay shepherd, reason not with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106120">I'll manifest thy fact unto the King;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106130">Whose doom will be thy death, as thou deservest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106140">What ho: mouse come away. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e106150"><pb facs="10"/>Enter mouse.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106160" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106170">Why how now? what's the matter? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106180">I thought you would be calling before I had done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106190" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e106200">Come help away with my friend.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106210" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e106220">Why, is he drunk? can he not stand on his feet?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106230" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e106240">No, he is not drunk, he is slain.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106250" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e106260">Slain? No by lady, he is not slain.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106270" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e106280">He is killed I tell thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106290" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e106300">What do you use to kill your friends? I will serve you no longer.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106310" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e106320">I tell thee the shepherd killed him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106330" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e106340">O did he so? But master, I will have all his apparel if I carry him away.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106350" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e106360">Why so thou shalt.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106370" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e106380">Come then I will help: mass master I think his mother sung looby to him, he is so heavy.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e106390">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106400" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106410">Behold the fickle state of man, always mutable, never at one. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106420">Sometime we feed our fancies with the sweet of our desires:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106430">Sometimes again, we feel the heat of extreme miseries. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106440">Now am I in favour about the court and country,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106450">Tomorrow those favours will turn to frowns. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106460">Today I live revenged on my foe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106470">Tomorrow I die, my foe revenged on me. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e106480">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e106490">Enter Bremo a wild man.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106500" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bremo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106510">No passenger this morning? what not one? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106520">A chance that seldom doth befall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106530">What, not one? Then lie thou there,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106540">And rest thyself till I have further need:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106550">Now Bremo sith thy leisure so affords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106560">An endless thing, who knows not Bremo's strength,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106570">Who like a King commands within these woods? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106580">The bear, the boar dare not abide his sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106590">But haste away to save themselves by flight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106600">The crystal waters in the bubbling brooks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106610">When I come by do swiftly slide away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106620">And claps themselves in closets under banks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106630">Afraid to look bold Bremo in the face. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106640">The aged oaks at Bremo's breath do bow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106650">And all things else are still at my command. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106660"><pb facs="10"/>Else what would I? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106670">Rend them in pieces, and pluck them from the earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106680">And each way else I would revenge myself. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106690">Why, who comes here? with whom dare I not fight? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106700">Who fights with me and doth not die the death? Not one. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106710">What favour shows this sturdy stick to those</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106720">That here within these woods are combatants with me? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106730">Why, death, and nothing else but present death. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106740">With restless rage I wander through these woods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106750">No creature here, but feareth Bremo's force:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106760">Man, woman, child, beast, and bird,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106770">And every thing that doth approach my sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106780">Are forced to fall, if Bremo once do frown. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106790">Come, Cudgel come, my partner in my spoils:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106800">For here I see this day it will not be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106810">But when it falls that I encounter any,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106820">One pat sufficeth for to work my will. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106830">What, comes not one? then let's be gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106840">A time will serve when we shall better speed. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e106850">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e106860">Enter the King, Segasto, the shepherd, and the clown, with others.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106870" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106880">Shepherd, thou staft heard thine accusers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106890">Murder is laid to thy charge:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106900">What canst thou say? thou hast deserved death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106910" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106920">Dread sovereign, I must needs confess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106930">I slew this captain in my own defence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106940">Not of any malice, but by chance:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106950">But mine accuser hath a further meaning. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106960" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106970">Words will not here prevail. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e106980">I seek for justice, and justice craves his death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e106990" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107000">Shepherd, thine own confession hath condemned thee;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107010">Sirrah, take him away, and do him to execution straight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107020" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107030">So he shall, I warrant him:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107040">But do you hear master King? he is kin to a monkey,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107050">His neck is bigger than his head. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107060" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107070">Come sirrah, away with him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107080">And hang him about the middle. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107090" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107100">Yes forsooth, I warrant you, come you sirrah:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107110">A, so like a sheep-biter 'a looks. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e107120"><pb facs="11"/>Enter Amadine, and a boy with a bear's head.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107130" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107140">Dread sovereign, and well beloved sir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107150">On bent knee I crave the life of this condemned shepherd, which heretofore preserved the life of thy sometime distressed daughter. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107160" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107170">Preserved the life of my sometime distressed daughter! </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107180">How can that be? I never knew the time</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107190">Wherein was thou distressed: I never knew the day</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107200">But that I have maintained thy estate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107210">As best beseemed the daughter of a King. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107220">I never saw the shepherd until now. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107230">How comes it then that he preserved thy life? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107240" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107250">Once walking with Segasto in the woods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107260">Further than our accustomed manner was,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107270">Right before us down a steep fall hill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107280">A monstrous ugly bear did hie him fast</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107290">To meet us both: now whether this be true,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107300">I refer it to the credit of Segasto. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107310" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107320">Most true an't like your majesty.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107330" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107340">How then?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107350" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107360">The bear being eager to obtain his prey,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107370">Made forward to us with an open mouth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107380">As if he meant to swallow us both at once:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107390">The sight whereof did make us both to dread;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107400">But specially your daughter Amadine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107410">Who, for I saw no succour incident</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107420">But in Segasto's valour, I grew desperate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107430">And he most cowardlike began to fly. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107440">Left me distressed to be devoured of him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107450">How say you Segasto, is it not true? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107460" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107470">His silence verifies it to be true: what then?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107480" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107490">Then I amazed, distressed all alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107500">Did hie me fast, to scape that ugly bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107510">But all in vain; for why he reached after me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107520">And hardly I did oft escape his paws. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107530">Till at the length this shepherd came,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107540">And brought to me his head. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107550">Come hither boy, lo here it is, which I do present unto your majesty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107560" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107570">The slaughter of this bear deserves great fame.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107580" who="A41993-segasto">
          <pb facs="11"/>
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107590">The slaughter of a man deserves great blame.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107600" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107610">Indeed occasion oftentimes so falls out.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107620" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107630">Tremelio in the wars (Oh King) preserved thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107640" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107650">The shepherd in the woods (Oh King) preserved me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107660" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107670">Tremelio fought when many men did yield.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107680" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107690">So would the shepherd had he been in field.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107700" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107710">So would my master, had he not run away.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107720" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107730">Tremelio's force saved thousands from the foe,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107740" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107750">The shepherd's force hath many thousand more.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107760" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107770">Ay shipsticks nothing else.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107780" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107790">Segasto cease to accuse the shepherd,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107800">His worthiness deserves a recompense;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107810">All we are bound to do the shepherd good. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107820">Shepherd, whereas it was my sentence thou shouldst die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107830">So shall my sentence stand, for thou shalt die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107840" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107850">Thanks to your majesty.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107860" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107870">But soft Segasto, not for this offence ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107880">Long mayst thou live; and when the sisters shall decree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107890">To cut in twain the twisted thread of life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107900">Then let him die, for this I set him free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107910">And for thy valour I will honour thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107920" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107930">Thanks to your majesty.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107940" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e107950">Come daughter, let us now depart to honour the worthy valour of the shepherd, with our rewards.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e107960">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e107970" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107980">O master, hear you, you have made a fresh hand now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e107990">I thought you would beshrew you: what will you do now? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108000">You have lost me a good occupation by this means:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108010">Faith master now I cannot hang the shepherd,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108020">I pray you let me take pains to hang you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108030">It is but half an hour's exercise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108040" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108050">You are still in your knavery,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108060">But sith I cannot have his life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108070">I will procure his banishment for ever: come on sirrah. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108080" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108090">Yes forsooth I come. Laugh at him I pray you.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e108100">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e108110">Enter Mucedorus solus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108120" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108130">From Amadine, and from her father's court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108140">With gold and silver and with rich rewards,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108150">Flowing from the banks of gold and treasures:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108160"><pb facs="12"/> more may I boast and say: but I</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108170">Was never shepherd in such dignity. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e108180">Enter the messenger and the clown.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108190" who="A41993-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108200">All hail worthy shepherd.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108210" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108220">All rain lousy shepherd.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108230" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108240">Welcome my friends, from whence come you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108250" who="A41993-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108260">The King and Amadine greet thee well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108270">And after greeting done, bids thee depart the court;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108280">Shepherd be gone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108290" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108300">Shepherd take law-legs: fly away shepherd.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108310" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108320">Whose words are these? came these from Amadine?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108330" who="A41993-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108340">Ay, from Amadine. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108350" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108360">Ay from Amadine. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108370" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108380">Ah luckless fortune, worse than Phaeton's tale,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108390">My former bliss is now become my bale. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108400" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108410">What, wilt thou poison thyself?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108420" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108430">My former heaven is now become my hell.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108440" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108450">The worst alehouse that ever I came in, in all my life.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108460" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108470">What shall I do?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108480" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108490">Even go hang thyself.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108500" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108510">Can Amadine so churlishly command,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108520">To banish the shepherd from her father's court? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108530" who="A41993-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108540">What should shepherds do in the court?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108550" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108560">What should shepherds do among us;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108570">Have not we lords enough on us in the court? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108580" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108590">Why, shepherds are men, and Kings are no more.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108600" who="A41993-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108610">Shepherds are men, and masters over their flocks.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108620" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108630">That's a lie, who pays them their wages then?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108640" who="A41993-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108650">Well, you are always interrupting of me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108660">But you were best to look to him, lest you hang for him when he is gone. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e108670">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e108680">The clown sings.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108690" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108700">And you shall hang for company,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108710">For leaving me alone. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108720">Shepherd stand forth and hear my sentence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108730">Shepherd be gone within three days, in pain of my displeasure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108740">Shepherd be gone, shepherd be gone, be gone, be gone, be gone. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108750">Shepherd, shepherd, shepherd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108760" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108770">And must I go? and must I needs depart? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108780"><pb facs="12"/>Ye goodly groves, partakers of my songs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108790">In time before when fortune did not frown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108800">Pour forth your plaints, and wail awhile with me;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108810">And thou bright sun, the comfort of my cold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108820">Hide, hide thy face and leave me comfortless;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108830">Ye wholesome herbs and sweet smelling savours;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108840">Yea each thing else prolonging life of man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108850">Change, change your wonted course,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108860">That I wanting your aid, in woeful sort may die. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e108870">Enter Amadine and Ariena her maid.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108880" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108890">Ariena, if anybody ask for me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e108900">Make some excuse till I return. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108910" who="A41993-ariena">
          <speaker>Ari.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108920">What and Segasto call?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108930" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108940">Do you the like to him, I mean not to stay long.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e108950">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108960" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108970">This voice so sweet my pining spirit revives.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e108980" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e108990">Shepherd well met, tell me how thou dost.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109000" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109010">I linger life, yet wish for speedy death.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109020" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109030">Shepherd, although thy banishment already he decreed, and all against my will, yet Amadine —</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109040" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109050">Ah Amadine, to hear of banishment is death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109060">I double death to me: but since I must depart, one thing I crave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109070" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109080">Say on with all my heart.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109090" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109100">That in absence either far or near,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109110">You honour me as servant to your name. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109120" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109130">Not so.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109140" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109150">And why?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109160" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109170">I honour thee at sovereign of my heart.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109180" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109190">A shepherd and a sovereign, nothing like.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109200" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109210">Yet like enough where there is no dislike,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109220" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109230">Yet great dislike, or else no banishment.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109240" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109250">Shepherd it is only Segasto that procures thy banishment.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109260" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109270">Unworthy wights are more in jealousy.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109280" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109290">Would God they would free thee from banishment,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109300">Or likewise banish me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109310" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109320">Amen I say, to have your company.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109330" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109340">Well shepherd, sith thou sufferest thus for my sake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109350">With thee in exile also let me live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109360">On this condition shepherd thou canst love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109370" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109380">No longer love, no longer let me live.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109390" who="A41993-amadine">
          <pb facs="13"/>
          <speaker>Am.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109400">Of late I loved one indeed, but now I love none but only thee,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109410" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109420">Thanks worthy Princess: I burn likewise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109430">Yet smother up the blast:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109440">I dare not promise what I may perform. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109450" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109460">Well shepherd, hark what I shall say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109470">I will return unto my father's court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109480">There for to provide me of much necessaries</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109490">As for my journey I shall think most fit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109500">This being done, I will return to thee;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109510">Do thou therefore appoint the place</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109520">Where we may meet ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109530" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109540">Down in the valley where I slew the bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109550">And there doth grow a fair broad branched beech</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109560">That overshades a well, so who comes first,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109570">Let them abide the happy meeting of it both. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109580">How like you this? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109590" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109600">I like in well.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109610" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109620">Now if you please, you may appoint the time.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109630" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109640">Full three hours hence, God willing I will return.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109650" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109660">The thanks that Paris gave the Grecian Queen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109670">The like doth Mucedorus yield. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109680" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109690">Then Mucedorus for three hours farewell.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e109700">Exit,</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109710" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109720">Your departure lady breeds a privy pain.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e109730">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e109740">Enter Segastus solus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109750" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109760">'Tis well Segasto, that thou hast thy will ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109770">Should such a shepherd, such a simple swain as he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109780">Eclipse thy credit famous thorough the court? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109790">No, ply Segasto, ply, let it not in Aragon be said,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109800">A shepherd hath Segasto's honour won. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e109810">Enter mouse the clown, calling his master.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109820" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109830">What, ho master, will you come away?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109840" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109850">Will you come hither, I pray you, what is the matter?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109860" who="A41993-unassigned">
          <speaker>Clown ▪</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109870">Why, is it not passed eleven of the clock?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109880" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109890">How then sir?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109900" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109910">I pray you come away to dinner.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109920" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109930">I pray you come hither.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109940" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109950">Here's such ado with you, will you never come?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109960" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e109970">I pray you sir, what news of the message I sent you about?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e109980" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e109990">I tell you all the messes be on the table already. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110000"><pb facs="13"/>There wants not so much as a mess of mustard, half an hour ago. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110010" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110020">Come sir, your mind is all upon your belly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110030">You have forgotten what I bid you do. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110040" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110050">Faith, I know nothing but you bade me go to breakfast.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110060" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110070">Was that all?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110080" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110090">Faith I have forgotten it, the very scent of the meat hath made me forget it quite.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110100" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110110">You have forgotten the errand I bid you do.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110120" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110130">What errand, an arrant knave, or an arrant whore?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110140" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110150">Why thou knave, did I not bid thee banish the shepherd.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110160" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110170">O the shepherd's bastard.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110180" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110190">I tell thee the shepherd's banishment.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110200" who="A41993-collen">
          <speaker>Col.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110210">I tell you the shepherd's bastard shall be well kept,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110220">I'll look to it myself: but I pray you come away to dinner. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110230" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110240">Then you will not tell me whether you have banished him or no?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110250" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110260">Why I cannot say banishment if you would give me a thousand pounds to say so.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110270" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110280">Why you whoreson slave, have you forgotten that I sent you and another to drive away the shepherd?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110290" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110300">What an ass are you? here's a stir indeed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110310">Here's message, arrant, banishment, and I cannot tell what. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110320" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110330">I pray you sir, shall I know whether you have driven him away?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110340" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110350">Faith I think I have, and you will not believe me, ask my staff.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110360" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110370">Why can thy staff tell?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110380" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110390">Why he was with me too.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110400" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110410">Then happy I, that have obtained my will.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110420" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110430">And happier I if you would go to dinner.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110440" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110450">Come sirrah, follow me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110460" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110470">I warrant you I will not lose an inch of you now you are going to dinner: I promise you I thought seven years before I could get him away.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e110480">Enter Amadine sola.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110490" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110500">God grant my long delay procures no harm</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110510">For this my tarrying frustrate my pretence:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110520">My Mucedorus surely stays for me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110530"><pb facs="14"/> and thinks me overlong, at length I come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110540">My present promise to perform;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110550">Ah what a thing is firm unfeigned love! </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110560">What is it which true love dares not attempt? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110570">My father he may make, but I must match:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110580">Segasto loves, but Amadine must like</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110590">Where likes her best: compulsion is a thrall? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110600">No, no, the hearty choice is all in all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110610">The shepherd's virtue Amadine esteems. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110620">But what, methinks the shepherd is not come;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110630">I muse at that, the hour is at hand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110640">Well here I'll rest till Mucedorus come. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e110650">She sits down.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e110660">Enter Bremo, looking about hastily, takes hold on her.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110670" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110680">A happy prey; now Bremo feed on flesh:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110690">Dainties Bremo, dainties thy hungry paunch to fill;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110700">Now glut thy greedy guts with lukewarm blood:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110710">Come fight with me, I long to see thee dead. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110720" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110730">How can she fight that weapons cannot wield?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110740" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110750">What canst not fight? then lie thee down and die.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110760" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110770">What must I die?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110780" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110790">What needs these words? I thirst to suck thy blood.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110800" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110810">Yet pity me, and let me live awhile.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110820" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110830">No pity I, I'll feed upon thy flesh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110840">And tear thy body piecemeal joint by joint. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110850" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Am.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110860">Ah now I want my shepherd's company.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110870" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110880">I'll crush thy bones between two oaken trees.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110890" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Am.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110900">Hast shepherd, haste, or else thou comest too late.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110910" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110920">I'll suck the sweetness from thy marrowbones.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110930" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e110940">Ah spare, ah spare to shed my guiltless blood.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110950" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110960">With this my bat I will beat out thy brains;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110970">Down, down I say, prostrate thyself upon the ground. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e110980" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e110990">Then Mucedorus' farewell, my hoped joys farewell;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111000">Yea farewell life, and welcome present death. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e111010">She kneels.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111020">To thee, oh God, I yield my dying ghost. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111030" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111040">Now Bremo, play thy part. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111050">How now? what sudden chance is this? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111060">My limbs do tremble, and my sinews shake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111070"><pb facs="14"/> my unweakened arms have lost their former force:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111080">Ah Bremo, Bremo, what a foil hadst thou,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111090">That yet at no time was afraid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111100">To dare the greatest gods to fight with thee,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e111110">He strikes.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111120">And now wants strength for one down driving blow? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111130">Ah how my courage fails when I should strike! </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111140">Some new-come spirit abiding in my breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111150">Saith, spare her Bremo, spare her, do not kill:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111160">Shall I spare her that never spared any? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111170">To it Bremo, to it; say again:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111180">I cannot wield my weapon in my hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111190">Methinks I should not strike so fair a one:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111200">I think her beauty hath bewitched my force,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111210">Or else with me altered natures course. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111220">Ay woman, wilt thou live in woods with me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111230" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111240">Fain would I live, yet loath to live in woods.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111250" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Br.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111260">Thou shalt not choose, it shall be as I say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111270">And therefore follow me. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e111280">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e111290">Enter Mucedorus solus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111300" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111310">It was my will an hour ago and more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111320">As was my promise for to make return;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111330">But other business hindered my pretence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111340">It is a world to see, when men appoints,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111350">And purposely on certain things decrees,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111360">How many things may hinder his intent:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111370">What one would wish, the same is farthest off,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111380">But yet th' appointed time cannot be passed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111390">Nor hath her presence yet prevented me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111400">Well here I'll stay, and expect her coming. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e111410">They cry within, hold him, hold him.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111420">Some one or other is pursued no doubt. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111430">Perhaps some search for me, 'tis good to doubt the worst:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111440">Therefore I'll be gone. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e111450">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e111460">Cry within, hold him, hold him. Enter mouse the clown, with a Pot.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111470" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111480">Hold him, hold him, hold him: here's, a stir indeed; here came hu after the crier; and I was set close at mother nips house,<pb facs="15"/> and there I called for three pots of ale, as 'tis the manner of us courtiers; now sirrah, I had taken the maidenhead of two of them, and as I was lifting up the third to my mouth, there came, hold him, hold him: now I could not tell whom to catch hold on, but I am sure I caught one, perchance 'a may be in this pot; well I'll see, mass I cannot see him yet; well I'll look a little further; mass he is a little slave if he be here: why here's nobody ; all this is well yet. But if the old trot should come for her pot, I marry there's the matter: but I care not, I'll face her out, and call her old rusty, dusty, musty, fusty, crusty firebrand, and worse than all that, and so face her out of her pot: but soft, here she comes.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e111490">Enter the old woman.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111500" who="A41993-old_merrithought">
          <speaker>Old_merrithought</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111510">Come you knave; where's my pot you knave?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111520" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111530">Go look your pot, come not to me for your pot, 'twere good for you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111540" who="A41993-old_merrithought">
          <speaker>Old_merrithought</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111550">Thou liest thou knave, thou hast my pot.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111560" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111570">You lie and you say it, I your pot? I'll know what I'll say.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111580" who="A41993-old_merrithought">
          <speaker>Old_merrithought</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111590">What wilt thou say?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111600" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111610">But say I have it and thou darest.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111620" who="A41993-old_merrithought">
          <speaker>Old_merrithought</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111630">Why thou knave, thou hast not only my pot, but my drink unpaid for.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111640" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111650">You lie like an old ▪ I will not say whore.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111660" who="A41993-old_merrithought">
          <speaker>Old_merrithought</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111670">Dost thou call me whore? I'll cap thee for my pot.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111680" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111690">Cap me and thou darest;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111700">Search me whether I have it or no. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e111710">She searcheth him, and he drinketh over her head, and casteth down the pot, she stumbleth at it: and then they fall together by the ears: she takes up her pot and runs out.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e111720">Enter Segasto.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111730" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111740">How now sirrah, what's the matter?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111750" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111760">O flies master, flies.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111770" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111780">Flies, where are they?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111790" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111800">O here master, all about your face.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111810" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111820">Why thou liest, I think thou art mad.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111830" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111840">Why master I have killed a dungcart full at the least.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111850" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111860">Go to sirrah, leave this idle talk, give ear to me</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111870" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111880">How, give you one of my ears ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111890"><pb facs="15"/> not an you were ten masters. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111900" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111910">Why sir, I pray you give ear to my words.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111920" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e111930">I tell you I will not be made a Curtal for no man's pleasure.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111940" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111950">I tell thee attend what I say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111960">Go thy ways straight and rear the whole town. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e111970" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111980">How, rear the whole town? even go yourself, it is more than I can do: why, do you think I can rear a town, that can scarce rear a pot of ale to my head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e111990">I should rear a town, should I not? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112000" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112010">Go to the constable and make a privy search,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112020">For the shepherd is run away with the King's daughter. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112030" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e112040">How? is the shepherd run away with the King's daughter, or is the King's daughter run away with the shepherd?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112050" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e112060">I cannot tell, but they are both gone together.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112070" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e112080">What a fool is she to run away with the shepherd; why I think I am a little handsomer man than the shepherd myself; but tell me master, must I make a privy search, or search in the privy?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112090" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e112100">Why dost thou think they will be there?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112110" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e112120">I cannot tell.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112130" who="A41993-missing">
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e112140">Seg.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112150">Well then search everywhere ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112160">Leave no place unsearched for them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112170" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e112180">O now I am in office: now will I to that old firebrands house, and will not leave one place unsearched: nay, I'll to the ale-stand, and drink so long as I can stand; and when I have done, I'll let out all the rest, to see if he be not hid in the barrel; and if I find him not there, I'll to the cupboard, I'll not leave one corner of her house unsearched, i'faith ye old crust, I'll be with you now.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e112190">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e112200">Sound music.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e112210">Enter thee King of Valentia, Anselmo, Roderigo, lord Barachius, with others.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112220" who="A41993-king_valentia">
          <speaker>King va</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112230">Enough of music, it but adds to torment,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112240">Delights to vexed spirits are as dates</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112250">Set to a sick man, which rather cloy than comfort:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112260">Let me entreat you to entreat no more. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e112270">Music ceaseth.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112280" who="A41993-roderigo">
          <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e112290">Let your strings sleep, have done there:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112300" who="A41993-king_valentia">
          <speaker>King va</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112310">Mirth to a soul disturbed, are embers turned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112320"><pb facs="16"/> which sudden gleam with molestation,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112330">But sooner lose their sight for't,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112340">'Tis gold bestowed upon a rioter,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112350">Which not relieves but murders him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112360">'Tis a drug given to the healthful,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112370">Which infects, not cures. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112380">How can a father that hath lost his son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112390">A prince both wise, virtuous, and valiant,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112400">Take pleasure in the idle acts of time? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112410">No, no, till Mucedorus I shall see again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112420">All joy is comfortless, all pleasure pain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112430" who="A41993-anselmo">
          <speaker>Ans.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e112440">Your son (My lord) is well.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112450" who="A41993-king_valentia">
          <speaker>King. va</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e112460">I prithee speak that thrice.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112470" who="A41993-anselmo">
          <speaker>Ansel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e112480">The prince your son is safe.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112490" who="A41993-king_valentia">
          <speaker>King. va</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e112500">O where Anselmo? surfeit me with that.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112510" who="A41993-anselmo">
          <speaker>Ans.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112520">In Aragon, my liege, and at his parting,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112530">Bound my secrecy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112540">By his affections love not to disclose it:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112550">But care of him, and pity of your age</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112560">Makes my tongue blab what my breast vowed, concealment. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112570" who="A41993-king_valentia">
          <speaker>King va</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112580">Thou not deceivest me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112590">I ever thought thee what I find thee now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112600">An upright loyal man. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112610">But what desire, or young-fed humour</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112620">Nursed within his brain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112630">Drew him so privately to Aragon? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112640" who="A41993-anselmo">
          <speaker>Ans.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112650">A forcing adamant,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112660">Love mixed with fear and doubtful jealousy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112670">Whether report gilded a worthless trunk,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112680">Or Amadine deserved her high extolment. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112690" who="A41993-king_valentia">
          <speaker>King va</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112700">See our provision be in readiness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112710">Collect us followers of the comeliest hue</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112720">For our chief guardians, we will thither wend;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112730">The crystal eye of heaven shall not thrice wink,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112740">Nor the green flood six times his shoulders turn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112750">Till we salute the Aragonian King. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112760">Music speak loudly now, the season's apt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112770">For former dolours are in pleasures wrapped. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e112780">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e112790"><pb facs="16"/>Enter Mucedorus to disguise himself.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e112800" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112810">Now Mucedorus, whither wilt thou go? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112820">Home to thy father to thy native soil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112830">Or try some long abode within these woods? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112840">Well I will hence depart and hie me home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112850">What hie me home said I? that may not be:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112860">In Amadine rests my felicity. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112870">Then Mucedorus do as thou didst decree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112880">Attire thee hermit-like within these groves:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112890">Walk often to the beech, and view the well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112900">Make settles there, and seat thyself thereon:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112910">And when thou feelest thyself to be a thirst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112920">Then drink a hearty draught to Amadine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112930">No doubt she thinks on thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112940">And will one day come pledge thee at this well. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112950">Come habit, thou art fit for me:</l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e112960">He disguiseth himself.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112970">No shepherd now, an hermit must I be:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112980">Methinks this fits me very well;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e112990">Now must I learn to bear a walking staff,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113000">And exercise some gravity withal. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e113010">Enter the clown.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113020" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113030">Here's through the woods, and through the woods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113040">To look out a shepherd, and a stray King's daughter:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113050">But soft, who have we here? what art thou? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113060" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113070">I am an hermit.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113080" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113090">An Emmet, I never saw such a big Emmet in all my life before.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113100" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113110">I tell you sir, I am an hermit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113120">One that leads a solitary life within these woods. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113130" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113140">O I know thee now; thou art he that eats up all the hips and haws: we could not have one piece of fat bacon for thee all this year.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113150" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113160">Thou dost mistake me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113170">But I pray thee tell me, whom dost thou seek in these woods? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113180" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113190">What do I seek? for a stray King's daughter,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113200">Run away with a shepherd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113210" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113220">A stray King's daughter, run away with a shepherd,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113230">Wherefore, canst thou tell? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113240" who="A41993-clown">
          <pb facs="17"/>
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113250">Yes that I can, 'tis this; my master and Amadine walking one day abroad, nearer these woods than they were used (About what I cannot tell) but towards them comes running a great bear. Now my master played the man, and ran away, and Amadine crying after him: now sir, come, me a shepherd, and he strikes off the bear's head, now whether the bear were dead before or no I cannot tell, for bring twenty bears before me, and bind their hands and feet, and I'll kill them all: now ever since Amadine hath been in love with the shepherd, and for good will she is even run away with the shepherd.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113260" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113270">What manner of man was he? canst describe him to me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113280" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113290">Scribe him, ay I warrant you that I can; 'a was a little, low, broad, tall, narrow, big, well favoured fellow, a jerkin of white cloth, and buttons of the same cloth.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113300" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113310">Thou describest him well, but if I chance to see any such, pray you where shall I find you, or what's your name?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113320" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113330">My name is called master mouse. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113340" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113350">O master mouse, I pray you what office might you bear in the court?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113360" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113370">Marry sir, I am Rusher of the stable.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113380" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113390">O, usher of the table.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113400" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113410">Nay, I say Rusher, and I'll prove mine office good: for look you sir, when any comes from under the sea, or so, and a dog chance to blow his nose backward, then with a whip I give him the good time of the day, and strew rushes presently, therefore I am a Rusher: a high office I promise ye.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113420" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113430">But where shall I find you in the court?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113440" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113450">Why, where it is best being, either in the kitchen eating, or in the buttery drinking: but if you come, I will provide for thee a piece of beef and brews knuckle deep in fat: pray you take pains, remember master mouse. </p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e113460">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113470" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113480">Ay sir, I warrant I will not forget you. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113490">Ah Amadine, what should become of her? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113500">Whither shouldst thou go so long unknown? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113510">With watch and ward each passage is beset,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113520">So that she cannot long escape unknown. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113530">Doubtless, she hath lost herself within these woods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113540">And wandering to and fro, she seeks the well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113550"><pb facs="17"/> which yet she cannot find, therefore will I seek her out. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e113560">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e113570">Enter Bremo and Amadine.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113580" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113590">Amadine, how like you Bremo and his woods?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113600" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113610">As like the woods of Bremo's cruelty:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113620">Though I were dumb and could not answer him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113630">The beasts themselves would with relenting tears</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113640">Bewail thy savage and inhumane deeds. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113650" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113660">My love why dost thou murmur to thyself? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113670">Speak louder, for thy Bremo hears thee not. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113680" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113690">My Bremo, no, the shepherd is my love.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113700" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113710">Have I not saved thee from sudden death. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113720">Given thee leave to live that thou mightest love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113730">And dost thou whet me on to cruelty? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113740">Come kiss me (Sweet) for all my favours past. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113750" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113760">I may not Bremo, therefore pardon me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113770" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113780">See how she flies away from me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113790">I will follow and give attend to her. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113800">Deny my love? A worm of beauty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113810">I will chastise thee: come, come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113820">Prepare thy head upon the block. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113830" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113840">O spare me Bremo, love should limit life. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113850">Not to be made a murderer of himself. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113860">If thou wilt glut thy loving heart with blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113870">Encounter with the lion or the bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113880">And like a wolf, prey not upon a lamb. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113890" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113900">Why then dost thou repine at me? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113910">If thou wilt love me, thou shalt be my Queen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113920">I'll crown thee with a chaplet made of ivory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113930">And make the rose and lily wait on thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113940">I'll rend the burley branches from the oak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113950">To shadow thee from burning sun. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113960">The trees shall spread themselves where thou dost go,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e113970">And as they spread, I'll trace along with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e113980" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e113990">You may, for who but you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114000" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114010">Thou shalt be fed with quails and partridges,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114020">With blackbirds, larks, thrushes, and nightingales. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114030">Thy drink shall be goats-milk, and crystal water,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114040">Distilling from the fountains and the clearest springs:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114050"><pb facs="18"/> and all the dainties that the woods afford,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114060">I'll freely give thee to obtain thy love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114070" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114080">You may, for who but you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114090" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114100">The day I'll spend to recreate my love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114110">With all the pleasures that I can devise:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114120">And in the night I'll be thy bedfellow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114130">And lovingly embrace thee in my arms. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114140" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114150">One may, so may not you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114160" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114170">The satyrs and the wood-nymphs shall attend on thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114180">And lull thee asleep with music sound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114190">And in the morning when thou dost awake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114200">The lark shall sing good morrow to my Queen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114210">And whilst he sings I'll kiss mine Amadine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114220" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114230">You may, for who but you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114240" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114250">When thou art up, the wood-lanes shall be strewed</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114260">With violets, cowslips, and sweet marigolds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114270">For thee to trample and to tread upon:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114280">And I will teach thee how to kill the dear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114290">To chase the heart, and how to rouse the roe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114300">If thou wilt live to love and honour me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114310" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114320">You may for who but you?</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e114330">Enter Mucedorus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114340" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bremo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114350">Welcome sir, an hour ago I looked for such a guest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114360">Be merry wench, we'll have a frolic feast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114370">Here's flesh enough for to suffice us both,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114380">Say sirrah, wilt thou fight, or dost thou mean to die? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114390" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114400">I want a weapon ▪ how can I fight?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114410" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114420">Thou wantest a weapon, why then thou yieldst'st to die?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114430" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114440">I say not so, I do not yield to die.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114450" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114460">Thou shalt not choose, I long to see thee dead.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114470" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114480">Yet spare him Bremo, spare him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114490" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114500">Away, I say I will not spare him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114510" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114520">Yet give me leave to speak.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114530" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114540">Thou shalt not speak.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114550" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114560">Yet give him leave to speak for my sake.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114570" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114580">Speak on, but be not overlong.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114590" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114600">In time of yore, when men-like brutish beasts</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114610">Did lead their lives in loathsome cells and woods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114620"><pb facs="18"/> and wholly gave themselves to witless will:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114630">A rude unruly rout, than man to man became</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114640">A present prey; then might prevailed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114650">The weakest went to walls;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114660">Right was unknown, for wrong was all in all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114670">As men thus lived in their great outrage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114680">Behold one Orpheus came (As poets tell)</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114690">And them from rudeness unto reason brought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114700">Who led by reason soon forsook the woods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114710">In stead of caves they built them castles strong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114720">Cities and towns were founded by them then:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114730">Glad were they, they found such ease,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114740">And in the end they grew to perfect amity. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114750">Weighing their former wickedness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114760">They termed the time wherein they lived then,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114770">A golden age, a good golden age. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114780">New Bremo (For so heard I thee called)</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114790">If men which lived tofore as thou dost now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114800">Wild in woods, addicted all to spoil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114810">Returned were by worthy Orpheus means:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114820">Let me (Like Orpheus) cause thee to return</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114830">From murder, bloodshed, and like cruelties. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114840">What should we fight before we have a cause? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114850">No, let's live and love together faithfully:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e114860">I'll fight for thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114870" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114880">Fight for me, or die: or fight or else thou diest.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114890" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114900">Hold Bremo, hold.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114910" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114920">Away I say, thou troublest me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114930" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114940">You promised me to make me Queen.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114950" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114960">I did, I mean no less.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114970" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e114980">You promised that I should have my will.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e114990" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115000">I did, I mean no less.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115010" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115020">Then save the hermit's life, for he may save us both.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115030" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115040">At thy request I'll save him, but never any after him</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115050">Say hermit, what canst thou do? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115060" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115070">I'll wait on thee, sometime upon thy Queen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115080">Such service shalt thou shortly have as Bremo never had. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e115090">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e115100"><pb facs="19"/>Enter Segasto, the clown, and Rumbelo.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115110" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115120">Come sirs, what shall I never have you find out Amadine and the shepherd?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115130" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115140">I have been thorough the woods, and thorough the woods, and could see nothing but an Emmet.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115150" who="A41993-rumbelo">
          <speaker>Rum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115160">Why I see a thousand emmets, thou meanest a little one.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115170" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115180">Nay, that Emmet that I saw was bigger than thou art.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115190" who="A41993-rumbelo">
          <speaker>Rum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115200">Bigger then I? what a fool have you to your man? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115210">I pray you master turn him away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115220" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115230">But dost thou hear, was he not a man?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115240" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115250">I think he was, for he said he did lead a saltseller's life round about the woods.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115260" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115270">Thou wouldst say a solitary life about the wood.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115280" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115290">I think it was indeed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115300" who="A41993-rumbelo">
          <speaker>Rum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115310">I thought what a fool thou art.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115320" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115330">Thou art a wise man: why he did nothing but sleep since he went.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115340" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115350">But tell me mouse, how did he go?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115360" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115370">In a white gown, and a white hat on his head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115380">And a staff in his hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115390" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115400">I thought so, he was an hermit, that walked a solitary life in the woods. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115410">Well, get you to dinner, and after, never leave seeking till you bring some news of them, or I'll hang you both. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e115420">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115430" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115440">How now Rumbelo, what shall we do now?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115450" who="A41993-rumbelo">
          <speaker>Rum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115460">Faith I'll whom to dinner, and afterwards to sleep.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115470" who="A41993-unassigned">
          <speaker>Clown ▪</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115480">Why then thou wilt be hanged.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115490" who="A41993-rumbelo">
          <speaker>Rum.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115500">Faith I care not, for I know I shall never find them:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115510">Well, I'll once more abroad; and if I cannot find them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115520">I'll never come home again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115530" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115540">I tell thee what Rumbelo, thou shalt go in at one end of the wood, and I at the other, and we will both meet together in the midst.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115550" who="A41993-rumbelo">
          <speaker>Rum.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115560">Content, let's away to dinner.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e115570">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e115580">Enter Mucedorus solus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115590" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115600">Unknown to any, here within these woods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115610">With bloody Bremo do I lead my life;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115620">The monster he doth murder all he meets,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115630"><pb facs="19"/> he spareth none, and none doth him escape:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115640">Who would continue, who but only I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115650">In such a cruel cutthroats company? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115660">Yet Amadine is there, how can I choose? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115670">Ah silly soul, how oftentimes she sits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115680">And sighs, and calls, come shepherd, come:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115690">Sweet Mucedorus come set me free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115700">When Mucedorus (Peasant) stands her by;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115710">But here she comes: what news fair lady,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115720">As you walk these woods? </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e115730">Enter Amadine.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115740" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115750">Ah hermit, none but bad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115760">And such as thou knowest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115770" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115780">How do you like your Bremo and his woods?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115790" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115800">Not my Bremo, nor his Bremo woods.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115810" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115820">And why not yours? methinks he loves you well.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115830" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115840">I like not him, his love to me is nothing worth.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115850" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115860">Lady, in this methinks you offer wrong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115870">To hate the man that ever loves you best. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115880" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115890">Ah hermit, I take no pleasure in his love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115900">Neither doth Bremo like me best. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115910" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115920">Pardon my boldness, fair lady, sith we both</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115930">May safely talk now out of Bremo's sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115940">Unfold to me, if you please, the full discourse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115950">How, when, and why you came into these woods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e115960">And fell into this bloody butcher's hands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115970" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e115980">Hermit I will: of late a worthy shepherd I did love.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e115990" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116000">A shepherd (Lady) sure a man unfit to match with you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116010" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116020">Hermit, this is true: and when we had —</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116030" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116040">Stay there, the wild man comes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116050">Refer the rest until another time. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e116060">Enter Bremo.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116070" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116080">What secret tale is this? what whispering have we here? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116090">Villain, I charge thee tell thy tale again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116100" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116110">If needs I must, lo here it is again. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116120">Whenas we both had lost the sight of thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116130">It grieved us both, but specially thy Queen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116140">Who in thy absence e'er fears the worst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116150">Lest some mischance befall your royal grace. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116160"><pb facs="20"/>Shall my sweet Bremo wander through the wood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116170">Toil to and fro, for to redress my want,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116180">Hazard his life, and all to cherish me? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116190">I like not this quoth she:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116200">And thereupon crave to know of me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116210">If I could teach her handle weapons well. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116220">My answer was, I had small skill therein:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116230">But gladsome (Mighty King) to learn of thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116240">And this was all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116250" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116260">Wast so? none can mislike of this:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116270">I'll teach you both to fight, but first my Queen begin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116280">Here take this weapon, see how thou canst use it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116290" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116300">This is too big, I cannot wield it in mine arm.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116310" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116320">Is't so? we'll have a knotty crabtree staff for thee;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116330">But sirrah, tell me, what sayest? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116340" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116350">With all my heart I willing am to learn.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116360" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116370">Then take my staff and see how thou canst wield it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116380" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116390">First teach me to how hold it in mine hand.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116400" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116410">Thou holdest it well; look how he doth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116420">Thou mayest the sooner learn. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116430" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116440">Next tell how, and when 'tis best to strike.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116450" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116460">'Tis best to strike when time doth serve,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116470">'Tis best to lose no time. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116480" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116490">Then now or never it is time to strike.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116500" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116510">And when thou strikest, be sure to hit the head.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116520" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116530">The head?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116540" who="A41993-bremo">
          <speaker>Bre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116550">The very head.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116560" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116570">Then have at thine. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e116580">He strikes him down dead.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116590">So, lie there and die, a death (No doubt) according to desert,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116600">Or else a worse, as thou deservest worse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116610" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116620">It glads my heart this tyrant's death to see.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116630" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116640">Now lady it remains in you</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116650">To end the tale you lately had begun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116660">Being interrupted by this wicked wight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116670">You said you loved a shepherd. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116680" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116690">Ay, so I do, and none but only him:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116700">And will do still as long as life shall last. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116710" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116720">But tell me lady, sith I set you free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116730"><pb facs="20"/> what course of life do you intend to take? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116740" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116750">I will disguised wander thorough the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116760">Till I have found him out. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116770" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116780">How if you find your shepherd in these woods?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116790" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116800">Ah! none so happy then as Amadine. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e116810">He discloseth himself.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116820" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116830">In tract of time a man may alter much:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116840">Say lady, do you know your shepherd well? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116850" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116860">My Mucedorus, hath he set me free?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116870" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116880">He hath set thee free.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116890" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e116900">And lived so long unknown to Amadine?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e116910" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116920">Ay that's a question whereof you may not be resolved:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116930">You know that I am banished from the court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116940">I know likewise each passage is beset,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116950">So that we cannot long escape unknown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116960">Therefore my will is this, that we return,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116970">Right thorough the thickets to the wild man's cave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116980">And there a while live on his provision,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e116990">Until the search and narrow watch be passed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117000">This is my council, and I like it best. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117010" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117020">I think the very same.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117030" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117040">Come let's be gone.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e117050">The clown searcheth, and falls over the wild man, and so caries him away.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117060" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117070">Nay soft sir, are you here? abot● on you</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117080">I was like to be hanged for not finding of you:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117090">We would borrow a certain stray King's daughter of you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117100">A wench, a wench sir, we would have. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117110" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117120">A wench of me? I'll make thee eat my sword.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117130" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117140">O lord, nay, and you are so lusty, I'll call a calling-card for you: oh master, master, come away quickly.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e117150">Enter Segasto.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117160" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117170">What's the matter?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117180" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117190">Look, Amadine and the shepherd ▪ oh brave.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117200" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117210">What minion, have I found you out?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117220" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117230">Nay that's a lie, I found her out myself.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117240" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Seg.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117250">Thou gadding housewife, what cause hadst thou</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117260">To gad abroad? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117270"><pb facs="21"/> whenas thou knowest our wedding day so nigh? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117280" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117290">Not so Segasto, no such thing in hand:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117300">Show your assurance, then I'll answer you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117310" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117320">Thy father's promise my assurance is.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117330" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117340">But what he promised he hath not performed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117350" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117360">It rests in thee for to perform the same.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117370" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117380">Not I.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117390" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117400">And why?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117410" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117420">So is my will, and therefore even no.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117430" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117440">Master with a none, none so.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117450" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117460">Ah wicked villain, art thou here?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117470" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117480">What need these words? weigh them not.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117490" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117500">We weigh them not, proud shepherd I scorn thy company.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117510" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117520">We'll not have a corner of thy company.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117530" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117540">I scorn not thee, nor yet the least of thine.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117550" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117560">That's a lie, 'a would have killed me with his pugs-nando.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117570" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117580">This stoutness Amadine contents me not.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117590" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117600">Then seek another that may you better please.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117610" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117620">Well Amadine it only rests in thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117630">Without delay to make thy choice of three:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117640">There stands Segasto, a second here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117650">There stands the third: now make thy choice. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117660" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117670">A lord at the least I am.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117680" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117690">My choice is made, for I will none but thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117700" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117710">A worthy mate (No doubt) for such a wife.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117720" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117730">And Amadine, why wilt thou none but me? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117740">I cannot keep thee as thy father did;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117750">I have no lands for to maintain thy state:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117760">Moreover, if thou mean to be my wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117770">Commonly this must be thy use,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117780">To bed at midnight, up at four,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117790">Drudge all day, and trudge from place to place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117800">Whereby our daily victual for to win;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117810">And last of all, which is the worst of all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117820">No Princess then, but a plain shepherd's wife. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117830" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117840">Then God give you good morrow goody shepherd.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117850" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117860">It shall not need if Amadine do live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117870">Thou shalt be crowned King of Aragon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117880" who="A41993-clown">
          <pb facs="21"/>
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117890">O master laugh, when he is a King, I'll be a Queen.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117900" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117910">Then know that which heretofore was known:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117920">I am no shepherd, no Aragonion I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117930">But born of royal blood: my father's of Valentia King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117940">My mother Queen; who for thy sacred sake</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117950">Took this hard task in hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117960" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e117970">Ah how I joy my fortune is so good.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e117980" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e117990">Well now I see Segasto shall not speed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118000">But Mucedorus, I as much do joy</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118010">To see thee here within our court of Aragon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118020">As if a kingdom had befallen me this time:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118030">I with my heart surrender her to thee. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e118040">He gives her to him.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118050">And look what right to Amadine I have. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118060" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118070">What barns door, and born where my father was constable? A bot's on thee, how dost thou?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118080" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118090">Thanks Segasto, but you levelled at the crown.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118100" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118110">Master, bear this and bear all.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118120" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118130">Why so sirrah?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118140" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118150">He says you take a goose by the crown.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118160" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118170">Go too sirrah; away, post you to the King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118180">Whose heart is fraught with careful doubts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118190">Glad him up, and tell him these good news,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118200">And we will follow as fast as we may. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118210" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118220">I go master, I run master.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e118230">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e118240">Enter the King and Collin.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118250" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118260">Break heart, and end my pallid woes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118270">My Amadine, the comfort of my life;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118280">How can I joy except she were in sight? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118290">Her absence breeds great sorrow to my soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118300">And with a thunder breaks my heart in twain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118310" who="A41993-collen">
          <speaker>Collin.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118320">Forbear those passions gentle King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118330">And you shall see 'twill turn unto the best,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118340">And bring your soul to quiet and to joy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118350" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118360">Such joy as death, I do assure me that,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118370">And naught but death, except of her I hear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118380">And that with speed, I cannot sigh thus long:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118390">But what a tumult do I hear within? </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e118400"><pb facs="22"/>They cry within, joy and happiness.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118410" who="A41993-collen">
          <speaker>Collin.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118420">I hear a noise of overpassing joy</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118430">Within the court: my lord be of good comfort,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118440">And here comes one in haste. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e118450">Enter the clown running.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118460" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118470">A King, a King.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118480" who="A41993-collen">
          <speaker>Col.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118490">Why how now sirrah, what's the matter?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118500" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118510">O 'tis news for a King, 'tis worth money.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118520" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118530">Why sirrah, thou shalt have silver and gold if it be good.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118540" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118550">O 'tis good, 'tis good Amadine. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118560" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118570">O what of her? tell me, and I will make thee a knight.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118580" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118590">How a spright, no by lady, I will not be a spright. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118600">Master get you away, if I be a spright, I shall be so lean</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118610">I shall make you all afraid. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118620" who="A41993-collen">
          <speaker>Col.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118630">Then (Sot) the King means to make thee a gentleman.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118640" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118650">Why I shall want 'parel.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118660" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118670">Thou shalt want for nothing.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118680" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118690">Then stand away, strike up thyself, here they come.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e118700">Enter Segasto, Mucedorus, and Amadine.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118710" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118720">My gracious father, pardon thy disloyal daughter.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118730" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118740">What, do mine eyes behold my daughter Amadine? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118750">Rise up daughter, and let these embracing arms</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118760">Show some token of thy father's joy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118770">Which ever since thy departure hath languished in sorrow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118780" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118790">Dear father, never were your sorrows</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118800">Greater than my griefs:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118810">Never you so desolate as I comfortless:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118820">Yet nevertheless knowing myself</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118830">To be the cause of both, on bent knees</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118840">I humbly crave your pardon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118850" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118860">I'll pardon thee (Dear daughter) but as for him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118870" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118880">Ay father, what of him?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118890" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118900">As sure as I am King, and wear the crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e118910">I'll be revenged on that accursed wretch. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118920" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118930">Yet worthy prince, work not thy will in wrath, show favour.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118940" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118950">Ay, such favour as thou deservest.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118960" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118970">I do deserve the daughter of a King.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e118980" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e118990">O impudent! A shepherd and so insolent.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119000" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <pb facs="22"/>
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e119010">No shepherd I, but a worthy prince.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119020" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e119030">In fair conceit, not princely born.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119040" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119050">Yes princely born, my father is a King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119060">My mother a Queen, and of Valentia both. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119070" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119080">What Mucedorus, welcome to our court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119090">What cause hadst thou to come to me disguised? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119100" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119110">No cause to fear, I caused no offence;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119120">But this, desiring thy daughters virtues for to see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119130">Disguised myself from out my father's court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119140">Unknown to any in secret I did rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119150">And passed many troubles near to death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119160">So hath your daughter my partaker been. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119170">As you shall know hereafter more at large:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119180">Desiring you, you will give her to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119190">Even as mine own, and sovereign of my life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119200">Then shall I think my travels all well spent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119210" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119220">With all my heart, but this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119230">Segasto claims my promise made tofore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119240">That he should have her as his only wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119250">Before my council when he came from war. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119260">Segasto, may I crave thee let it pass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119270">And give Amadine as wife to Mucedorus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119280" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119290">With all my heart, were it a far greater thing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119300">And what I may to furnish up their rites,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119310">With pleasing sports and pastimes you shall see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119320" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e119330">Thanks good Segasto, I will think of this.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119340" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119350">Thanks good my lord, and whilst I live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119360">Account of me in what I can or may. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119370" who="A41993-amadine">
          <speaker>Ama.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119380">Good Segasto, these great courtesies</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119390">Shall not be forgotten. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119400" who="A41993-clown">
          <speaker>Clown</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119410">Why hark you master, bones what have you done? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119420">What, given away the wench you made me take such pains for? You are wise indeed. Mass and I had known of that, I would have had her myself: faith master now we may go to breakfast with a wood-cock-pie. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119430" who="A41993-segasto">
          <speaker>Segast.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e119440">Go too sirrah ▪ you were best to leave this knavery.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119450" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119460">Come on my lords, let's now to court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119470">Where we may finish up the joyfullest day</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119480"><pb facs="23"/> that ever happed to a distressed King:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119490">Were but thy father the Valentia lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119500">Present in view of this combined knot. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e119510">A shout within: enter messenger.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119520">What shout was that? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119530" who="A41993-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119540">My lord the great Valentia King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119550">Newly arrived, entreats your presence. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119560" who="A41993-mucedorus">
          <speaker>Muc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e119570">My father?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119580" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King ara.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119590">Prepared welcomes give him entertainment;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119600">A happier planet never reigned then that</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119610">Which governs at this hour. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e119620">Sound.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e119630">Enter the King of Valentia, Anselmo, Roderigo, Brachius, with others: the King runs and embraceth his son.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119640" who="A41993-king_valentia">
          <speaker>King Val.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119650">Rise honour of my age, food to my rest:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119660">Condemn not (Mighty King of Aragon)</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119670">My rude behaviour, so compelled by nature,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119680">That manners stood unknowledged. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119690" who="A41993-king">
          <speaker>King ara.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119700">What we have to recite would tedious prove</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119710">By declaration, therefore in and feast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119720">Tomorrow the performance shall explain</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119730">What words conceal: till then drums speak, bells ring ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119740">Give plausive welcomes to our brother King. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e119750">Sound drums and trumpets.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e119760">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A41993-e119770">Enter comedy and envy.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119780" who="A41993-comedy">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119790">How now envy; what blushest thou already? </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119800">Peep forth, hide not thy head with shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119810">But with courage praise a woman's deeds;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119820">Thy threats were vain, thou couldst do me no hurt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119830">Although thou seemed'st to cross me with despite,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119840">I overwhelmed and turned upside down thy blocks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119850">And made thyself to stumble at the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119860" who="A41993-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119870">Though stumbled, yet not overthrown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119880">Thou canst not draw my head to mildness:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119890">Yet must I needs confess thou hast done well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119900">And played thy part with mirth and pleasant glee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119910">Say all this; yet canst thou not conquer me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119920">Although this time thou hast got,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119930">Yet not the conquest neither. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119940"><pb facs="23"/>A double revenge another time I'll have. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e119950" who="A41993-comedy">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119960">Envy spit thy gall;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119970">Plot, work, contrive, create new fallacies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119980">Teem from thy womb each minute a black traitor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e119990">Whose blood and thoughts have twins conception:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120000">Study to act deeds yet unchronicled,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120010">Cast native monsters in the moulds of men;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120020">Case vicious devils under sancted robes;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120030">Unhasp the wicket where all perjuries roost,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120040">And swarm this ball with treasons, do thy worst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120050">Thou canst not (Hellhound) cross my star too night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120060">Nor blind that glory where I wish delight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e120070" who="A41993-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e120080">I can, I will.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e120090" who="A41993-comedy">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120100">Nefarious hag begin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120110">And let us tug till one the mastery win. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e120120" who="A41993-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120130">Comedy, thou art a shallow goose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120140">I'll overthrow thee in thine own intent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120150">And make thy fall my comic merriment. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e120160" who="A41993-comedy">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120170">Thy policy wants gravity, thou art too weak;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120180">Speak friend, as how? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e120190" who="A41993-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120200">Why thus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120210">From my foul study will I hoist a wretch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120220">A lean and hungry meager cannibal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120230">Whose jaws swell to his eyes with chewing malice;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120240">And him I'll make a poet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e120250" who="A41993-comedy">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A41993-e120260">What's that to the purpose?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e120270" who="A41993-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120280">This scrambling raven with his needy beard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120290">Will I whet on to write a comedy;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120300">Wherein shall be composed dark sentences,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120310">Pleasing to factious brains;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120320">And every otherwhere place me a jest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120330">Whose high abuse shall more torment then blows. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120340">Then I myself (Quicker than lightning)</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120350">Will fly me to the puissant magistrate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120360">And waiting with a trencher at his back,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120370">In midst of jollity rehearse those gauls</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120380">(With some additions) so lately vented in your theater;</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120390">He on this cannot but make complaint</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120400"><pb facs="24"/> to our great danger, or at least restraint. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e120410" who="A41993-comedy">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120420">Ha, ha, ha, I laugh to hear thy folly:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120430">This is a trap for boys, not men, nor such,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120440">Especially deceitful in their doings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120450">Whose staid discretion rules their purposes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120460">I and my faction do eschew those vices:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120470">But see, oh see, the weary sun for rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120480">Hath lain his golden compass to the West,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120490">Where he perpetual bide, and ever shine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120500">As David's offspring in his happy clime. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120510">Stoop envy, stoop, bow to the earth with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120520">Let's beg our pardon on our bent knee. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e120530">They kneel.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e120540" who="A41993-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120550">My power hath lost her might, envies date's expired. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120560">And I amazed am. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A41993-e120570">Fall down and quake.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e120580" who="A41993-comedy">
          <speaker>Com.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120590">Glorious and wise Arch-caesar on this earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120600">At whose appearance envy's strucken dumb,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120610">And all bad things cease operation:</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120620">Vouchsafe to pardon our unwilling error,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120630">So late presented to your gracious view,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120640">And we'll endeavour with excess of pain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120650">To please your senses in a choicer strain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120660">Thus we commit you to the arms of night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120670">Whose spangled carcase would for your delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120680">Strive to excel the day: be blessed then,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120690">Who other wishes, let him never speak. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A41993-e120700" who="A41993-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120710">Amen. </l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120720">To fame and honour we commend your rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A41993-e120730">Live still more happy, every hour more blessed. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer xml:id="A41993-e120740">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A41993"><item xml:id="A41993-clown" n="128">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-clown</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">128</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-segasto" n="104">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-segasto</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">104</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-mucedorus" n="94">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-mucedorus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">94</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A41993-amadine" n="82">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-amadine</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">82</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-bremo" n="38">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-bremo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">38</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-king" n="30">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-king</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">30</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-envy" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-envy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-comedy" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-comedy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-anselmo" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-anselmo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-collen" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-collen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-king_valentia" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-king_valentia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-messenger" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-tremelio" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-tremelio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-rumbelo" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-rumbelo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-old_merrithought" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-old_merrithought</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-unassigned" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-mouse" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-mouse</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-ariena" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-ariena</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-missing" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-missing</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A41993-roderigo" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A41993-roderigo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

