<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A19347">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>2 The Cid<date type="creation_date">1640</date></title>
        <author>Desfontaines, Nicolas-Marc</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nayoon Ahn</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A19347.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The second part of the Cid.</title>
            <author>Desfontaines, Nicolas-Marc, d. 1652.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>35 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2007 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99844351</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 5771.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 596.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">9155</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19347</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The second part of the Cid.</title>
            <title type="alt">Vraye suitte du Cid. English</title>
            <title type="alt">La vraye suitte du Cid.</title>
            <title type="add">Le Cid.</title>
            <author>Desfontaines, Nicolas-Marc, d. 1652.</author>
            <author>J.R. fl. 1635-1640,</author>
            <author>Corneille, Pierre, 1606-1684.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[72] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by I. Okes, for Samuell Browne, and are to be sold at his shop in St. Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the white Lion,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>M.D.C.XL. [1640]</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Translator's dedication signed: J. Rutter.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>A translation of: Desfontaines, Nicolas-Marc. La vraye suitte du Cid.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>A sequel to: Corneille, Pierre. Le Cid.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-C12.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>With an initial imprimatur leaf.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Cid, -- ca. 1043-1099 -- Drama -- Early works to 1800.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A19347-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A19347-e100020">
      <div type="imprimatur" xml:id="A19347-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A19347-e100040">Imprimatur Matth</p>
        <p xml:id="A19347-e100050">Clay.</p>
        <p xml:id="A19347-e100060">Aprilis 6.</p>
        <p xml:id="A19347-e100070">1639.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A19347-e100080">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A19347-e100090">The second part of the Cid.</p>
        <p xml:id="A19347-e100100">London, printed by I. Okes, for Samuel brown, and are to be sold at his shop in st. Paul's churchyard at the sign of the white lion.</p>
        <p xml:id="A19347-e100110"> mdcxl Xl.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A19347-e100120">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head><pb facs="2"/>To the truly noble the lady, Theophila Cooke. </head>
        <opener xml:id="A19347-e100130">
          <salute xml:id="A19347-e100140">Madam,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p xml:id="A19347-e100150">If I had no obligation to your ladyship, which might challenge my endeavours of honouring you, a fitter or a happier name could not protect this piece, (Whose subject is the preferring of duty, and respects before love, as the former did honour and courage:) which I therefore offer to<pb facs="3"/> your ladyship; because in them there is none better studied than yourself, in whom I have observed from the strength of virtue, such a serenity as conducts your mind to the performance of whatsoever is fit and decent in humane life. And I remember I had the honour to hear your ladyship discourse of this subject, when you concluded that a perfect lover should submit his desires to his mistress's advancement: which made me wish that our French author had spoken with those graces here in this, with which your ladyship then did. But since it pleased his majesty to think it worth the translating, and commanded it to be put into my hands, I will not censure it, though I believe, if that may carry the place which is free from deformities, without excellence before that which is here and there exceeding fair, and as much blemished, I think this may deserve it, which is rather not to be excepted to then much extolled. Whatsoever it be, I beseech your ladyship to let it<pb facs="3"/> pass under your name, lest I be thought indiscreet in placing it elsewhere, or unmindful of what I owe you, though this be the least part of that return which is meant to you from</p>
        <closer xml:id="A19347-e100160">
          <signed xml:id="A19347-e100170">Your most humble and obedient servant, Erutter.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A19347-e100180">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <head>The persons of the play. </head>
        <list xml:id="A19347-e100190">
          <item xml:id="A19347-e100200">The young King of Castille. </item>
          <item xml:id="A19347-e100210">Dam. Urraca the infanta his sister.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19347-e100220">Celimant King of Corduba. </item>
          <item xml:id="A19347-e100230">Spheranti prince of Toledo. </item>
          <item xml:id="A19347-e100240">Seriffa sister to Celimant.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19347-e100250">D. Diego father to the Cid.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19347-e100260">Roderigo the Cid.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19347-e100270">Cimena.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19347-e100280">D. Sancho favourite to the King.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19347-e100290">D. Arias.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19347-e100300">Guard. Attendants. Page to Cimena.</item>
        </list>
        <p xml:id="A19347-e100310">The scene.</p>
        <p xml:id="A19347-e100320">The court of Seville.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A19347-e100330">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A19347-e100340">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <head>The second part of the Cid.</head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A19347-e100350">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e100360">
            <head>Act i. scene i.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e100370">Infanta. Cimena.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e100380" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>Infanta.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e100390">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100400">Tell me Cimena and deal truly with me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100410">What makes you thus disdain to be a Queen,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100420">Are the allurements of a kingdom such</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100430">As they can hardly touch, less charm your heart? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100440">No, I shall ne'er believe it, but must wonder</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100450">At your refusal: do you think your Cid</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100460">With all his fortune, and the best effects</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100470">Of his great valour, can at any time</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100480"><pb facs="5"/> impale this fair head with a diadem? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100490">That from the King alone you must expect</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100500">Cid is as much a subject as thyself,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100510">And though he lift thy fortune to a height</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100520">As great as any subjects, yet a thousand</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100530">Will side with thee, when this my brother offers</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100540">Will set thy beauties in a point to strike</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100550">The gazer's eyes with envy, or amazement. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e100560" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e100570">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100580">Madam, 'tis true so great a prince's love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100590">Might take another, though it cannot me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100600">And the false lustre of a sovereign greatness</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100610">May dazzle any fond young virgin's eyes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100620">But for my own direction I'll take less</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100630">Of their ambition, more of modesty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100640">And truly madam, I shall never envy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100650">Her who enjoys the happiness you offer,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100660">The pomp of thrones seems troublesome to me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100670">My desires draw themselves within their compass,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100680">And look no higher than their proper reach:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100690">Equality does make the perfect match,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100700">Unequal persons render the link so weak</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100710">That love can hardly make it hold together. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e100720" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e100730">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100740">I know Cimena thy great modesty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100750">But let it not divert thee from a good</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100760">Sent from the hand of heaven, and a King. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100770">That power, which gave thee such rare parts, would never</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100780">They should be straightened in a narrow fortune</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100790">It knows this fore head's destined for a crown</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100800">Which to confirm, it makes a monarch know</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100810">That naught less than himself can suit thy merit</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100820">Though Cid have heretofore made thee his idol. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100830">Dost think his love's not subject unto change</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100840">And that he must continue in his absence</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100850">As a great soldier, so a faithful lover ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100860"><pb facs="5"/> perhaps thy love may trouble him at present,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100870">Whilst his ambition grows up with his fortune ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100880">If e'er he gained his glorious name of Cid,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100890">He thought himself already worthy thee,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100900">Dost think his heart will stay in the same bounds,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100910">Now that all Spain, and other nations</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100920">Admire and fear his valour? ah Cimena</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100930">Some thing persuades me that his hopes fly higher,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100940">A throne will be the certain rock whereon</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100950">Thy so much boasted faith must find its tomb. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e100960" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e100970">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100980">O heavens, how handsomely she would surprise me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e100990">And ravish that from me herself would have! <stage xml:id="A19347-e101000">Aside</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101010">I without doubt she loves him; and I know</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101020">She speaks more for herself then for the King:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101030">Madam, if Roder go leave Cimena</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101040">To give his heart unto a nobler love,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101050">You shall perceive that she is one can suffer</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101060">With as much ease his lightness, as his absence. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101070" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e101080">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101090">But since thou hast the very same advantage</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101100">Serve thyself of it, and as his great honours</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101110">Alter his passions, so let thine Cimena</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101120">Take the same flight, and do not think thou shalt</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101130">For that, be called inconstant or less faithful,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101140">Or that thy change should stick a crime upon thee,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101150">The wills of Kings can render all things lawful. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101160">Besides thy father's death may well excuse thee,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101170">And I remember with how much constraint</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101180">Thou madest a promise of thy love to him</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101190">Which was no more than hope; the King has power</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101200">To cancel that, nor must thy virtue suffer</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101210">So great a stain as to prefer the man</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101220">Who killed thy father to the King. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101230" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e101240">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101250">But madam. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101260"><pb facs="6"/>You know how strong a conflict I had in me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101270">Before I gave consent, whilst his great love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101280">Did less than my obedience, I resisted</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101290">Till in the end I saw I must obey</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101300">What the King willed, he said, I must forget</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101310">His crime and my revenge: your father madam</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101320">Gave me into his hands, and since I am</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101330">His prisoner ▪ the same bonds shall end my life</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101340">And fortune both at once. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101350" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e101360">But hear my reasons. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101370" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e101380">To what purpose. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e101390">Should we dispute of what's resolved already? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101400" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e101410">Well you may think of it at better leisure. <stage xml:id="A19347-e101420">Exit.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101430" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e101440">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101450">Yes: and I know the object of my choice:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101460">If the cid's glory do put out his flame;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101470">And that's great lustre quench the heat of this</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101480">I shall not stay the progress of his fortune,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101490">Let him be on a throne, me in my grave,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101500">Yet if this head must ever wear a crown</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101510">From none but Cid himself shall I accept it. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101520">But what's the reason that he writes not to me? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101530">I had some letters from him at the first,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101540">When the same hand which was bedewed in blood</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101550">Dried up my tears, but yet (Alas) I fear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101560">Lest distance of our eyes estrange our hearts:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101570">For of late (Save the conquest of the rebels)</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101580">I can hear nothing from him, he destroys</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101590">His enemies and my hopes both at one time,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101600">His glory makes him to forget his duty;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101610">But yet dear heart excuse my sad complaint</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101620">True love was never yet without some fear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101630">Thou canst not be so generous and inconstant,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101640"><pb facs="6"/> and I should fear less, loved I not so much. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101650">Come then my foul and make no longer trial</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101660">Both of my passion and my patience:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101670">Come to deliver me from those my doubts</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101680">Or know that here I cannot live without thee. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e101690">
            <head>Scene ii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e101700">Don Sancho.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A19347-e101710">Who's this don Sancho? what may his business be? </l>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101720" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e101730">The best of news unto the best of women. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101740" who="A19347-unassigned">
              <speaker>Cim ▪</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e101750">What news? Is Cid returned? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101760" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e101770">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101780">Not yet sweet madam,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101790">He's still expected, but a greater joy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101800">Attends you, which will soon dispel these clouds,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101810">How glorious is your fortune like to be? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101820" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e101830">What? has he overcome his enemies? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e101840">Is he come home laden with palms and laurels? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101850" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e101860">I hear his valour has assured our state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e101870">But that is not the cause of this my visit. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101880" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e101890">What's then my happiness, pray let me know it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e101900" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e101910">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101920">Madam advise but with your own perfections</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101930"><pb facs="7"/> and you will know the good provided for you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101940">Ask counsel of your eyes; and they will tell you</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101950">'Gainst whom their quick and burning darts are thrown</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101960">They'll tell you that a King sprightly and young</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101970">Chooses to be a slave before himself:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101980">And that he finds his chains so sweet and pleasant</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e101990">He seems to have no will to reign without you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102000">And I am sent to ask what he implores,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102010">Be not then rigorous to yourself and him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102020">But think what baits a sceptre carries in it,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102030">And that 'twill ill become you to be cruel</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102040">When a crown, and title of a Queen is offered. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e102050" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e102060">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102070">I me sure it less becomes thee to afflict me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102080">With a discourse so hateful, perjured man</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102090">Hast thou so little shame, and courage in thee</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102100">To speak this and not blush; hast thou forgotten</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102110">The glory of thy bonds; and that myself</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102120">Permitted thee to wear 'em, whilst my pity</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102130">Made my looks gracious to thee, couldst thou then</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102140">Having been once a lover, proud to be so,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102150">Speak for another now, and that I should</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102160">For thy sake take his love into my heart. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102170">Thou showst by this thy baseness, how unworthy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102180">Was Roderigo's rival, since thou canst not</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102190">Preserve the honour which thou hadst, for once</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102200">To have been his competitor. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e102210" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e102220">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102230">Did I think</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102240">That you bore any thoughts of love to me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102250">Or that th' impression of my former flame</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102260">Were not quite worn out of your heart, I should not</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102270">Speak for the King a word, but for myself,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102280">And you should see by my great constancy,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102290">How much I'd cherish such a hope. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e102300" who="A19347-cimena">
              <pb facs="7"/>
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e102310">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102320">What traitor</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102330">Should I love thee? canst thou imagine it? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102340">Or tempt thyself with such a vanity;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102350">I never yet received a flame so hateful</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102360">And if I thought my heart could entertain it,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102370">I'd pull it out myself: but canst thou have</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102380">The confidence, don Sancho to pretend</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102390">To what thou wert not able to defend;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102400">Hast thou forgotten the duel where thou wert</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102410">Forced to bring me the sword thou vainly hadst</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102420">Employed against the Cid, is it for that</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102430">Thou layest thy claim to my affection? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102440">For that must I prefer thee to the man</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102450">Whom the Moors fear, and Spain does reverence? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102460">Come let me hear thy actions; were our enemies</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102470">Defeated by thy valour? Did the Moors</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102480">Yield themselves at the hearing of thy name? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102490">Does thy arm hold our tottering kingdom up? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102500">Art thou the glory of it? prove it true</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102510">And I will run into thy dear embraces. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e102520" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e102530">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102540">Madam, I have not so much arrogance</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102550">To challenge to myself such mighty deeds. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102560">My actions bound themselves more narrowly:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102570">I never did defeat the Moors, my arm</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102580">Could ne'er do any thing worth your acceptance,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102590">And yet it reek, not with your father's blood. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e102600" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e102610">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102620">Knows thy fierce rage no bounds, takest thou delight</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102630">To persecute me still, art thou not weary</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102640">To see my tears run? thou mightst easier draw</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102650">My blood, and kill me with less cruelty. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102660">Come make it perfect, and revenge thy shame</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102670">Upon my life's loss; yet let thy rage forbear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102680">To wrong that goodness, which has spared thy life. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e102690" who="A19347-sancho">
              <pb facs="8"/>
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e102700">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102710">In telling truth I offer no man wrong,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102720">Nor did my rage suggest my words unto me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102730">Your design's fair indeed, but your hope vain;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102740">You care not how y'affront a monarch's will;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102750">Nor can you think that your Cid will be faithless,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102760">You are the only she in all the court</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102770">To whom his love's unknown, you have not heard</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102780">That Corduba's infanta is his mistress;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102790">But he himself avows it in his letters,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102800">Which he has done so to the life, that all</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102810">Believe he's less their enemy, than her lover. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e102820" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e102830">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102840">Well let th' infanta come, let her instead</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102850">Of being captive be a conqueress,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102860">Let Cid that should be victor, be her slave,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102870">It matters not, so I may have thy absence:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102880">I'll wait th'effects of his inconstancy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102890">With more assurance, and far less disquiet,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102900">Pray leave ▪ me, I demand it as a favour</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102910">And find some better office when you next</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102920">Address yourself to any ▪ 'tis no shame</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102930">Not to have well discharged such an employment</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102940">As being done must needs betray thy honour. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e102950" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e102960">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102970">'Long as I serve my King, I fear no blame</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102980">But here's an end of this; I leave you madam,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e102990">Till time shall make you to digest my counsel. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103000">In the meanwhile i' me silent, and obey. <stage xml:id="A19347-e103010">Exit.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e103020">
            <pb facs="8"/>
            <head>Scene iii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e103030">King, don Diego, guard, and attendants.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e103040" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e103050">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103060">Do not believe don Diego, though I share</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103070">My heart and crown with the beloved Cimena,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103080">That I'll usurp by my authority</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103090">A treasure which thy son deserved so well. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103100">No, his great services do live too fresh</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103110">In my remembrance to be so requited:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103120">Rather I mean t'augment his happiness,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103130">And his reward shall parallel his valour,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103140">A nobler mistress I design for him</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103150">To whom Cimena without blushing may</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103160">Give place unto; nor should thy son complain</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103170">Of this my affection, or of that his change. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e103180" who="A19347-diego">
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e103190">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103200">But we have never sir deserved this honour,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103210">Nor dare my son pretend to such a fortune,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103220">A higher happiness attends the Princess,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103230">Who is too generous to descend so low. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e103240" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e103250">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103260">His actions tell me that he merits more</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103270">Which to reward according to his value</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103280">A sceptre is too little; I will share</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103290"><pb facs="9"/> with him in his desires, he in my power. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103300">Love may content us both, if as my sister</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103310">Is willing to receive him for her servant,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103320">So will the fair Cimena me for hers. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103330">Don Sancho from me is gone to see her,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103340">He knows her spirit, and should, how to tame it:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103350">I hope well of his fair tongues good success. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103360">But why is he so slow in his return? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103370">Since he is conscious of my nearest secrets</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103380">He must needs know that I burn all this while</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103390">And that his slowness causes me to languish. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e103400">
            <head>Scene iv.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e103410">Don Sancho.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e103420" who="A19347-diego">
              <speaker>Die.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e103430">Your majesty has no cause of further trouble,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e103440">See where he is. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e103450" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e103460">O don Sancho welcome,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e103470">What says Cimena? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e103480" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e103490">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103500">All that rigour can</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103510">All that disdain and scorn does usually</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103520">Inspire proud spirits with, that cruel fair</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103530">Permitted to her tongue, my gentle words</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103540">Were spent in vain; the Northern wind would sooner</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103550"><pb facs="9"/> have given them hearing, Roderigo's love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103560">Has made her to all else inexorable</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103570">Nor can we hope to treat with her again. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103580">As for a crown, sceptre, or any greatness</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103590">They seem but to stir up her anger more. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e103600" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e103610">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103620">What? will she be so cruel to her King? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103630">I must abate the pride of that fierce humour,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103640">And my resentment of 't shall make her see</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103650">That princes must be treated otherwise:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103660">But these scorns her, I'll turn into her shame:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103670">And Cid whom she believes her own already,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103680">Shall as well fail her hopes, as she has mine</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103690">When a more worthy object shall invite him</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103700">To change his love, and his disdains of her</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103710">Shall revenge hers of me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e103720">
            <head>Scene v.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e103730">Don Arias.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A19347-e103740">Don Arias,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19347-e103750">What news is it you bring? </l>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e103760" who="A19347-arias">
              <speaker>Ari.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e103770">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103780">Of Cid's good fortune,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103790">And of the rebel's fate, he is hard by</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103800">Victorious and in health. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e103810" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e103820">I long to see him</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e103830" who="A19347-arias">
              <pb facs="10"/>
              <speaker>Ari.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e103840">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103850">He is not far sir from the city walls,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103860">Meanwhile this letter will confirm your majesty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103870">Ith' truth of what I said. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e103880" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e103890">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103900">How am I ravished</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103910">And my soul burns with hot impatience</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103920">After this object which she so desires,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103930">Go tell him that my thoughts are swift to see him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e103940">Don Diego see that he be well received. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A19347-e103950">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e103960">
            <head>Act ii. scene i.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e103970">King, infanta; and Cimena.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e103980" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e103990">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104000">It seems Cimena, you have no room left</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104010">In this hard heart of yours for him that loves you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104020">Must a King live and die in the same fetters? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104030">Were I a private man you'd be ingrateful</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104040">To hate me, 'cause I love you, howsoever</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104050">You were too blame to use don Sancho so. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104060">Coming from me, and offering my service</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104070"><pb facs="10"/> he might deserve a kinder entertainment</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104080">Civility would require so much; and though</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104090">He had displeased you, courting you for me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104100">Duty should have made good your want of love. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e104110" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e104120">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104130">I cannot tell, sir, what has raised your anger,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104140">Nor how don Sancho has described me to you:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104150">But certainly, no vanity of mine</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104160">Did make me to forget my duty to you:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104170">And my refusal of the sovereign title</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104180">Showed my respect, and not my cruelty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104190">Don Sancho perhaps might be displeased,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104200">But his discourse moved me to what I said,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104210">Since he durst call to mind my father's murder</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104220">(A wound still bleeding in my memory.) </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e104230" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e104240">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104250">If thou hast yet a feeling of this grief</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104260">Both for thy honour, and content Cimena</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104270">'Tis fit thou banish from thy kinder thoughts</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104280">The author of it, nor does he now bear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104290">The same affection to thee which he did;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104300">When he left thee he left his first intentions</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104310">And having changed his climate, changed his love,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104320">Seriffa's beauty is the mark he aims at,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104330">Who once thy enemy, is now thy rival. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104340">I'm sure he's much engaged to this infanta,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104350">But if he were not, yet the services</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104360">My father had from all his family</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104370">Design for him the infanta of Castille. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e104380">
            <pb facs="11"/>
            <head>Scene ii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e104390">Don Arias.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e104400" who="A19347-arias">
              <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e104410">Sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e104420" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e104430">What wouldst thou? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e104440" who="A19347-arias">
              <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e104450">Roderigo is without. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e104460" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e104470">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104480">Admit him then: now you shall see Cimena</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104490">This glorious conqueror, I know he'll come</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104500">Triumphantly, leading his mistress with him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104510">You'll easily perceive in this encounter</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104520">Either his love or his ingratitude. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104530">Make your best use then of this time, compare</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104540">Your graces with your rivals, and by them</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104550">Guess what your fortune's like to be. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e104560" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Ci.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e104570">O heavens! </l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e104580">With what eyes can I see this his approach? </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e104590">
            <pb facs="11"/>
            <head>Scene iii. to them.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e104600">Roderigo, Seriffa; Spheranti, and Celimant.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e104610" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e104620">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104630">Great King, than whom the sun sees nothing happier,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104640">(Joy of your subjects' terror of your foes)</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104650">At length the war respiring, gives me leave</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104660">To have the honour to kneel here before you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104670">But as unto the deity ▪ of which</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104680">You are the image, none should dare to come</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104690">Without an offering, so nor could I</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104700">Hope to deserve the happiness to see you</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104710">Without a present: then be pleased, great sir,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104720">T'accept from my hand what heaven's bounty gives you</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104730">This crown, and these two princes, so far happy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104740">That they are fallen your prisoners, under whom</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104750">To be commanded is to live with freedom:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104760">This was the King of Corduba, and this</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104770">The heir apparent of Toledos kingdom. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e104780" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e104790">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104800">He hear thy full relation, but before it</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104810">Let me embrace thee, and behold this forehead</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104820">Where love and Mars do sit enthroned, and make thee</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104830">Victorious in either of their wars. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e104840" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e104850">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104860">O sir, how can I answer this discourse</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104870"><pb facs="12"/> to spare my modesty, sir, spare your favours</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104880">And share the honours, as you've done the labours</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104890">Your soldiers as much as I procured</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104900">This victory, 'tis just they should receive</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104910">Part of the honour from your majesty</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104920">Both for their valour and fidelity. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e104930" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e104940">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104950">Their merit can be easily satisfied</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104960">But for thy deeds there can be no rewards:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104970">Sure thou wert born to make all men ungrateful,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104980">Thy tongue's no less a conqueror than thine arm,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e104990">But for my sake spare thy sweet eloquence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105000">Else I shall be thy captive as are these</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105010">But now recite the fortune of thy arms;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105020">No entertainment can be half so pleasant. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e105030" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e105040">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105050">Sir ( whatsoe'er it be) since you command it,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105060">'Tis fit that I obey: your rebels slain</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105070">Or taken, and those darers that opposed</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105080">The current of your fortune quite defeated</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105090">To make your name more glorious, I advanced</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105100">My army towards Corduba, which even then</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105110">I had made sure of, if some timely succours</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105120">Had not prevented me. This noble prince</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105130">Seeing it beleaguered straight; by his forces</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105140">Thought to relieve it, but that hope being vain</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105150">He like a wise commander changed his purpose,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105160">And meant to try no valour but his own:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105170">Then by a herald sent he me a challenge</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105180">Which easily my spirit gave consent to</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105190">I named the place, where when we both were met,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105200">Many fierce blows were dealt, and sure the heavens</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105210">Looked pale to see the storms our anger made,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105220">Shine more in our wild looks than in their lightning</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105230">Whilst men durst do, that which they durst not see</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105240">'Twas equally between us fought, until</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105250"><pb facs="12"/> at length your fortune gave me th'advantage,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e105260" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sphr.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e105270">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105280">Here, sir, your modesty betrays your valour,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105290">I suffered by your strength not my mishap,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105300">You may vaunt freely what I can't deny. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e105310" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e105320">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105330">This was the blow made Corduba to fall,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105340">After this princes yielding their great thoughts</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105350">A bated of their pride, and this fair Princess</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105360">To whom I owe for her intelligence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105370">Made the town yours almost without resistance,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e105380" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e105390">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105400">'Tis true great King, this woman, nature's monster,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105410">By her base treachery betrayed my state,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105420">You have my goods, my sceptre and my person;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105430">But look, sir, who it is that gives them you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105440">See from what hand you do receive these presents,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105450">The same put her brother in these fetters,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105460">It is my sister, or some devil rather,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105470">That took that name upon her to betray me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e105480" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e105490">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105500">Leave to upbraid me thus, that name of sister</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105510">Has been the greatest stain upon my life:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105520">But you that stand so on the point of honour</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105530">Was I used as a sister by you, rather</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105540">Was I not treated as a slave? the name</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105550">Away, I felt the thing ▪ pray sir, believe not</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105560">That out of any womanish impudence ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105570">I gave th' intelligence I am accused of;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105580">But when I captived him, I freed myself</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105590">From those more cruel chains, where in his rage</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105600">Shut up my will and free election,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105610">Designing me the object of my hate:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105620">Which when I saw, and that this haughty prince</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105630">Came from his country to my ravishment,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105640">Armed not with fair deserts, but soldiers</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105650"><pb facs="13"/> I thought I justly might to his violence</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105660">Oppose my artifice, which was to render</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105670">Unto his enemies his place of refuge,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105680">Which my design I kept long in suspense,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105690">Till this more noble object took my heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105700">And made me perfect my intentions. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e105710" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e105720">I without doubt, his false heart does adore her. <stage xml:id="A19347-e105730">Aside.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e105740">Can I then see my rival, and yet I live? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e105750" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e105760">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105770">When the wit's nimble, and the courage ready,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105780">A good success still follows the design,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105790">The business that halts forward is half lost. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e105800" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e105810">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105820">Sir, to neglect the execution,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105830">My courage, and my love were too important,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105840">I quickly was resolved, when love came in</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105850">To finish up the plot my hate begun,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105860">This valiant Cid whose fame prevented him</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105870">In my good thoughts, was of my enemy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105880">Become the object of my best desires;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105890">His virtue conquered me, and had I not</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105900">Been overcome I had not been so happy:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105910">For giving up my arms to such a conquest,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105920">'Steed of my own loss I have got a prize,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e105930">The honour of all soldiers: Roderigo. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e105940" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e105950">Alas, what canst thou hope poor lady now. <stage xml:id="A19347-e105960">Aside.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e105970">Canst thou doubt yet whether he be engaged. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e105980" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e105990">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106000">Madam, you put a double tie upon me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106010">That having done me a courtesy so happy,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106020">You add to it, so much of kind respect,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106030">And believe, madam, that occasion</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106040">Will make me blessed, which points out my obedience,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106050">What may I do to serve you, pray command me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106060" who="A19347-cimena">
              <pb facs="13"/>
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106070">What has she to desire, she has thy heart? <stage xml:id="A19347-e106080">Aside.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106090" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106100">Ah sir, you can do all, and I'd have all. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106110" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106120">Madam, the King is here sole sovereign,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106130">He only can give all. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106140" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e106150">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106160">Which thou mayst promise,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106170">Such is thy merit as does challenge all,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106180">Freely dispose of my authority,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106190">And think I have done less than thou deservest. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106200" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e106210">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106220">So great a favour, sir, I not desire</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106230">The good I wish (Great Cid) is in thyself,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106240">Which is the object my desires aim at,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106250">And that sweet hope, which only makes me live. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106260" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e106270">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106280">I know not, madam, upon what appearance</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106290">You have conceived this hope, I'm sure Roderigo</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106300">Ne'er spoke to you about it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106310" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106320">O, how finely! <stage xml:id="A19347-e106330">Aside.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106340">He carries it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106350" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106360">'Tis prettily dissembled. <stage xml:id="A19347-e106370">Aside.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106380" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e106390">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106400">Have you then, sir, forgotten your promises,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106410">Is this the love, and are these the endearments</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106420">You promised to the action I performed. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106430" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106440">Who gave you that false hope. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106450" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106460">Yourself. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106470" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106480">Who I,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106490">I doubt it much. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106500" who="A19347-serifa">
              <pb facs="14"/>
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106510">O heavens, do you know</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106520">This letter? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106530" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106540">Yes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106550" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106560">Pray read it sir, and there</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106570">You shall perceive the reasons of my hope. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106580" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106590">I know well what I owe, and what I promised,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106600">You shall see madam, I am not ungrateful. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106610" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e106620">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106630">O then excuse my anger, my disdain</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106640">Caused it, and not my will, I can be calm,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106650">Having my fear abated by those comforts</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106660">You promised to my passion. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106670" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e106680">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106690">Your desires,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106700">Madam, exceed my power, but from me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106710">Expect all duty, and all courtesy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106720">That you could hope for, from a gentleman,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106730">Or I know how to give. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106740" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e106750">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106760">How faithless man? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106770">Do you fall back unto your first discourse? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106780">Thou paper which betrayd'st my heart at first</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106790">Discover to his infamy thy secrets,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106800">And show his breach of faith. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106810" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e106820">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106830">Let it be read</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106840">I'll ne'er oppose it, and I swear t'observe</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106850">Whatever that enjoins. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106860" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e106870">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106880">The thing you offer</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106890">Seems reasonable, thou art just Roderigo</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e106900">By it we shall perceive your interest. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106910" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <pb facs="14"/>
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106920">Sir, if you please, I will be judged by it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106930" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106940">And so will I. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106950" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106960">Then I shall do you justice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e106970" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e106980">Here must I stand with patience to hear<stage xml:id="A19347-e106990">Aside.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107000">The sentence of my punishment. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107010" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107020">From this,<stage xml:id="A19347-e107030">Aside.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107040">I must expect either to live or die. </l>
            </sp>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:id="A19347-e107050">
              <body xml:id="A19347-e107060">
                <head>Seriffa reads the letter.</head>
                <opener xml:id="A19347-e107070">
                  <salute xml:id="A19347-e107080">Madam,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p xml:id="A19347-e107090">If your brother have so little sense both of his own blood and your beauty, that he had rather please himself in your afflictions, than his own duty, let me entreat you to make good that bravery of spirit which you mentioned to me in your letters; which is to leave him to his cruelty, letting him first know that you were sensible of it, by the revenge you take. And then enter into the victor's camp, where you shall make your own conditions ▪ and<pb facs="15"/> find an entertainment to your content by</p>
                <closer xml:id="A19347-e107100">
                  <signed xml:id="A19347-e107110">Your most humble servant, Roderigo.</signed>
                </closer>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <lg xml:id="A19347-e107120">
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107130">You understand the sense, sir, of these words,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107140">These are not terms that should make void a promise</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107150">Am not I that Seriffa; you the victor,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107160">Did not I give you entrance into Corduba,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107170">And my own heart at once, and will you now</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107180">Bereave me of the hope yourself has raised</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107190">Is this the great content you promised me:</l>
            </lg>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107200" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e107210">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107220">What is't you can complain of madam? who</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107230">Durst be so insolent to do you hurt? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107240">Are you not here in covert of that storm</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107250">Which your fierce brother mean should overtake you? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107260">What could you hope more than this noble usage</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107270">Did you suppose your eyes could conquer me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107280">Alas, I am another's; and when ere</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107290">I change that object, I must think myself</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107300">Led into blindness, and mistake of beauty. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107310" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e107320">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107330">O do not change, but end my misery,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107340">Let my blood quite deface this character,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107350">As it looks black already with thy crime,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107360">So let it blush to punish me for mine,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107370">Why stayest thou? satisfy thy hate in me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107380">Tear from my breast my love and heart together. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107390" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e107400">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107410">How am I ravished with this sweet revenge,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107420">What pleasure 'tis to see thee in this case</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107430"><pb facs="15"/> where thy best hope is to sit down with nothing,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107440">Now lady you may triumph, though you wear not</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107450">These fetters, you're no less a slave than I. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107460" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107470">What villain? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107480" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e107490">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107500">Fie, madam, calm your anger. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107510">In the word of a King to both of you</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107520">I promise a fair treatment, I am one</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107530">That know to use a victory. Take you care</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107540">That in their several lodgings they want nothing</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107550">That their state may requires howe'er they be</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107560">My prisoners, I'll not bate their due respect</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107570">Go Roderigo home unto thy father,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107580">I know he longs to see thee. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107590">
                  <stage xml:id="A19347-e107600">Exeunt omnes praeter Cimena, infanta, Roderigo.</stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107610" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e107620">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107630">I obey,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107640">Pray, madam, give me leave to do the duty</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107650">I owe unto Cimena. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107660" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e107670">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107680">To me sir? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107690">Pray spare the labour, for you owe me none. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107700">Besides Seriffa, being vexed already</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107710">Has too much reason to complain of you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107720">Though you committed not this last offence. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107730">
                  <stage xml:id="A19347-e107740">She makes a curtsy, and goes out.</stage>
                </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107750" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107760">What may the reason be she quits me so? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107770">What crime have I committed? what's my fault? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107780" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e107790">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107800">I know not, but you see her cruelty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107810">And what a little makes her to fly off;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107820">Perhaps you're pleased well with your punishment,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107830">Thou shouldst show more of courage Roderigo</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107840">And let her see that he who comes home victor</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107850"><pb facs="16"/> should receive better welcome ▪ she is ( methinks )</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107860">Some what too full of vanity. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107870" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e107880">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107890">Ah, madam,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107900">I must not murmur though she be ungrateful,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e107910">She is Cimena, and I cannot hate her. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107920" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107930">But this thy too much goodness will betray thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107940">Thou mak'st thy constancy unhappy to thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107950" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107960">Madam, you know where 'tis my duty calls me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e107970">Pray give me leave to wait upon my father. <stage xml:id="A19347-e107980">Exit.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e107990" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e108000">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108010">Go; this was a pretext I know to leave me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108020">But I shall be revenged of this neglect</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108030">When against all thy hopes of future joy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108040">The rigor of Cimena I employ. <stage xml:id="A19347-e108050">Exit.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A19347-e108060">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e108070">
            <head>Act iii. Scene i.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e108080">Roderigo from Cimena's lodging.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108090" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e108100">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108110">Henceforth Cimena live for ever quiet,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108120">Roderigo shall no more be so unhappy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108130">As to disturb your peace, since you deny him</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108140">The sight of you he is content to suffer,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108150"><pb facs="16"/> not only want of that but all things else</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108160">You being all to him, that he desired:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108170">Good heaven was there ever so much rigour</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108180">Practised on any as on wretched me? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108190">Did I hope any other recompense</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108200">Of all my services, my labours, watchings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108210">To bring home victory? but that she should</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108220">Crown 'em with her acceptance; and must I</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108230">(Courted by all else) be by her despised</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108240">Into whose arms I looked to have been received? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108250">Nor is her anger more apparent than</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108260">The cause of it concealed, I am not worthy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108270">To know the reason of my banishment. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108280">Therefore farewell for ever cruel mistress,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108290">I'll seek some place habited by women,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108300">Where I may never see such shining eyes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108310">As only light us to our miseries. <stage xml:id="A19347-e108320">Exit.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e108330">
            <head>Scene ii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e108340">King, th'infanta, Seriffa, don Sancho, don Diego.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108350" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e108360">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108370">But, madam, spare Roderigo's innocence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108380">His virtues, and your worth are both too great</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108390">To suffer such a stain. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108400" who="A19347-infanta">
              <pb facs="17"/>
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e108410">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108420">Think of it madam,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108430">And call not him a traitor, but your heart</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108440">Which entertained a love that was not sent</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108450">You were too credulous, not he perfidious,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108460">What you desired you were willing to believe,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108470">And knowing the command of your own beauty</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108480">With the advantage of your birth and fortune,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108490">I cannot blame you if you thought that love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108500">Which was but civil application:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108510">But now you have found your error, let your courage</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108520">Find scorn for him that has not love for you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108530" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e108540">How easily the whole counsel the sick,<stage xml:id="A19347-e108550">Aside.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e108560">And yet they have not hit my true disease. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108570" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e108580">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108590">My sister madam, tells you right, desires</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108600">That are not honourable ought to be short,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108610">Your quality which your beauty only equals,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108620">Invites a higher match than Roderigo. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108630" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e108640">A conqueror is next unto a King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e108650">Since he's denied me, how can my hopes look higher? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108660" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e108670">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108680">Don Sancho wait the Princess to her lodgings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108690">And see that she command ▪ my court as freely</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108700">As I myself. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108710" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e108720">Your grace's humble creature. <stage xml:id="A19347-e108730">Exit.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108740" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e108750">Don Diego, is the Cid contented with</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e108760">The offer which I make him of my sister? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108770" who="A19347-diego">
              <speaker>D. Die.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e108780">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108790">You are the King sir; he your humble vassal,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108800">He could not be my son if disobedient</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108810">To you that are his master, and I find</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108820"><pb facs="17"/> his inclination ready only fear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108830">And modesty keeps in his strong desires. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108840" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e108850">'Tis not his fear but mistress which restrains him ▪</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108860" who="A19347-diego">
              <speaker>D. Die.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e108870">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108880">He will forget her sooner then his duty</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108890">Of which the count can give you the best proof,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108900">For though at that time he adored Cimena,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108910">Yet ventured he to lose her for my sake</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108920">(His honour and his duty so commanding)</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108930">He can love well 'tis true, but obey better. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e108940" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e108950">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108960">I never doubled his obedience</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108970">Of which his excellent virtue does assure me:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108980">I'd have (You sister) to accept the courtship</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e108990">Which he shall make to you, and if you ask</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109000">A reason why, know I will have it so;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109010">Though fortune have not blessed him with a crown,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109020">And though his greatness be within himself,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109030">Yet there propitious heaven has showed its power,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109040">Heaping its richest treasures on his person,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109050">He heart is valour's proper sphere, his soul</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109060">The throne of virtue where she sits and governs</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109070">Directing all his actions to honour;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109080">These rare perfections must be the objects</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109090">Sister, of your desires. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e109100" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e109110">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109120">Such a command</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109130">Makes my obedience ready to love virtue,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109140">When you that are my King requires it of me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109150">I not to give consent to hard conditions,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109160">'Tis your part to command, mine to obey. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e109170" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e109180">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109190">'Tis well, it only rest now that Cimena</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109200">Comply with my desires I will no longer</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109210">Burn to so little purpose, my affection</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109220"><pb facs="18"/> hastes to its end, there can be no content</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109230">To approach a fire that will consume, not cherish,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109240">I am resolved to have her, as for love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109250">Which to the Cid she promised, I have power</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109260">To absolve her of it; princes render lawful</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109270">Whatever pleases them: respects become</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109280">The people, not a King: send for her sister</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109290">And tell her I would see her in your lodgings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109300">To treat of something that concerns her nearly,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109310">'Tis wearisome to live thus in desire,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109320">This day enjoying her, I'll quench my fire. <stage xml:id="A19347-e109330">Exit.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e109340">
            <head>Scene iii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e109350">Seriffa, don Sancho.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e109360" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e109370">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109380">Beauty is love's object, madam and 'twere hard</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109390">T'approach such flames and keep a frozen heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109400">Dull fouls have eyes lent 'em to see their way,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109410">But men of courage to behold what's fair. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109420">Pardon divinest lady if my spirit</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109430">Made me to love where I should have adored</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109440">And though you do estrange me from your heart</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109450">Envy me not the glory of my sufferings. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e109460" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e109470">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109480">Don Sancho cannot be so young a courtier</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109490"><pb facs="18"/> to think that any lady can despise</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109500">A noble love bounded with due respects,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109510">We have no other witness of our beauty</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109520">And heaven defend that we should hate our lovers. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e109530" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e109540">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109550">Accept my vows then, madam, with the temper</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109560">Of one that seemed to love; and let my service</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109570">Be entertained at least with fair acceptance. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e109580" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e109590">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109600">How can I do that without injury</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109610">Either to you or my own modesty? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109620">To cherish you in what you cannot have</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109630">Were to augment your punishment: to give</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109640">A heart which is not mine, in me were falsehood,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109650">And no less wrong to you should you receive it</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109660">Then to its proper owner. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e109670" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e109680">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109690">But he seems</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109700">(As one that does not know his happiness)</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109710">To be insensible of what your goodness</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109720">Has offered him: why should you cast away</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109730">That whereof Kings would be ambitious? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e109740" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e109750">Ay me! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e109760" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e109770">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109780">That sigh the greatest monarch scarce deserves</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109790">Much less, a subject, thrust him from your thoughts</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109800">And let some nobler love take up his room. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e109810" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e109820">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109830">Take heed don Sancho, you begin to forfeit</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109840">Your first pretensions, I must not think,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109850">You can love one whom you believe to have</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109860">The easy power to dislodge a love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109870">Which she had once received , but henceforth know</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109880">My flame runs up into a point so small</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109890">As cannot be divided into parts. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e109900" who="A19347-sancho">
              <pb facs="19"/>
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e109910">Not though there be division of your hearts</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e109920">The Cid I shame to say't, neglects you madam:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e109930" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e109940">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109950">If he did not I were more miserable</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109960">This now seems strange to you, but when I shall</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109970">Relate that to you which in part concerns you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109980">As you are favourite to the King your master,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e109990">And one that should advise him to be just,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110000">You will perceive, that what I uttered of</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110010">Love to the Cid was to secure myself. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110020">But here's my brother, let's withdraw a little. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e110030">
            <head>Scene iv.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e110040">Spheranti, Celimant.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110050" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sphe.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e110060">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110070">Is not this fight enough dear Celimant,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110080">To choke that fire up within my breast</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110090">Which I too long have nourished to my ruin</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110100">For an ungrateful, and perfidious woman,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110110">Was it too little to disdain a prince,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110120">And run into the hands of one she knew not</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110130">Unless having quit him, for whom his worth</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110140">And valour pleaded she become the prey</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110150">Of a y that will seize her, see don Sancho</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110160">Has made her his already ▪ and shall I</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110170">Love where I am so rivalled, no my heart</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110180"><pb facs="19"/> if thou must be a captive, let thy fetters</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110190">Be such as need not shame the wearer. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110200" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e110210">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110220">Friend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110230">Which name I rather choose to call you by</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110240">Then brother, (Since you cannot be her husband</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110250">With safety of your honour) could you think</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110260">That she can spare her modesty, whose falsehood</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110270">Spared not her brother, and her country too,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110280">No sir, believe, she that is base herself</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110290">Cannot love virtue in another person:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110300">For how should she love that she never knew;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110310">Here then put out your flame, and think Spheranti</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110320">That this conformity of our lives and fortune</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110330">Which makes me share in all your passions</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110340">May link our hearts so fast we shall not need</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110350">Such an alliance to confirm the knot. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110360" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e110370">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110380">I know not friend whether I be more happy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110390">In losing of my love, then in the finding</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110400">Th'assurance of thy friendship; now let fortune</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110410">Look well or ill upon me in thy love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110420">I'll sum up all my bliss, nor can I think</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110430">Brave Celimant, will profess less to me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110440" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e110450">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110460">Which to confirm, no ceremonious oath</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110470">The band of doubtful, and inconstant souls</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110480">Shall I now take; thee friendship, I invoke,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110490">When I do leave this prince, let me be left</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110500">Without a friend, I and without a name. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110510" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e110520">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110530">I know my father at this time endeavours</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110540">My liberty, (If at least I can call</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110550">This thraldom, where I am so well received)</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110560">But I'm resolved to run your course of fortune,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110570">My freedom joined with yours is welcome to me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110580"><pb facs="20"/> else a worse torment than that bondage was</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110590">Your sister's rigour did impose. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110600" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e110610">No more</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e110620">Dear friend of her; come, come forget her name. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110630" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e110640">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110650">Since she could be so thankless to disdain,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110660">The man that quit his liberty for her,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110670">Which when the Cid did offer, I refused</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110680">To follow her, who follow all men else</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110690">And that her crime has merited my hate ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110700">I have shook off that chain; but find myself</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110710">Caught in another which thou dost not know</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110720">'Tis such as makes me fear my liberty</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110730">I cannot go from hence, and think I'm free. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110740" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e110750">You are in love it seems. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110760" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e110770">Yes Celimant. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e110780">I am in love, and as much in despair. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110790" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e110800">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110810">Is there a beauty can oppose your courtship,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110820">What quality is higher than your own? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110830">Why should you then despair? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110840" who="A19347-unassigned">
              <speaker>S. P.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e110850">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110860">I but the horror</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110870">Of being vanquished makes me think myself</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110880">Unworthy to look up to such a height. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110890" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e110900">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110910">Consider that your fortune was to yield</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110920">His to o'ercome, yet did you long dispute it</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110930">And bravely too; what can you fear Spheranti? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110940" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e110950">To be too rash ▪</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e110960" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e110970">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110980">To be too rash, let hope</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e110990"><pb facs="20"/> remove those thoughts, and you will not displease her,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111000">A virtuous love was never odious. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111010">But tell me sir, what name has this your mistress,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111020">Honour my freedom with this trust. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111030" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e111040">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111050">Th' infanta,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111060">Dear Celimant has snatched my heart, and though</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111070">My eyes were caught in their first motion to her,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111080">Yet durst I not discover it till now;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111090">But such force has my flame, it will not be</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111100">Contained within the limits of my heart</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111110">But must break out to thee and suddenly</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111120">To her, which if displeasing is my death. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111130" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111140">Hope better sir, I am your caution</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111150">She shall receive the offer of your vows. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e111160">
            <head>Scene v.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e111170">Enter don Arias.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A19347-e111180">But here's don Arias. </l>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111190" who="A19347-arias">
              <speaker>D. Ari.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111200">The King sir asks for you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111210" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111220">I'll wait him sir. <stage xml:id="A19347-e111230">Exeunt.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111240" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111250">'Tis strange he should be sent for and not I. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e111260">
            <pb facs="21"/>
            <head>Scene vi.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e111270">Enter infanta.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111280" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111290">What, all alone? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111300" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111310">I madam, Celimant,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111320">Is sent for to the King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111330" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e111340">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111350">O, I know why</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111360">His liberty is now in proposition,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111370">And yours too shortly, if you desire it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111380" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111390">That madam, is the least part of my care</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111400">I am so far from wishing it, I fear it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111410" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111420">This is a courtship sir, I understand not</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111430">Were not Toledo better than Seville to you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111440" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111450">Madam, th' effect will make you see it is not. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111460" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111470">Well, we shall hope to see it then; adieu. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111480" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e111490">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111500">My duty, madam, will not give me leave</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111510">To let you go alone, do not deny me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111520">The honour to wait on you ▪</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e111530">
            <pb facs="21"/>
            <head>Scene vii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e111540">Cimena. Page.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111550" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111560">What said Roderigo, boy? when he departed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111570" who="A19347-page">
              <speaker>Page.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111580">Nothing, but in his looks one might discover,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111590">Amazement joined with grief to be excluded. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111600" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e111610">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111620">Excluded, whence? not from my heart I'm sure</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111630">There he makes good the place he ever had,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111640">Were it a easy to remove him thence</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111650">As from my presence, I should fear no rival,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111660">Take your lute boy, and sing the song I gave you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111670">It suits my present state. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111680" who="A19347-boy">
              <speaker>The boy sings.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e111690">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111700">'Twas not his person nor his parts,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111710">Though ne'er so famed that won me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111720">He loved, he said, which I believed;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111730">And that faith has undone me. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e111740">
                <pb facs="22"/>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111750">His virtues were alike to all,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111760">Nor were they more to me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111770">I honoured them, but loved the man ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111780">Because that he was he. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e111790">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111800">Who since he has his love foregone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111810">And is himself no more:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111820">I love him not as he is now,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111830">But as he was before. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111840" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e111850">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111860">'Tis true I must still love him, the remembrance</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111870">That I was once Roderigo's only object,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e111880">Is that I cherish now. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e111890">
            <head>Scene viii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e111900">Don. Arias.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111910" who="A19347-arias">
              <speaker>D. Ari.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111920">Madam, the King</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111930">Stays for you to come to him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111940" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111950">The King! where? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111960"><pb facs="22"/>Why would he speak with me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e111970" who="A19347-arias">
              <speaker>D. Ari.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111980">I cannot tell,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e111990">But he expects you on the infantas side. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e112000" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e112010">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112020">Tell him I come, I know what he would have</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112030">But all his power shall not shake my firmness,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112040">In vain he tries to win me by his greatness. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112050">What is a throne to me that seek a grave? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112060">I'm sure he has no power o'er my will,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112070">He that first took my heart shall keep it still. Exeunt. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A19347-e112080">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e112090">
            <head>Act iv. scene i.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e112100">Spheranti, infanta.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e112110" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e112120">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112130">Madam, 'tis true, I may have been too rash</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112140">To offer you a heart unworthy of you</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112150">But yet my fault is such as cannot give</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112160">Consent to any low thoughts of repentance;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112170">And if my service find no other grace,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112180">Let me have leave to cherish my attempt,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112190">And let me love myself for loving you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112200"><pb facs="23"/> then if you shall deny your presence to me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112210">My soul may do the office of mine eyes</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112220">Which may contemplate what these cannot see,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112230">And if my love cannot appear from thence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112240">From this you shall perceive my obedience. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e112250" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e112260">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112270">Though I am better read in my own faults,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112280">Then to believe I could charm any man;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112290">Yet for your sake, because you ▪ le have it so. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112300">I am content to think you love me sir,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112310">And I am sensible of what I owe you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112320">But you must know that I depend upon</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112330">A brother to whose will I am confined,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112340">So that I am not mistress of my heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112350">Nor dare I hazard it without his leave,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112360">Therefore to warrant your pretensions</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112370">Make your address to him, till then I dare not</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112380">Be known to entertain you for a suitor. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e112390" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sph.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e112400">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112410">'Tis fit I be obedient to this law</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112420">Which is most reasonable, but may I be</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112430">As sure of your favour, as his leave. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e112440" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e112450">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112460">Your virtue, sir, will be your best assurance,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112470">My love proceeds not freely, but deserts</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112480">Must challenge it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e112490" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e112500">Kissing your fair hands, madam,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e112510">I go to make my way to bliss or ruin. <stage xml:id="A19347-e112520">Exit.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e112530" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e112540">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112550">What shall I do, my heart, this prince is lovely,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112560">So is the Cid, but he less tractable,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112570">Spheranti is more soft and courteous,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112580">And yet not of less spirit than the other,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112590">Let Roderigo then endear his mistress,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112600">And since that love is th' only price of love,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112610"><pb facs="23"/> let him that offers his, have his reward. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112620">Alas, what did I say? how can I leave</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112630">That object, which rules all within my heart? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112640">Roderigo's free possessor there, and yet</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112650">Methinks , there is a room left for Spheranti. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112660">What shall I do then in this labyrinth? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112670">Shall I to oblige Cimena, quit the Cid. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112680">No I'll not leave him, but with patience wait</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112690">The pleasure of my brother and my fate. <stage xml:id="A19347-e112700">Exit.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e112710">
            <head>Scene ii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e112720">King, Celimant, don Arias.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e112730" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e112740">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112750">Done Sancho, sir, and Arias do wait you</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112760">With the conditions of your liberty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112770">They are but gentle ones, that you forgive</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112780">Your sister, in the recompense of which</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112790">Your ransom is remitted. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e112800" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e112810">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112820">Greatest monarch,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112830">Who may dispose my life, you know that here,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112840">I am no less without a will than power</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112850">I must obey, whatever you impose,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112860">But yet her crime joined with the insolence</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112870">In facing it is such, that giving me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112880">My kingdom back with her, is worse to me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112890">Then to live here your captive, with what pleasure</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112900">Can I behold that power redelivered</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112910"><pb facs="24"/> which with my enemies I must receive. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e112920" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e112930">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112940">I'll quit you of that fear, in taking care</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112950">To keep Seriffa in the terms of duty</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112960">You shall command her wholly, but at present</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112970">Till you be better satisfied, her fight</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112980">Shall not offend you, since her love has caused</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e112990">The treason which you blame her for, I mean</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113000">To keep her fast in fetters, until love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113010">And Hymen be the executioners</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113020">Of the sweet sentence which I will pronounce. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113030" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e113040">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113050">Such is her want of worth, the prince you meant</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113060">To join her to, despises her, and truly</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113070">I should believe him to be worth my pity,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113080">Of whom so base an object were considered. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113090" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e113100">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113110">Sir, your too quick resentment makes you speak so,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113120">But leave that care to me, there is a lord</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113130">Within my court, of birth as great as any,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113140">But virtue much beyond his quality,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113150">Which does a done your sister, though it be true</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113160">That he has mingled with his love some boldness,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113170">Since he can't plead any descent from Kings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113180">Yet if our spirit bids us despair nothing,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113190">This noble lover must obtain his wishes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113200">In a word 'tis don Sancho that I mean. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113210" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e113220">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113230">Sir, I beseech you think how great the distance</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113240">Is between their conditions ▪ don Sancho</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113250">Has much worth in him, but he is no prince,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113260">And though Seriffa has disgraced her birth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113270">She's never the less descended from a King. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113280" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e113290">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113300">Don Sancho, sir, is all you can desire</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113310">Being my favourite, I will advance</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113320"><pb facs="24"/> his fortune to that height as shall deserve,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113330">Seriffa's and your love: but did you know</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113340">How much he has employed his favour with me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113350">For your advantage, you would recompense</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113360">His care with this alliance, but if all</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113370">That he has done, can't make you flexible,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113380">Yet hear me that am King, and do conjure you</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113390">To love your sister, and confirm this match,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113400">A King's entreaties must have no denial. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113410" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e113420">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113430">Sir, I am yours, and since this marriage</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113440">Is welcome to your thoughts: don Sancho may</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113450">In Celimant meet a brother, and Seriffa</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113460">Being looked on by me, through you and him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113470">Shall see I can forget what she has done. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113480" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e113490">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113500">Now you oblige me, and this clemency</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113510">Shows whence you are descended: how I love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113520">This sweetness in you, trust me your sister</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113530">(Now I may tell you so) will well deserve</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113540">This favour of you; such a beauty, sir,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113550">Ought not to dwell clouded in your dislikes:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113560">But you are for your business: Arias,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113570">See he find no delay, and call Roderigo ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113580">My sister too; I know they are without,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113590">So good success when I speak for another</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113600">Makes me hope all things in my own behalf:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113610">But I must change my countenance: Roderigo. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e113620">
            <pb facs="25"/>
            <head>Scene iii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e113630">The King, Roderigo, infanta.</stage>
            <lg xml:id="A19347-e113640">
              <l xml:id="A19347-e113650">All Spain from thy brave hand has felt that peace</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e113660">And quiet, which thy prince cannot obtain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e113670">This work is wanting to fill up thy glory,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e113680">Therefore to make thy victory more perfect,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e113690">For my sake undertake this enemy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e113700">That would cut from thy valour half thy conquest. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113710" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e113720">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113730">How sir? dares any, who may be so blessed</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113740">As to live under your just laws, shake off</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113750">Their due obedience? what vain insolence</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113760">Dares lift itself against so sweet a power:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113770">Name him sir, to me, that I may destroy him. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113780" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e113790">There's none can do't Roderigo. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113800" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e113810">None sir, why? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113820" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e113830">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113840">'Tis love that little tyrant which rules all,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113850">The enemy which makes this war upon me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113860">Regards not majesty, but as a victor</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113870">Triumphs already in my captived heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113880">Which has consented to its own defeat</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113890"><pb facs="25"/> so much that I am on the brink of ruin,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113900">If Roderigo's hand sustain me not. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113910" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e113920">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113930">If your ease sir, depend upon my service,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113940">You may be sure of my readiness,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e113950">Only sir, let me know what you desire? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113960" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e113970">O, Roderigo! </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e113980" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e113990">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114000">Why do you sigh, sir? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114010">Is't that you doubt of my obedience? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114020">Or that my power is less than your desires. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114030" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e114040">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114050">By no means Roderigo, but I fear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114060">Lest some ill fortune, stead of putting me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114070">Into the haven, cast me further from't,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114080">And lest the difficulty should change thy courage,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114090">And leave me to myself in this fierce storm. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114100" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e114110">My courage is exempted from such fear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114120" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e114130">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114140">I'm well assured of thy faith and valour,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114150">And yet in this I fear, because thou must</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114160">Combat thyself, subdue thy own desires,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114170">Conquer thy own dear passions to make</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114180">Thyself a sacrifice to my affections. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114190" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e114200">Your majesty may dispose then of my life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114210" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e114220">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114230">'Tis not my purpose, nor for all Castille</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114240">Shall it be said that I wished any good</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114250">Which must be purchased at so dear a rate. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114260" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e114270">What can I do then for you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114280" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e114290">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114300">Thou mayst put</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114310"><pb facs="26"/> an end to all my pain in quitting of</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114320">Cimena: do not start, they are her charms</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114330">By which I'm caught and suffer, nor can I</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114340">Believe though now she slight my offered love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114350">Any thing else withholds her, but the thought</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114360">Of being thine. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114370" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e114380">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114390">O sir, assure yourself,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114400">If that be all, and that your majesty</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114410">Vouchsafe to cast your eyes upon this beauty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114420">I shall not be so rash to hope that good,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114430">Which has the honour to please you my prince. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114440">In this sir, you may free me from suspect,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114450">My love is (Much indeed) more my respect,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114460">And howsoe'er my heart be linked to hers,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114470">I owe more to my master then my mistress. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114480" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e114490">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114500">O royal soul, and truly generous,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114510">Great Cid, this instant thou hast made me happy:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114520">Now I am King indeed, for what thou givest me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114530">I prize above the value of a crown,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114540">In lieu of which I mean to give thee one,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114550">Behold th' infanta, whom I freely offer:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114560">'Tis fit, the state, which owes all to thy valour,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114570">Should make thee a great sharer in her fortune. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114580" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e114590">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114600">Every thing smiles upon me, blessed effects<stage xml:id="A19347-e114610">Aside</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114620">O'er take my wishes, what could I hope more? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114630">Love is made for me to my hand, Cimena</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114640">Engaged, to which Roderigo gives consent. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114650" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e114660">Thou dost not answer me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114670" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e114680">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114690">Excuse me sir,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114700">I am your subject, and you are my King,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114710">'Tis not a kingdom, which I wish or hope for</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114720"><pb facs="26"/> to serve you is the honour I aspire to,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114730">Obeying you, I learn how to command,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114740">And since — but see Cimena. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e114750">
            <head>Scene iv.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e114760">Cimena.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114770" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e114780">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114790">O, madam,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114800">The date now of your cruelty is out,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114810">Your coldness, and your hate no more in season ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114820">Roderigo for my sake has quit you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114830">And if he had an interest in your person,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114840">He has now put me in full possession of it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e114850" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e114860">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114870">Sir, Roderigo's free and may renounce me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114880">I have no sceptres to bestow upon him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114890">But yet I think my birth is not so mean,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114900">As to live under his command; a slave</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114910">I am not yet, and my affections</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114920">Are not to be inclined and rule by his,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114930">Since greatness is the thing, not love he aims at,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114940">Let him have his desires, I shan't be jealous</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114950">Though love do wound him with more pleasing darts</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114960">So that the tyrant which shall end his sufferings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114970">Do not put me on new, nor that his great</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114980">Felicity be purchased at the rate</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e114990">Of my lost honour, or my liberty. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e115000" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <pb facs="27"/>
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e115010">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115020">Madam, think better of the man which loves you ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115030">To get you happiness I quit mine own:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115040">And to obtain the sovereign power for you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115050">I make my affection stoop unto my duty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115060">If when I see a crown is offered you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115070">I should come in, to cross your better fortune,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115080">I must believe my love did then betray you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115090">And had relation to myself not you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e115100" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e115110">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115120">This Roderigo were a fair pretext,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115130">If both our thoughts were levelled at one height,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115140">But let not any right that I can plead</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115150">Divert your dear ambition, mount upon</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115160">A throne, and taste its sweetness, as for me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115170">I am so far from blaming this your change,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115180">You cannot find more pleasure than I praise,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115190">T'applaud your act; you see sir, I submit</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115200">To the same laws yourself has made. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e115210" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e115220">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115230">O, heavens! <stage xml:id="A19347-e115240">Aside.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115250">How am I fallen from all my hopes at once,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115260">He is Roderigo still, and she Cimena. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e115270" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e115280">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115290">You are resolved then madam, to continue</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115300">In the same cruelty? my love I see</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115310">Is useless, and my vows superfluous:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115320">Yet think I am a King, and can command. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115330">What you deny my love, you'll give my power,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115340">And since I can't persuade, I must constrain. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e115350" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e115360">Sir since my presence does but move your anger</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e115370">Suffer me to retire I beseech you. <stage xml:id="A19347-e115380">Exit.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e115390" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e115400">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115410">See Roderigo, how my love is answered,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115420">She flies my present; leaving not so much</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115430"><pb facs="27"/> as a kind look behind her; if by this</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115440">She thinks to cool the fire which burns my heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115450">She is deceived; for this her suddenness</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115460">Does not restrain but quicken more my flame,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115470">Tell me was ever King so rudely treated? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e115480" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e115490">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115500">This her judicious and wise retreat,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115510">Being no effect of spite or arrogance,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115520">Should not excite your anger: sir you know</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115530">A modest fear keeps subjects in restraint,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115540">When they are near their King, and in that sex</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115550">The dazling lustre of a prince's person,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115560">Strikes more respect into their hearts then love. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e115570" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e115580">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115590">Why, was I made a King then? if my quality</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115600">Must cross my dearest wishes, let me be</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115610">A subject, any thing, so I have her:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115620">Some kind fare rob me of my crown and sceptre,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115630">And you shall see that I will bless your rigour,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115640">If in exchange you'll give me but one heart:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115650">Cimena limits my ambition,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115660">On her depends either my life or death,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115670">Then if thou ever hadst a thought to please me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115680">Roderigo win Cimena to my love,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115690">Accomplish what thou hast begun, and try</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115700">To melt the ice which circles in her heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115710">Or if it be a fire, o turn it this way,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115720">From thee I must expect all my content:<stage xml:id="A19347-e115730">Exit.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e115740" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e115750">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115760">And I from you sir, all my punishment:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115770">Did ever any mischief equal this,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115780">I'm made the confident of my own rival,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115790">To myself faithless, true to him that wrongs me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115800">My duty and my love run contraries,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115810">One binds me to obey a wilful prince,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115820">Th'other my mistress, whom my heart adores,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115830"><pb facs="28"/> if I obey my love, I get his hate,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115840">And if my duty, I must lose her love,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115850">But that I may however, since the King</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115860">Has power to take her from me when he will:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115870">Then let me serve my King which I have promised,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115880">But that Cimena claims as well as he;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115890">On both sides thus engaged, and thus distracted. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115900">Roderigo, what canst thou resolve to do,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115910">Since with thy love or duty thou must part</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e115920">Give him thy life, and let her have thy heart. <stage xml:id="A19347-e115930">Exit.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A19347-e115940">
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e115950">
            <head>Act v. scene i.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e115960">Roderigo, Cimena.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e115970" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e115980">Th' Infanta's lodgings are that way. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e115990" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e116000">Madam. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116010" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e116020">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116030">You are mistaken, sir, I am Cimena,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116040">He that courts titles must forget a name</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116050">That sounds not Princess, nor would I divert</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116060">The full stream of your hopes: here lies my way. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116070" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e116080">Madam, Cimena, stay and hear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116090" who="A19347-cimena">
              <pb facs="28"/>
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e116100">My ruin. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116110" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e116120">One word. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116130" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e116140">Pray let me go. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116150" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e116160">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116170">The last I mean</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116180">To speak to any of your sex: what rigor</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116190">Is this you use, did ever any yet</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116200">Refuse to be a witness to a will? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116210" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e116220">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116230">Was ever any cruelty like this? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116240">Ah Roderigo, is it not enough,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116250">First to betray me to your love, and then</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116260">Leave me, unless to shake my resolution:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116270">You set upon me with new battery,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116280">I cannot hear and live. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116290" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e116300">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116310">I do not come</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116320">To urge ought in my own behalf, my duty</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116330">And promise made to him, who may command me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116340">Forces this from me, can you love the King? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116350" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e116360">Can you be Roderigo, and demand it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116370" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e116380">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116390">I have no more to say then, but to take</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116400">My last farewell, perhaps when I'm removed</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116410">Your duty or ambition will persuade</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116420">What from your servant is not credited,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116430">And when by this your obstinacy (As sure</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116440">It must fall out so) my poor life grows forfeit,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116450">You will too late repent the loss of both. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116460">A lover and a crown. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116470" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e116480">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116490">'Tis vainly urged. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116500"><pb facs="29"/>How can I lose a lover, when he first</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116510">Renounces me? A crown I never had,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116520">And if I never seek it, as I shall not,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116530">Where is my loss? but rather where's thy courage</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116540">Ah Roderigo must the fear of death</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116550">Only come in to make some small pretence</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116560">For leaving me, you did not use to be</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116570">Frighted at such a name. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116580" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e116590">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116600">Nor must you think</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116610">That I am now, yet would I live to see</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116620">Cimena in that lustre with her virtues</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116630">Ever designed her to, for me I think</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116640">Nothing can add unto my present state</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116650">More happiness than to have been the ground</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116660">Where on my mistress would erect her glory. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116670" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e116680">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116690">And can you think Cimena will go less,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116700">While you discourse thus, you but teach my duty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116710">The honour of our love must not be yours</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116720">More than mine own, I have as great a share</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116730">In it as you, and should it come to suffering</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116740">I can as well expect to see you great</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116750">As myself miserable; which must be so</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116760">If fortune once divide us. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116770" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e116780">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116790">Can our faith</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116800">Be so rewarded? heavens, where is your justice? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116810">If we must needs be severed; why to both</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116820">Gave you an equal mind, and thoughts alike? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116830" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e116840">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116850">That being parted, we might be more near,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116860">For they that love alike are always one,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116870">Since but the sight naught can distinguish them. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116880" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e116890">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116900">These mysteries Cimena, are not strange</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116910"><pb facs="29"/> unto our loves, in which there has not been</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116920">Any thing known, or easy, yet methinks ,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e116930">We might find out a way for intercourse. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116940" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e116950">Thy love is too material Roderigo,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e116960">I could be satisfied with thy idea. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e116970" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e116980">And I with thine, but is it not some pleasure</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e116990">To stand thus, and to gaze on one another? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117000" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e117010">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117020">Go Roderigo, for I feel within me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117030">Since this thy stay, some thing, that prompts me to</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117040">Desire thy company, which must be fatal</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117050">To both of us; adieu, and think we may</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117060">Be severed yet continue still ourselves. <stage xml:id="A19347-e117070">Exit.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117080" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e117090">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117100">Ourselves! am I Roderigo, or has she</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117110">Bereft me of my spirit, can she brave</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117120">The majesty of Kings secured within</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117130">Her own firm constancy, and must I tremble,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117140">If the Kings will have not the wished success? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117150">I ought him duty, and I have performed it,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117160">I've offered with my life all my desires,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117170">Yet though I give, I may refuse to take,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117180">He cannot force me to a new affection,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117190">Or make me love her less, than she does me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117200">In other things he rules, in this I'm free. <stage xml:id="A19347-e117210">Exit.</stage></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e117220">
            <pb facs="30"/>
            <head>Scene ii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e117230">Don Sancho, Seriffa.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117240" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e117250">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117260">Madam believe, I could not justify</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117270">The love I did pretend, if in this business</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117280">I should prefer my passion before</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117290">Your honour and content, I hear your brother</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117300">The King has reconciled to you, it rests</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117310">I let him know how much he owes to justice. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117320" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e117330">But as you do it, spare my modesty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e117340">I would not be an offer, but his choice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117350" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e117360">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117370">As you have given credit to my faith,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117380">In this distrust not my discretion,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117390">It is your honour which I seek, to which</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117400">I made my love submit, and can you think</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117410">I will not now preserve it, I am here</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117420">T'attend the King as sent for, and shall use</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117430">All opportunities to do you service,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117440">Please but your highness to retire. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117450" who="A19347-serifa">
              <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e117460">Bequeathing to thy care, the hopes of all</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e117470">My future happiness. <stage xml:id="A19347-e117480">Exit.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117490" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e117500">Your highness' servant. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e117510">
            <pb facs="30"/>
            <head>Scene iii.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e117520">King, Celimant, don Sancho.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117530" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>King.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e117540">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117550">In this sir, I confess, Spheranti has</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117560">Obliged our family, the prince is noble,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117570">And I could wish my sister would embrace</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117580">The love he offers, what I can confer,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117590">He may be sure of: but you know th' infanta</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117600">Is promised Roderigo, to whose valour</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117610">She has been long a debt, and yet this business</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117620">Is not arrived so far as to cut off</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117630">This noble rival's hopes, sometimes a moment</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117640">Alters the state of things; a lady's mind</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117650">Is not less changeable: tell him from me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117660">He shall have all assistance. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117670" who="A19347-celimant">
              <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e117680">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117690">'Tis the sum</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117700">Of his desires, your majesty will pardon</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117710">Th' abruptness of my parting, he's my friend</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117720">And such a happiness he longs to hear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117730">As much as I to tell him. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117740" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e117750">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117760">Your own time</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117770">You may command brave Celimant: don Sancho</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117780">This prince has royal thoughts and more your friend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117790">Than you could hope. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117800" who="A19347-sancho">
              <pb facs="31"/>
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e117810">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117820">Your majesty still puts</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117830">Fresh obligations on your humble vassal,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117840">I am your creature, and the prince through you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117850">Looking on me, may happily bestow</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117860">His grace upon me as I am your servant,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117870">Though otherwise I be not worth his thought. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117880" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e117890">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117900">This modesty becomes thee, and sets off</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117910">Thy virtues which I cherish; in reward</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117920">Of which, and for thou hast been still an aid</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117930">To my desires, I have assisted thine,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117940">The love thou madest to Corduba's infanta,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117950">I have ta'en notice of, and though another</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117960">Might suffer in the like attempt, in thee</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117970">I've not disliked it, but commend thy choice,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e117980">She is as great, in beauty as in birth. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e117990" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e118000">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118010">She is an object for which mighty Kings</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118020">Being rivals should take arms, such excellence</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118030">Was never meant to be attained with ease. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118040" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e118050">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118060">You speak sir, like a lover, but don Sancho</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118070">What would he say, that should be made the owner</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118080">Of this rare beauty by consent of all? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118090" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e118100">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118110">That fortune had left nothing to confer,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118120">Being undone in this, hope cannot look</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118130">So high. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118140" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e118150">She shall be thine, nay more, she is. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118160" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e118170">Leave me not now my faith and honesty. <stage xml:id="A19347-e118180">Aside.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e118190">For I had ne'er more need of your assistance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118200" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e118210">Thou dost not answer, has thy sudden joy</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e118220"><pb facs="31"/> surprised thy senses, and shut up thy speech? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118230" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e118240">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118250">I must confess, I'm ravished with this offer;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118260">And on my knees in sign of gratitude</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118270">I here restore her to you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118280" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e118290">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118300">Dost thou mock,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118310">My courtesy, or is it madness in thee? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118320">Return unto thyself. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118330" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e118340">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118350">Your favours, sir,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118360">Have come so thick upon me, that my thanks</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118370">Are still o'er taken, only now my fortune,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118380">Has given me leave to show my gratitude,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118390">This Princess whom you offer I adore,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118400">But dare not love, nor any but yourself. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118410" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e118420">Thou mak'st me wonder, how can she concern me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118430" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e118440">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118450">In justice, sir, she is your wife, if contracts</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118460">Can stand in force with princes, by your father,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118470">In your minority, with her a match</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118480">Was made and ratified, of which don Diego</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118490">Cannot be ignorant, nor don Arias,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118500">Who did transact the business. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118510" who="A19347-unassigned">
              <speaker>L.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e118520">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118530">Some such thing</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118540">I heard, but have forgotten, my Cimena</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118550">Calls back my thoughts and fixes them on her;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118560">Beside she loved the Cid, and for his sake</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118570">Betrayed her country and her brother. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118580" who="A19347-sancho">
              <speaker>D. San.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e118590">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118600">True,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118610">She did, but not for him: had you great sir,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118620">But heard the story of her love, and how</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118630">It grew up in her fancy, since the time</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118640"><pb facs="32"/> the King her father mentioned first your name</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118650">To her yet infant apprehension,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118660">And gave your picture to her, you would say</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118670">Love entering by degrees, gathers his strength</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118680">From small beginnings, but makes sure his hold. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118690">In fine, your majesty has been the object,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118700">For whom she has despised the prince Spheranti. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118710">Endured her brother's fury, and at length</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118720">To colour her desires, made the occasion</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118730">Of Roderigo's being there, the means</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118740">To bring her to your court, and acted that</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118750">Unto the Cid, she truly meant to you:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118760">Feigned love is often better showed then true. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e118770" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e118780">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118790">I must confess myself a debtor to her,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118800">But yet Cimena is my choice, the Princess</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118810">Consulted well for her own modesty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118820">And no less for her good, when she made you</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118830">Her speaker, I shall think on't: call don Diego,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118840">My sister and Seriffa, to them all</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118850">I have to say, entreat the fair but cruel. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118860">Cimena come, and Roderigo too. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118870">I shall dispose of them: how unhappy<stage xml:id="A19347-e118880">Exit San.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118890">Are princes that must love by others reason,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118900">And not their own affections, this Princess</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118910">Is fair and loves me, so is my Cimena,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118920">But she abhors me; should I sacrifice</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118930">To fame, Seriffa must be mine, but if</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118940">To love, Cimena; one of these I'm led to</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118950">By reason, to the other forced by love:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118960">Must a prince suffer violence? he must</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118970">Or else imprison them that offer it,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118980">(His wild desires) there being no other course,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e118990">But to submit to reason or to force. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A19347-e119000">
            <pb facs="32"/>
            <head>Scene iv.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19347-e119010">All the actors, the infanta and Cimena on one side; Roderigo, Celimant, and Spheranti on the other.</stage>
            <lg xml:id="A19347-e119020">
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119030">But here they are ▪ sister, I am resolved</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119040">This day to see you married, and to make</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119050">Your joy more perfect, I shall give you leave</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119060">To choose your husband: the prince of Toledo</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119070">Courts you with such a love as naught can equal</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119080">But his perfections, which you must honour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119090">As well as he your beauty: yet Roderigo</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119100">Is for himself so much to be considered,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119110">That we can hardly find a mistress for him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119120">Which may deserve his virtues; both of them</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119130">Outweigh your merits, yet since equally</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119140">They make an offer of their service to you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119150">Declare which is the object of your choice. </l>
            </lg>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119160" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e119170">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119180">I cannot, sir, believe myself so happy,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119190">As to have either of 'em for my husband:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119200">But if they do submit to my desires,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119210">Being both equal, I have no election. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119220" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119230">They both adore you, and on this assurance</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119240"><pb facs="33"/> you may distinguish of their love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119250" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119260">How, both. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119270">I doubt it much. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119280" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119290">If you do not believe me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119300">From their own voice I shall confirm it to you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119310" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e119320">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119330">Yes divine beauty from my heart I speak,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119340">That heart which your fair eyes have set on fire,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119350">The light of which may show you how I love. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119360">And if I lose my hope, I lose my life. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119370" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119380">Can you doubt yet of his affection? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119390">And Roderigo sure will say as much. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119400" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e119410">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119420">'Tis true great King, all men adore the Princess ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119430">She has such universal power o'er hearts,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119440">She can't be seen by any, and not loved,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119450">But here's the difference between my love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119460">And theirs, they live with hope, I with despair. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119470" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119480">What robs thee of thy hope? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119490" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119500">Love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119510" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e119520">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119530">Speak more clearly,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119540">'Tis without reason that thou sayest: can love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119550">Take thy hope from thee, when it gives it thee? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119560" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119570">Then when I love, my hope forsakes me quite. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119580" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119590">But now it does restore what then it took. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119600" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119610">In doing so it keeps me further from't. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119620" who="A19347-king">
              <pb facs="33"/>
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119630">These terms are too obscure, I can't conceive 'em. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119640" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119650">Time and my constancy will make it plain ▪</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119660" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119670">But I would know their meaning at this present. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119680" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119690">Th' effect will quickly tell you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119700" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119710">What effect. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119720" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119730">My death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119740" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119750">Thy death, who can cause it? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119760" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119770">Cimena, sir. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119780" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119790">Cimena, thou hast yielded her to me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119800" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119810">It was your will prescribed that law unto me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e119820">I am your subject sir, and you my King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119830" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e119840">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119850">Though you be so, I never had intent</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119860">To do you wrong, to do myself a pleasure:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119870">Thou knowest how dear thy person is to me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119880">And that my sister is thy valour's prize,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119890">Will you refuse her your affection. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119900" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e119910">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119920">I have not, sir, ambition enough</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119930">To look so high: pray sir, regard not me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119940">But leave me to myself, possess Cimena;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119950">In your love let her drown the memory</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119960">Of mine, I am your subject, you my King. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e119970" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e119980">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e119990">Well then since you refuse my proffered honours,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120000">And that my sister cannot touch your heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120010"><pb facs="34"/> my promises are disengaged for me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120020">I shall accept Cimena, and this Princess</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120030">You are content to part with, are you not? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120040">What do you fix upon? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120050" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e120060">On what I ought,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e120070">I am your subject sir, and you my King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120080" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e120090">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120100">Spheranti, if my sister be your choice,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120110">So that your father will give his consent,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120120">I freely shall give mine. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120130" who="A19347-spheranti">
              <speaker>Sp.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e120140">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120150">Your majesty</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120160">Shall quickly see that cleared, I know my father</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120170">Will be well satisfied, when he shall hear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120180">That I have joined the kingdoms of Toledo</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120190">And Seville by a match: but may I madam</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120200">Receive this happiness from your consent? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120210" who="A19347-infanta">
              <speaker>In.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e120220">The King has made you, sir, disposer of me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e120230">And what he chooses answers my desires. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120240" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e120250">Thou'rt silent Roderigo, what dost think? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120260" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e120270">That she could hardly have a braver prince,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e120280">Nor he hope more than her. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120290" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e120300">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120310">And you Cimena,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120320">Will you not put an end unto my sufferings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120330">Will you be still obdurate to your King? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120340" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e120350">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120360">Sir, I have no other faith then what I have given,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120370">You know your father made me wear these bonds,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120380">Which only death can break. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120390" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e120400">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120410">My constancy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120420"><pb facs="34"/> shall overcome thy stubborness, I know</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120430">The ground and cause of thy aversion,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120440">Thou hast some feeble hope t'enjoy the Cid,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120450">But that's without appearance; his own mouth</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120460">Has ruined it, speak it again Roderigo,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120470">Assure her that her hopes but flatter her,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120480">Or if thou doffed repent thy courtesy,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120490">Deal freely with me, say thy mind is changed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120500">And that thou lovest her spite of all her rigours. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120510" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e120520">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120530">Great sir, my duty here restrains my tongue,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120540">It is enough for me that I have told you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120550">You are my King, and I your humble vassal. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120560" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e120570">Though I am so, I will not force my subject</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e120580">To suffer for concealing his desires. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120590" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e120600">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120610">Ah sir, cast off all thoughts that may retard</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120620">The course of your contentments, when a business</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120630">Concerns the good of such a gracious King,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120640">What is the death of one unhappy man? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120650">'Twill be a fair employment for my arm,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120660">To punish him that's troublesome to his prince. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120670" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e120680">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120690">Well thou hast overcome, thy extreme virtue</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120700">Shall serve for an example to thy King. <stage xml:id="A19347-e120710">To Seriffa.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120720">See where I am obliged, madam, don Sancho,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120730">I hope has ta'en these blushes off, I know</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120740">What right you have to me, and I to you. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120750">This should have been your work don Diego rather</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120760">Then his that did it, you were privy to</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120770">All passages between our fathers; but</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120780">You I say, as all else do, 'tis dangerous</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120790">To turn the stream of King's affections. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120800" who="A19347-diego">
              <speaker>D. Die.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e120810">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120820">Your majesty is gracious, and prevents</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120830"><pb facs="35"/> excuses from your subjects, I could say</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120840">No more in my own defence. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120850" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e120860">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120870">Here I restore to thee thine own Cimena,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120880">(Most perfect lover) madam, I hope your rigour</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120890">Is not habitual, he's Roderigo,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120900">Who spite of my desires, has always loved</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120910">And honoured you, do not defer then longer,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120920">His and your own contentment, let his love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120930">Wracked with so many storms, find here its harbour,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120940">He has conquered still abroad, let him not lose</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120950">At home, but add thy myrtles to his laurels,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120960">And so confirming to him the same faith,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e120970">Thou gavest him once, receive him for thy husband. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e120980" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e120990">On what shall I resolve? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e121000" who="A19347-roderigo">
              <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e121010">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e121020">To take my life,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e121030">If you deny the price of my dear love,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e121040">For since the hope of that has yet preserved it,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e121050">They both must fall together, and 'twill be</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e121060">Some satisfaction to have died your lover. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e121070" who="A19347-cimena">
              <speaker>Cim.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e121080">Rise, 'tis enough, I am Cimena ever,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19347-e121090">Thou Roderigo, and I wholly thine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19347-e121100" who="A19347-king">
              <speaker>K.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19347-e121110">
                <l xml:id="A19347-e121120">Live happy lovers then, and taste the pleasures,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e121130">Which with so many crosses you have purchased:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e121140">Quit all your cares, and celebrate this day,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e121150">My court shall be love's palace, come fair Princess:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e121160">Y' are mine by a double tie of love and duty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e121170">Which I shall still preserve, since I am taught</l>
                <l xml:id="A19347-e121180">To do not what I would; but what I ought. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer xml:id="A19347-e121190">Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="35"/>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A19347"><item xml:id="A19347-king" n="72">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-king</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">72</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19347-roderigo" n="58">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-roderigo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">58</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19347-cimena" n="40">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-cimena</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">40</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19347-sancho" n="26">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-sancho</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">26</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19347-infanta" n="25">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-infanta</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">25</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19347-serifa" n="22">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-serifa</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">22</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19347-spheranti" n="18">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-spheranti</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">18</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A19347-celimant" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-celimant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19347-arias" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-arias</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19347-diego" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-diego</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19347-unassigned" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19347-boy" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-boy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19347-page" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19347-page</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

