<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A13613">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Two First Comedies (Andria, The Eunuch)<date type="creation_date">1627</date></title>
        <author>Terence</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A13613_00.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The two first comedies of Terence called Andria, and the Eunuch newly Englished by Thomas Newman. Fitted for scholler priuate action in their schooles.</title>
            <author>Terence.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>88 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2011 December (TCP phase 2)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99838757</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 23897.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">3145</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13613</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The two first comedies of Terence called Andria, and the Eunuch newly Englished by Thomas Newman. Fitted for scholler priuate action in their schooles.</title>
            <title type="alt">Andria. English</title>
            <title type="alt">Andria.</title>
            <title type="add">Eunuchus.</title>
            <author>Terence.</author>
            <author>Newman, Thomas, fl. 1627,</author>
            <author>Terence.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[16], 110 [i.e. 108], [2] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by G. M[iller] and are to be sold at the house of M. Fenricus next to the Grayhound Tauerne in the Black-Friers,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1627.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Verse translations, by Thomas Newman, of Terence's Andria and Eunuchus.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The Eunuch begins on verso of F2 [i.e. E2].</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Pages 50-51 repeated in number only; 60-61 and 63-64 missing in number only; 56-57 misnumbered 58-59; E2 missigned F2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Errata on recto of H8, final leaf.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Preliminary pages and 81-82 torn. Beginning-page 1 and 76-101 from Folger Shakespeare Library copy spliced at end.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A13613_00-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A13613_00-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A13613_00-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A13613_00-e100040">The two first comedies of Terence called Andria, and the eunuch newly englished by Thomas Newman.</p>
        <p xml:id="A13613_00-e100050">Fitted for scholar private action in their schools. </p>
        <quote xml:id="A13613_00-e100060">
          <p xml:id="A13613_00-e100070">Nec verbum verbo curabis reddere fidus interpres.</p>
          <bibl xml:id="A13613_00-e100080">Horace.</bibl>
        </quote>
        <p xml:id="A13613_00-e100090">London, printed by G. m. and are to be sold at the house of m. Fenricus next to the greyhound tavern in the Blackfriars. 1627.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="poem" xml:id="A13613_00-e100100">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>Author ad librum</head>
        <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100110">Old wives and fools have faith, the cricket's song</l>
        <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100120">In the warmed chimney portends death ere long</l>
        <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100130">My creed holds no such thing. If crickets sing,</l>
        <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100140">I rather doubt th'o'reheated bricks may bring</l>
        <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100150">Some danger to my house when these I hear,</l>
        <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100160">(If any thing) I only fire do fear:</l>
        <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100170">But many things (Poor book) I justly fear,</l>
        <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100180">When critics descants on thy lines I hear. </l>
        <div type="poem" xml:id="A13613_00-e100190">
          <head>Libri ad authorem responsio.</head>
          <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100200">Fear no true critic; all that know you, know</l>
          <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100210">What love and honour to such men you owe:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100220">And men of that high name, will never throw</l>
          <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100230">Their censures on an argument so low. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100240">These I not fear; but I do doubt them though,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13613_00-e100250">Who would from fools censorious critics grow. </l>
        </div>
        <closer xml:id="A13613_00-e100260">
          <signed xml:id="A13613_00-e100270">T. N</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A13613_00-e100280">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To the scholars of Paul's school, T. N. wisheth increase in grace and learning.</head>
        <p xml:id="A13613_00-e100290">What I at first intended for mine own employment to pass away spare time, and afterwards purposed for your private exercise only, is now made public not by my free and voluntary election; but by an accident of near nature to constraint. For having hastily finished the translation of these two first comedies of Terence, and ended the four first acts of the third, I missed my book one alone day, and then found it again gelded of the three latter acts of the third comedy. Shortly after I met the copy thereof in the hands of a stationer: whence I conjectured that my book had been copied out by character for sale; and that done by some lame and ignorant author, who was not able to be his own decipherer. I had neglected this thief, this plagiary; and had suffered him to make use of my labour, but that one honest and learned gentleman had seen my doings in Andria, and who also knew I was about the residue. You apprehend the just reason of this publication. As touching my<pb facs="3"/> dedication, I do not so much doubt the imputation of carelessness of my credit in seeking patronage from raw and green youth, as I fear the challenge of ambitiousness in providing patrons, who are to stand up in all succession of times so long as your schools foundation shall continue: and some of you being likely very shortly to become of most full ability to defend your unknown client. But till you arrive at such maturity, give me leave to maintain myself, and to prepare you.</p>
        <p xml:id="A13613_00-e100300">I have already heard somewhat, whereby I further suspect how I may be further quarrelled. There will perhaps some be found who on their good faiths will protest that this general licentiousness of turning Latin books into English, caries with it much inconvenience. I hope in the general looseness they include not those extant translations of Livy, Pliny, Plutarch, Suetonius, Tacitus, and the like authors: if they mean only such versions as was that of Ovid's art of love, and the like books tending to corruption of youth, I will join with them; and add, that such translations are not only inconvenient but impious also. But in Terence is no such danger. In those few passages where his matter bears any rank sent or sense, you shall find it hushed by some modest close eclipse, or stopping aposiopesis; or else couched under such dark and mystical terms, as the young scholar cannot apprehend to any danger of defiling: which course I have also<pb facs="3"/> pursued. Besides Terence (As I heard) hath formerly been englished and published: so that this way I might decline the crime, of first turning him into our tongues, but because I never saw that English author, and therefore know not how he hath carried it, I dare not shelter myself under such precedent: but I dare venture to share with Theod. Beza in any hazard of this imputation; and let such cavillers know, that they by this aspersion shall be found to wound that learned Frenchman through my sides: for his translation is extant, imprinted in French on one side and in Latin on the other side of every leaf: and is now in the hands of all young scholars, throughout the whole French kingdom. From the matter of the translation I come to the manner, and therein do foresee, that it may be objected, that where Terence many times useth general terms, I do so rashly perticularlize him, places that in many places I retain not the purpose and meaning of my author; and again, that in some my English doth not render the Latin truly: by the first they would enforce, that I conceive not the drift and scope of my author; by the later that I understand not his words. I will only give you two or three instances, the better to prepare you to apprehend the rest. An. act. 1. Sc. 1. ver. 3. Curentur haec that these things be well ordered or looked too, I in special terms thus restrain, that these things be well cooked; having relation to isthaec intrò auferte<pb facs="4"/><pb facs="4"/><pb facs="5"/> going before, where I understand isthaec to be meant of provision for a dissembled wedding supper. Here it may be opposed by some, not out of their own brains or conceit, but by arguments filched out of blind and ignorant authors, that I am beside the cushion. I am not ignorant of three reasons used above a hundred years ago against this interpretation. First it is said that auferre is a word denoting things contemptible, and therefore cannot be meant of cates or dainties of diet. Secondly, it is affirmed that here was no such provision made as would require these servants to carry in: and this they ground on the words of Davus act. 2. scen. 2. Paululum obsonij. And again, act. 2. scen. 6. Vix drachmis inquit obsonatus est decem. Thirdly, they urge the old French printed books, where by the pictures expressing the arguments of every scene certain logs or billets are figured, and not baskets with provision from the market. Whence they would infer that by isthaec no feasting stuff is intended but matter of fuel only. Perceive you not the blockish conceit of these loggerhead arguers? stay a while; and perhaps I shall afford you means, better to understand the matter. First, therefore I confess and avoid the argument of contempt: for though auferre (According to Donat) be commonly used of things spoken of with disdain, yet not always so; for that which Terence meant by auferte isthaec in the first line, is<pb facs="5"/> named curentur haec in the third: now curatio in its proper notion is medicinae, aut (Quae est eius famula) coquinae; and cannot be said of any thing whereof we speak with disdain or loathing. Davus words prove nothing: they only extenuate, do not deny the provision. And for the French pictures. Painters and poets (You know) take much liberty: but for answer I say, that Ascensius a learned critic, great grammarian and famous printer above 100. years ago in France, and so best able to determine, the doubt, taking upon him to argue the question, hath left the matter indifferent: yet inclines rather to Edulia than ligna. And methinks such interpretation may be evinced by evidence of reasons; for besides that a wedding was strongly to be born up (This could not handsomely be carried without a feast) it is manifest that Simo came from the market: for so Pamphilus, act. 1. scen. 5. Pater praeteriens modò apud forum. Did these servants attend Simo thence with billets or bavins on their shoulders? this construction were as ridiculous, as improbable that a man of Simo's estate whose son was worthy to receive ten talents in portion with a wife, act. 5. scen. 4. should be unfurnished of such ordinary provision. Or came these servants empty home after Simo? and were appointed to carry in logs and faggots then lying before their master's door? this conjecture is as absurd; for how came the wood there? why did it trouble the stage? or<pb facs="6"/> which way might it concern the argument? Especially why should Sosia formerly made free, now suspect that his master Simo would mutare factum; and recall him to a second bondage, by imposing upon him such slavish drudgery as curare focum; a scullion's no freed man's office? what art needed hereto? and Sosia tenders employment of art in the words immediately following quid est, quod ars mea tibi efficere possit amplius? Indeed to steward a feast had in it some art, and seems to have been a part of freed men's employments, eunuch, act. 3. scen. 5. ver. 60. Thus I hope I have given you some reason of this interpretation. Besides Guido hath long ago so construed it, viz. anno Dom. 1497. and Ascensius reviewing Guido and in many places correcting him, hath yet herein against his own French printed copies allowed him, at lest left it indifferent. I told you before I had heard somewhat: it was of him in whose hands I met with my adulterate copy. This man charged the book with many foul errors, and that justly: one thing he taxed which was mine own; yet which I durst not maintain, for fear of giving suspicion that I was father of the rest. Ander. Act. 2. scen. 2. The words were olera et pisciculos portantem in coenam seni, which I render with herbs and small sprats for the old man's supper: the challenge was, that the doer took pisciculus to be Latin for the sprot; beside (Said he) it would be considered whether this fish were to be<pb facs="6"/> found in the Attic seas. I would not have vouchsafed answer hereunto, but that many coincident passages in the book will directly fall under the same frivolous cavil. In this respect therefore I thought good to satisfy you herein; that by the same reason you may be the better armed to defend the residue. I know pisciculus to be a general word including every species of small fishes, and not the sprot only, as well as coetus doth comprehend quamuis belluam marinam, and not the whale alone: yet should I translate immania cete hideous or dreadful whales, I think the sharpest sighted grammarian would wink at it. Whither the sprot hath ever been eaten in Athens, I neither know nor care: I writ in London, and would speak to be understood: and being to set down a poor and homely fish supper thought by sprats it might be well expressed. Master Gascoigne long since translated a comedy of Ariosto's, which he englished supposes: this was presented in Gray's inn. He therein thus describes an homely and scanty supper — one small shotterel a pennyworth of cheese, and ten spurlings. I think no wise man would press that translator to instance in the very fishes in kind by Ariosto named: I could indeed have wished he had named some other course fish better known to his audience: which he might have done if he had said, one shotten herring, and some half score of red sprats: for my part, I do not understand what a shottrellor a Spurling meaneth. <pb facs="7"/>Yea Terence himself in the eunuch act. 2. sc 2. brings in Gnato reckoning up a number of several kinds of victuallers, cetarij, lanij, coqui, fartores, piscatores etc. It shall be hard for the best critic to prove all these professions to be had in Athens in Menander's time. This is<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A13613_00-e100310"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg> comicum as pardonable as usual among translators. Furcifer I call pillory rogue: the pillory being with us a punishment of reproach, nearest to that which they underwent, who thence were called furciferi amongst the ancient Romans. Grammarians divide themselves into two parties about the word riscus, eunuch A. 4.1.6. I incline to the one side, and imagine it some such thing as is our hamper of wicker covered with leather. Peniculus is a word of large extent, and manifold signification, I render it a mop wherewith our servants use to cleanse wet floors; if another shall call it the cook's malkin wherewith they clear ovens, I will not challenge it. Many things were in Athens in Menander's time, which Terence had never seen, there were as many in Rome in Terence his time, which no English man knoweth. Shall I be driven to give names of things not extant? If I put in things now in being to supply the place of other things long since lost, to the understanding of my reader and sufficient expression of my author, I hope I can be no further required. These and the like are the main things which I doubt to hear of; for the rest I leave to your free and courteous censure; which yet<pb facs="7"/> I desire you to spare, till a few years more be over your heads; and then also to use this method. Let the original and the English copy be laid together; consult for evidence with the old expositors: if they chance to wrangle (As they do almost everywhere ) then if you please hearken to Donat and Ascensius; if these at any time be silent, or else vary (This happens seldom) then make use of your own judgement. After this course taken you may with pleasure stuff your book with marginal castigations; to me it shall be no disparagement, to you it will prove much advantageous; there being no book of this kind, to the studious and often turning over whereof I would more willingly excite you. The hope of this your diligence shall encourage me to let slip no vacant time till I have sent the other four comedies among you. Now the father of lights and giver of all good gifts enlighten your understandings; strengthen your memories; rectify your wills; and furnish you with all needful graces, that you may become a comfort to your parents and governors, a credit to your schoole-masters, and tutors, an ornament to the church and state wherein you are to live. In the mean time. committing you to your studies, I bid you heartily farewell.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A13613_00-e100320">
          <signed xml:id="A13613_00-e100330">Your very hearty well wisher T. N. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A13613_00-e100340">
      <div type="errata" xml:id="A13613_00-e100350">
        <pb facs="66"/>
        <p xml:id="A13613_00-e100360">Faults escaped in Andria. </p>
        <p xml:id="A13613_00-e100370">Page 1. l 3. I think, r. Sir think. p. 2. l. 20. one some, 1. some one. p. 8 l. 23. roundabouts , r. windabout. p. 9. l. 25. nothing, r. noting. P, 36. l. 1. now I, r. i. l. 16. leave the course, r. I leave. p. 39 l. 6. this the, r. 'tis the p. 17. l. 22. ought, r. oft. p. 49. O Charinus, r. who's that o Charinus. </p>
        <p xml:id="A13613_00-e100380">Eunuch. </p>
        <p xml:id="A13613_00-e100390">Argument l. 56 hath down, r. hath set down. Char. of au. l. 7 straggling, r. struggling. Pro. l. 64. plays, r. play. Ac. 1. S. 1. l. 10. not one, r. one. between 14 and 15 line, put in this verse, you are cast in law, you may go shake the care. l. 29 she it. r. she yet. L 32. shall allay, r. she'll allay, s. 2. l. 87 lovely woman, r. lonely woman. l. 88. kinsmen, 1. kinsman. l. 112. and eu. an eu. l. 113. great ladies have, r. great ladies only have. Act. 2. Sc. 3. l. ult. his soldiers, r. the soldiers sc. 5. l. 70. I wormeling, r. I a wormeling l. 99 whom, r. home. Ac 4 sc. 2 l 3 ought, r. oft. l. 10. torn, r. turn. l. 12. be pent, r. here be pent. Sc. 3. l. 35. and accident, r. an accident l. 68. i● be, r. if 't be. l. 7. Simatio and Sannto, r. Simatio and sannto l. 14. but, r. that. l. 15. or soldiers, r. our soldier's l. 27. thinks, r. Thinkst l. 39. assure, r. assured. Act. 5. sc 1. l. 19. jest 'Him. read, left'em . pag. 104. l. 6. he cause. read, case, l. 18. Ile-but, r. I'll —, but.</p>
        <pb facs="67"/>
        <pb facs="67"/>
        <pb facs="68"/>
        <pb facs="68"/>
        <pb facs="69"/>
        <pb facs="69"/>
        <pb facs="70"/>
        <pb facs="70"/>
        <pb facs="71"/>
        <pb facs="71"/>
        <pb facs="72"/>
        <pb facs="72"/>
        <pb facs="73"/>
        <pb facs="73"/>
        <pb facs="74"/>
        <pb facs="74"/>
        <pb facs="75"/>
        <pb facs="75" n="1"/>
        <pb facs="76" n="76"/>
        <pb facs="76" n="77"/>
        <pb facs="77" n="78"/>
        <pb facs="77" n="79"/>
        <pb facs="78" n="80"/>
        <pb facs="78" n="81"/>
        <pb facs="79" n="82"/>
        <pb facs="79" n="83"/>
        <pb facs="80" n="84"/>
        <pb facs="80" n="85"/>
        <pb facs="81" n="86"/>
        <pb facs="81" n="87"/>
        <pb facs="82" n="88"/>
        <pb facs="82" n="89"/>
        <pb facs="83" n="90"/>
        <pb facs="83" n="91"/>
        <pb facs="84" n="92"/>
        <pb facs="84" n="93"/>
        <pb facs="85" n="94"/>
        <pb facs="85" n="95"/>
        <pb facs="86" n="96"/>
        <pb facs="86" n="97"/>
        <pb facs="87" n="98"/>
        <pb facs="87" n="99"/>
        <pb facs="88" n="100"/>
        <pb facs="88" n="101"/>
      </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

