<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A12969">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Gammer Gurton's Needle <date type="creation_date">1575</date></title>
        <author>Stevenson, William</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A12969.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A ryght pithy, pleasaunt and merie comedie: intytuled Gammer gurtons nedle played on stage, not longe a go in Christes Colledge in Cambridge. Made by Mr. S. Mr. of Art.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>21 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2004 November (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99846663</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 23263.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 67(a).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">11647</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12969</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A ryght pithy, pleasaunt and merie comedie: intytuled Gammer gurtons nedle played on stage, not longe a go in Christes Colledge in Cambridge. Made by Mr. S. Mr. of Art.</title>
            <title type="alt">Gammer Gurtons nedle.</title>
            <author>Stevenson, William, d. 1575,</author>
            <author>Bridges, John, d. 1618,</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[40] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>In Fleetestreat beneth the Conduit at the signe of S. Iohn Enangelist [sic] by Thomas Colwell,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>[1575]</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Gammer Gurton's needle.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Sometimes attributed to William Stevenson and to John Bridges; misattributed to John Still.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Publication date from colophon.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-E4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: Gammer Gurtons nedle.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Title-page variants: (1): "anp" for "and" in second line; (2) "impr nted"; (3) "imprented".</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A12969-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A12969-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A12969-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A12969-e100040">A right pithy, pleasant and merry comedy: entituled gammer Gurton's needle: played on stage, not long ago in Christ's college in Cambridge.</p>
        <p xml:id="A12969-e100050">Made by Mr●. S. Mr. of art.</p>
        <p xml:id="A12969-e100060">Imprinted at London in Fleetstreet beneath the conduit at the sign of s. John evangelist by Thomas Colwell.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A12969-e100070">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>¶ The names of the speakers in this comedy.</head>
        <list xml:id="A12969-e100080">
          <item xml:id="A12969-e100090">¶ Diccon the bedlam.</item>
          <item xml:id="A12969-e100100">¶ Hodge gammer Gurton's servant.</item>
          <item xml:id="A12969-e100110">¶ Tib gammer Gurton's maid.</item>
          <item xml:id="A12969-e100120">¶ Gammer Gurton.</item>
          <item xml:id="A12969-e100130">¶ Dock gammer Gurton's boy.</item>
          <item xml:id="A12969-e100140">¶ Dame chat,</item>
          <item xml:id="A12969-e100150">¶ Doctor rat the curate.</item>
          <item xml:id="A12969-e100160">¶ Master bailiee.</item>
          <item xml:id="A12969-e100170">¶ Doll dame chattels maid.</item>
          <item xml:id="A12969-e100180">¶ Scapethrift mayst Bailey's servant.</item>
        </list>
        <p xml:id="A12969-e100190">¶ Mu●es. </p>
        <closer xml:id="A12969-e100200">¶ God save the Queen.</closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A12969-e100210">
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="A12969-e100220">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>¶ The prologue.</head>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100230">As gammer Gurton, with many a wide stitch</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100240">Sat pesynge and patching of Hodgher man's briche</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100250">By chance or misfortune as she's her grare to●●</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100260">In Hodge leather breeches her needle she lost ▪</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100270">When Diccon the bedlam had hard by report</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100280">That good gammer Gurton was ●ob●e in this sort,</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100290">He quietly persuaded with her in that stound</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100300">Dame chat her dear gossyp this needle had found,</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100310">Yet knew she no more of this matter (Alas)</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100320">Then knoweth Tom our clerk what the priest saith at mass</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100330">Here of there ensued so fearful a fray,</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100340">Mass doctor was sent for these gossyps to stay,</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100350">Because he was curate, and esteemed full wise</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100360">Who found that he sought not, by Diccon's device,</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100370">When all things were tumbled and clean out of fashion</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100380">Whether it were by fortune, or some other constellation</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100390">Suddenly the needle Hodge found by the pricking</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100400">And drew it out of his buttock where he felt it sticking</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100410">Their hearts then at rest with perfect security,</l>
        <l xml:id="A12969-e100420">With a pot of good ale they stroke up their plaudite. </l>
      </div>
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A12969-e100430">
        <head>¶ The first act.</head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e100440">
          <head>The first scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e100450">¶ Diccon.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e100460" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100470">Many a mile have I walked, divers and sundry wai●●</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100480">And many a good man's house have I been at in my days</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100490">Many a gossip's cup in my time have I tasted</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100500">And many a broche and spit, have I both turned and basted</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100510">Many a piece of bacon have I had out of their balks</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100520">In running over the country, with long and were walks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100530">Yet came my foot never, within those door ch●ekes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100540">To seek flesh or fish ▪ garlic, onions or leeks. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100550">That ever I saw a sort, in such a plight</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100560">As here within this house ap●er●th to my s●ght,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100570">There is howling and scowling a●l 〈…〉 adamye,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100580"><pb facs="3"/> with whewling and puling, as though they had lost a trump</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100590">Sighing and sobbing, they weep and they wail</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100600">I marvel in my mind, what the devil they ail</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100610">The old trot sits groaning, with alas and alas,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100620">And Tib wrings her hands, and takes on in worse case</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100630">With poor cock their boy, they be driven in such fits</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100640">I fear me the folks be not well in their wits,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100650">Ask them what they ail, or who brought them in this stay? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100660">They answer not at all, but alack and wellaway</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100670">When I saw it booted not, out at doors I hied me</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100680">And caught a slip of bacon, when I saw that none spied me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100690">Which I intend not far hence, unless my purpose fail</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100700">Shall serve for a shoeing-horn to draw on two pots of ale. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e100710">
          <head>¶ The first art.</head>
          <head>The second scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e100720">Hodge. Diccon.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e100730" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100740">See so cham arrayed with dabbling in the dirt</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100750">She that set me to ditching, ich would she had the squirt</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100760">Was never poor soul that such a life had? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100770">Gog's bones this filthy glaye hase dressed me to bad</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100780">God's soul, see how this stuff tears</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100790">Iche were better to be a bearward and set to keep bears</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100800">By the mass here is a gash, a shameful hole in dead</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100810">And one stitch tear further, a man may thrust in his head. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e100820" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100830">¶ By my father's soul Hodge, if I should now be sworn</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100840">I can not choose but say thy breech is foul be torn,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100850">But the next remedy in such a case and hap</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100860">Is to planch on a piece, as broad as thy cap. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e100870" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100880">¶ Gog's soul man, 'tis not yet two days fully ended</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100890">Since my dame Gurton (●hem sure) these breeches amended,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100900">But Cham made suce a drudge to trudge at every need</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100910">Chwold rend it though it were stitched what sturdy packthread,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e100920" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100930">¶ Hoge, let thy breeches go, and speak and tell me soon</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100940">What devil aileth gammer gurton, and Tib her maid to frown,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e100950" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100960">¶ Tush man thou'rt deceived, ●ys their daily look,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100970">They coure so over thecoals, their eyes be bleared with smoke,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e100980" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e100990">¶ Nay by the mass, I perfectly perceived as I came hither</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101000"><pb facs="3"/> that either Tib and her dame hath been by the cares to gether</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101010">Or else as great a matter as thou shalt shortly see. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101020" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101030">¶ Now iche beseech our lord they never better agree. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101040" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101050">¶ By gog's soul there they sit as still as stones in the streite</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101060">As though they had been taken with fairies or else with some ill sprite</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101070" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101080">¶ Gog's heart, I durst have laid my cap to a crown</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101090">Chwould learn of some prancome as soon as ich came to town. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101100" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101110">¶ Why Hodge art thou inspired? or didst thou thereof here? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101120" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101130">¶ Nay, but ich saw such a wonder as ich saw nat this ▪ vii. year</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101140">Tom Tankard's cow (Be gog's bones) she set me up her sail</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101150">And flinging about his half acre frisking with her tail,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101160">As though there had been in her arse a swarm of bees,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101170">And Chad not cried tphrowh hoore, shed leapt out of his lees. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101180" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101190">¶ Why Hodge lies the cunning in Tom tankards cow's tail? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101200" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101210">¶ Well Ich chave hard some say such tokens do not fail,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101220">But cast thou not till in faith Diccon, why she frowns or where at</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101230">Hath no man stolen her ducks or hens, or gelded gyb her cat</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101240" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101250">¶ What devil can I tell man, I could not have one word</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101260">They gave no more heed to my talk than thou wouldst to a lord</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101270" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101280">¶ Iche can not still but muse, what marvellous thing it is</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101290">Chyll in and know myself what matters are amiss. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101300" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101310">¶ Then farewell hodge a while, since thou dost inward haste,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101320">For I will into the good wife chats, to feel how the ale doth taste. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e101330">
          <head>¶ The first acre.</head>
          <head>The thyrd scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e101340">¶ Hodge. Tyb.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101350" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101360">Cham aghast by the mass, ich wot not what to do</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101370">Chad need bless me well before ich go them to</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101380">Perchance some felon spirit may haunt our house indeed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101390">And then chwere but at noddy to venture where cha no need</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101400" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>Tib,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101410">¶ Cham worse than mad by the mass to be at this stay</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101420">Cham chid, Cham blamed, and beat on all th'hours on the day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101430">Lamed and hunger starved, pricked up all in jags</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101440">Having no patch to hide my back, save a few rotten rags. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101450" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101460">¶ I say Tib, if thou be Tib, as I trow sure thou be,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101470">What devil make ado is this, between our dame and thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101480" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>Tyb.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101490">¶ Gog's bread Hodge thou had a good turn thou wart not here this while. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101500"><pb facs="4"/>It had been better for some of us to have been hence a mile</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101510">〈◊〉 gammer is so out of course, and frantic all at ones</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101520">That co●ke our boy●● I poor wench, have felt it on our bones. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101530" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>H●●ge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101540">●; what is the matter, say on Tib whereat she taketh so on. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101550" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>Tyb.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101560">¶ 〈◊〉 is undone she say (Alas,) her joy and life is gone</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101570">If 〈◊〉 here not of some comfort, she is say but dead</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101580">Shall never ●ome within her lips, one inch of meat ne bread. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101590" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101600">¶ 〈◊〉 la●●e Cham not very glad, to see her in this dump</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101610">Cholde a noble ●er stole hath fallen, and she hath broke her rump</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101620" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>Tyb.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101630">● nay and t●at were the worst, we would not greatly care</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101640">For bursting of her huckle bone, or breaking of her chair,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101650">But greater, greater, is her grief, as hodge we shall all feel. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101660" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101670">¶ Gog's wounds Tib, my gammer has never lost her needle? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101680" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>Tyb.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101690">¶ Her needle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101700" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101710">¶ Her needle? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101720" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>T●b,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101730">¶ Her neele by him that made me, it is true Hodge I tell thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101740" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101750">¶ Gog's sacrament, I would she had lost, tharte out of her belli●</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101760">The devil or else his dame, they ought her sure a shame</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101770">How a murrion came this chance, (Say Tib) unto our dame? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101780" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101790">¶ My gammer sat her down on her pes, and had me reach thy breeches</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101800">And ●y and by, a vengeance in it or she had take two stitches</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101810">To clap a clout upon thine arse, by chance a side she ●eares</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101820">And gyb our ●at in the milk pan, she spied over head and ears</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101830">Ah hoar, out these, she cried aloud, and swapped the breeches down</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101840">Up went her staff, and out leapt gyb, at doors into the town</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101850">And since that time was never wight, cold set their eyes upon it</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101860">Gog's malison cha●e cock and I, b●d twenty times light on it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101870" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101880">¶ And is not them my breeches sewn up, to morrow that I should were</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101890" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101900">¶ No in faith ●odge thy breeches lie for 〈◊〉 this never the ●ere. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101910" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101920">¶ Now a vengeance light on all the sort, that better should have kept it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101930">The cat● the house, and t●b our maid, thatbetter should have swept it</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101940">S● where we cometh crawling, come on in twenty devil's way</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101950">Ye have made a fair day's work, have you not● pray you say. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e101960">
          <head>¶ The first act.</head>
          <head>The iv. Scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e101970">¶ Gammer. Hodge. Tyb. Cocke.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e101980" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>●āmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e101990">Alas h●ge, alas. I may well curse and ban</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102000"><pb facs="4"/> this day that ever I saw it, with gyb and the milk pan</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102010">For these and ill luck to gather, as knoweth Cocke my boy</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102020">Have stack away my dear needle, and robbed me of my io●e</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102030">My fair long straight needle that was mine only treasure</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102040">The first day of my sorrow is, and last end of my pleasure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102050" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102060">¶ Might ha' kept it when ye had it, but fools will be fools still. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102070">Lose that is vast in your hands, ye need not but ye will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102080" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102090">¶ Go hie thee tib, and run thou hoore, to th'end here of the town</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102100">Didst carry out dust in thy lap seek where thou pour'st it down</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102110">And as thou sawest me roking, in the ashes where I mourned</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102120">So see in all the heap of dust, thou leave no straw unturned. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102130" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102140">¶ That chal gammer swythe and tyte, and soon be here again,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102150" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102160">¶ Tib stoop and look down to theground to it, and take some pain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102170" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102180">¶ Here is a pretty matter, to see this gere how it goes</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102190">By gog's soul I thank you would loes your arse, and it were loose</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102200">Your needle lost, it is pity you should lack care and endless sorrow</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102210">Gog's death how shall my breeches be sewed, shall I go thus to morrow</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102220" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102230">¶ Ah Hodge, Hodge, if that ich could find my needle by the reed</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102240">Chould sow thy breeches ich promise y●, with full good double thread</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102250">And set a patch on either knee, should last this months twain</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102260">Now god and good saint sith I pray, to send it home again. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102270" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102280">¶ Whereto served your hands and eyes, but this your needle to keep</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102290">What devil had you else to do ye kept ich wot no sheep</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102300">Cham fain a broad to dyg and del●e ▪ in water ▪ mire and clay</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102310">Sossing and possing in the dirt, still from day to day</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102320">A hundred things that be abroad, Cham set to see them we'll</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102330">And ●oure of you sit ●●le at home, and can not k●●pe 〈◊〉. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102340" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102350">¶ My neele alas ich lost it hodge, what 〈◊〉 Ich m● up h●●t ●</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102360">To save the milk set up for thee, which g●b our c●t hath wasted</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102370" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102380">¶ The devil ●e burst both gib, and 〈…〉 th' all the rest</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102390">Cham alwa●es sure of the worst end, whoever have the best</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102400">Where ha you ben flaging abroad, since you your ●eele l●●t</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102410" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102420">¶ Within the house, and at the door, sittin● by this same post</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102430">Where I was looking a long hour, before these folks came here,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102440">But wellaway, all was in vain, my neel● is never th● n●r●. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102450" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102460">¶ Set me a candle let me seek and grope wherever it 〈◊〉</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102470">Gog's heart ye be so foolish (Ich think) you kn●w● it not when you ●● see</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102480" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102490">¶ Come hither cock, what cock I say. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102500" who="A12969-cock">
            <speaker>Cocke.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102510">¶ How gammer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102520" who="A12969-gurton">
            <pb facs="5"/>
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102530">¶ ●oe hie thee soon, and grope behind the old brass pan,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102540">Which thing when thou hast done</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102550">There shalt thou find an old shoe, where in if thou look well</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102560">Thou shalt find lying an inch of a white tallow candle,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102570">Light it, and bring it right away. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102580" who="A12969-cock">
            <speaker>Cocke.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102590">¶ That shall be done anon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102600" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102610">¶ Nay tarry Hodge till thou hast light, and then we'll seek each one. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102620" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102630">¶ Come away ye whoreson boy, are ye asleep : ye must have a crier. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102640" who="A12969-cock">
            <speaker>Cocke.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102650">¶ Ich cannot get the candle light here is almost no fire. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102660" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102670">¶ Chil hold the a penny Chil make that come if thatich may catch thine ears</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102680">Art deaf thou whoreson boy● cock I say, why canst not hears. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102690" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102700">¶ Beat him not Hodge but help the boy and come you two together. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e102710">
          <head>¶ The i. Act.</head>
          <head>The v. Scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e102720">¶ Gammer. ¶ Tyb, ¶ Cock. ¶ Hodge.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102730" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102740">How now Tib, quick let's here, what news thou hast brought hither. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102750" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>Tyb.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102760">¶ Chave tossed and tumbled yender heap our and over again</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102770">And winnowed it through my fingers, as men would winow grain</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102780">Not so much as a hen's turd but in pieces I tore it</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102790">Or whatsoever clod or clay I found, I did not spare it</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102800">Looking within and eke without, to find your needle (Alas)</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102810">But all in vain and without help, your needle is where it was. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102820" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102830">¶ Alas my needle we shall never meet, adieu, adieu for aye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102840" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>Tyb.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102850">¶ Not so gammer, we might it find if we knew where it say. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e102860" who="A12969-cock">
            <speaker>Cocke.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102870">¶ Gog's cross gammer if ye will laugh look in but at the door</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102880">And see how Hodge lieth tumbling and tossing amids the floury</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102890">Raking there some fair to find among the ashes dead</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102900">Where there is not one spark, so big as a pin's head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102910">At last in a dark corner two sparks he thought he sees</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102920">Which where indeed naught else but Gyb our cats two eyes</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102930">Puff quoth Hodge thinking thereby to have fire without doubt</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102940">With that Gyb shut her two eyes, and so the fire was out</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102950">And by and by them opened, even as they were before,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102960">With that the sparks appeared even as they had done of yore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102970">And even as hodge blew the fire as he did think</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102980">Gyb as she felt the blast straight way began to wink,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e102990"><pb facs="5"/> till Hodge fell of swearing, as cam● h●st to his turn,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103000">The ●●er was sure bewitched, and therefore would not burn:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103010">At last Gyb up the slayers, among the old posts and pins,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103020">And Hodge he hied him after till broke were both his shins:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103030">Cursing and swearing oaths, were never of his making,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103040">That Gyb would fire the house, if that she were not taken. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103050" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103060">¶ See here is all the thought that the foolish Urchy● taketh,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103070">And Lyb methink at his elbow almost as merry maketh</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103080">This is all the wit ye have when others make their mo●e,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103090">Come down Hodge, where art thou and let the cat alone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103100" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103110">¶ Gog's heart, help and come up, Gyb in her tail hath fire. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103120">And is like to burn all if she's get a little hire:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103130">Come down (Quoth you,) nay then you might count me a patch,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103140">The soul cometh down on your ●eads if it take once that thatch. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103150" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103160">¶ It is the cat's eyes fool that shineth in the dark. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103170" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103180">¶ Hath the cat do you think in every eye a spark. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103190" who="A12969-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103200">¶ ●e, but they shine as like fire as ever man see. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103210" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103220">¶ By the mass and she burn all, youth hear the blame for me</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103230" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103240">¶ Come down and help to seek here our needle that it were found</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103250">D●wne ●yb on t●o knees I say, down C●ck● to the ground. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103260">To God I make a vow, and so to good saint Anne</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103270">'A candle shall they have a piece, get it where I can,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103280">It I may my needle find in one place or in other. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103290" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103300">¶ Now a vengeance on 〈◊〉 light, on gyb and gybs mother</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103310">And all the generation of cats both far and near</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103320">Look on the ground ●orson thinks thou the needle is here. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103330" who="A12969-cock">
            <speaker>Cocke.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103340">¶ ●y my troth gammer methought your needle here I saw</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103350">But when my fingers touched it, I ●ell it was a straw. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103360" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103370">¶ See Hodge what's ty●, may it not be within it,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103380" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103390">¶ Break it ●oo●e with thy hand and see and thou canst find it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103400" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>●yb</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103410">¶ Nay break it you Hodge according to your word. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103420" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103430">¶ ●ogs ●ydes, fie it stinks ▪ it is a cat's turd,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103440">It were well done to make thee ere it by the mass. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e103450" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103460">¶ This matter amendeth not my needle is 〈◊〉 where it was</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103470">Our candle is at an end let us all in ●u●ght</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103480">And come another time, wh●● we have more light</l>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A12969-e103490">
        <pb facs="6"/>
        <head>The ii. act.</head>
        <div n="1" type="song" xml:id="A12969-e103500">
          <head>First a song.</head>
          <lg xml:id="A12969-e103510">
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103520">¶ Back and side go bare, go bare,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103530">Booth foot and hand go cold:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103540">But belly god send thee good ale enough,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103550">Whether it be new or old. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A12969-e103560">
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103570">I can not eat, but little meat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103580">My stomach is not good:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103590">But sure I think, that I can drink</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103600">With him that wears a hood. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103610">Though I go bare, take ye no care,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103620">I am nothing a cold:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103630">I stuff my skill, so full within,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103640">Of jolly good ale and old. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103650">Back and side go bare, go bare,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103660">Booth foot and hand go cold:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103670">But belly god send the good ale enough</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103680">Whether it be new or old. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A12969-e103690">
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103700">I love no roast, but a nut brown toast</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103710">And a crab laid in the fire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103720">A little bread, shall do me stead</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103730">Much bread I not desire:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103740">No frost nor snow, no wind I trow</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103750">Can hurt me if I would,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103760">I am so wrapped, and throughly leapt</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103770">Of jolly good ale and old. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103780">Back and side go bare. Etc. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A12969-e103790">
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103800">And Tib my wife, that as her life</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103810">Loveth well good ale to seek,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103820">Full oft drinks she, till ye may see</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103830">The tears run down her cheeks:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103840">Then doth she troll, to me the bowl</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103850">Even as a malt worm should,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103860">And say sweet heart, I took my part</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103870">Of this jolly good ale and old. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103880">Back and side go bare. Etc. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A12969-e103890">
            <pb facs="6"/>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103900">Now let them drink, till they nod and wink,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103910">Even as good fellows should do</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103920">They shall not miss, to have the bliss,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103930">Good ale doth bring men to:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103940">And all poor souls that have scoured bouls</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103950">Or have them lustily trolled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103960">God save the lives, of them and their wives</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103970">Whether they be young or old. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e103980">●acke and side go bare. Etc. </l>
          </lg>
        </div>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e103990">
          <head>The first scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e104000">¶ Diccon. Hodge.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104010" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104020">Well done be gog's malt, well song and well said,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104030">Come on mother chat as thou art true maid,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104040">〈◊〉 fresh pot of ale let's see to make an end</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104050">Against this cold weather my naked arms to defend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104060">This gere it warms the so●le, now wind blow on the worst,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104070">And let us drink and swill, till that our bellies burst</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104080">Now were he a wise man, by cunning cold define</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104090">Which way my journey lieth or where Dyccon will dine</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104100">But one good turn I have ▪ be it by night or day</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104110">South, East, North or West, I am never out of my way. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104120" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104130">¶ Chym goodly rewarded, cham I not, do you think? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104140">Chad a goodly dinner for all my sweat and swink,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104150">Neither butter cheese, milk onions flesh nor fish</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104160">Save this poor piece of barley bread, 'tis a pleasant costly dish. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104170" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104180">¶ Hail fellow Hodge and will to face, with thy meat, if thou have any! </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104190">But by thy words as I them smelled, thy daintrels be not many. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104200" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104210">¶ Daintrels diccon (Gog's soul man (Save this piece of dry horsebread,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104220">Cha bit no bit this live long day, no crome come in my head</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104230">My guts they yawl crawl and all my belly rumbleth</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104240">The puddings can not lie still, each one over other tumbleth</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104250">By gog's heart Cham so ver●e, and in my belly penned</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104260">Chould one piece were at the spittlehouse another at the castle's end. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104270" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104280">¶ Why hodge, was there none at home thy dinner for to set:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104290" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104300">¶ Godg● bread Diccon ich came too late, was nothing there to get</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104310">G●b (A ●owle fiend might on her light (Licked the milk pan so clean</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104320">See Diccon, 'twas not so well washed this vii year as ich were</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104330">A pestilence light on all ill luck, Chad thought yet for all this</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104340"><pb facs="7"/> of a morsel of bacon behind the do●● at worst should not miss,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104350">But when ich sought a slip to cut, as ich was wont to do</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104360">Gog's soul Diccon, gyb our cat had 〈◊〉 the bacon to. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104370">Which bacon Diccon stole, as is declared before. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104380" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104390">¶ Ill luck quod he, marry swear it Hodge, this day thetruth to tell</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104400">Thou rose not on thy right side, or else bl●●t thee not well. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104410">Thy milk slopped up, thy bacon filched, that was to bad luck Hodge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104420" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104430">¶ Nay, nay, there was a fouler fa●●t, my gammer game thedog</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104440">Seest not how cham rent and torn, my heels, my knees and my breech</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104450">Chad thought as ich sat by the fire, help here and there a stitch,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104460">But there ich was powpte indeed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104470" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104480">¶ Why Hodge? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104490" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104500">¶ Boots not man to tell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104510">Cham so dressed amongst a sort of fools, Chad better be in hell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104520">My gammer (Cham ashamed to say) by god served me not we'll</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104530" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104540">¶ How so Hodge? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104550" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104560">¶ Hase she not gone trowest now and lost her needle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104570" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104580">¶ Her eel Hodge, who fished of late? that was a dainty dish. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104590" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104600">¶ Tush tush, her needle, her needle, her neele man. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104610">('tis neither flesh nor fish. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104620">A little thing with an hole in the end, as bright as any syller,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104630">Small, long, sharp at the point, and straight as any pillar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104640" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104650">¶ I know not what a devil thou meanest, thou bringst me more in doubt</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104660" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104670">¶ Knowest not with what Tom tailor's man, fits broaching through a clout</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104680">A needle, neele, a needle, my Gammer's needle is gone. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104690" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104700">¶ Her neele Hodge, now I smell thee, that was a chance alone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104710">By the mass thou hadst a shameful loss, and it were but for that 〈◊〉</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104720" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104730">¶ Gog's soul man chould give a crown Chad it but iii. stitches. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104740" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104750">¶ How sayest thou Hodge, what should he have, again thy n●●le got</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104760" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104770">¶ Gem vathers soul, and Chad it chould give him a new grot. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104780" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104790">¶ Canst thou keep counsel in this case. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104800" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104810">¶ Else chwold my thong were out. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104820" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104830">¶ Do than but then by my advice, and I will fetch it without doubt,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104840" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104850">¶ I'll run, I'll ride, I'll dig, chyl 〈◊〉,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104860">(Chill toil, Chill trudge shalt see:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104870">Chill hold Chil draw, Chil pull, Chill pinch</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104880">(Chill kneel on my bare knee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104890">Chill scrape, Chill scratch, Chill syfte ▪ I'll seek,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104900">(Chill bow, Chill bend, Chill sweat. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104910"><pb facs="7"/>Chil sto●p, Chil stir, Chil cap Chil knee, Chil creep on hands and feet ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104920">Chil be thy bondman Diccon, ich swear by sun and moon</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104930">And channot sum what to stop this gap, Cham utterly undone</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104940">Pointing behind to his torn breeches. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104950" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104960">¶ Why, is there any special cause, thou takest hereat such sorrow</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e104970" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104980">¶ Kirstian Clack Tom simsons maid, by the mass coms hither to morrow</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e104990">Cham not able to say, between us what may hap,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105000">She smiled on me the last Sunday when ich put of my cap,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105010" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105020">¶ Well Hodge this is a matter of weight, and must be kept close,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105030">It might else turn to both our costs as the world now goose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105040">Shalt sware to be no blab Hodge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105050" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105060">¶ I'll Diccon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105070" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105080">¶ Then go to,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105090">Lay thine hand here, say after me as thou shalt hear me do</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105100">Haste no book? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105110" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105120">¶ Cha no book I. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105130" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105140">¶ Then needs must force us both,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105150">Upon my breech to lay thine hand, and there to take thine oath. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105160" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105170">¶ I Hodge breathless,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105180">Swear to Diccon reckless</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105190">By the cross that I shall kiss,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105200">To keep his counsel close</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105210">And always me to dispose</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105220">To work that his pleasure is. <stage xml:id="A12969-e105230">¶ Here he kyssech diccons breech.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105240" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105250">¶ Now Hodge see thou take heed</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105260">And do as I thee bid</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105270">For so I judge it meet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105280">This ●eole again to win</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105290">There is no shift therein</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105300">But conjure up a spirit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105310" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105320">¶ What the great devil Diccon I say? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105330" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105340">¶ Yea in good faith, that is the way,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105350">Fetched with some pretty charm. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105360" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105370">¶ Soft Diccon be not too hasty yet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105380">By the mass for ich begin to sweat</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105390">Cham afraid of syme harm. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105400" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105410">¶ Come hither then and stir the nat</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105420">One inch out of this circle plat</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105430">But stand as I thee teach. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105440" who="A12969-hodge">
            <pb facs="8"/>
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105450">¶ And shall ich be here safe from their claws:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105460" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105470">¶ The master devil with his long paws</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105480">Here to thee can not reach:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105490">Now will I settle me to this gear. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105500" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105510">¶ I say Diccon, hear me, hear:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105520">Go softly to this matter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105530" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105540">¶ What devil man, art afraid of naught</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105550" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105560">¶ Canst not tarry a little thought</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105570">Till ich make a courtesy of water. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105580" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105590">¶ Stand still to it, why shouldst thou fear him? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105600" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105610">¶ Gog's sides Diccon, methink ich hear him</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105620">And tarry chal mare all. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105630" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105640">¶ The matter is no worse than I told it,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105650" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105660">¶ By the mass Cham able no longer to ●olde it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105670">To bad iche must bewray the hall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105680" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105690">¶ Stand to it Hodge, stir not you whoreson,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105700">What devil, be thine arse strings brusten? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105710">Thyself a while but stay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105720">The devil I smell him will be here anon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105730" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105740">¶ Hold him fast Diccon, Cham gone, Cham gone</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105750">I'll not be at that fray. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e105760">
          <head>The ii. act.</head>
          <head>The ii. scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e105770">Diccon. Chat.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105780" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105790">Fie shytten knave, and out upon thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105800">Above all other louts fie on thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105810">Is not here a cleanly prank? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105820">But thy matter was no better</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105830">Nor thy presence here no sweeter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105840">To fly I can the thank:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105850">Here is a matter worthy glozing</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105860">Of gammer Gurton needle losing</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105870">And a foul piece of work,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105880">A man I think might make a play</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105890">And need no word to this they say</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105900">Being but half a clerk. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105910"><pb facs="8"/>Soft, let me alone, I will take the charge</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105920">This matter further to en large</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105930">Within a time short,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105940">If ye will mark my toys, and note</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105950">I will give ye leave to cut my throat</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105960">If I make not good sport,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105970">Dame chat I say, where be ye, within? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e105980" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e105990">¶ Who have we there maketh such a din:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106000" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106010">¶ Here is a good fellow, maketh no great danger,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106020" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106030">¶ What diccon? come near, ye be no stranger,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106040">We be fast set at trump man, hard by the fire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106050">Thou shalt set on the King, if thou come a little nigher. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106060" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106070">¶ Nay, nay, there is no tarrying: I must be gone again</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106080">But first for you in council I have a word or twain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106090" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106100">¶ Come hither Dol, Dol, sit down and play this game,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106110">And as thou sawest me do, see thou do even the same</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106120">There is 5. trumps beside the Queen, that hindmost thou shalt find her</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106130">Take heed of Sim glovers wife, she hath an eye behind her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106140">Now Diccon say your will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106150" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106160">¶ Nay soft a title yet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106170">I would not tell it my sister, the matter is so great,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106180">There I will have you swear by our dear lady of Bullaine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106190">S. Dunstone, and s. Donnyke, with the three Kings of Kullaine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106200">That ye shall keep it secret. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106210" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106220">¶ Gog's bread that will I do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106230">As secret as mine own thought, by god and the devil two. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106240" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106250">¶ Here is gammer gurton your neighbour, a sad and heavy wight</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106260">Her goodly fair red cock, at home. was stole this last night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106270" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106280">¶ Gog's foul her cock with the yellow legs, that nightly crowed so just? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106290" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106300">¶ That cock is stolen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106310" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106320">¶ What was he fetched out of the hens-rust? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106330" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106340">¶ I can not tell where thedevil he was kept, under key or lock. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106350">But Tib hath tickled in gammer's ear, that you should steal the cock</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106360" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106370">¶ Have I strong hoore? by bread and salt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106380" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106390">¶ What soft, I say be still. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106400">Say not one word for all this gear. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106410" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106420">¶ By the mass that I will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106430">I will have the young hoar by the head, and the old trot by thethroat</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106440" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106450">¶ Not one word dame chat I say, not one word for my coat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106460" who="A12969-chat">
            <pb facs="9"/>
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106470">¶ Shall such a beggar's brawl as the thinkest thou make me a thief</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106480">The pocks light on her hores sides, a pestilence and a mischief</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106490">Come out thou hungry needy bitch, oh that my nails be short. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106500" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106510">¶ Gog's bred woman hold your peace, this gere will else pass sport</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106520">I would not for an hundred pound, this matter should be known,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106530">That I am author of this tale, or have abroad it blown</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106540">Did ye not swear ye would be ruled, before the tale I told</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106550">I said ye must all secret keep, and ye said sure ye would. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106560" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106570">¶ Would you suffer yourself diccon, such a sort, to revile you</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106580">With slanderous words to blot your name, and so to defile you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106590" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106600">¶ No goodwi●e chat I would be lot● such drabs should blot my name</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106610">But yet ye must so order all, theDiccon hear no blame. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106620" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chal.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106630">¶ Go to then, what is your rede: say on your mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106640">(Ye shall me rule herein. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106650" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106660">¶ God a mercy to dame chat, in faith thou must the gere begin</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106670">It is twenty pound to a goose turd, my gammer will not tarry</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106680">But hitherward she comes as fast as her legs can her carry,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106690">To brawl with you about her cock, for well and hard Tib say</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106700">The cock was roasted in your house, to breakfast yesterday,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106710">And when ye had the carcase eaten, the feathers ye out flung</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106720">And d●ll your maid the legs she hid a foot deep in the dung. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106730" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106740">¶ Do gracious god my heart is bursts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106750" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106760">¶ Well ro●e yourself a space</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106770">And gammer gurton when she cometh a●on into this place</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106780">Then to the quean let's see tell her your mind and spare not</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106790">So 〈◊〉 Diccon blameless be, and then go to I care not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106800" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106810">¶ 〈…〉 beware her t●rot●, I can abide no longer</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106820">In 〈◊〉 old witch it shall be seen, which of us two be stronger</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106830">〈◊〉 Diccon but at your request, I would not stay one hour,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106840" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106850">¶ Well keepe it in till she be here and then out let it pour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106860">In the meanwhile get you in, and make no words of this</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106870">More of this matt●● with in this hour to hear you shall not miss</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106880">Because I know you are my friend, hide it I could not doubtless</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106890">Ye know your harm, see ye be wise about your own business</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106900">So fare ye will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106910" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106920">▪ 〈…〉 di●con and drink, what doll I say</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106930">Bring here a cup of the best ale, let's see, come quickly a way. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e106940">
          <pb facs="9"/>
          <head>The ii. act.</head>
          <head>The iii. scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e106950">Hodge. Diccon.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e106960" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106970">Ye see masters theone end tapped of this my short device</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106980">Now must woe br●che theter to, hour the smoke arise</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e106990">And by the time they have a while run. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107000">(I trust ye need not crave it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107010">But look what lieth in both their hearts ye are like sure to have it</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107020" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107030">¶ Yea gog's soul, art alive yet? what Diccon dare ich come? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107040" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107050">¶ A man is well hied to trust to thee, I will say nothing but mum</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107060">But and ye come any nearer I pray you see all be sweet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107070" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107080">¶ Tush man, is Gammer's neele found, that chould gladly weet</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107090" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107100">¶ She may thank thee it is not found, for if thou had kept thy standing</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107110">The devil he would have fetched it out, even Hodge at thy commanding</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107120" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107130">¶ Gog's heart, and cold h● tell nothing where the needle might be found</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107140" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107150">¶ Ye foolish dolt, ye were to seek, ere we had got our ground,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107160">Therefore his tale so doubtful was, that I could not perceive it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107170" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107180">¶ Then ich se well something was said, chope one day yet to have it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107190">But diccon, diccon, did not the devil cry ho, ho, ho,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107200" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107210">¶ If thou hadst tarried where thou stoodst, thou wouldst have said so</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107220" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107230">¶ Durst swear of a book, chard him roar, straight after ich was gone</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107240">But tell me diccon what said theknave: let me here it anon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107250" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107260">¶ The whoreson talked to me. I know not well of what</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107270">One while his tongue it ran and paltered of a cat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107280">Another while he stammered still upon a rat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107290">Last of all there was nothing but every word chat, chat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107300">But this I well perceived before I would him rid,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107310">Between chat, and the rat, and the cat, the needle is hid,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107320">Now whether Gyb our cat have eat it in her maw,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107330">Or doctor rat our curate have found it in the straw,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107340">Or this dame chat your neighbour have stolen it, god he knoweth</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107350">But by the morrow at this time, we shall learn how the matter goeth</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107360" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107370">¶ Canst not learn tonight man, seest not what is here,</l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e107380">¶ Pointing behind to his torn breeches.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107390" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107400">¶ 'tis not possible to make it sooner appear,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107410" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107420">¶ Alas Diccon then chave no shift, but lest ich tarry to long</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107430">Hie me to Sym glovers shop, there to seek for a thong,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107440">There with this breech to tatch and tie as ich may. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107450" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107460">¶ To morrow Hodge if we chance to meet, shalt see what I will say. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e107470">
          <pb facs="10"/>
          <head>The ii. act.</head>
          <head>The iiii. scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e107480">Diccon: gammer.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107490" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107500">Now this gere must forward go, for here my gammer: cometh,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107510">Be still a while and say nothing, make here a little room. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107520" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107530">¶ Good lord, shall never be my luck my needle again to spy ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107540">Alas the while 'tis passed my help, where 'tis still it must lie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107550" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107560">¶ Now Jesus gammer Gurton, what driveth you to this sadness</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107570">I fear me by my conscience, you will sure fall to madness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107580" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107590">¶ Who is that, what Diccon, Cham lost man: fie fie. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107600" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107610">¶ Marry fie on them that be worthy, but what should be your trouble,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107620" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107630">¶ Alas the more ich think on it, my sorrow it waxeth double</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107640">My goodly tossing sporyars neele, chave lost ich wot not where. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107650" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107660">¶ Your neele, when? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107670" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107680">¶ My needle (Alas) ich might full ill it spare,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107690">As god himself he knoweth near one beside chave. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107700" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107710">¶ If this be all good gammer, I warrant you all is save. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107720" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107730">¶ Why know you any tidings which way my needle is gone? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107740" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107750">¶ Yea that I do doubtless, as ye shall here anon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107760">A see a thing this matter toucheth, within these xx hours,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107770">Even at this gate, before my face, by a neighbour of yours,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107780">She stooped me down, and up she took a needle or a pin:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107790">I durst be sworn it was even yours, by all my mother's kin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107800" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107810">¶ It was my needle diccon Ich wot, for here even by 〈◊〉 p●ste</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107820">Ich sat, what time as ich up start, and so my needle it lost:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107830">Who was it le●●e son? speak ich pray thee, and quickly tell me that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107840" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107850">¶ A s●ttle quean as any in this town,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107860">(Your neighbour here dame chat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107870" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107880">¶ Dame chat diccon let me be gone, Chil thither in post haste. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e107890" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107900">¶ Take my council yet or ye go, for fear ye walk in waste,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107910">It is a murrion crafty drab, and froward to be pleased. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107920">And ye take not the better way, our needle yet ye lose it:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107930">For when she took it up, even here before your doors</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107940">What soft dame chat (Quoth I) that same is none 〈◊〉 yours</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107950">Avant (Quoth she) sir knave, what pratest thou of that 〈…〉:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107960">I would that hadst kissed me I wot where: (She meant I know 〈◊〉)</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107970">And home she went as brag, as it had been a 〈◊〉,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107980">And I after as bold, as it had been, the goodman of the 〈◊〉:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e107990"><pb facs="10"/> but there and ye had heard her, how she began to scold</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108000">The tongue it went on patins, by him that Judas sold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108010">Each other word I was a knave, and you a bore of hores,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108020">Because I spoke in your behalf, and said the needle was yours,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108030" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108040">¶ Gog's bread, and thinks that callet thus to keep my needle me fro? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108050" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108060">¶ Let her alone, and she minds none other but e'en to dress you so</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108070" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108080">¶ By the mass Chil rather spend the coat that is on my back. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108090">Thinks the false quean by such a slygh, that chill my needle lack</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108100" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108110">¶ Sleep not you gere I counsel you, but of this take good heed</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108120">Let not be known I told you of it, how well soever ye speed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108130" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108140">¶ Chil in Diccon a clean apron to take, and set before me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108150">And ich may my needle once see, Chil sure remember the</l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e108160">
          <head>The ii. act.</head>
          <head>The v. scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e108170">Diccon.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108180" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108190">Here will the sport begin, if these two once may meet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108200">Their cheer durst lay money will prove scarcely sweet</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108210">My gammer sure intends, to be upon her bones,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108220">Which staves, or with clubs, or else with cobble stones. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108230">Dame chat on the other side, if she be far behind</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108240">I am right far deceived she is given to it of kind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108250">He that may tarry by it a while, and that but shorts</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108260">I warrant him trust to it, he shall see all the sport</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108270">Into the town will I, my friends to vysit there</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108280">And hither straight again to see th'end of this gere</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108290">In the mean time fellows, pipe up your fiddles, I say take them</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108300">And let your friends here such mirth as ye can make them. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A12969-e108310">
        <head>The iii. act.</head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e108320">
          <head>The i scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e108330">Hodge.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108340" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108350">Sym glover yet gramercy, Cham meetly well sped now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108360">Thou'rt e●en as good a fellow as ever kyste a cow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108370">Here is a thing in deed, by the mass though ich speak it</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108380">Tom Tankard's great bald cortal, I think could not break it</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108390">And when he spied my need, to be so straight and hard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108400"><pb facs="11"/> Hays lent me here his naull, to set the ●yd forward,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108410">As for my Gammer's neele, the ●lyenge fiend go we●te,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108420">Chill not now go to the ●oore again with it to meet:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108430">Chould make shift good enough and Chad a candle's ●●●e,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108440">The cheese hole in my breech, with these two Chil amend. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e108450">
          <head>¶ The iii. act.</head>
          <head>¶ The ii. scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e108460">Gammer. Hodge.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108470" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108480">How Hodge, mayst now be glad, Cha news to tell thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108490">Ich know who ●ais my needle, ich trust soon shalt it see</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108500" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108510">¶ The devil thou does, hast hard gammer in deed, or dost but jest</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108520" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108530">¶ 'tis as true as steel Hodge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108540" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108550">¶ Why, knowest well where didst lose it? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108560" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108570">¶ Ich know who found it, and took it up shalt see or it be long. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108580" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108590">¶ God's mother dear, if that be true, farewell both naule an thong</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108600">But who hais it gammer say on: chould fain here it disclosed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108610" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108620">¶ That false fixen, that same dame chat, that counts herself so honest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108630" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108640">¶ Who told you so:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108650" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108660">¶ That same did Diccon the bedlam, which saw it done. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108670" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108680">¶ Diccon: it is a vengeable knave gammer, 'tis a bonable whoreson,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108690">Can do more things than that else Cham deceived evil:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108700">By the mass Ich saw him of late call up a great black devil,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108710">Oh the knave cried ho ▪ ho, he roared and he thundered,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108720">And yead bene here, Cham sure you'd murrenly ha' wondered. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108730" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108740">¶ Was not thou afraid Hodge to see him in this place:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108750" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108760">¶ No, and Chad come to me, chould have laid him on the face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108770">Chould have promised him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108780" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108790">¶ But Hodge, had he no horns to push:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108800" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108810">¶ As long as your two arms, saw ye never friar rush</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108820">Painted on a cloth, with a side long cow's tail:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108830">And crooked cloven feet, and many a hoked nail? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108840">For all the world (If I should judge) chould reckon him his brother</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108850">Look even what face friar rush had, the devil had such another</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108860" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108870">¶ New Jesus mercy Hodge. did diccon in him bring:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108880" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108890">¶ Nay gammer (Hear me speak) Chil to● you a greater thing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108900">The devil (When diccon had him, ich heard him wondrous we'll)</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108910"><pb facs="11"/> said plainly (Here before us, that dame chat had your needle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108920" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>●●●mer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108930">¶ They let us go, and ask her wherefore she minds to keep it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108940">Sing 〈◊〉 know so much, 'twere a madness now to sleep it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e108950" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108960">¶ Go to 〈◊〉 ●ammer see ye not where she stands in her doors</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e108970">Bid her give you the needle, 'tis none of hers but yours. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e108980">
          <head>¶ The iii. act.</head>
          <head>¶ The iii scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e108990">Gammer. Chat. Hodge.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109000" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109010">Same chat cholde pray the fair, let me have that is mine</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109020">Chil not this twenty years take one fart that is thine</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109030">Therefore give me mine own and let me live beside the</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109040" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109050">¶ Why art thou crept from home hither, to mine own doors to chide me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109060">Hence doting drab, avaunt, or I shall set the further. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109070">Intends thou and that ●na●e, me in my house to murder:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109080" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109090">¶ Tush gape not so no me woman ▪ shalt not yet eat me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109100">Nor all the friends thou hast, in this shall not entreat me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109110">Mine own goods I will have, and ask thee on believe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109120">What woman: poor folks must have right, though the thing you agrees. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109130" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109140">¶ Give thee thy right, and hang thee up, with all thy beggar's brood</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109150">What wilt thou make me a thief ▪ and say I stole thy good:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109160" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109170">¶ Chil say nothing (Ich warrant thee, but that ich can prove it well</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109180">Thou set my good even from my door, Cham able this to tell,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109190" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109200">¶ Did I (Old witch) steal oft was thine:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109210">(How should that thing be known:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109220" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109230">¶ Ich can not tell, but up thou tookest it as though it had been thine own,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109240" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109250">¶ Marry fie on thee, thou old gyb, with all my very heart. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109260" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109270">¶ Nay fie on thee thou ramp, thou ryg, with all that take thy part. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109280" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109290">¶ A vengeance on those lips that layeth such things to my charge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109300" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109310">¶ A vengeance on those callet's hips, whose conscience is so large</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109320" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109330">¶ Come out hog. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109340" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109350">¶ Come out hog, and let have me right. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109360" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109370">¶ Thou arrant witch. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109380" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109390">¶ Thou bawdy bitch, Chil make thee curse this night. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109400" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109410">¶ A bag and a wallet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109420" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109430">¶ A cart for a callet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109440" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109450">¶ Why weenest thou thus to prevail,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109460">I hold thee a groat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109470"><pb facs="12"/> I shall patch thy coat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109480" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109490">¶ Thou wart as good kiss my tail:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109500">Thou siut thou kut, thou rokes ▪ y● jakes: will not shawms make y● ●ide</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109510" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109520">¶ Thou shald thou bald, thou rotten, thou glutton, I will no longer chid thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109530">But I will teach thee to keep home. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109540" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109550">¶ Wilt thou drunken b●●ste. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109560" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109570">¶ Stick to her gammer, take her by the head, Chil warrant you this feast. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109580">Sm●te I laye gammer,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109590">〈◊〉 I lay gammer,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109600">I trow ye will ●●●●one:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109610">Where by your ●●yl●? claw her by the jaws, pull me out both her eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109620">Gog's bones gammer, hold up your head,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109630" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109640">¶ I trow drab I shall dress thee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109650">Tarry thou knave i hold the a gr●te, I shall make these hands bless thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109660">Take y● this old hoar for amends, and learn thy tongue well to tame</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109670">And say thou met at this bickering, not thy fellow but thy dame. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109680" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109690">¶ Where is the strong stewed hoar, Chil gear a hores mark,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109700">Stand out ones way, that ich kill none in the dark:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109710">Up gammer and ye be alive, Chil feygh now for us both,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109720">Come no near me thou ●calde ●allet, to kill the Ich were loath. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109730" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109740">¶ Art here again thou hoddy-peke , what doll bring me out my spit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109750" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109760">¶ I'll broche thee with this, him father soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109770">(I'll conjure that foul spirit:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109780">Let der● stand cock, why come in deed? keep door thou whoreson boy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109790" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109800">¶ Stand to it thou bastard for thine ears, Ise teach y● a sluttish toy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109810" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109820">¶ Gigs wounds hoar, Chil make the avaunt,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109830">(Take heed cock, pull in the latch,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109840" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109850">¶ I'faith sir loose breach had ye tarried, ye should have found your match. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109860" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109870">¶ Now ware thy throat lozel, thouse prey for all</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109880" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109890">¶ Well said gammer by my soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109900">Hoist her, souse her, bounce her, trounce her, pull out her throat bowl</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109910" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109920">¶ Com'st behind me thou withered witch, and I get once on foot</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109930">Thouse pay for all, thou ol● tar leather, I'll teach the what longs to it</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109940">Take that this to make up thy mouth, till time thou come by more</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109950" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109960">¶ Up gammer stand on your feet, where is the old hore●</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109970">Faith would Chad her by the face</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e109980">(Choulde crack her ●allet crown</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e109990" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110000">¶ A Hodge, Hodge, where was thy help, when fixen had me down. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110010" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110020">¶ By the mass gammer, but for my staff</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110030">(Chat had gone nigh to spyl you</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110040"><pb facs="12"/> ich think the harlot had not cared, and Chad not come to kill you</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110050">But shall well cost our needle thus? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110060" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110070">¶ No Hodge chwarde loath do so. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110080">Thinkest thou Chill take that at her hand, no Hodge ich tell thee no</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110090" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110100">¶ Chold yet this fray were well take up and our own needle at home</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110110">'Twill be my chance ●ls some to kill, where ever it be or whom</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110120" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110130">¶ We have a parson, (Hodge thou knows) a man esteemed wise</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110140">Mast doctor rat, Chil for him lend, and let me here his advice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110150">He will her shrive for all this gere, and give her penance straight</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110160">Wese have our needle, else dame that comes never with in heaven gate</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110170" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110180">¶ Ye marry gammer, y● Ich think best: will you now for him send</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110190">The sooner doctor rat be here, the sooner wes● ha an end,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110200">And here gammer Diccon's devil, (As iche remember well)</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110210">Of cat, and chat, and doctor rat: a felonius tale did tell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110220">Chold you forty pound, that is the way your needle to ●et again. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110230" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110240">¶ Chil ha' him straight, call out theboy, we'll make him take the pain</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110250" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110260">¶ What coke I say, come out what devil canst not ●e●e. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110270" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110280">¶ How now Hodge? how does gammer, is yet the weather cl●●re●</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110290">What would chave me to do? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110300" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110310">¶ Come ●ether cock anon:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110320">Hence swythe to doctor rat, hie thee that thou were gone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110330">And pray him come speak with me, Cham not well at ease,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110340">Shalt have him at his chamber, of else at mother bees,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110350">E●s seek him at Hobfitcher's shop for as charred it reported</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110360" who="A12969-cock">
            <speaker>Cock.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110370">There is the best ale in all the town ▪ and now is most resorted. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110380" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110390">● and shall ich bring him with me gammer? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110400" who="A12969-cock">
            <speaker>Cocke.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110410">● yea, by and by good cock. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110420" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Ho●ge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110430">¶ Shalt see that shall be here anon, else let me have one the dock</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110440">¶ Now gammer shall we two go in, and tarry for his coming</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110450">What devil woman pluck up your heart, and leave of all this glooming</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110460">Though she were stronger 〈◊〉 first, as ich think ye did find her</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110470" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110480">Yet there ye breast the drunken ●ow, what time ye came behind her</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110490">¶ Nay, nay ▪ cham sure she lost not all, for let them to the beginning</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110500">And ich doubt not, but she will make small boast of her winning. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e110510">
          <head>¶ The iii. act.</head>
          <head>¶ The iiii. scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e110520">Tyb. Hodge. Gammer. Cocke.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110530" who="A12969-tyb">
            <pb facs="13"/>
            <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110540">See gammer, gammer, gib our cat, cham afraid what she aileth</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110550">She stands me gasping behind the door,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110560">(As though her wind her faileth:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110570">Now let ich doubt what gib should mean, that now she doth so dote. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110580" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110590">¶ Hold hither, ichould twenty pound, your needle is in her throat</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110600">Grope her ich say, methinks ich feel it, does not prick your hand? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110610" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110620">¶ Ich can feel nothing. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110630" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110640">¶ No, ich know thars not within this land</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110650">A muryner cat then Gyb is, betwixt the Thames and Tyne,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110660">Sh'as as much wit in her head almost as chave in mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110670" who="A12969-tyb">
            <speaker>Tyb</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110680">¶ Faith she's eaten some thing, that will not easily down</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110690">Whether she got it at home, or abroad in the town</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110700">Iche can not tell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110710" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110720">¶ Alas Ich fear it he some crooked pin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110730">And then farewell gyb, she is undone, and lost all save the skin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110740" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110750">¶ Tib, your neele woman, I say: gags soul give me a knife</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110760">And Chil have it out of her maw, or else chal lose my life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110770" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110780">¶ What nay Hodge, fie kill not our cat, 'tis all the cats we ha' now. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110790" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110800">¶ By the mass dame chat bays me so moved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110810">(Iche care not what I kill, ma god a vow:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110820">Go to then Tib to this gear, hold up har tail and take her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110830">Chil see what devil is in her guts Chil take thou pains to rake her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110840" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110850">¶ Rake a cat Hodge, what wouldst thou do? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110860" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110870">¶ What think'st that cham not able? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110880">Did not Tom Lankard rake his Curtal toore day standing in the stable. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110890" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110900">¶ Soft be content, let's here what news</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110910">(Cock bringeth from mayst rat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110920" who="A12969-cock">
            <speaker>Cocke.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110930">¶ Gammer chave b●n there as you bade, you wot well about what</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110940">'Twill not be long before he come, ich durst swear of a book</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110950">He bids you see ye be at home, and there for him to look. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110960" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110970">¶ Where didst thou find him boy was he not where I told thea? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e110980" who="A12969-cock">
            <speaker>Cocke.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e110990">¶ Yes, yes even at hob●ilchers house, by him that bought and sold me</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111000">A cup of ale had in his hand, and a crab lay in the fire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111010">Ch●d much ado to go and come, all was so full of mire:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111020">And gammer one thing I can tell, Hobfilcher's nawl was lost</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111030">And doctor rat found it again, hard beside the door post,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111040">I chould a p●nny can say something, your needle again to fet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111050" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>●●●mer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111060">● cham glad to hear so much cock, then trust he will not let,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111070">To help us herein best he can therefore till time he come</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111080">
              <gap extent="1" unit="lines" xml:id="A12969-e111090" n="13-a-5380"/>
            </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e111100">
          <pb facs="13"/>
          <head>¶ The ii. act.</head>
          <head>¶ The iiii. scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e111110">Doctor Rat. Gammer Gurton.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111120" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111130">A man were better twenty times be a bandog and bark. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111140">Then here among such a sort, be parish priest or clerk</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111150">Where he shall never be at rest, one pissing while a day</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111160">But he must trudge about the town, this way, and that way,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111170">Here to a drab, there to a thief, his shoes to tear and rent</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111180">And that which is worst of all, at every knave's commandment</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111190">I had not sit the space, to drink two pots of ale</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111200">But gammer Gurton's sorry boy, was straight way at my tail,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111210">And she was sick, and I must come, to do I wot not what,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111220">If once her finger's end but ache, trudge, call for doctor rat</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111230">And when I come not at their call, I only thereby lose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111240">For I am sure to lack therefore, a tithe pyg or a goose:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111250">I warrant you when truth is known, and told they have their tale</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111260">The matter where about I come, is not worth a half penny worth of ale,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111270">Yet must I talk so sage and smooth, as though I were a glos●er</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111280">Else or the year come at an end. I shall be sure the loser. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111290">What work ye gammer Gurton? how here is your friend m. rat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111300" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111310">¶ A good m. doctor cha troubled, Cha troubled you, chwot well ●hat</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111320" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111330">¶ How do ye woman: be ye lusty, or be ye not well at ease:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111340" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111350">¶ By gys master cham not 〈◊〉, but yet chave a disease. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111360">Chad a foul turn now of late, Chill tell it you by gigs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111370" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111380">¶ Hath your brown cow cast her calf, or your sandy sow her pigs</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111390" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111400">¶ No, but Chad ben as good they had, as this ich wot we'll. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111410" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111420">¶ What is the matter●</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111430" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111440">¶ Alas, alas, Cha lost my good needle,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111450">My necle I say, and wot ye what: a drab came by and spied it</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111460">And when I asked her for the same, the s●●th flatly deemed it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111470" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111480">¶ What was she that:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111490" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111500">¶ A dame ich warrant you she began to scold and brawl●</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111510">Alas, ala●, come hither Hodge: this wriche can tell you all. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A12969-e111520">
        <head>The iiii. act.</head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e111530">
          <head>The ii. scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e111540">Hodge doctor Rat. gammer. Diccon. Chat.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111550" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111560">
              <gap extent="1" unit="lines" xml:id="A12969-e111570" n="13-b-4760"/>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111580" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111590">〈…〉 us hear. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111600"><pb facs="14"/>Thy dame hath said to me, thou knowest of all this gear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111610">Let's see what thou canst say. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111620" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111630">¶ Bym say sir that ye shall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111640">What matter soever here was done, ich can fell your mashly</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111650">My gammer gurton hear see now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111660">Sat her down at this door see now:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111670">And as she began to stir her, see now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111680">Her needle fell in the floor, see now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111690">And while her staff she took, see now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111700">At Gyb her cat to fling, see now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111710">Her needle was lost in the floor, see now</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111720">Is not this a wondrous thing, see now? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111730">Then came the quean dame chat see now</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111740">To ask for her black cup, see now:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111750">And even here at this gate, see now:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111760">She took that needle up see now:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111770">My gammer than she yeede, see now</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111780">Her needle again to bring, see now</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111790">And was caught by the head see now</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111800">Is not this a wondrous thing, see now</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111810">She tore my Gammer's coat see now</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111820">And scratched her by the face, see now</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111830">Chad thought shad stopped her throat, see now</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111840">Is not this a wondrous case, see now ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111850">When ich saw this, ich was worth see now</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111860">And start between them twain, see now</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111870">Else ich durst take a book oath, see now</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111880">My gammer had been slain, see now. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111890" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111900">¶ This is even the whole matter, as Hodge has plainly told</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111910">And chould fain be quiet for my part that chould</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111920">But help us good master, beseech ye that ye do</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111930">Else shall we both be beaten and lose our needle too. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111940" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111950">¶ What would ye have me to do tell me that I were gone</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111960">I will do the best that I can, to set you both at one</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111970">But be ye sure dame chat hath this your needle found:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e111980" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e111990">¶ Here comes the man that see her take it up on the ground,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112000">Ask him yourself master rat if ye believe not me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112010">And help me to my needle, for god's sake and saint charity. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112020" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112030">¶ Come ne'er diccon and let us hear, what thou can express. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112040"><pb facs="14"/>Wilt thoube sworn y●〈…〉 have ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112050" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112060">¶ Nay by s. Benit Will I not, then might 〈…〉 ra●●. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112070" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112080">¶ Why did 〈…〉 deny it</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112090" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112100">¶ I marry gammer: but I said I 〈…〉 by it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112110" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112120">¶ Will you say a thing, and not stick do it to try it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112130" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112140">¶ Stick to it quoth you master rat, marry ●r I defy it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112150">Nay there is many an honest man, when he such blasts hath blown</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112160">In his friend's ears, he would be loath the same by him were known</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112170">If such a toy be used oft among the honesty</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112180">It may be a simple man, if your and my degree</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112190" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112200">¶ Then we be never the nearer, for all that you can tell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112210" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112220">¶ Yes marry sir, if ye will do by mine advice and counsel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112230">If mother chat see all us here, she knoweth how the matter goes</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112240">Therefore I read you three go hence, and within keep close,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112250">And I will into dame chats house, and so the matter use,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112260">That or you could go twice to church, I warrant you hot now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112270">She shall look well about her, but I durst say a pledge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112280">Ye shall of Gammer's neele, have shortly better knowledge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112290" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112300">¶ Now gentle Diccon do so, and good sir let us trudge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112310" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>Worser Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112320">¶ By the mass ● may not tarry so long to be your judge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112330" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112340">¶ Dys but a little while man, what take so much pain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112350">If I hear no news of it I will come sooner again. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112360" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112370">¶ Carry so much good master doctor of your gentleness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112380" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112390">¶ Then let us hie ●e inward, and Diccon speed thy business. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112400" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112410">¶ Now sirs do ye no more, but keep my counsel just,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112420">And doctor rat shall thus catch, some good I trust,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112430">But mother chat my gossip, talk first with all I must:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112440">For she must be chief captain to lay the rat in the dust,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112450">God deven ●ame chat in faith, and well met in this place. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112460" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112470">¶ God deven my friend Diccon, whether walk ye this pace? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112480" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112490">¶ By my truth even to you, to learn how the world goeth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112500">Hard ye no more of the other matter, say me now by your troth</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112510" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112520">¶ O yes diccon, here the old hoore, and hodge that great knave. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112530">But in faith I would thou hadst seen, oh lord I dressed them brave</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112540">She bore me two or three souses behind in the nape of the neck</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112550">Till I made her old wesen, to answer again keck:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112560">And Hodge that dirty dastard, that at her elbow stands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112570">If one pair of legs had not been worth two pair of hands</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112580">He had had his beard shaven, if my nails would have served</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112590"><pb facs="15"/> and not without a cause for the knave it well deserved. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112600" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112610">¶ By the most I can the thank wench, 〈…〉 so w●l acquit the</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112620" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112630">¶ And 〈…〉 him Di●con, it would have made y● beshit the</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112640">For laughter. The 〈…〉 hast caught up a club,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112650">As though he would have slain the master devil Belsabub,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112660">But I set him soon in word. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112670" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112680">¶ O lord there is the thing</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112690">That Hodge is so offended, that makes him start and ding</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112700" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112710">¶ Why? makes the knave any moiling, as ye have seen or hard</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112720" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112730">¶ Even now I saw him last, like a mad man he ●arde,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112740">And sware by heaven and hell ▪ he would a wreak his sorrow</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112750">And leave you never a hen on li●e ▪ by viii. of the clock to morrow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112760">Therefore mark what I say, and my words see that ye trust</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112770">Your hens be as good as dead, if ye leave them on the rust. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112780" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112790">¶ The knave dare as well go hang himself, as go upon my ground</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112800" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112810">¶ Well yet take heed I say, I must tell you my tale round,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112820">Have you not about your house, behind your furnace or lead:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112830">A hole where a crafty knave, may creep in for need? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112840" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112850">¶ Yes by the mass, a hole broke down, even with in these ii. days. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112860" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112870">¶ Hodge, he intends this same night, to slip in there aways. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112880" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112890">¶ O Christ that I were sure of it, in faith he should have his meed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112900" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112910">¶ Watch well, for the knave will be there as sure as is your creed</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112920">I would spend myself a shilling: to have him swinged well. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112930" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112940">¶ I am as glad as a woman can be of this thing to here tell</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112950">By gog's bones when he cometh, now that I know the matter</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112960">He shall sure at the first skip, to leap in scalding water:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112970">Wish a worse turn besides when he will, let him come. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e112980" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e112990">¶ I tell you as my sister, you know what meaneth mum,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113000">Now lack I but my doctor, to play his part again</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113010">And so where he cometh towards, peradventure to his pain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113020" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113030">¶ What good news Diccon? fellow, is mother chat at home,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113040" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113050">¶ She is sir, and she is not, but it please her to whom:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113060">Yet did I take her tardy, as subtle as she was. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113070" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113080">¶ The thing that thou ween'st for, hast thou brought it to pass? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113090" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113100">¶ I have done that I have done, be it worse be it better. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113110">And dame chat at her wits end, I have almost set her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113120" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>Worser Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113130">¶ Why hast thou spied the needle quickly I pray thee tell. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113140" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113150">¶ I have spied it in faith sir, I handled myself so well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113160">And yet the crafty quean, had almost take my trump. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113170"><pb facs="15"/>But or all came to an end. I set her in a dump:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113180" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113190">¶ How so I pray thee Diccon? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113200" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113210">¶ Marry sir will ye hear? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113220">She was clapped down on the backside, by cock's mother dear</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113230">And there she sat sewing a halter, or a band,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113240">With no other thing save Gammer's needle in her hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113250">As soon as any knock, if she filth be in double,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113260">She needs but once puff, and her candle is out:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113270">Now I sir knowing of every door she pin. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113280">Came nicely, and said no word, till time I was within,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113290">And there I saw the needle, even with these tw●●yes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113300">Whoever say the contrary, I will swear he lies. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113310" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113320">¶ O Diccon that I was not there, then in thy stead. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113330" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113340">¶ Well, if ye will be ordered, and do by my reed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113350">I will bring you to a place, as the house stands. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113360">Where ye shall take the drab, with the needle in her hands</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113370" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113380">¶ For god's sake do so Diccon, and I will gauge my gown</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113390">To give thee a full pot, of the best ale in the town,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113400" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113410">¶ Follow me but a little, and mark what I will say,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113420">Lay down your gown beside you, go to, come on your way:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113430">See ye not what is here a hole wherein ye may creep</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113440">Into the house, and suddenly unwares among them leap,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113450">There shall ye find the bitchfox ▪ and the needle together</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113460">Do as I bid you man, come on your ways hither. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113470" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113480">¶ Art thou sure diccon, the swill tub stands not here about. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113490" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113500">¶ I was within myself man even now, there is no doubt,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113510">Go softly, make no noise, give me your foot sir John,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113520">Here will I wait upon you, till you come out anon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113530" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113540">¶ Help Diccon, out alas, I shall be slain among them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113550" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113560">¶ If they give you not the needle, tell them that ye will hang them</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113570">Ware that, hoow my wenches, have ye caught the fox,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113580">That used to make revel, among your hens and cocks:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113590">Save his life yet for his order, though he sustain some pain</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113600">Gog's bread, I am afraid, they will beat out his brain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113610" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113620">¶ Woe worth the hour that I came hear. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113630">And woe worth him that wrought this gear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113640">A sort of drabs and queans have me blessed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113650">Was ever creature half so evil dressed? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113660">Whoever it wrought, and first did ●●uent it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113670"><pb facs="16"/> he shall I warrant him, err long repent it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113680">I will spend all I have without my skin</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113690">But he shall be brought to the plight I am in,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113700">Master baily I trow, and he be worth his ears. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113710">Will snaffle these murderers and all that them bears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113720">I will surely neither bite nor sup</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113730">Till I fetch him hither, this matter to take up. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A12969-e113740">
        <head>The v. act.</head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e113750">
          <head>The i. scene.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A12969-e113760">Master baily. Doctor Rat.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113770" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bailie.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113780">I can perceive none other, I speak it from my heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113790">But either ye are in all the fault or else in thegreatest part</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113800" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113810">¶ If it be counted his fault, besides all his grieves</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113820">When a poor man is spoilt: and beaten among thieves? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113830">Then I confess my fault herein, at this season,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113840">But I hope you will not judge so much against reason. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113850" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113860">¶ And methinks by your own tale, of all that ye name. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113870">If any played the thief you were the very same. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113880">The women they did nothing, as your words make probation</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113890">But stoutly withstood your forcible invasion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113900">If that a thief at your window, to enter should begin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113910">Would you hold forth your hand, and help to pull him in:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113920">Or you would keep him out: I pray you answer me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113930" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113940">¶ Marry keep him out, and a good cause why:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113950">But I am no theef● sir but an honest learned clerk. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e113960" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113970">¶ Yea but who knoweth that, when he mee●s you in the dark</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113980">I am sure your learning shines not out at your nose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e113990">Was it any mar●a●●●, though the poor woman arose</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114000">And start up, being afraid of that was in her purse</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114010">Methink you may be glad that you luck was no worse. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114020" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114030">¶ Is not this ●ill enough, I pray you as you think,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114040">Showing his broken head. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114050" who="A12969-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114060">● yea but a man in the dark, of chances do wink,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114070">〈…〉 he smites his father as any other man. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114080">〈◊〉 for ●●●ke of ●ight, discern him he ne can. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114090">〈◊〉 it not have been your luck, with a spit to have been slain:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114100" who="A12969-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114110">〈…〉 I am little better, my scalp is cloven to the brain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114120"><pb facs="16"/> if there be all the remedy, I know who bears the kockes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114130" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114140">¶ By my troth and well worthy, besides to kiss the stocks</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114150">To come in on the back side, when ye might go about,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114160">I know none such, unless they long to have their brains knocked out</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114170" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114180">¶ Well, will you be so good sir, as talk with dame chat ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114190">And know what she intended: I ask no more but that ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114200" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114210">¶ Let her be called fellow because of master doctor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114220">I warrant in this case, she will be her own proctor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114230">She will tell her own tale in metre or in prose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114240">And bid you seek your remedy, and so to wipe your nose. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A12969-e114250">
          <head>¶ The v. act.</head>
          <head>¶ The ii. scene,</head>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114260" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <stage xml:id="A12969-e114270">M. baily. Chat. D. Rat. gammer. Hodge. Diccon.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114280">Same chat, master doctor upon you here complained</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114290">That you ● your maids should him much misorder. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114300">And taketh many an o●h, that no word he feigned,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114310">Laying to your charge, how you thought him to murder:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114320">And on his part again, that same man saith further</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114330">He never offended you in word nor intent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114340">To hear you answer hereto, we have now for you sent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114350" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114360">¶ That I would have murdered him, fie on him wretch,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114370">And evil might be thee for it ▪ our lord I beseech. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114380">I will swear on all the books that opens and shuts</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114390">〈◊〉 fai●eth this tale out of his own guts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114400">For this seven weeks with me, I am sure he sat not down,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114410">Nay ye have other minions, in the other end of the town,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114420">Where ye were like● to ca●ch such a blow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114430">Then anywhere else, as far as I know. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114440" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114450">¶ 〈◊〉 like then master doctor, you stripe there ye got not? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114460" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114470">¶ Think you I am so mad, that where I was bet, I would not ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114480">Will ye believe this quean, before she hath tried it? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114490">It 〈◊〉 the first deed she hath done and afterwards divide it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114500" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114510">¶ 〈◊〉 at ma●, will you say I broke your head? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114520" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114530">¶ 〈◊〉 canst thou prove the contrary? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114540" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114550">¶ Nay how provest thou that I did the 〈◊〉 ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114560" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114570">¶ To plainly, by s. Mary. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114580">This proof I trow may serve, though I no 〈…〉</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114590">Showing his broken head. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114600" who="A12969-chat">
            <pb facs="17"/>
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114610">¶ Because thy head is broken, was it I that it broke? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114620">I saw thee rat I tell thee, not once within this fortnight,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114630" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114640">¶ No marry, thou sawest me not, for why thou hadst no light,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114650">But I felt thee for all the dark, be shrew thy smooth cheeks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114660">And thou groped me this will declare, any day this six weeks</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114670">Showing his head. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114680" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114690">¶ Answer me to this m. rat, when caught you this harm of yours? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114700" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114710">¶ A while ago sir, god he knoweth, with in les than these ii. hours. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114720" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114730">¶ Dame chat was there none with you:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114740">(Confess i'faith) about that season. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114750">What woman, let it be what it will, 'tis neither felony nor treason</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114760" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114770">¶ Yes by my faith master baily, there was a knave not far</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114780">Who caught one good fillip on the brow, with a door bar</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114790">And well was he worthy, as it seemed to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114800">But what is that to this man, since this was not he. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114810" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114820">¶ Who was it then? let's here. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114830" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114840">¶ Alas sir, ask you that? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114850">Is it not made plain enough (By the own mouth of dame chat</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114860">The time agreeth, my head is broken, her tongue can not lie,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114870">Only upon a bare nay she saith it was not I. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114880" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114890">¶ No marry was it not indeed ye shall here by this one thing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114900">This afternoon a friend of mine, for good will gave we warning</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114910">And bade more well look to my rust, and all my capons pens,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114920">For if I ●●ke not better heed, a knave would have my hens,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114930">Than I to save my goods took so much pains as him to watch</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114940">And as good fortune served me, it was my chance him for to catch</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114950">What strokes he bore away, or other what was his gains</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114960">I wot not, but sure I am, he had something for his pains</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114970" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Ba●l●.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e114980">¶ Yet tells thou not who it was. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e114990" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat ▪</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115000">¶ Who it was a false thief,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115010">That came like a false fore, my ●ull●i●e to kill and mischief. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115020" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115030">¶ But knowest thou not his name ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115040" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115050">¶ I know it but what than. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115060">It was that cra●ty cullion Hodge my gammer Gurton's man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115070" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bailie.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115080">¶ Call me the knave hither, he shall sure kiss the stocks. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115090" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115100">I shall te●ch him a lesson, for filching hens or cocks. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115110">¶ I marvel master baily, so bleared be your eyes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115120">An egg is not so full of meat as she is full of lies:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115130">When she hath played this prank, to excuse all this gear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115140"><pb facs="17"/> she layeth the fault in such a one, as I know was not there. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115150" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115160">¶ Was he not there look on his pate, that shall be his witness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115170" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115180">¶ I would my head were half so h●●e, I would seek no redress,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115190" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115200">¶ God bless you gammer Gurton. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115210" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115220">¶ God ●ylde you master mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115230" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115240">¶ Thou hast a knave with in thy house, Hodge, a servant of thine. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115250">They tell 〈◊〉 busy knave, is such a filching one,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115260">That hen. 〈◊〉 goose or capon, thy neighbour can have none,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115270" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115280">¶ By go● 〈◊〉 ●uch ameued, to bear any such report:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115290">Hodge was not wo●●●ch trow, to have him in that sort. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115300" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115310">¶ A thievisher knave is not on live, more filching nor more false</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115320">Many a truer man than he, have hanged up by the half. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115330">And thou his dame of all his theft, thou art the sole receiver</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115340">For hodge to catch, and thou to keep, I never knew none better</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115350" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115360">¶ Sir reverence of your masterdom, and you were out adoor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115370">Chold be so bold for all her brags, to call her arrant whore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115380">And ich knew Hodge so bad as tow, Ich with me endless sorrow</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115390">And chould not take the pains, to hang him up before to morrow? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115400" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115410">¶ What have I stolen from thee or thine: thou ill-favoured old trot. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115420" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115430">¶ A great deal more (By gods blessed,) then chever by the got,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115440">That thou knowest well I need not say it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115450" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115460">¶ Stop there I say,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115470">And tell me here I pray you, this matter by the way:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115480">How chance hodge is not here him would I fain have had. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115490" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115500">¶ Alas sir, he'll be here anon, h● be handled to ●ad. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115510" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115520">¶ Master baily, sir ye be not such a fool well I know,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115530">But ye perceive by this lingering, there is a pad in the straw. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115540">Thinking that Hodge, his head was broke, and that gammer</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115550">Would not let him come before them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115560" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115570">¶ Ch●l show you his face, ich warrant thee, lo now where he is. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115580" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bailie.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115590">¶ Come on fellow it is told me thou art a shrew iwis,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115600">Thy neighbour's hens thou takest, and plays the two legged fore</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115610">Their chickens and their capons to, and now and then their cocks. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115620" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115630">¶ Ich defy them all that dare it say, Cham as true as the best. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115640" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115650">¶ Wart not thou take within this hour, in dame ●hats hen's nest? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115660" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115670">¶ Take there? no master chold not dot, for a house full of gold. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115680" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115690">¶ Thou or the devil in thy ●ote, swear this I dare be bold. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115700" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115710">¶ ●w●●re me no swearing quean, the devil h● 〈◊〉 the sorrow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115720">All is not worth a gua●, thou canst swear till to morrow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115730"><pb facs="18"/> where is the harm he hath? show it by god's bread,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115740">Ye beat him with a witness, but the stripes light on my head. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115750" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115760">¶ Bet me? gog's blessed body, chold first ich trow have burst the</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115770">Ich think and Chad my hands loose callet chould have crust th●. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115780" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115790">¶ Thou shitten knave I trow thou knowest the full weight of my fist</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115800">I am foully deceived, unless thy head and my d●ore bar kissed</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115810" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115820">¶ Hold thy chat whore thou criest so loud, 〈◊〉 man else be hard</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115830" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115840">¶ Well knave, and I had the alone, I 〈◊〉 ●●rely rap the Costard. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115850" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115860">¶ Sir answer me to this, is thy head whole or broken? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115870" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat ▪</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115880">¶ Yea master baily, blessed be ever● good token. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115890" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115900">¶ Is my head whole? ich warrant you, 'tis neither scurvy nor sealed</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115910">What you foul beast, does think 'tis either pil● or bald. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115920">Nay ich thank god: Chil not for all that thou mayst sp●nd</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115930">That Chad one scab on my narse, as broad as thy finger's end. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115940" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115950">¶ Come nearer hear. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115960" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115970">¶ Yes that iche dare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e115980" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e115990">¶ By our lady here is no harm,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116000">Hodges head is hole enough, for all dame chats charm. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116010" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116020">¶ By gog's blessed, however the thing he clockes or smolders,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116030">I know the blows he bore away, either with head or shoulders,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116040">Camest thou not knave within this hour, creeping into my pens</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116050">And there was caught within my house, groping among my hens. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116060" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116070">¶ A plague both on thy hens and the, a cart whore, a cart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116080">Chould I were hanged as high as a tree, and chware as false as thou art</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116090">Geve my gammer again her washi●al, thou stole away in thy lap. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116100" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116110">¶ Yea master baily there is a thing, you know not on may hay</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116120">This drab she keeps away my good, thedevil he might her snare</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116130">Ich pray you that ich might have, a right action on her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116140" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116150">¶ Have I thy good old filth, or any such old ●owes? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116160">I am as true, I would thou knew, as skin between thy brows</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116170" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116180">¶ Many a truer hath been hanged, though you escape the danger</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116190" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116200">¶ Thou shalt answer by god's pity, for this thy foul slander. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116210" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116220">¶ Why, what can ye charge her withal to say so, ye do not well. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116230" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116240">¶ Marry a vengeance to her heart, thewhore hase stolen my needle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116250" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116260">¶ Thy needle old witch, how so? it were al●nes thy skull to knock</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116270">So didst thou say, the other day, that I had stolen thy cock</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116280">And roasted him to my breakfast, which shall not be forgotten,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116290">The devil pull out thy lying tongue, and teeth that be so rotten. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116300" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116310">¶ Give me my needle, as for my cock, chould be very loath</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116320"><pb facs="18"/> that chuld here tell he should h●●g, on thy false faith and troth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116330" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116340">¶ Your talk is such, I can ●●arse learn● who should be most in fault</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116350" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116360">¶ Yet shall ye ●●nd no other wight, save ●●e, by bred and salt</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116370" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116380">¶ Keep ye content a while ▪ see that your songs ye hold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116390">Methinks you should remember, this is no place to scold ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116400">How knowest thou gammer gurton, dame chat thy needle 〈◊〉</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116410" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116420">¶ To name you sir the party, chould not be very glad. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116430" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116440">¶ Yea but we must needs hear it, and therefore say it boldly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116450" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116460">¶ Such one as told the tale, full soberly and coldly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116470">Even he that looked on, will swear on a book:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116480">What time this drunken gossip, my fair ●●ng neele up took</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116490">Diccon (Master) the bedlam, Cham very sure ye know him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116500" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bailie.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116510">¶ A false knave by God's pity, ye were but a fool to trow him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116520">I durst adventure well the price of my best cap,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116530">That when the end is known, all will turn to a jape,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116540">Told he not you that besides, she stole your cock that tied ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116550" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116560">¶ No master no indeed, for then he should have lied,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116570">My cock is I thank Christ, safe and well a fine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116580" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116590">¶ Yea but that ragged colt, that whore that tyb of thine</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116600">Said plainly thy cock was stolen, and in my house was eaten,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116610">That lying cut is lost, that she is not swinged and beaten,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116620">And yet for all my good name, it were a small amends</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116630">I pick not this gear (Hearst thou) out of my finger's end</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116640">But he that hard it told me, who thou of late didst name</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116650">Diccon whom all men knows, it was the very same. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116660" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116670">¶ This is the case, you lost your needle about the doors</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116680">And she answers again, she hase no cock of yours,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116690">Thus in you talk and action, from that you do intend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116700">She is whole five mile wide, from that she doth defend:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116710">Will you say she hath your cock? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116720" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116730">¶ No me●y sir that Chil not,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116740" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116750">¶ Will you confess her neele? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116760" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116770">¶ Will i●●o sir will I not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116780" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116790">¶ Then there lieth all the matter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116800" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116810">¶ Soft ●●i●er by the way,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116820">Ye know she could do li●le, and she could not say nay. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116830" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116840">¶ Yea but he that made one lie about your cock stealing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116850">Will not stick to make another, what time lies be in dealing</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116860">I ween the end will prove, this brawl did first arise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116870"><pb facs="19"/> upon no other ground, but only diccons lies. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116880" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116890">¶ Though some be lies as you belike have espied them. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116900">Yet other some be true, by proof I have well tried them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116910" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116920">¶ What other thing beside this dame chat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e116930" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116940">¶ Marry sir even this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116950">The tale I told before, the self same tale it was his,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116960">He gave me like a friend, warning against my lo●●e,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116970">Else had my hens be stolen, each one, by god's cross:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116980">He told me Hodge would come, and in he came indeed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e116990">But as the matter chanced, with greater haste than speed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117000">This truth was said, and true was found, as truly I report. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117010" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117020">¶ If doctor rat be not deceived, it was of another sort. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117030" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117040">¶ By god's mother thou and he, be a couple of subtle foxes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117050">Between you and Hodge. I bear away the boxes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117060">Did not diccon apoynt the place, where thou shouldst stand to meet him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117070" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117080">¶ Yes by the mass, and if he came, bade me not stick to spit him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117090" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117100">¶ God's sacrament the villain knave hath dressed us round about,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117110">He is the cause of all this brawl, that dyrty shitten lout:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117120">When gammer gurton here complained, and made a rueful moan</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117130">I heard him swear that you had gotten, her ned●e that was gone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117140">And this to try he further said, he was full lo●h how be it</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117150">He was content with small ado, to bring me where to see it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117160">And where ye sat, he said full certain, if I would follow his read</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117170">Into your house a privy way, he would me guide and lead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117180">And where ye had it in your hands, sewing about a clout,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117190">And set me in the back hole, thereby to find you out:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117200">And whiles I sought a quietness, creeping upon my knees,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117210">I found the weight of your door bar, for my reward and fees,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117220">Such is the luck that some men gets, while they begin to mell</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117230">In setting at one such as were out ▪ minding to make all well. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117240" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117250">¶ Was not well blessed gammer, to scape thescour ▪ and Chad ben there</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117260">Then Chad ben dressed be like, as ill by the mass, as ga●●ar vicar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117270" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117280">¶ Marry sir, here is a sport alone, I looked for such an end</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117290">If diccon had not played the knave, this had been soon amend</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117300">My gammer here he made a fool, and dressed her as she was</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117310">And good wife chat he set to school, till both parts cried alas,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117320">And D. rat was not behind, whiles chat his crown did pare,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117330">I would the knave had been stark blind, 〈◊〉 Hodge had not his share. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117340" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117350">¶ Cham meetly well sped already amongst, Cham dressed like a colt</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117360"><pb facs="19"/> and Chad not had the better wit, Chad been made a ●oul●. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117370" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117380">¶ Sir knave make haste diccon were here, fetch him wherever he be</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117390" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117400">¶ Fie on the villain, fie, fie, that makes us thus agree,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117410" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117420">¶ Fie on him knave, with all my heart, now fie, and fie again. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117430" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117440">¶ Now fie on him may I best say, whom he hath almost slain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117450" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117460">¶ Lo where he cometh at hand, belike he was not fare</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117470">Diccon hear be two or three, thy company can not spare. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117480" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117490">¶ God bless you, and you may be blessed so many all at once</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117500" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117510">¶ Come knave, it were a good deed to geld thee by cock's bones</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117520">Seest not thy handiwork ▪ sir rat can ye forbear him? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117530" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117540">¶ A vengeance on those hands light, for my hand came not near him</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117550">The horsen priest hath lift the pot, in some of these alewives chairs</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117560">That his head would not serve him, belike</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117570">To come down the stairs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117580" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Baily.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117590">¶ Nay soft, thou mayst not play theknave, and have this language to</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117600">If thou thy tongue bridle a while, the better mayst thou do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117610">Confess the truth as I shall ask, and cease a while to fable. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117620">And for thy fault I promise thee, thy handling shall be reasonable</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117630">Hast thou not made a lie or two, to set these two by the ears? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117640" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117650">¶ What if I have ▪ five hundred such</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117660">Have I seen within these seven years:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117670">I am sorry for nothing else but that I see not the sport</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117680">Which was between them when they met, as they themselves report</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117690" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117700">¶ The greatest thing master rat, ye see how he is dressed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117710" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117720">¶ What devil need he be groping so deep, in good wife chats hens nest</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117730" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117740">¶ Yea but it was thy drift to bring him into thebriers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117750" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117760">¶ God's bread, hath not such an old fool, wit to save his ears? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117770">He showeth himself herein ye see, so very a cox,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117780">The cat was not so madly allured by the fox,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117790">To run into the snares, was set for him doubtless,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117800">For he leapt in for mice, and this sir John for madness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117810" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117820">¶ Well and ye shift no better, ye losel, lyther, and la●●●,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117830">I will go near for this, to make ye leap at a dasye. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117840">In the King's name master baily, I charge you set him fast. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117850" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117860">¶ What fast at cards, or fast on sleep? it is the thing I did last. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117870" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117880">¶ Nay fast in fetters false varlet, according to thy deeds. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117890" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117900">¶ Master doctor there is no remedy, I must entreat you needs</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117910">Some other kind of punishment,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117920" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117930">¶ Nay by all halowes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117940"><pb facs="20"/>His punishment if I may judge, shall be naught else but the gallous. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117950" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117960">¶ That were to sore, a spiritual man to be so extreme. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117970" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e117980">¶ Is he worthy any better, sir how do ye judge and deem? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e117990" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118000">¶ I grant him worthy punishment, but in no wise so great. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118010" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118020">¶ It is a shame Ich tell you plain, for such false knaves entreat</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118030">He has almost undone us all, that is as tr●e as steel ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118040">And yet for all this great a do'cham never the near my needle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118050" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118060">¶ Canst thou not say any thing to that diccon, wish least or most ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118070" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118080">¶ Yea marry sir, thus much I can say well, the needle is lost. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118090" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118100">¶ Nay canst not thou tell which way, that needle may be found</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118110" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118120">¶ No by my fay sir. though I might have an hundred pound. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118130" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118140">¶ Thou liar lickdis●, didst not say the needle would be gitten? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118150" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118160">¶ No hodge, by the same token, you where that time be s●itten? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118170">For fear of hobgoblin, you wot well what I mean,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118180">As long as it is sense, I fear me yet ye be scarce clean. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118190" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118200">¶ Well master rat, you must both learn, and teach us to forgive</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118210">Since Diccon hath confession made, ● is so clean shreve,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118220">If ye to me consent, to amend this heavy chance. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118230">I will enjoin him here, some open kind of penance:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118240">Of this condition, where ye know my fee is twenty pence</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118250">For the bloodshed, I am agreed with you here to dispense,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118260">Ye shall go quite, so that ye grant, the matter now to run,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118270">To end with mirth among us all, even as it was begun. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118280" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118290">¶ Say yea master vicar, and he shall sure confess to be your dotter</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118300">And all we that be hear present, will love you much the better</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118310" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118320">¶ My part is the worst, but since you all here on agree. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118330">Go even to master baily ▪ let it be so for me,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118340" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118350">¶ How sayest thou diccon, art content this shall on me depend</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118360" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118370">¶ Go to m. baily say on your mind, I know ye are my friend ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118380" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118390">¶ Then mark ye well, to recompense this thy former action</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118400">Because thou hast offended all, to make them satisfaction,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118410">Before their faces, here kneel down, and as I shall the teach. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118420">For thou shalt take on oath, of Hodge's leather breach</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118430">First for master doctor, upon pain of his cuisse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118440">Where he will pay for all ▪ thou never draw thy pur●●e. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118450">And when ye meet at one pot, he shall have the first pull,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118460">And thou shalt never offer him the cup, but it be full. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118470">To good wife ch●t thou shalt be sworn, even on the same wise</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118480">If she refuse thy money once, never to offer it twice. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118490"><pb facs="20"/>Thou shalt be bound by the same here, as thou dost take it</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118500">When thou mayst drink of free cost, thou never forsake it:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118510">For gammer Gurton's sake, again sworn shalt thou be</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118520">To help her to her needle again if it do lie in thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118530">And likewise be bound: by the virtue of that</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118540">To be of good abering to Gib her great cat:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118550">Last of all for Hodge, the oath to scan,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118560">Thou shalt never take him, for fine gentleman. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118570" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118580">¶ Come on fellow Diccon chalbe even with thee now. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118590" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118600">¶ Thou wilt not stick to do this Diccon I trow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118610" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118620">¶ No by my father's skin, my hand down I lay it? </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118630">Lo●e as I have promised, I will not denay it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118640">But Hodge take good heed now, thou do not beshit me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118650">And gave him a good blow on the buttock. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118660" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118670">¶ Gog's heart thou false villain dost thou bite me●</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118680" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118690">¶ What Hodge doth he hurt the or ever he begin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118700" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118710">¶ He thrust me into the buttock, with a bodkin or a pin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118720">I say gammer, gammer? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118730" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118740">¶ How now Hodge, how now:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118750" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118760">¶ God's ma●t gammer gurton. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118770" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118780">¶ Thou art mad ich trow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118790" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118800">¶ Will you see the devil gammer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118810" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118820">¶ The devil son, god bless us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118830" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118840">¶ Chould iche were hanged gammer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118850" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118860">¶ Marry see ye might dress us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118870" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118880">¶ ● have it by the mass gammer</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118890" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118900">¶ What not my needle Hodge? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118910" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118920">¶ Your needle gammer, your needle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118930" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118940">¶ No fie, dost but dodge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118950" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118960">¶ Cha ●ound ●our neele gammer, here in my hand be it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118970" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e118980">¶ For all the loves on earth Hodge, let me see it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e118990" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Ho●ge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119000">¶ Soft gammer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119010" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119020">¶ Good Hodge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119030" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119040">¶ Soft Ich say, tarry a while. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119050" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119060">¶ Nay sweet Hodge say truth, and do not me beguile. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119070" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119080">¶ Cham sure on it ich warrant you: it goes no more a stray</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119090" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119100">¶ Hodge when I speak so fair: wilt still say me na●:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119110" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119120">¶ Go near the ●ight gammer this well in faith good luck:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119130">Chwas almost undone: 'twas so far in my buttock</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119140" who="A12969-gurton">
            <pb facs="21"/>
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119150">¶ 'tis min own dear needle Hodge, sickerly I wot</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119160" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119170">¶ Cham I not a good son gammer, cham I not,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119180" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gāmer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119190">¶ Christ's blessing light on thee, hast made me for ever</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119200" who="A12969-hodge">
            <speaker>Hodge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119210">¶ Ich knew that Ich must find it, else choud a had it never</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119220" who="A12969-chat">
            <speaker>Chat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119230">¶ By my troth go●●py gurton, I am even as glad</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119240">As though I mine own self as good a turn had:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119250" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119260">¶ And I by my conscience, to see it so come forth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119270">Rejoice so much at it, 〈◊〉 three needles be worth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119280" who="A12969-rat">
            <speaker>D. Rat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119290">¶ I am no whit sorry to see you so rejoice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119300" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119310">¶ Nor I much the gladder for all this noise:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119320">Yet say gramercy Diccon, for springing of the game. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119330" who="A12969-gurton">
            <speaker>Gammer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119340">¶ Gramercy Diccon twenty times, ● how glad cham,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119350">If that chould do so much, your masterdom to come hither,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119360">Master rat, good wife chat, and Diccon together:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119370">Cha but one half penny, as far as iche know it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119380">And Chil not rest this night, till ich bestow it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119390">If ever ye love me, let us go in and drink. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119400" who="A12969-baily">
            <speaker>Bayly.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119410">¶ I am content if the rest think as I think ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119420">Master rat it shall be best for you if we so do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119430">Then shall you warm you and dr●●se yourself too. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A12969-e119440" who="A12969-diccon">
            <speaker>Diccon</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119450">¶ Soft sirs, take us with you, the company shall be the more,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119460">As proud coms behind they say, as any goes before,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119470">But now my good masters since we must be gone</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119480">And leave you behind us, here all alone:</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119490">Since at our last ending, thus merry we be,</l>
            <l xml:id="A12969-e119500">For gammer Gurton's needle's sake, let us have a plaudyti●. </l>
          </sp>
          <closer xml:id="A12969-e119510">Finis, Gurton. Perused and allowed, etc.</closer>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A12969-e119520">
      <div type="colophon" xml:id="A12969-e119530">
        <p xml:id="A12969-e119540">Imprinted at London in Fleetstreet beneath the conduit, at the sign of s. John evangelist, by Thomas Colwell. 1575.</p>
        <pb facs="21"/>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A12969"><item xml:id="A12969-hodge" n="115">
    <seg type="character_name">A12969-hodge</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">115</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A12969-gurton" n="102">
    <seg type="character_name">A12969-gurton</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">102</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12969-diccon" n="101">
    <seg type="character_name">A12969-diccon</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">101</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12969-chat" n="66">
    <seg type="character_name">A12969-chat</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">66</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12969-baily" n="50">
    <seg type="character_name">A12969-baily</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">50</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12969-rat" n="43">
    <seg type="character_name">A12969-rat</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">43</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12969-tyb" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A12969-tyb</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12969-cock" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A12969-cock</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A12969-unassigned" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A12969-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

