<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A18416">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Masque of the Middle Temple and Lincoln's Inn <date type="creation_date">1613</date></title>
        <author>Chapman, George</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A18416.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The memorable maske of the two honorable houses or Innes of Court; the Middle Temple, and Lyncolns Inne. As it was performd before the King, at White-Hall on Shroue Munday at night; being the 15. of February. 1613. At the princely celebration of the most royall nuptialls of the Palsgraue, and his thrice gratious Princesse Elizabeth. &amp;c. With a description of their whole show; in the manner of their march on horse-backe to the Court from the Maister of the Rolls his house: with all their right noble consorts, and most showfull attendants. Inuented, and fashioned, with the ground, and speciall structure of the whole worke: by our kingdomes most artfull and ingenious architect Innigo Iones. Supplied, aplied, digested, and written, by Geo: Chapman.</title>
            <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>28 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99843391</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 4981.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 310(a).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">8121</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18416</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The memorable maske of the two honorable houses or Innes of Court; the Middle Temple, and Lyncolns Inne. As it was performd before the King, at White-Hall on Shroue Munday at night; being the 15. of February. 1613. At the princely celebration of the most royall nuptialls of the Palsgraue, and his thrice gratious Princesse Elizabeth. &amp;c. With a description of their whole show; in the manner of their march on horse-backe to the Court from the Maister of the Rolls his house: with all their right noble consorts, and most showfull attendants. Inuented, and fashioned, with the ground, and speciall structure of the whole worke: by our kingdomes most artfull and ingenious architect Innigo Iones. Supplied, aplied, digested, and written, by Geo: Chapman.</title>
            <title type="alt">Masque of the middle Temple, and Lincolns Inne.</title>
            <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
            <author>Jones, Inigo, 1573-1652.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[56] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by G. Eld, for George Norton, and are to be sould at his shoppe neere Temple-bar,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
            <date>[1613]</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Publication date from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: [par.]2 A4 a4 B-E4 F2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: The masque of the middle Temple, and Lincolns Inne.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Leaf a4r has errata. Variant: a4r lacks errata; the argument in a different setting.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Frederick, -- I, -- King of Bohemia, -- 1596-1632.</term>
          <term>Elizabeth, -- Queen, consort of Frederick I, King of Bohemia, -- 1596-1662.</term>
          <term>Masques.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A18416-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A18416-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A18416-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100040">The memorable mask of the two honourable houses or inns of court; the middle temple, and Lincoln's inn.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100050">As it was performed before the King, at white-hall on Shrove Monday at night; being the 15. of February. 1613.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100060">At the princely celebration of the most royal nuptials of the palgrave, and his thrice gracious Princess Elizabeth. Etc.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100070">With a description of their whole show; in the manner of their march on horseback to the court from the master of the rolls his house: with all their right noble consorts, and most showfull attendants. </p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100080">Invented, and fashioned, with the ground, and special structure of the whole work,</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100090">By our kingdoms most artful and ingenious architect Innigo Jones.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100100">Supplied, applied, digested, and written, by Geo: Chapman. </p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100110">At London, printed by G. eld, for George Norton and are to be sold at his shop near Temple-bar.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A18416-e100120">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To the most noble, and constant combiner of honour, and virtue, sir Edward Philips, knight, Mr. of the rolls.</head>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100130">This noble and magnificent performance, renewing the ancient spirit, and honour of the inns of court; being especially furthered and followed by your most laborious and honoured endeavours, (For his majesty's service; and honour of the all-grace-deserving nuptials, of the thrice gracious Princess Elizabeth, his highness' daughter) deserves especially to be in this sort consecrate, to your worthy memory and honour. Honour, having never her fair hand more freely and nobly given to riches (Being a fit particle of this invention) then by yours, at this nuptial solemnity. To which assisted, and<pb facs="3"/> memorable ceremony; the joined hand and industry, of the worthily honoured knight, sir H. Hubberd, his majesty's attorney general, deserving, in good part, a joint memory with yours; I have submitted it freely to his noble acceptance. The poor pains I added to this royal service, being wholly chosen, and commanded by your most constant, and free favour; I hope will now appear nothing neglective of their expected duties. Hearty will, and care enough, I am assured was employed in me; and the only ingenuous will, being first and principal step to virtue; I beseech you let it stand for the performing virtue itself. In which addition of your ever-honoured favours, you shall ever bind all my future service to your most wished commandment.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100140">God send you long health, and your virtues will endue you with honour enough,</p>
        <closer xml:id="A18416-e100150">
          <signed xml:id="A18416-e100160">By your free merits ever vowed honourer, and most unfeignedly affectionate observant. Geo. Chapman.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="text" xml:id="A18416-e100170">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>The mask of the gentlemen of the two combined houses, or inns of court, the Middle-temple, and Lincoln's inn.</head>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100180">At the house of the most worthely honoured preferrer and gracer of all honourable actions, and virtues, (Sir Edward Philip's knight, master of the rolls) all the performers and their assistants made their rendezvous , prepared to their performance, and thus set forth.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100190">Fifty gentlemen, richly attired, and as gallantly mounted, with footmen particularly attending, made the noble vanguard of these nuptial forces. Next (A fit distance observed between them) marched a mock-mask<pb facs="4"/> of baboons, attired like fantastical travellers, in Neapolitan suits, and great ruffs, all horsed with asses; and dwarf palfreys, with yellow foot-cloths, and casting cockle-demois about, in courtesy, by way of largesse; torches borne on either hand of them; lighting their state as ridiculously, as the rest nobly. After them were sorted two cars triumphal, adorned with great mask heads, festoons, scrolls, and antic leaves, every part enriched with silver and gold. These were through-varied with different invention, and in them advanced, the choice musicians of our kingdom, six in each; attired like Virginian priests, by whom the sun is there adored; and therefore called the Phoebades. Their robes were tucked up before; strange hoods of feathers, and scallops about their necks, and on their heads turbans, stuck with several coloured feathers, spotted with wings of flies, of extraordinary bigness; like those of their country: and about them marched two ranks of torches. Then road the chief maskers, in Indian<pb facs="4"/> habits, all of a resemblance: the ground cloth of silver, richly embroidered, with golden suns, and about every sun, ran a trail of gold, imitating indian work,: their bases of the same stuff and work, but betwixt every pane of embroidery, went a row of white ostrich feathers, mingled with sprigs of gold plate; under their breasts, they wore baldrics of gold, embroidered high with pearl, and about their necks, ruffs of feathers, spangled with pearl and silver. On their heads high sprigged-feathers, compassed in coronets, like the Virginian princes they presented. Betwixt every set of feathers, and about their brows, in the underpart of their coronets, shined suns of gold plate, sprinkled with pearl; from whence sprung rays of the like plate, that mixing with the motion of the feathers, showed exceedingly delightful, and gracious. Their legs were adorned, with close long white silk-stockings: curiously embroidered with gold to the middelegge.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100200"><pb facs="5"/>And over these (Being on horse back) they drew greaves or buskins embroidered with gold, and interlaced with rues of feathers; altogether estrangfull, and Indian like.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100210">In their hands (Set in several postures as they road) they brandished cane darts of the finest gold. Their vizerds of olive colour; but pleasingly visaged: their hair, black and large, waving down to their shoulders.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100220">Their horse, for rich show, equalled the maskers themselves; all their caparisons being enchased with suns of gold and ornamental jewels. To every one of which, was tacked a scarffing of silver; that ran sinously in works over the whole caparison, even to the daseling of the admiring spectators.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100230">Their heads, no less gracefully and properly decked with the like light scarfing that hung about their ears wantonly dangling.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100240">Every one of these horse, had two Moors, attired like Indian slaves, that for state sided them; with swelling wreaths of gold, and watshed on their heads, which arose in all to<pb facs="5"/> the number of a hundred.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100250">The torch-bearers habits were likewise of the Indian garb, but more stravagant than those of the maskers; all showfully garnished with several-hewed feathers. The humble variety whereof, stuck off the more amply, the maskers high beauties, shining in the habits of themselves; and reflected in their kind, a new and delightfully-varied radiance on the beholders.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100260">All these sustaind torches of virgin wax, whose staves were great canes all over gilded; and these (As the rest) had every man his Moor, attending his horse.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100270">The maskers, riding single; had every masker, his torchbearer mounted before him.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100280">The last chariot, which was most of all adorned; had his whole frame filled with moulded work; mixed all with paintings, and glittering scarffings of silver; over which was cast a canopy of gold, borne up with antic figures, and all composed a la Grotesea. Before this in the seat of it, as the charioteer;<pb facs="6"/> was advanced a strange person, and as strangely habited, half French, half Swiss; his name capriccio; wearing on his head a pair of golden bellows, a guilt spur in one hand, and with the other managing the reigns of the four horses that drew it:</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100290">On a seat of the same chariot, a little more elevate, sat Eunomia, the virgin priest of the goddess honour, together with Phemis, her herald: the habit of her priest, was a robe of white silk, gathered about the neck; a pentacle of silvered stuff about her shoulders, hanging foldedly down, both before and behind.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100300">A vestal veil on her head of Tiffany, stripped with silver, hanging with a train, to the earth.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100310">The herald was attired in an antique cuirass of silver stuff, with labels at the wings and bases; a short gown of gold stuff; with wide sleeves, cut in panes: a wreath of gold on his head, and a rod of gold in his hand.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100320"><pb facs="6"/>Highest of all in the most eminent seat of the triumphal sat, side to side, the celestial goddess, honour; and the earthy deity, Plutus; or riches. His attire; a short robe of gold, fringed; his wide sleeves turned up, and out-showed his naked arms: his head and beard sprinkled with showers of gold: his buskins, clinckant, as his other attire. The ornaments of honour were these: a rich full robe of blue silk girt about her, a mantle of silver worn overthwart, full gathered, and descending in folds behind: a veil of netlawn, embroidered with Oos and spangled; her tresses in tucks, braided with silver: the hinder part shadowing in waves her shoulders.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100330">These, thus particularly, and with propriety adorned, were strongly attended with a full guard of two hundred halberdiers: two marshals (Being choice gentlemen, of either house) commander-like attired, to and fro coursing, to keep all in their orders.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100340"><pb facs="7"/>A show at all parts so novel, conceitful and glorious, as hath not in this land, (To the proper use and object it had purposed) been ever before beheld. Nor did those honourable inns of court, at any time in that kind, such acceptable service to the sacred majesty of this kingdom, nor were returned by many degrees, with so thrice gracious, and royal entertainment and honour. But, (As above said) all these so marching to the court at white hall, the King, bride, and bridegroom, with all the lords of the most honoured privy council, and our chief nobility, stood in the gallery before the tiltyard, to behold their arrival; who, for the more full satisfaction of his majesty's view, made one turn about the yard, and dismounted: being then honourably attended through the gallery to a chamber appointed, where they were to make ready for their performance in the hall, etc.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100350">The King being come forth, the maskers ascended unseen to their scene. Then for the works.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100360">First there appeared at the lower end of the<pb facs="7"/> hall, an artificial rock, whose top was near as high as the hall itself. This rock, was in the undermost part craggy, and full of hollow places, in whose concaves were contrived, two winding pair of stairs, by whose greeces the persons above might make their descents, and all the way be seen: all this rock grew by degrees up into a gold-colour; and was run quite through, with veins of gold: on the one side whereof, eminently raised on a fair hill, was erected a silver temple of an octangle figure, whose pillars were of a composed order, and bore up an architrave, frieze, and Cornish: over which stood a continued plinth; whereon were advanced statues of silver: above this, was placed a bastard order of architecture, wherein were carved compartements: in one of which was written in great gold capitals, honoris Fanum: above all, was a Coupolo, or type, which seemed to be scaled with silver plates.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100370">For finishing, of all, upon a pedestal, was fixed a round stone of silver, from which grew a pair of golden wings, both feigned to be<pb facs="8"/> fortunes: the round stone (When her feet trod it) ever affirmed to be rolling; figuring her inconstancy: the golden wings, denoting those nimble powers, that pompously bear her about the world; on that temple (Erected to her daughter, honour; and figuring this kingdom) put off by her, and fixed, for assured sign she would never forsake it.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100380">About this temple, hung festoons wreathed with silver from one pillars head to another. Besides, the frieze was enriched with keruings, all showing greatness and magnificence.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100390">On the other side of the rock, grew a grove, in whose utmost part appeared a vast, withered, and hollow tree, being the bare receptacle of the baboonery.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100400">These following should in duty have had their proper places, after every fitted speech of the actors; but being prevented by the unexpected haste of the printer, which he never let me know, and never sending me a proof, till he had passed those speeches; I had no reason to imagine he could have been so forward. His fault is therefore to be supplied by the observation,<pb facs="8"/> and reference of the reader, who will easily perceive, where they were to be inserted.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100410">After the speech of Plutus (Who as you may see after, first entered) the middle part of the rock began to move, and being come some five paces up towards the King, it split in pieces with a great crack; and our brake capriccio, as before described. The pieces of the rock vanished and he spoke as in his place.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100420">At the singing of the first song, full, which was sung by the Virginian priests; called the Phoebades, to six lutes (Being used as an Orphean virtue, for the state of the mines opening): the upper part of the rock was suddenly turned to a cloud, discovering a rich and refulgent mine of gold; in which the twelve maskers were triumphantly seated: their torch-bearers attending before them. All the lights being so ordered, that though none were seen, yet had their lustre such virtue, that by it, the least spangle or spark of the maskers rich habits, might with ease and clearness be discerned as far off as the seat.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100430"><pb facs="9"/>Over this golden mine, in an evening sky, the ruddy sun was seen ready to be set; and behind the tops of certain white cliffs, by degrees descended, casting up a bank of clouds; in which, a while he was hidden: but then gloriously shining, gave that usually-observed good omen, of succeeding fair weather.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100440">Before he was fully set, the Phoebades (Showing the custom of the Indians to adore the sun setting) began their observance with the song, to whose place, we must refer you for the manner and words; all the time they were singing; the torch-bearers holding up their torches to the sun; to whom the priests themselves, and the rest, did as they sung obeisance: which was answered by other music and voices, at the commandment of honour, with all observances used to the King etc. As in the following places.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100450"><pb facs="9"/>To answer certain insolent objections made against the length of my speeches, and narrations; being (For the probability of all accidents, rising from the invention of this mask; and their application, to the persons, and places: for whom, and by whom it was presented) not convenient, but necessary; I am enforced to affirm this; that: as there is no poem nor oration so general; but hath his one particular proposition; nor no river so extravagantly ample, but hath his never-so-narrow fountain, worthy to be named; so all these courtly, and honouring inventions (Having poesy, and oration in them, and a fountain, to be expressed, from whence their rivers flow) should expressively-arise; out of the places, and persons for; and by whom they are presented; without which limits, they are luxurious, and pain. But what rules soever are set down, to any art, or act (Though, without their observation; no art, nor act, is true, and worthy) yet are they nothing the more followed; or those few that follow them credited. Every vulgarly-esteemed upstart; dares break the dreadful dignity of ancient and authentical poesy: and presume luciforously, to proclaim in place thereof, repugnant precepts of their own spawn. Truth, and worth, have no faces, to enamour the licentious, but vainglory, and humour. The same body: the same beauty, a thousand men seeing: only the man whose blood is fitted, hath that which he calls his soul, enamoured. And this, out of infallible cause; for, men understand not these of Maenander — est morbus<pb facs="10"/> oportunitas</p>
        <quote xml:id="A18416-e100460">Animae, quodictus, vulnus accipit grave.</quote>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100470">But the cause of all men's being enamoured with truth. And of her slight respect, in others; is the divine freedom; one touching with his aprehensive finger, the other, passing. The hill of the Muses (Which all men must climb in the regular way, to truth) is said of old, to be forked. And the two points of it, parting at the top; are insania, and, divinus furor. Insania, is that which every rank-brained writer; and judge of poetical writing, is rapt withal; when he presumes either to write or censure the height of poesy; and that transports him with humour, vainglory and pride, most profane and sacrilegious: when divinus furor; makes gentle, and noble, the never so truly inspired writer —</p>
        <quote xml:id="A18416-e100480">Emollit mores nec sinit esse feros.</quote>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100490">And the mild beams of the most holy inflamer; easily, and sweetly enter, with all understanding sharpness, the soft, and sincerely humane; but with no time; no study; no means under heaven: any arrogant, all-occupation devourer (That will chandler-like set up with all wares; selling, poesy's nectar and ambrosia; as well as mustered, and vinegar.) The chaste and restrained beams of humble truth will ever enter; but only graze, and glance at them: and the further fly them.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="argument" xml:id="A18416-e100500">
        <pb facs="10"/>
        <head>The applicable argument of the mask.</head>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100510">Honour, is so much respected, and adored; that she hath a temple erected to her, like a goddess; a virgin priest consecrated to her (Which is Eunomia, or law; since none should dare access to honour, but by virtue; of which law being the rule, must needs be a chief) and a herald (Called Phemis, or fame) to proclaim her institutions, and commandments. To amplify yet more the divine graces of this goddess; Plutus, (Or riches) being by Aristophanes, Lucian. Etc. presented naturally blind, deformed, and dull witted; is here by his love of honour, made see, made sightly, made ingenious; made liberal: and all this converted and consecrate to the most worthy celebration of these sacred nuptials; all issuing (To conclude the necessary application) from an honourable temple. Etc. <quote xml:id="A18416-e100520"><l xml:id="A18416-e100530">Non est certa fides, quam non iniuria versat. </l><l xml:id="A18416-e100540">— fallit portus et ipse fidem. </l></quote></p>
      </div>
      <div type="errata" xml:id="A18416-e100550">
        <head>Errata.</head>
        <p xml:id="A18416-e100560">In Capri. first speech, for many ▪ read main, in c. 1. for pot, re. post. in c. 3. for answer, re. austerity, for purposes, re. purses, in c. 3. for seemingly, re. securely, in d. 2. for law, and virtue, re. love and beauty, in the first stance of the second song, for this re. his. for sweet devotions, re. fit devotions.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A18416-e100570">
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A18416-e100580">
        <pb facs="11"/>
        <pb facs="11"/>
        <head>The names of the speakers.</head>
        <list xml:id="A18416-e100590">
          <item xml:id="A18416-e100600">Honour, a goddess.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18416-e100610">Plutus, (Or riches) a God.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18416-e100620">Eunomia (Or law) priest of honour.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18416-e100630">Phemis, honour's herald.</item>
          <item xml:id="A18416-e100640">Capriccio, a man of wit, etc.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="play" xml:id="A18416-e100650">
        <head>The presentment.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e100660">Plutus appeared surveying the work with this speech.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100670" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plutus.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100680">Rocks? Nothing but rocks in these masking devices? Is invention so poor she must needs ever dwell amongst rocks? But it may worthily have chanced (Being so often<pb facs="12"/> presented) that their vain custom is now become the necessary hand of heaven, transforming into rocks, some stony hearted ladies, courted in former masks; for whose loves, some of their repulst servants have perished: or perhaps some of my flinty-hearted usurers have been here metamorphosed; betwixt whom and ladies, there is resemblance enough: ladies using to take interest, besides their principal, as much as usurers. See, it is so; and now is the time of restoring them to their natural shapes: it moves, opens, excellent! This metamorphosis I intend to overhear.</p>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="12"/>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e100690">A rock, moving and breaking with a crack about capriccio, he enters with a pair of bellows on his head, a spur in one hand, and a piece of gold o'er in the other, etc.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e100700">He speaks, ut sequitur.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100710" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capriccio.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100720">How hard this world is to a man of wit? he must eat through many rocks for his food, or fast; a restless and tormenting stone, his wit is to him: the very stone of Sisyphus in hell; nay, the philosopher's stone, makes not a man more wretched: a man must be a second Proteus, and turn himself into all shapes (Like Ulysses) to wind through the straits of this pinching vale of misery; I have turned myself into a tailor, a man, a gentleman, a nobleman, a worthy man; but had never the wit to turn myself into an alderman. There are many shapes to perish in, but one to live in, and that's an alderman's:<pb facs="13"/> 'tis not for a man of wit to take any rich figure upon him: your bold, proud, ignorant, that's brave and clinkant, that finds crowns put into his shoes every morning by the fairies and will never tell; whose wit is humour, whose judgement is fashion, whose pride is emptiness, birth his full man, that is in all things something, in sum total, nothing. He shall live in the land of Spruce, milk and honey flowing into his mouth sleeping.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100730" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plutus.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100740">This is no transformation, but an intrusion into my golden mines: I will hear him-further.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100750" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capric.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100760">This breach of rocks I have made, in needy pursuit of the blind deity, riches: who is miraculously arrived here. For (According to our rare men of wit) heaven standing, and earth moving, her motion (Being circular) hath brought one of the most remote<pb facs="13"/> parts of the world, to touch at this all-exceeding island: which a man of wit would imagine must needs move circularly with the rest of the world, and so ever maintain an equal distance. But, poets (Our chief men of wit) answer that point directly; most ingeniously affirming: that this I'll is (For the excellency of it) divided from the world (Divisus ab orbe Britannus) and that though the whole world besides moves; yet this I'll stands fixed on her own feet, and defies the world's mutability, which this rare accident of the arrival of riches, in one of his furthest-off-situate dominions, most demonstratively proves.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100770" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plutus.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100780">This is a man of wit indeed, and knows of all our arrivals.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100790" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capric.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100800">With this dull deity riches, a rich island lying in the South-sea, called Poeana, (Of the paeans (Or songs) sung to the sun, whom they<pb facs="14"/> there adore (Being for strength and riches, called the navel of that South-sea) is by earth's round motion moved near this Briton shore. In which island (Being yet in command of the Virginian continent.) A troop of the noblest Virginians inhabiting; attended hither the god of riches, all triumphantly shining in a mine of gold. For hearing of the most royal solemnity, of these sacred nuptials; they crossed the ocean in their honour, and are here arrived. A poor snatch at some of the golden ore, that the feet of riches have turned up as he trod here, my poor hand hath purchased; and hope the remainder of a greater work, will be shortly extant.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100810" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100820">You sir, that are miching about my golden mines here.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100830" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100840">What, can you see sir? you have heretofore been presented blind: like your mother<pb facs="14"/> fortune; and your brother love.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100850" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100860">But now sir, you see I see.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100870" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100880">By what good means, I beseech you sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100890" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100900">That means, I may vouchsafe you hereafter; mean space, what are you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100910" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100920">I am sir a kind of man; a man of wit: with whom your worship has nothing to do I think.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100930" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100940">No sir, nor will have any thing to do with him: a man of wit? what's that? A beggar.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100950" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100960">And yet no devil sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100970" who="A18416-plutus">
          <pb facs="15"/>
          <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e100980">As I am, you mean.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e100990" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101000">Indeed sir your kingdom is under the earth.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101010" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101020">That's true; for riches is the Atlas that holds it up, it would sink else.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101030" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101040">'Tis rather a wonder, it sinks not with you sir, you're so sinfully, and damnably heavy.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101050" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101060">Sinful? and damnable? what a Puritan? These bellows you wear on your head, show with what matter your brain is puffed up sir: a religion-forger I see you are, and presume of inspiration from these bellows; with which ye study to blow up the settled governments of kingdoms.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101070" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <pb facs="15"/>
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101080">Your worship knocks at a wrong door sir, I dwell far from the person you speak of.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101090" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101100">What may you be then, being a man of wit? A buffoon, a jester. Before I would take upon me the title of a man of wit, and be baffled by every man of wisdom for a buffoon; I would turn bankrupt, or let up a tobacco shop, change cloaks with an alchemist, or serve an usurer, be a watering pot for every groom; stand the push of every rascal wit; enter lifts of jests with trencher-fools, and be fooled down by them, or (Which is worse) put them down in fooling: are these the qualities a man of wit should run proud of?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101110" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101120">Your worship I see has obtained wit, with sight, which I hope yet my poor wit will well be able to answer; for touching my jesting, I<pb facs="16"/> have heard of some courtiers, that have run themselves out of their states with justing; and why may not I then raise myself in the state with jesting? An honest shoemaker, (In in a liberal King's time) was knighted for making a clean boot, and is it impossible, that I for breaking a clean jest, should be advanced in court, or counsel? or at least, served out for an ambassador to a dull climate? Jests, and merriments are but wild weeds in a rank soil, which being well manured, yield the wholesome crop of wisdom and discretion at time ath' year.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101130" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plu.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101140">Nay, nay, I commend thy judgement for cutting thy coat so just to the breadth of thy shoulders; he that cannot be a courser in the field, let him learn to play the jackanapes in the chamber, he that cannot personate the wiseman well amongst wizards, let him learn to play the fool well amongst dizzards.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101150" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <pb facs="16"/>
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101160">'Tis passing miraculous, that your dull and blind worship should so suddenly turn both sightful, and witful.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101170" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101180">The riddle of that miracle, I may chance dissolve to you in sequel; mean time, what name sustainest thou? and what toys are these thou bearest so fantastically about thee?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101190" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101200">These, toys sir, are the ensigns that discover my name and quality: my name being capriccio, and I wear these bellows on my head, to show I can puss up with glory all those that affect me: and besides, bear this spur, to show I can spur gall, even the best that contemn me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101210" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101220">A dangerous fellow, but what makest thou (Poor man of wit) at these pompous nuptials;</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101230" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <pb facs="17"/>
          <speaker>Capric.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101240">Sir, I come hither with a charge; to do these nuptials, I hope, very acceptable service; and my charge is; a company of accomplished travellers; that are excellent at antimasques; and will tender a taste of their quality, if your worship please.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101250" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101260">Excellent well pleased; of what virtue are they besides.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101270" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101280">Passing grave sir, yet exceeding acute: witty, yet not ridiculous; never laugh at their own jests: laborious yet not base, having cut out the skirts of the whole world, in amorous quest of your gold and silver.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101290" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101300">They shall have enough; call them: I beseech thee call them: how far hence abide they?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101310" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <pb facs="17"/>
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101320">Sir (Being by another eminent quality the admired soldiers of the world) in contempt of softness, and delicacy, they lie on the naturally hard boards of that naked tree; and will your worship assure them rewards fit for persons of their freight.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101330" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101340">Dost thou doubt my reward being pleased?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101350" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101360">I know sir, a man may sooner win your reward, for pleasing you, than deserving you. But you great wise persons, have a fetch of state; to employ with countenance, and encouragement, but reward with answer and disgrace, save your purposes, and lose your honours.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101370" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101380">To assure thee of reward, I will now satisfy<pb facs="18"/> thee touching the miraculous cause, both of my sight and wit, and which consequently moves me to humanity, and bounty; and all is, only this; my late being in love, with the lovely goddess honour.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101390" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capric.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101400">If your worship love honour, indeed, sir you must needs be bountiful. But where is the rare goddess you speak of to be seen?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101410" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plutus.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101420">In that rich temple, where fortune fixed those her golden wings, thou seest; and that rolling stone she used to tread upon, for sign she would never forsake this kingdom; there is adored, the worthy goddess honour. The sweetness of whose voice, when I first heard her persuasions, both to myself, and the Virginian princes arrived here, to do honour and homage, to these heavenly nuptials, so most powerfully enamoured me, that the fire of my love flew up to the sight<pb facs="18"/> of mine eyes: that have lighted within me a whole firmament of bounty, which may semingly assure thee, thy reward is certain: and therefore call thy accomplished company to their anti-masque.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101430" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capric.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101440">See sir, the time, set for their appearance, being expired; they appear to their service of themselves.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e101450">Enter the baboons after whose dance, being antic, and delightful, they returned to their tree, when Plutus spoke to Capriccius.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101460" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plutus.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101470">Gramercy now capriccio, take thy men of compliment, and travail with them to other marriages. My riches to thy wit; they will get something somewhere.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101480" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101490">What's this?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101500" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101510">A strain of wit beyond a man of wit. I have employed you, and the grace of that, is reward enough; hence; pack, with your complemental fardel: the sight of an attendant for reward, is abominable in the eyes of a turn-served politician, and I fear, will strike me blind again. I can not abide these bellows of thy head, they and thy men of wit have melted my mines with them, and consumed me, yet take thy life and be gone. Neptune let thy predecessor, Ulysses, live after all his slain companions, but to make him die more miserably living; gave him up to ship wracks, enchantments; men of wit are but enchanted, there is no such thing as wit in this world. So, take a tree, enure thy soldiers to hardness, 'tis honourable, though not clinkant.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101520" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101530">Can this be possible?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101540" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101550">Alas! poor man of wit, how want of reward daunts thy virtue? But because I must send none away discontented, from these all-pleasing nuptials; take this wedge of gold, and wedge thyself into the world with it, renouncing that loose wit of thine, 'twill spoil thy complexion.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101560" who="A18416-capriccio">
          <speaker>Capr.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A18416-e101570">Honour, and all Argus eyes, to earth's all-commanding riches. Pluto etiam cedit Jupiter</p>
          <stage xml:id="A18416-e101580">Exit capr.</stage>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="20"/>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e101590">After this low induction, by these succeeding degrees, the chief maskers were advanced to their discovery</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101600" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plutus.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101610">These humble objects can no high eyes draw,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A18416-e101620">Plutus, calls to Eunomia.</note></l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101630">Eunomia? (Or the sacred power of law)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101640">Daughter of Jove, and goddess honour's priest;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101650">Appear to Plutus, and his love assist. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101660" who="A18416-eun">
          <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101670">What would the god of riches? <note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A18416-e101680">Eunomia in the temple gates.</note></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101690" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101700">Join with honour:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101710">In purposed grace of these great nuptials;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101720">And since to honour none should dare access,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101730">But helped by virtue's hand (Thy self, chaste love</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101740">Being virtues rule, and her directful light)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101750">Help me to th'honour of her speech and sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101760" who="A18416-eun">
          <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101770">Thy will shall straight be honoured; all that seek</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101780">Access to honour, by clear virtues beam,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101790">Her grace prevents their pains, and comes to them. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="20"/>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e101800">Loud music, and honour appears, descending with her herald Phemis, and Eunomia (Her priest) before her. The music ceasing Plutus spoke.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101810" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101820">Crown of all merit, goddess, and my love;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101830">'Tis now high time, that th'end for which we come</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101840">Should be endeavoured in our utmost right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101850">Done to the sweetness of this nuptial night. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101860" who="A18416-honour">
          <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101870">Plutus? The princes of the virgin land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101880">Whom I made cross the Britan ocean</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101890">To this most famed I'll, of all the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101900">To do due homage to the sacred nuptials</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101910">Of law, and virtue, celebrated here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101920">By this hour of the holy even I know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101930">Are ready to perform the rites they owe</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101940">To setting Phoebus; which (For greater state</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101950">To their appearance) their first act advances. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101960">And with songs ushers their succeeding dances,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101970">Herald! give summons to the virgin knights,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e101980">No longer to delay their purposed rites. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e101990" who="A18416-herald">
          <speaker>Her.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102000">Knights of the virgin land, whom beauties lights</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102010">Would glorify with their inflaming sights;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102020">Keep now obscured no more your fair intent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102030"><pb facs="21"/> to add your beams to this night's ornament,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102040">The golden-winged hour strikes now a plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102050">And calls out all the pomp ye entertain;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102060">The princely bridegroom, and the bride's bright eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102070">Sparkle with grace to your discoveries. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e102080">At these words, the Phoebades (Or priests of the sun) appeared first with six lutes, and six voices, and sung to the opening of the mine and maskers discovery, this sul song.</stage>
        <floatingText xml:id="A18416-e102090">
          <body xml:id="A18416-e102100">
            <div type="song" xml:id="A18416-e102110">
              <head>The first song.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e102120">Ope earth thy womb of gold,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e102130">Show heaven thy cope of stars. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e102140">All glad aspects unfold,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e102150">Shine out, and clear our cares:</l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e102160">Kiss heaven and earth, and so combine</l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e102170">In all mixed joy our nuptial twine. </l>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e102180">This song ended, a mount opened, and spread like a sky, in which appeared a sun setting; beneath which, sat the twelve maskers, in a mine of gold; twelve torch-bearers holding their torches before them, after which honour, etc. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e102190" who="A18416-honour">
          <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102200">See now the setting sun, casts up his bank,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102210">And shows his bright head at his seas repair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102220">For sign that all days future shall be fair. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e102230" who="A18416-plutus">
          <pb facs="21"/>
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102240">May he that rules the nights and days confirm it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e102250" who="A18416-honour">
          <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102260">Behold the sun's fair priests the Phaebades,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102270">Their evening service in an hymn address</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102280">To Phoebus setting; which we now shall hear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102290">And see the forms of their devotions there. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e102300">The phoehades sing the first stance of the second song, ut sequitur.</stage>
        <lg xml:id="A18416-e102310">
          <head>One alone 1.</head>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102320">Descend (Fair sun) and sweetly rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102330">In Tethis crystal arms, thy toil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102340">Fall burning on her marble breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102350">And make with love her billows boil. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A18416-e102360">
          <head>Another alone. 2.</head>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102370">Blow blow, sweet winds, oh blow away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102380">All vapours from the fined air:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102390">That to this golden head no ray,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102400">May languish with the least impair. </l>
        </lg>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e102410" who="A18416-chorus">
          <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102420">Dance Tethis, and thy love's red beams,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102430">Embrace with joy he now descends:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102440"><pb facs="22"/> burns burns with love to drink thy streams,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102450">And on him endless youth attends. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e102460">After this stance, honour etc.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e102470" who="A18416-honour">
          <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102480">This superstitious hymn, sung to the sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102490">Let us encounter with fit duties done</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102500">To our clear Phoebus; whose true piety,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102510">Enjoys from heaven an earthly deity. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e102520">Other music, and voices; and this second stance was sung, directing their observance to the King.</stage>
        <lg xml:id="A18416-e102530">
          <head>One alone 1.</head>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102540">Rise, rise oh Phoebus, ever rise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102550">Descend not to th'inconstant stream,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102560">But grace with endless light, our skies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102570">To thee that sun is but a beam. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A18416-e102580">
          <head>Another 2.</head>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102590">Dance ladies in our sun's bright rays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102600">In which the bride and bridegroom shine:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102610">Clear sable night with your eyes days,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102620">And set firm lights on Hymen's shrine. </l>
        </lg>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e102630" who="A18416-chorus">
          <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102640">O may our sun not set before,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102650">He sees his endless seed arise:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102660">And deck his triple crowned shore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102670">With springs of humane deities. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e102680"><pb facs="22"/>This ended the Phoebades sung the third stance.</stage>
        <lg n="1" xml:id="A18416-e102690">
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102700">1. Set set (Great sun) our rising love</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102710">Shall ever celebrate thy grace:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102720">Whom entering the high court of Jove,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102730">Each God greets rising from his place. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg n="2" xml:id="A18416-e102740">
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102750">2. When thou thy silver bow dost bend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102760">All start aside and dread thy draughts:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102770">How can we thee enough commend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102780">Commanding all worlds with the shafts? </l>
        </lg>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e102790" who="A18416-chorus">
          <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102800">Blessed was thy mother bearing thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102810">And Phoebe that delights in darts:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102820">Thou artful songs dost set; and she</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102830">Winds horns, loves hounds, and high palmed hearts</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e102840">After this honour.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e102850" who="A18416-honour">
          <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102860">Again our music and conclude this song,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102870">To him, to whom all Phoebus beams belong:</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e102880">The other voices sung to other music the third stance. </stage>
        <lg n="1" xml:id="A18416-e102890">
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102900">1 rise still (Clear sun) and never set,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102910">But be to earth her only light:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102920">All other Kings in thy beams met,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102930">Are clouds and dark effects of night. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg n="2" xml:id="A18416-e102940">
          <pb facs="23"/>
          <head>2.</head>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102950">As when the rosy morn doth rise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102960">Like mists, all give thy wisdom way;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102970">A learned King, is, as in skies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e102980">To poor dim stars, the flaming day ▪</l>
        </lg>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e102990" who="A18416-chorus">
          <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103000">Blessed was thy mother, bearing thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103010">Thee only relic of her race,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103020">Made by thy virtue's beams a tree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103030">Whose arms shall all the earth embrace. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e103040">This done Eunomia spoke to the maskers set yet above.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e103050" who="A18416-eun">
          <speaker>Eun.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103060">Virginian princes, ye must now renounce</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103070">Your superstitious worship of these suns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103080">Subject to cloudy darknings and descents,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103090">And of your sweet devotions, turn the events</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103100">To this our britain Phoebus, whose bright sky</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103110">(Enlightened with a Christian piety)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103120">Is never subject to black errors night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103130">And hath already offered heavens true light,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103140">To your dark region, which acknowledge now;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103150">Descend, and to him all your homage vow. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A18416-e103160"><pb facs="23"/>With this the torch-bearers descended, and performed another antemaske, dancing with torches lighted at both ends; which done, the maskers descended, and fell into their dances, two of which being passed, and others with the ladies.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A18416-e103170">Honour spoke.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103180">Musiquely our voices, now tune sweet and high,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103190">And sing the nuptial hymn of love,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A18416-e103200">the bride and bride groom were figured in love and beauty.</note> and beauty. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103210">Twins, as of one age, so to one desire</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103220">May both their bloods give, an unparted fire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103230">And as those twins that fame gives all her prize,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103240">Combined their life's power in such symphathies;<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A18416-e103250">twins of which Hippocrates speaks.</note></l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103260">That one being merry; mirth the other graced:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103270">If one felt sorrow, th' other grief embraced. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103280">If one were healthful; health the other pleased:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103290">If one were sick: the other was diseased;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103300">And all ways joined in such a constant troth</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103310">That one like cause had like effect in both,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103320">So may these nuptial twins,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A18416-e103330">called Twynns being both of an age.</note> their whole lives store,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103340">Spend in such even parts, never grieving more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103350">Then may the more set off their joys divine;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103360">As after clouds, the sun, doth clearest shine. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="24"/>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e103370">This said, this song of love, and Bewty was sung; single.</stage>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e103380">Bright Panthaea born to pan,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e103390">Of the noblest race of man,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e103400">Her white hand to Erisychthon giving,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e103410">With a kiss, joined heaven to earth</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e103420">And begotten so fair a birth,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e103430">As yet never graced the living. </l>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e103440" who="A18416-chorus">
          <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A18416-e103450">
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103460">A twin that all worlds did adorn,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103470">For so were love and beauty born. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="1" xml:id="A18416-e103480">
            <head>2.</head>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103490">Both so loved, they did contend</l>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103500">Which the other should transcend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103510">Doing either, grace, and kindness;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103520">Love from beauty did remove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103530">Lightness called her stain in love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103540">Beauty took from love his blindness. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e103550" who="A18416-chorus">
          <pb facs="24"/>
          <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A18416-e103560">
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103570">Love's sparks made flames in beauties sky,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103580">And beauty blew up love as high. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg n="2" xml:id="A18416-e103590">
            <head>3</head>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103600">Virtue then commixed her fire;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103610">To which bounty did aspire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103620">Innocence a crown conferring;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103630">Mine, and thine, were then unused,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103640">All things common: naught abused,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18416-e103650">Freely earth her fruitage bearing. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e103660" who="A18416-chorus">
          <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103670">Naught then was cared for, that could fade,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103680">And thus the golden world was made. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e103690">This sung, the maskers danced again with the ladies, after which honour. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e103700" who="A18416-honour">
          <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103710">Now may the blessings of the golden age,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103720">Swim in these nuptials, even to holy rage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103730">A hymn to sleep prefer, and all the joys</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103740">That in his empire are of dearest choice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103750"><pb facs="25"/> betwixt his golden slumbers ever flow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103760">In these; and theirs, in springs as endless grow. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e103770">This said, the last song was sung full.</stage>
        <floatingText xml:id="A18416-e103780">
          <body xml:id="A18416-e103790">
            <div type="song" xml:id="A18416-e103800">
              <head>The last song.</head>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e103810">Now sleep, bind fast, the flood of air,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e103820">Strike all things dumb and deaf,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e103830">And, to disturb our nuptial pair,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e103840">Let stir no aspen leaf. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e103850">Send flocks of golden dreams</l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e103860">That all true joys presage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e103870">Bring, in thy oily streams,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e103880">The milk and honey age. </l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e103890">Now close the world-round sphere of bliss,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18416-e103900">And fill it with a heavenly kiss. </l>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e103910">After this Plutus to the maskers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18416-e103920" who="A18416-plutus">
          <speaker>Plut.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103930">Come virgin knights, the homage ye have done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103940">To love and beauty, and our Britan sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103950">Kind honour, will requite with holy feasts</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103960">In her fair temple; and her loved guests,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103970">Gives me the grace t'invite, when she and I</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103980">(Honour and riches) will eternally</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e103990"><pb facs="25"/> a league in favour of this night combine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e104000">In which loves second hallowed tapers shine;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e104010">Whose joys, may heaven and earth as highly please</l>
          <l xml:id="A18416-e104020">As those two nights that got great Hercules. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18416-e104030">The speech ended; they concluded with a dance, that brought them off; Plutus, with honour and the rest conducting them up to the temple of honour. </stage>
        <trailer xml:id="A18416-e104040">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
      <div type="hymn" xml:id="A18416-e104050">
        <pb facs="26"/>
        <pb facs="26"/>
        <head>A hymn to Hymen for the most time-fitted nuptials of our thrice gracious Princess Elizabeth ▪ etc.</head>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104060">Sing, sing a rapture to all nuptial ears,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104070">Bright Hymen's torches, drunk up Parca's tears:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104080">Sweet Hymen; Hymen, mightiest of gods,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104090">Atoning of all-taming blood the odds;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104100">Two into one, contracting; one to two</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104110">Dilating, which no other god can do. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104120">Makest sure, with change, and let'st the married try,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104130">Of man and woman, the variety. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104140">And as a flower, half scorched with days long heat Simil. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104150">Thirsts for refreshing, with night's cooling sweat,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104160">The wings of Zephire, fanning still her face,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104170">No cheer can add to her heart-thirsty grace;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104180">Yet wears she 'gainst those fires that make her fade,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104190">Her thick hair's proof, all hid, in midnight's shade;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104200">Her health, is all in dews; hope, all in showers,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104210">Whose want bewailed, she pines in all her powers:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104220">So love-scorched virgins, nourish quenchless fires;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104230"><pb facs="27"/> the father's cares; the mother's kind desires. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104240">Their gold, and garments, of the newest guise,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104250">Can nothing comfort their scorcht fantasies,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104260">But, taken ravished up, in Hymen's arms,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104270">His circle holds, for all their anguish, charms:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104280">Then,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A18416-e104290">Simil. ad eandem explicat.</note> as a glad graft, in the spring sun shines,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104300">That all the helps, of earth, and heaven combines</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104310">In her sweet growth: puts in the morning on</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104320">Her cheerful airs; the sun's rich fires, at noon;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104330">At even the sweet dews, and at night with stars,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104340">In all their virtuous influences shares;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104350">So, in the bridegroom's sweet embrace; the bride,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104360">All varied joys tastes, in their naked pride:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104370">To which the richest weeds: are weeds, to flowers;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104380">Come Hymen then; come close these nuptial hours</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104390">With all years comforts. Come; each virgin keeps</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104400">Her odorous kisses for thee; golden sleeps</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104410">Will, in their humours, never steep an eye,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104420">Till thou invit'st them with thy harmony. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104430">Why stayest thou? see each virgin doth prepare</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104440">Embraces for thee; her white breasts lays bare</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104450">To tempt thy soft hand; let's such glances fly</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104460">As make stars shoot, to imitate her eye. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104470">Puts arts attires on, that put nature's down:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104480">Sings, dances, sets on every foot a crown,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104490">Sighs, in her songs, and dances; kisseth air</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104500">Till rites, and words past, thou in deeds repair;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104510">The whole court Io sings: io the air:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104520">Io, the floods, and fields: io, most fair,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104530">Most sweet, most happy Hymen; come: away;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104540"><pb facs="27"/> with all thy comforts come; old matrons pray,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104550">With young maids languors; birds bill, build, and breed</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104560">To teach thee thy kind, every flower and weed</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104570">Looks up to gratulate thy longed for fruits;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104580">Thrice given, are free, and timely-granted suits:</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104590">There is a seed by thee now to be sown,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104600">In whose fruit earth, shall see her glories shown,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104610">At all parts perfect; and must therefore lose</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104620">No minutes time; from times use all fruit flows;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104630">And as the tender hyacinth, that grows</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104640">Where Phoebus<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A18416-e104650">Simil.</note> most his golden beams bestows,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104660">Is propped with care; is watered every hour;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104670">The sweet winds adding their increasing power,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104680">The scattered drops of night's refreshing dew,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104690">Hasting the full grace, of his glorious hue,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104700">Which once disclosing, must be gathered straight,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104710">Or hue, and odour both, will lose their height;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104720">So, of a virgin, high, and richly kept,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104730">The grace and sweetness full grown must be reaped,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104740">Or, forth her spirits fly, in empty air;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104750">The sooner fading; the more sweet and fair. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104760">Gentle, oh gentle Hymen, be not then</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104770">Cruel, that kindest arts to maids, and men;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104780">These two, one twin are; and their mutual bliss,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104790">Not in thy beams, but in thy bosom is. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104800">Nor can their hands fast, their heart's joys make sweet;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104810">Their hearts, in breasts are; and their breasts must meet. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104820">Let, there be peace, yet murmur: and that noise,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104830">Beget of peace, the nuptial battles joys. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104840">Let peace grow cruel, and take wreck of all,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104850"><pb facs="28"/> the war's delay brought thy full festival. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104860">Hark, hark, oh now the sweet twin murmur sounds;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104870">Hymen is come, and all his heat abounds;</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104880">Shut all doors; none, but Hymen's lights advance. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104890">No sound stir; let, dumb joy, enjoy a trance. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104900">Sing, sing a rapture to all nuptial ears,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18416-e104910">Bright Hymen's torches drunk up Parca's tears. </l>
        <trailer xml:id="A18416-e104920">Finis.</trailer>
        <pb facs="28"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A18416"><item xml:id="A18416-plutus" n="27">
    <seg type="character_name">A18416-plutus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">27</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18416-capriccio" n="22">
    <seg type="character_name">A18416-capriccio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">22</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A18416-chorus" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A18416-chorus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18416-honour" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A18416-honour</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18416-eun" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A18416-eun</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18416-herald" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18416-herald</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

