<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1 The Matrimonial Trouble<date type="creation_date">1662</date></title>
        <author>Cavendish, Margaret</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A53060_12.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>356 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">11861873</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing N868.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">50022</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53060</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
            <author>Newcastle, William Cavendish, 1592-1676.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[24], 679 [i.e. 675], [4] p. : ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by A. Warren, for John Martyn, James Allestry, and Tho. Dicas ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1662.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>First edition.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Errata: p. [4] at end.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A53060_12-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A53060_12-e100020">
      <div n="1" type="play" xml:id="A53060_12-e100030">
        <pb facs="223" n="422"/>
        <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A53060_12-e100040">
          <list xml:id="A53060_12-e100050">
            <head>The actors names.</head>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100060">The lord widower. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100070">Sir William Lovewell, and the lady Hypocondria his wife.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100080">Sir Henry sage, and the lady chastity his wife.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100090">Sir Edward courtly, and the lady jealousy his wife.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100100">Sir Humphrey disagree, and the lady disagree his wife.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100110">Sir Thomas cuckold, and the lady wanton his wife.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100120">Sir Timothy Spendall, and the lady Poverty his wife.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100130">Sir John dotard, and the lady dripping his wife.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100140">Sir Francis inconstant, and the lady inconstant his wife.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100150">Sir James hearty, the lady Inconstant's father.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100160">Monsieur amorous. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100170">Monsieur disguise. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100180">The lady sprightly, the lord widowers daughter. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100190">The lady procurer.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100200">Mistress forsaken, afterwards named Monsieur disguise.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100210">Mistress single, sister to the lady jealousy.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100220">Doll subtlety, the lady Sprightly's chambermaid: also a waiting-gentlewoman. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100230">Nan Lightheel, the lady jealousies maid, and likewise a waiting-gentlewoman. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100240">Joan cry-out, the lady Hypocondria's chambermaid, and likewise a waiting-gentlewoman. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100250">Briget greasy, sir John dottards kitchen maid, and two other maids of his. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100260">Three maidservants of the lady poverty's.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100270">Two or three maidservants of the lady Disagree's.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100280">A maidservant to the lady inconstant.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100290">Nic adviser, sir Francis Inconstant's man. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100300">Roger trusty, sir William Lovewel's man. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100310">A servingman of sir James hearty's.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100320">A skipper.</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100330">Doctors and others. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_12-e100340">Steward.</item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A53060_12-e100350">
          <pb facs="223" n="423"/>
          <head>The first part of the play, called the matrimonial trouble a comedy.</head>
          <head type="sub">Act i.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e100360">
            <head>Scene 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e100370">Enter sir Francis inconstant, and mistress forsaken.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100380" who="A53060_12-francis_inconstant">
              <speaker>Sir Fran. Incon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100390">When I forsake you, let heaven forsake my soul.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100400" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Mistress forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100410">I do not doubt you: for if I did, I could not love you; and whilst I love you, I cannot doubt you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100420" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100430">O how it wounds my heart to part from you! my thoughts are tortured, and my mind is set upon a melancholy rack.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100440" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100450">Since your journey cannot be conveniently avoided, I will please myself with the hopes of your sudden return.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100460" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100470">Farewell, sweet mistress, death is the worst of nature, and your absence the worst of fortune.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e100480">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e100490">
            <head>Scene 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e100500">Enter master thrifty the steward, and Briget greasy the cookmaid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100510" who="A53060_12-briget">
              <speaker>Briget greasy.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100520">Good master steward, give order for some beef-suet to be brought in: for there is nor any left in the house, and I must make a venison-pasty; and if I should temper my pastry all with butter, you would be angry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100530" who="A53060_12-thrifty">
              <speaker>Thrifty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100540">Why, cannot you take some of the fat from the beef-broth for your crust?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100550" who="A53060_12-briget">
              <speaker>Briget.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100560">Yes, if every one that eat of it had as fresh a mouth as you, or loved drink so well as you do, it would serve, otherwise it would be too salt for their palates; besides, I am to make puddings in guts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100570" who="A53060_12-thrifty">
              <speaker>Thrifty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100580">If they prove as the last you made, the dogs may eat them<pb facs="224" n="424"/> for the guts stunk so much, as no man could eat any of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100590" who="A53060_12-briget">
              <speaker>Briget.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100600">I'm sure 'twas your fault, in that you did not bring me wherewithal to make them, until such time as the guts began to putrify.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100610" who="A53060_12-thrifty">
              <speaker>Thrifty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100620">No, no, you are a slut, and did not take all the dung out of them, nor wash, nor scrape, nor cleanse them as they should have been; but you order the guts, as you do the dishes, the one is dungy; the other greasy; besides, my master complains, that his fowl taste rank, and his brawn tastes strong, and his beef tastes musty, and that's because you are so lazy, as not to shift your brawn into fresh sousing-drink, nor make the brine strong enough in the powdering-tub, nor thrust your fingers far enough into the fowls rumps, to draw them clean; besides, when they are roasted, they are as dry as a chip, for want of basting-butter; besides, your sluttery is such, as you will poison all the house: for in one place I find a piece of butter, and a greasy comb full of nitty hairs lying by it; and in another place flour and old-worn stockings, the feet being rotted off with sweat; and in a third place, a dish of cold meat covered with a foul smock, and your dirty shoes (For the most part) stand upon the dresser-board, where you lay the hot meat; besides, by your carelessness you do waste and spoil so much, as it is unsufferable: for you will fling whole ladlefuls of dripping into the fire, to make the fire blaze underneath the pot; and because you have not the profit of the kitchenstuff, you will never scrape the dresser-board, nor dripping-pans, nor lick the platters, trays, or scummers, frying-pans, skillets, gridirons, spits, ladles, kettles, or any of the kitchen-vessels, as you should do, but wash them all with hot water at first, without taking off the grease beforehand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100630" who="A53060_12-briget">
              <speaker>Briget.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100640">Well, if you do not like me, pray pay me my wages, and I will be gone: I'm sure I never served in any place for so small wages and few vails as in this service: I'm sure 'tis no ways beneficial to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100650" who="A53060_12-thrifty">
              <speaker>Thrifty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100660">I'm sure you'll make it beneficial one way or another: for you have your female factors that lie abroad, to whom you send commodities by your she-porters, that come hither every day to transport them. Thus you traffic upon my master's cost, and my reputation: for I am thought the worse of either, as believing I am a false steward, or a negligent one. Thus a true man is thought a knave: for by your stealing I am thought a thief.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100670" who="A53060_12-briget">
              <speaker>Briget.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100680">You are a base man for saying I steal, I never was accounted a thief in my life, but always trusty and true, in what service soever I lived.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e100690">The steward goes out, and Briget greasie left as crying: then enters her master sir John dotard, and looks earnestly upon her, and then speaks as to himself. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100700" who="A53060_12-dotard">
              <speaker>Dotard.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100710">She's a pretty wench, if she had but clean clothes on, by Venus she would be very handsome; a silk gown would make her a rare beauty; her tears fall on her nose and cheeks like gentle showers of rain on roses and lilies sweet. O she is a heavenly creature!</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e100720">He speaks to her.</stage>
            <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100730">Sweetheart, where do you live?</p>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100740" who="A53060_12-briget">
              <speaker>Briget.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100750">In your worship's house.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100760" who="A53060_12-dotard">
              <speaker>Dotard.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100770">And whose servant are you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100780" who="A53060_12-briget">
              <speaker>Briget.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100790">Your worships.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100800" who="A53060_12-dotard">
              <pb facs="224" n="425"/>
              <speaker>Dotard.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100810">How long have you served me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100820" who="A53060_12-briget">
              <speaker>Briget.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100830">A quarter, an't please your worship.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100840" who="A53060_12-dotard">
              <speaker>Dotard.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100850">In what place serve you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100860" who="A53060_12-briget">
              <speaker>Briget.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100870">In the kitchen, an't please you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100880" who="A53060_12-dotard">
              <speaker>Dotard.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100890">What makes you cry?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100900" who="A53060_12-briget">
              <speaker>Briget.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100910">Your worship's steward hath wronged me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100920" who="A53060_12-dotard">
              <speaker>Dotard.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100930">How hath he wronged thee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100940" who="A53060_12-briget">
              <speaker>Briget.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100950">He says I stole your worship's kitchenstuff, when the gods know I am as innocent as the child that is newly born.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100960" who="A53060_12-dotard">
              <speaker>Dotard.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100970">He is a knave for saying so, and I will have him turned out of his authority for saying so: wherefore cry no more, fair maid; for thou shalt be preferred to a higher office.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e100980" who="A53060_12-briget">
              <speaker>Briget.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e100990">I thank your worship.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101000">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e101010">
            <head>Scene 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101020">Enter mistress forsaken, and a gentleman.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101030" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101040">Sir, did you come lately from Changeland? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101050" who="A53060_12-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101060">Yes lady.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101070" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101080">Pray did you not see a gentleman in that country, ha 〈…〉 Francis inconstant? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101090" who="A53060_12-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101100">I am very well acquainted with him, lady: for he is my most noble friend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101110" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101120">I hope he is well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101130" who="A53060_12-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101140">So well, madam, as he is resolved to marry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101150" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101160">That he might do, if it were for no other reason, but for a nurse to tend him, if he should chance to be sick.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101170" who="A53060_12-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101180">By your favour, lady, it were dangerous for a sick man to be married, especially to a fair young lady.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101190" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101200">But pray sir, is he to marry a lady in that country?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101210" who="A53060_12-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101220">So he told me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101230" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101240">Did he tell you so himself?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101250" who="A53060_12-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101260">Yes madam, I had it first from his own mouth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101270" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101280">Is she handsome?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101290" who="A53060_12-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101300">Truly I did not see her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101310" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101320">Is she rich sir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101330" who="A53060_12-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101340">Truly I heard not what portion she had; but I suppose if she had been rich, her wealth would have made her famous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101350" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101360">Nor you have not heard whether she is discreet, or witty, nor of what humour she is?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101370" who="A53060_12-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101380">No indeed, lady, I heard not anybody speak of her but himself, and that was only, that he was to marry a young lady in that city he was in, and that he thought would be the cause to persuade him to settle in that country.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101390" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101400">How long a time is required to go to that place where he is?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101410" who="A53060_12-gentleman">
              <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101420">According as the wind is: if the wind be good, twelve hours<pb facs="225" n="426"/> fail will land a passenger, and some eight hours riding from the shore, will bring them to the city.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101430" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101440">Will you please to walk in and rest yourself?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101450">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e101460">
            <head>Scene 4.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101470">Enter two servant-maids of sir John dotards.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101480" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101490">Lord, there is such a quarrel about the falling out of Briget greasy and master steward, as it is wonderful: for my master chides, Briget cries, and master steward maintains his words, as they do so offend and misprove, as you would bless yourself.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101500" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101510">I will go listen, and hear them.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101520">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e101530">
            <head>Scene 5.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101540">Enter the lord widower, and doctors. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101550" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101560">My wife, master doctor, is very ill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101570" who="A53060_12-doctor">
              <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101580">She is so: for her disease is not to be cured, my lord; for we cannot restore the decays of vital parts: for as they consume, life draws towards an end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101590" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101600">But prey do your endeavour to prolong her like as long as you can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101610" who="A53060_12-doctor">
              <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101620">We shall, my lord, to the utmost of our skill. Your lordship's humble servant.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101630">Exit doctor.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101640">Enter Dol Subtilty, the lady's chambermaid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101650" who="A53060_12-doll_subtilty">
              <speaker>Dol subtlety.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101660">My lady desires to speak with your lordship.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101670" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101680">And I desire to speak with your ladyship.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101690" who="A53060_12-subtilty">
              <speaker>Subtlety.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101700">I am ready to hear your lordship's commands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101710" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101720">And are you as ready to obey them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101730" who="A53060_12-subtilty">
              <speaker>Subtlety.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101740">Yes, so far as my duty doth oblige me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101750" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101760">Well, then pray do not forget when you are called to pay that duty where you owe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101770">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e101780">
            <pb facs="225" n="427"/>
            <head>Scene 6.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101790">Enter mistress forsaken alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101800" who="A53060_12-forsaken">
              <speaker>Mistress forsaken.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101810">If this news could deprive me of my life, it would have made me happy; but it hath almost deprived me of my reason, and quite from my patience, which makes me miserable, and misery is worse than death: for death is a cessation of pain, and misery a torment of life: but if this report be true, I will lay more curses on his head, than a long penitential life shall be able to take off.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101820">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e101830">
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101840">Enter the two maids of sir John dotard.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101850" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101860">Lord, Briget is so proud since she is preferred to be my master's laundry-maid, as she will touch none but my master's linen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101870" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101880">She is become very fine upon her preferment: I am sure it is not five or ten pound wages that will or can maintain her at that rate she goes: for she hath had, to my knowledge, two new pair of shoes within three weeks of each other; whereupon I told her, that the shoes that she cast by, would be very strong and serviceable, if they were cobbled; and her answer was, what, did I think she would wear cobbled shoes? I told her, why not now, as well as she did? for she used to send her shoes to be cobbled three or four times over, and her waistcoat to be patched, and her petticoats to be new-bordered, and her stockings to be heeled, as the rest of us did; and I knew of no lands that had befallen her, and therefore she may do the same still.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101890" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101900">And what said she then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101910" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101920">She bid me meddle with my own matters, and not meddle with her; and I dare not offend her, for fear I should be turned away: nay, she is so proud, as she turns her head aside when Richard the carter comes to kiss her, and she strives to shun his company, when once within a short time, she would make haste to wash her dishes, that she might have time to sit in Richard's lap, and there they would sit colling and kissing until the sea-coal-site was burned out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101930" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101940">But now she sits in a better seat.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101950">Exeunt</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="8" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e101960">
            <pb facs="226" n="428"/>
            <head>Scene 8.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e101970">Enter mistress forsaken in man's apparel, naming herself monsieur disguise.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e101980" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Monsieur disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e101990">I cannot believe he will prove so false and perjurious, but this disguise, I hope, will bring me to discover the truth: and if he be false, for his sake may all the masculine sex be slaves to the effeminate sex, not bound by love, but by base servile fear; may they long after the power, but never get it; may women govern the world, and when they command, the men dare not disobey, and be despised for their reward; may their jealousies disturb their rest, their cares increase their labours; may they work like horses, fawn like dogs, and bear like asses. But if he be constant, may all the masculine sex be blessed for his sake; may all women desire, admire, and love him; may pleasure embrace him, health preserve him, and time attend him; may he be armed with power, crowned with peace, and all obedience bow to his command; may the sound but of his name bring joy to all hearts; may all be pleased for his birth, pray for his life, and fear his death; may good fortune trace his ways, whilst he tides upon the wings of a glorious fame.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102000">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="9" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e102010">
            <head>Scene 9.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102020">Enter sir Francis inconstant, as in another country, with his new mistress. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102030" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102040">Sweet mistress, you are the elixir of beauty: all other women are as unrefined metal, like base coin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102050" who="A53060_12-new_mistris">
              <speaker>New mistress.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102060">Whilst I am unmarried you'll flatter me; but when I am your wife, you will change your complemental discourse to quarrelling disputes, or insulting commands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102070" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102080">O never, never, your eye shall direct all my actions, your commands shall rule my life, and your pleasures shall be my only delight.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102090">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="10" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e102100">
            <head>Scene 10.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102110">Enter sir James hearty and his man.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102120" who="A53060_12-hearty">
              <speaker>Hearty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102130">Here, take this note, that you may not forget the guests that are to be invited to my daughter's wedding.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102140">The man takes the note, and looks on it.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102150"><pb facs="226" n="429"/>Can you read it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102160" who="A53060_12-man">
              <speaker>Man.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102170">I cannot tell sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102180" who="A53060_12-hearty">
              <speaker>Hearty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102190">Let me hear if you can, or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102200" who="A53060_12-man">
              <speaker>Man.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102210">Imprimis, sir William Lovewell, and the lady Hypocondria his wife.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102220">Item sir Henry sage, and the lady chastity his wife.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102230">Item sir Edward courtly, and the lady jealousy his wife, and mistress Jane single her sister.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102240">Item sir Thomas cuckold, and the lady wanton his wife.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102250">Item sir Humphrey disagree, and the lady disagree his wife.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102260">Item sir Timothy Spendall, and the lady Poverty his wife.</p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102270">Item the lady procurer. </p>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102280">Item monsieur amorous. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102290" who="A53060_12-hearty">
              <speaker>Hearty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102300">Well read, well read: as for the lord widower, I know he will not come: for I hear his lady is newly dead. This is the nature of the world; some marry, and some die.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102310" who="A53060_12-man">
              <speaker>Man.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102320">Troth sir, of the two evils, I think it is better to die than to marry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102330" who="A53060_12-hearty">
              <speaker>Hearty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102340">I am not of your mind: for I had rather have a ruddy, plain, soft wench to be my bed-fellow, than pale, grim, lean, numb, cold death. But go your way about this employment, the whilst I will give direction for the entertainment.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102350">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="11" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e102360">
            <head>Scene 11.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102370">Enter the lord widower, and the lady sprightly his elder daughter, and other small children, and doll Subtilty, all weeping. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102380" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102390">We have reason to weep: for you, my children, have lost a good mother, and I a loving wife, and her servants a kind lady; but we cannot alter heavens decrees: wherefore we must take comfort in what is, and not grieve for what cannot be helped: and now, daughter sprightly, you must be as my wife, friend, and daughter all in one: for as your mother did, when she had health, govern my family, so must you now she is dead; and you must take care of your young brothers and sisters, and heaven will reward thee with a good husband and children of your own: and as for her maid here, who hath taken great pains all the time of your mother's sickness, ought to be rewarded for her care: wherefore, daughter, let her wait upon you, as she did upon your mother.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102400" who="A53060_12-doll_subtilty">
              <speaker>Doll subtlety.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102410">I thank your lordship.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102420">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="12" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e102430">
            <pb facs="227" n="430"/>
            <head>Scene 12.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102440">Enter all the bridal guests, and pass over the stage, as through a room.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="13" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e102450">
            <head>Scene. 13.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102460">Enter monsieur disguise, as from the sea. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102470" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Monsieur disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102480">Surely the fates have conspired against me, the winds were so cross, just like men, sometimes for us, and sometimes against us.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102490">Enter a skipper.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102500">Have you found out the gentleman's lodging?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102510" who="A53060_12-skipper">
              <speaker>Skipper.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102520">Yes sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102530" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102540">And was he at home?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102550" who="A53060_12-skipper">
              <speaker>Skipper.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102560">He hath that which will invite him to stay at home, and keep him from wandering abroad for some time sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102570" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102580">What's that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102590" who="A53060_12-skipper">
              <speaker>Skipper.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102600">A fair wife sir: for a drunken servingman told me that one sir Francis inconstant had married his master's daughter, and that the wedding-feast would continue a week, if not a fortnight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102610" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102620">And was the man drunk that told you so?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102630" who="A53060_12-skipper">
              <speaker>Skipper.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102640">Yes surely: he seemed so to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102650" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102660">Then (Perchance) he might tell you a lie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102670" who="A53060_12-skipper">
              <speaker>Skipper.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102680">He was not so drunk, but that he might tell a truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102690" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102700">Prithee friend do me one favour more, and then I will pay thee for thy pains.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102710" who="A53060_12-skipper">
              <speaker>Skipper.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102720">What you please to command me sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102730" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102740">Then inquire for a mans-tailor, to make me some clothes: for I am not accoutred fit for a bridal-house.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102750" who="A53060_12-skipper">
              <speaker>Skipper.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102760">I shall sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102770">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="14" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e102780">
            <head>Scene 14.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102790">Enter two maids of sir John dotards.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102800" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102810">I'faith I will go and inquire out a new service: for I will never be boxed by my fellow-servant that was, although now she is preferred to be housekeeper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102820" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102830">How came the quarrel betwixt you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102840" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102850">Why now, forsooth, she is come to order and to rectify, she's not only grown light-fingered, but fine-fingered, as to touch nothing that is<pb facs="227" n="431"/> not bright-scoured, nor then neither, without her gloves; and she called for a candle and a candlestick to carry into my master's chamber, and I for haste run up with the candle, and forgotten the candlestick, and had left it behind me: when I came, what, said she, do you bring a candle without a candlestick? Alas said I, I have forgotten it; but hold you the candle, said I, and I will run and fetch the stick straight, and so I put the candle into her hand: with that, she up with her hand, and gave me a box on the ear, what, said she, do you give me a greasy candle to hold? I will teach you more manners, said she, against the next time: I being heated at the blow she gave me, could her, that she had forgotten since the mouse bit her greasy face when she was asleep, taking it for a candles-end, or a piece of bacon: with that, she flew upon me, and I at her, where in the combat we made such a noise, as my master came forth of his chamber, and parted us, and then he bid me get me out of his house, but kissed her, and prayed her to pacify her anger, and not to distemper herself with a rude wench as I was.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102860" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102870">And what said she then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102880" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102890">Why she told my master I was a naughty baggage, a dirty slur, a base whore, and all the ill names she could; but I will not suffer this, for I will be gone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102900" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102910">Nay, let us stay until we are provided of other services.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102920">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="15" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e102930">
            <head>Scene 15.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102940">Enter monsieur disguise alone:</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e102950" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Monsieur disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102960">And is he married! O that I could pull out that part of my brain which imprints his memory! for the wrongs he hath done me are so great and heavy, as I wish I could unload my soul, and build a pyramid of curses, that may stand as a mark of his infamy.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102970">She studies a little time, then speaks.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e102980">I had rather banish myself, than live in disgrace in my own country.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e102990">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A53060_12-e103000">
          <pb facs="228" n="432"/>
          <head>Act ii.</head>
          <div n="16" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e103010">
            <head>Scene. 16.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e103020">Enter the lord widower, and doll Subtilty.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103030" who="A53060_12-subtilty">
              <speaker>Subtilty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103040">I'faith, my lord, your daughter is so jealous of me, as she says I am always in your lordship's chamber.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103050" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103060">Why so thou art most commonly, although not always.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103070" who="A53060_12-subtilty">
              <speaker>Subtlety.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103080">But yet it is not fit children should examine their parents' actions; and it were an indiscretion in parents to allow of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103090" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103100">She is young, she is young.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103110" who="A53060_12-subtilty">
              <speaker>Subtlety.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103120">Wherefore your lordship should have a care to have her prudently governed; and if she be too young to govern herself, how can she govern so great a family as your lordships is?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103130" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103140">O she hath but the name, my steward governs all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103150" who="A53060_12-subtilty">
              <speaker>Subtlety.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103160">Yes; but the mistress of the house governs the steward, and the steward gives order as an inferior officer, delivering the superiors commands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103170" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103180">You say true: wherefore you that have some more experience, should counsel her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103190" who="A53060_12-subtilty">
              <speaker>Subtlety.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103200">O, my lord, 'tis not manners for me to give her counsel, neither will she take it from me: for when I humbly offer her my advice, she cheques me, and threatens to turn me away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103210" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103220">Doth she so? But I will have her to take counsel, and to know she is too young to order after her own childish fancy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103230" who="A53060_12-subtilty">
              <speaker>Subtlety.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103240">Indeed, my lord, she wants years, which should make her experienced. Sweet child, she is fitter to dress babies, and order a closet, than govern a great family, which is a little commonwealth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103250" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103260">Well, I will order her otherwise.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e103270">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="17" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e103280">
            <head>Scene 17.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e103290">Enter the bride, the bridegroom, sir James hearty, and all the bridal guests. Then enters a servant to the bridegroom sir Francis inconstant.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103300" who="A53060_12-servant">
              <speaker>Servant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103310">Sir there is a young gentleman desires to speak with your worship.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103320" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103330">What manner of man is he?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103340" who="A53060_12-servant">
              <speaker>Servant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103350">A sweet-faced young man, by my troth sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103360" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103370">Of what country seems he to be?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103380" who="A53060_12-servant">
              <speaker>Servant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103390">Of your own country, sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103400" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <pb facs="228" n="433"/>
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103410">Direct him in.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e103420">Enter monsieur disguise.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103430" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103440">Sir, I was commanded by a young lady to give you this letter.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e103450">Sir Francis reads it, and in the reading seems very much troubled. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103460" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103470">She writes as if she were dying when she writ this letter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103480" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103490">She was dying indeed: for the last act she did, was to give me this letter; and the last words she spoke were, pray see this letter safe conveyed, and so she died.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103500" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Lady inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103510">What makes you so pale on a sudden, husband?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103520" who="A53060_12-francis_inconstant">
              <speaker>Sir Fran. Incon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103530">I am not well, and therefore I must go to my chamber; but pray sweetheart stay you here, lest my being ill should disturb our guests.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103540" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Lady inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103550">Do you think I can entertain them if you be sick?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103560" who="A53060_12-francis_inconstant">
              <speaker>Sir Fran. Incon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103570">I am not so sick as to be nursed, although not so well as to delight in company: for I am rather melancholy, than any other way distempered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103580" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Lady Inconst.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103590">What makes you melancholy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103600" who="A53060_12-francis_inconstant">
              <speaker>Sir Fran. Incon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103610">Why a dear friend of mine is dead.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e103620">He sighs a great sigh.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103630">But sweetheart, pray excuse me to the company, and pray let this gentleman, my noble friend, be well treated.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103640" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Lady Inconst.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103650">I shall obey your command.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e103660">Sir Francis goes out. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103670" who="A53060_12-james_hearty">
              <speaker>Sir Jam. hearty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103680">What, is my son-in-law gone?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103690" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Lady Inconst.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103700">Sir, he desires you and the rest of the company would excuse him: for he hath heard of the death of a friend, which makes him so melancholy, as he saith that his dull and indisposed humour would disturb the mirth of our noble friends.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103710" who="A53060_12-james_hearty">
              <speaker>Sir Jam. hearty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103720">'Tis a sign he is young, that he is so tender-natured, and so soft-hearted, to mourn and grieve for those that die; but when he comes to age, he will only commend his friends that are dead, but not grieve for them: for pity wears out, as age increases.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103730" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Lady Inconst.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103740">Pray sir let me entreat you to be one of our guests.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103750" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103760">You shall command me, lady.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103770" who="A53060_12-thomas_cuckold">
              <speaker>Sir Tho. cuckold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103780">Nay, since the gentleman hath brought such news as hath banished the bridegroom from the company, he shall now supply his place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103790" who="A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree">
              <speaker>Sir Hum. disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103800">Soft sir, he may at the board, but not in his bed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103810" who="A53060_12-henry_courtly">
              <speaker>Sir Hen. Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103820">He looks so modestly, as if he would play the part of a bride rather than a bridegroom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103830" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103840">Lady, will you accept of my modest service?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103850" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Lady Inconst.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103860">Sir, I must not refuse modesty.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e103870">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="18" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e103880">
            <pb facs="229" n="434"/>
            <head>Scene 18.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e103890">Enter two maidservants of sir John dotards.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103900" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103910">'Tis no wonder that Briget greasy is so proud now, being married to my master, he having made her a lady. Lord, lord, to see the fortune that some have over others: why, if my master would have married one of his maids, he might have chosen a prettier wench amongst any of us all than she is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103920" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103930">Yes i'faith: for she was thought the veriest puss of us all; for she is neither snout-fair, nor well-shaped, she hath splay-feet, and chilblainheels.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103940" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103950">Nay all will grant she was the dirtiest slut in the house: for there was never a manservant but would cry so at her when they kissed her; besides, she was the veriest fool amongst us: but lord, what wealth and honour will do! for now she is a lady, she looks as if she never washed a dish, or scoured a kettle or spit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103960" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103970">But I wonder how she came to be his wife, she might have served as her betters have done before her: I am sure there was Nan, a pretty pert, cleanly maid, who was kind, and willing to do any thing, either to serve our master, or fellow servants.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e103980" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e103990">O but Nan had not an old woman that used to come to her to get suet and scraps, as Briget had; and this old woman, they say, counselled Briget to seem nice and coy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104000" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104010">I wonder what Richard the carter will say, who was turned out of his service, because he should not share with my master.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104020" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104030">I'faith I heard that Richard was told of her advancement, and 'tis said he laughed, and said my master had a hungry stomach, that he could feed of his leavings; but by his troth he was glad she was become a lady: for now he could say he had kissed and courted a lady as well as the best gallant of them all.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104040">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="19" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e104050">
            <head>Scene 19.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104060">Enter the lord widower, and the lady sprightly his daughter. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104070" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104080">Daughter, although you do govern my family very well for your years, yet you are young, and wanting experience, may be cozened; and though I have a great estate, yet it will be all consumed, if order and method be not put into practice: wherefore I would have you take the counsel of mistress Dorothy subtlety, to assist you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104090" who="A53060_12-lady">
              <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104100">Who is that, my lord?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104110" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104120">Why, do not you know her? she that waited on your mother.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104130" who="A53060_12-lady">
              <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104140">Pardon me, my lord, I did not know her by that title: for she was plain Dol subtlety when she waited on my mother, and not knowing of her advancement<pb facs="229" n="435"/> from a chambermaid to a gentlewoman, I might easily mistake; besides, she is not so much older, as to have much more experience than myself: perchance she may have more craft, which was learned her in her poverty, than I, who have been bred at the horn of plenty, that knew no scarcity, nor sharking necessity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104150" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104160">You have a sharp tongue when spite moves it; but let me hear no more of these words, but do as I command you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104170" who="A53060_12-lady">
              <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104180">I never disobeyed you as I do know.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104190" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104200">Well, no more words.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104210">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="20" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e104220">
            <head>Scene 20.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104230">Enter the bride, and all the bridal guests; they dance, and monsieur disguise dances with the bride. Sir Spendall seems to whisper monsieur disguise in the ear, being half drunk. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104240" who="A53060_12-spendall">
              <speaker>Spendall.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104250">Sir, but that you look more like a woman than a man, you might give the bridegroom more cause to be melancholy for the living than the dead; but let me entreat you, young gentleman, that you strike not his head, as your news hath done his heart: for I perceive the bride's eyes are fixed upon you, and from the root of a fixed eye grows horns, when they are set in a married head.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104260" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104270">There is no fear.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104280" who="A53060_12-spendall">
              <speaker>Spendall.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104290">Yes sir, as long as there are doubts, there are fears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104300" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104310">There is no doubt sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104320" who="A53060_12-spendall">
              <speaker>Spendall.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104330">But that she will be sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104340" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104350">What, sir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104360" who="A53060_12-spendall">
              <speaker>Spendall.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104370">What you please sir; and let me tell you, young gentleman, that as long as there are women, there will be lovers and cuckolds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104380" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104390">And let me tell you, sir, that as long as there are men, there will be fools and drunkards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104400" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Lady inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104410">Sir, I doubt we have invited you rather to your trouble, than your delight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104420" who="A53060_12-disguise">
              <speaker>Disguise.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104430">Madam, you are the treasure of pleasure and delight; which none can receive but from your bounty, nor enjoy but by your favour.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104440">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="21" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e104450">
            <head>Scene 21.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104460">Enter the lady sprightly, and Dol Subtilty.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104470" who="A53060_12-sprightly">
              <speaker>Lady sprightly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104480">What had you to do to contradict my commands?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104490" who="A53060_12-doll_subtilty">
              <speaker>Dol subtlety.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104500">They were not fit to be obeyed, wherefore they were forbid.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104510"><pb facs="230" n="436"/>The lady gives Dol a lox on the ear. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104520" who="A53060_12-lady">
              <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104530">There, take that, to remember I forbid you to forbid my commands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104540" who="A53060_12-doll">
              <speaker>Dol.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104550">I will declare your blows to some that shall revenge me.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104560">Enter the lord widower.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104570" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104580">What, are you so light-fingered? 'tis time to get you a husband, to govern and rule your high spirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104590" who="A53060_12-lady">
              <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104600">No, pray sir get me no husband: for if my father takes part against me, surely a husband will be worse natured.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104610" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104620">So, you will say I am unnatural.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104630" who="A53060_12-lady">
              <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104640">No sir, I only say it is not my undutifulness that displeases you, but some that hath more wit than I, or at least good fortune to please you better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104650" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104660">Well, pray study your book and work, and leave the household. Affairs to my disposal.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104670" who="A53060_12-lady">
              <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104680">Sir, I took the office, as my duty to your commands, not for delight, pleasure, Ease, or profit, and I shall surrender it up again upon the same account, and with all the trouble, care, labour, vexations and disquiets belonging thereunto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104690" who="A53060_12-lord">
              <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104700">In doing so, you will do very well.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104710">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="32" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e104720">
            <head>Scene 32.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104730">Enter the lady Hypocondria as being frightly sick, and her husband sir William Lovewell.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104740" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104750">Heaven bless you wife, what makes you so extremely pale, and to seem so affrighted?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104760" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104770">O husband I have an imposthume broken within me, and the bag will rise and choke me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104780" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104790">Heaven forbid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104800" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104810">O I am choked, I am choked, I cannot fetch my breath.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104820">She takes her breath very short. Sir William Lovewell in a great fright calls for help. Enter some servants. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104830" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104840">O send for doctors straight: for my wife is ready to die.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104850">They go out running, he standing by the chair his wife sits in, trembling and quaking.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104860" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104870">How are you, dear wife? how do you feel yourself now? how are you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104880" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocondria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104890">O very ill; but yet methinks I can fetch my breath a little<pb facs="230" n="437"/> better than I could, I believe the imposthume-bag is fallen down: wherefore I will go to bed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104900" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104910">Pray do wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104920">He leads her out, and she goeth softly.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104930">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="23" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e104940">
            <head>Scene 23.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e104950">Enter sir Henry Sage, and the lady chastity his wife. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104960" who="A53060_12-sage">
              <speaker>Sage.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104970">Sweetheart, I was in your bedchamber, and in your cabinet-chamber, and missing you in both, I was afraid I must have been forced to have hired a crier, to have proclaimed my loss.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e104980" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e104990">Many a wife doth proclaim her husband's loss without the help of a crier: for the wives adulterous acts proclaim her husband a cuckold, and the loss of his honour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105000" who="A53060_12-sage">
              <speaker>Sage.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105010">But I am not afraid of that: for I am confident of thy chastity (Although the old saying is, confidence makes cuckolds.)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105020" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105030">Your confidence of me shall never harm you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105040" who="A53060_12-sage">
              <speaker>Sage.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105050">But your too serious studies will harm your health; and if you be sick, I cannot be well; besides, it will decay your beauty, waste your youth, like oil spent in a melancholy lamp, where life is always blinking.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105060" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105070">It were better that my body should be sick, than my mind idle; my beauty decay, than my understanding perish; my youth waste, than my fame lost; my life blinking, than my honour sinking: for an idle mind, not well employed creates a restless body, which runs from place to place, and hates to be at home. Thus mind and body both being out, extravagant words and actions run about, and riot keeps possession.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105080">And though the beauty withers and decays,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105090">Yet wit and wisdom with the ruin stays:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105100">And if the youth doth waste, and life's oil's spent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105110">Yet fame lasts long, and builds a monument:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105120">A melancholy life doth shadows cast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105130">But sets forth virtue, if they are well placed. </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105140">Then who would entertain an idle mirth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105150">Begotten by vanity, and dies in scorn? </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105160">Or proud, or pleased with beauty, when the birth</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105170">Becomes the grave or tomb as soon as born? </l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105180">But wisdom wishes to be old and glad,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105190">When youthful follies die, which seem as mad:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105200">If age is subject to repent what's past,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_12-e105210">Prudence and experience redeems what's lost. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105220" who="A53060_12-sage">
              <speaker>Sage.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105230">I perceive, wife, the Muses have kept you company, although you walk by yourself; but now I desire you will leave their company for a time, and entertain mine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105240" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <pb facs="231" n="438"/>
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105250">With all my heart; but the muses are never with me, but when you are employed about serious affairs: for though they are my visitors, yet they are your domestic servants.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e105260">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="24" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e105270">
            <head>Scene. 24.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e105280">Enter sir Humphrey Disagree, and his wife the lady Disagree.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105290" who="A53060_12-disagree">
              <speaker>Lady disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105300">Dear husband, where have you been?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105310" who="A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree">
              <speaker>Sir Hum. disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105320">My dear kind wife, I have been in the garden, where I have heard little robin redbreast sing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105330" who="A53060_12-disagree">
              <speaker>Lady disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105340">That's a sign, sweetheart, we shall have warm weather, otherwise they would come into the house.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105350" who="A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree">
              <speaker>Sir Hum. Disag.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105360">I had rather believe, my pretty bird, we shall have cold weather: for they sing always in the coldest time of the year, as in the depth of winter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105370" who="A53060_12-disagree">
              <speaker>Lady disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105380">How ignorantly you speak, good husband, as if the robin redbreast sings only in the cold winter, and not in the warm summer as well?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105390" who="A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree">
              <speaker>Sir Hum. disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105400">Why not, good wife, as well as nightingales, which only sing in the spring, and swallows in the heat of summer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105410" who="A53060_12-disagree">
              <speaker>Lady disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105420">That doth not prove that the robin doth not sing in summer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105430" who="A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree">
              <speaker>Sir Hum. Disag.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105440">I never heard the robin sing in summer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105450" who="A53060_12-disagree">
              <speaker>Lady disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105460">Your never hearing of it, is not a sufficient proof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105470" who="A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree">
              <speaker>Sir Hum. Disag.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105480">It is to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105490" who="A53060_12-disagree">
              <speaker>Lady disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105500">To say it is, without a reason, proves a fool.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105510" who="A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree">
              <speaker>Sir Hum. Disag.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105520">I only proved myself a fool in marrying you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105530" who="A53060_12-disagree">
              <speaker>Lady disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105540">I was accursed when first I gave consent to be your wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105550" who="A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree">
              <speaker>Sir Hum. Disag.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105560">You were easily won.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105570" who="A53060_12-disagree">
              <speaker>Lady disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105580">What, because I consented to a knave that wooed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105590" who="A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree">
              <speaker>Sir Hum. Disag.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105600">You are a false woman, for calling me a knave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105610" who="A53060_12-disagree">
              <speaker>Lady disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105620">You are a cuckold, for calling me false.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105630" who="A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree">
              <speaker>Sir Hum. Disag.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105640">Am I so, mistress? I will be sure to thrust my horns through your heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e105650">He offers to strike her, she gets up a stool, and slings at him, he gets a cushion and slings at her, and then gets hold of her, she cries out murder, in comes their friends and servants, and parts them.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105660" who="A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree">
              <speaker>Sir Hum. Disag.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105670">Damn me, I'll kill her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105680" who="A53060_12-disagree">
              <speaker>Lady disagree.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105690">You'll be hanged, will you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105700" who="A53060_12-friend">
              <speaker>Friend.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105710">Nay good sir be not angry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105720" who="A53060_12-servant">
              <speaker>Servant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105730">Good madam go away, until my master's anger is passed over.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e105740">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A53060_12-e105750">
          <pb facs="231" n="439"/>
          <head>Act iii.</head>
          <div n="25" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e105760">
            <head>Scene. 25.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e105770">Enter sir Francis inconstant, alone, as being very melancholy. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105780" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105790">I will read this letter once again, although it shakes my soul, and makes me almost mad.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e105800">He reads aloud the letter.</stage>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:id="A53060_12-e105810">
              <body xml:id="A53060_12-e105820">
                <opener xml:id="A53060_12-e105830">
                  <salute xml:id="A53060_12-e105840">Sir,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105850">The wrongs you have done me, are more than heaven can give me patience to endure; for which wrongs, may thick black clouds of infamy overspread your memory; and may my sorrows beat upon your soul, as Northern winds upon the sea, and raise up all your thoughts in discontent, as raging billows, causing your voice to roar out loud with hideous noise, confounding all the actions of your life; and weigh your hopes be drowned in the salt water of despairing tears. The heavens cannot condemn me for cursing a man which hath betrayed my youth by flattery, violated my chastity by protestations, tormented my harmless thoughts with perjury, disquieting my peaceable life with misfortunes. But the burden of my wrongs being too weighty for life to bear, hath sunk it to the grave, where I hope all my disgrace will be buried with me, though not the revenges of my wrongs; for those will punish you when I am dead: for the gods are just, although mankind is not. </p>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e105860">Enter Nic adviser, sir Francis inconstants man. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105870" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105880">O Nick, what a villain am I!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105890" who="A53060_12-adviser">
              <speaker>Adviser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105900">For what sir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105910" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105920">For perjury and murder: for I did not only break those bonds I had sealed with holy vows, but my falsehood hath killed a fair young lady: for she hearing I had forsaken her, and was to be married to another, she died for grief.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105930" who="A53060_12-adviser">
              <speaker>Adviser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105940">Alas sir, we are all by nature both frail and mortal: wherefore we must complain of nature, of her inconstancy and cruelty, in making our minds so changeable, and our bodies so weak, the one being subject to death, the other subject to variety. But sir, in my opinion, you have no cause to grieve, but rather to rejoice: for what you have erred by nature, you have repaired by fortune's favour: for if that lady which is dead, had lived, you would have been encumbered with many troubles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105950" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105960">As how Nick? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105970" who="A53060_12-adviser">
              <speaker>Adviser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e105980">Why you would have been as a young bear baired by two young whelps; the forsaken lady railing and exclaiming against you in all company she came into, and your wife tormenting you with sharp words and loud noise, insomuch as you would have neither ear, drank, or slept in quiet. Thus both abroad and at home you would have heard nothing but your own reproaches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e105990" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <pb facs="232" n="440"/>
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106000">But shall not I be the same now she is dead, think you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106010" who="A53060_12-adviser">
              <speaker>Adviser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106020">No faith sir: for death hath stopped the mouth of the one, and kisses may chance to muzzle the mouth of the other; but if you be melancholy, your lady will think you do repent, and will believe that you do prefer the memory of your dead mistress, before the enjoyment of your living wife; besides, women are so jealous, as they will not allow their husbands to think (That makes them talk so much as they do) for they think thoughts are bawds to adulterous actions, and that imaginations commit fornication with the ghosts and spirits of the dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106030" who="A53060_12-inconstant">
              <speaker>Inconstant.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106040">Well Nick I will take thy counsel, and cast off melancholy, and be merry in jovial company.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e106050">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="26" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e106060">
            <head>Scene 26.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e106070">Enter the lady jealousy as holding her head, and sir Edward courtly her husband. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106080" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106090">What, are you sick, wife?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106100" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106110">I have such a pain in my head, as I am not able to look up, or to speak.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106120" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106130">You should take some physic.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106140" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106150">I cannot take physic.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106160" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106170">You must take physic if you be not well; but prey have a care you do not catch cold, for that will do you hurt. But I must be gone about my several affairs: wherefore God be with you wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e106180">Sir Edward courtly goes out. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e106190">The lady jealousy calls her maid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106200" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106210">Nan.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106220" who="A53060_12-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106230">Madam?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106240" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106250">Go make me a whitewine caudle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106260" who="A53060_12-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106270">I shall madam.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e106280">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="27" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e106290">
            <head>Scene 27.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e106300">Enter the lady chastity, and the lady procurer.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106310" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106320">Madam, I am not come upon my own score, but upon a new one: for I am entreated, or rather commanded by a young gentleman to kiss your ladyship's hands, as from him who durst not come to do it himself without your leave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106330" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106340">Truly he shall never have leave from me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106350" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106360">He begs that your ladyship would give him leave to be your admiring servant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106370" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <pb facs="232" n="441"/>
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106380">He may admire without my leave; and I wish I had merits; worth admiring.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106390" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106400">By my troth, madam, he is a most sweet young gentleman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106410" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106420">Hath nature perfumed him, or art?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106430" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106440">Both, madam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106450" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106460">That's too much, and will be apt to give the headache.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106470" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106480">O madam, he is most desperately in love with your ladyship.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106490" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106500">Pray heaven, madam, he doth not hang himself before my door!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106510" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106520">I'faith madam, it is to be feared he will do some violent act upon himself, unless you pity him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106530" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106540">Is he in distress?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106550" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106560">As much as love can make him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106570" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106580">How should I help him, madam?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106590" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106600">Nothing can help him but Love's returns in kind embracements.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106610" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106620">Would you have me a married wife, embrace an amorous lover?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106630" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106640">O madam, stolen pleasures are sweet, and marriage is a cloak to hide Love's meetings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106650" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106660">And can it hide the sin from the gods, and the falsehood from my husband, as well as from the world? But let me tell you, the world is quick-sighted as to particulars, though blind as to the general, complaining against single crimes, yet never helps to mend them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106670" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106680">I'faith madam, the gods easily pardon natural faults, and husbands dare not spy them, at least not to divulge them; and the world censures all the virtuous as much as the wicked, and the chaste as much as the wanton; besides, you are excusable, being married to an ancient man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106690" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106700">Doth age deserve no love?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106710" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106720">I'faith little: for love wears out with time, and age wears out of love; and if you said you did love your husband, nobody would believe you: for who can think you that are young and fair, can love a man that's old?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106730" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106740">By heaven I never thought my husband old: for he doth appear to me to be just at maturity; adorned with all the graces.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106750" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106760">Surely you do not think his silver hair Apollo's locks!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106770" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106780">No; but I think them Pallas's his head-piece.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106790" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106800">Nor can you think his hollow eyes, that's sunk into his head, are Cupid's golden arrows?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106810" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106820">No; but I think them Minerva's Loom, which hath interweaved several objects, making various and most curious works of knowledge, and of wit, where judgement in the midst is placed, and understanding borders it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106830" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106840">And can you think his shoulder, bent by weak old age, are Cupid's. Bow?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106850" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106860">No; but I can think it's like a bank swelled out by generosity, to bear necessity's burdens on; or else a heap of noble deeds, falsed by heroic actions, whereon fame sits in triumph, and blows his praise abroad, that all the world may hear it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106870" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106880">I will never believe you can think the furrows in his face,<pb facs="233" n="442"/> ploughed up by time, as smooth as waters be when in a calm.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106890" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106900">No; but I can think them tracks or paths made by experience, in which walks prudence, fortitude, justice, and temperance: and though you strive to make my husband seem much older than he is, yet I believe that neither time nor age hath power over him: for to my sight his skin is as smooth as light, his eyes as darting as Apollo's beams, his body is as straight as Xerxes' wand, able to charm the youngest she, and turn her all to love; his strength is active, and his spirits quick, to carry arms, or sight his enemies; and for his brain, 'tis equally tempered, not burned with heat, nor frozen up with cold; nor are his sinews out of tune by slackened nerves, but just set to life's harmony, strength strings the cords, and health doth keep just time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106910" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106920">Ha, ha, ha, sweet lady, your love hath made him a most heavenly creature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106930" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106940">Foul devil, that seeks for to corrupt the marriage-bed with false dispraise, and flattering insinuations, carrying fond love's recommendations from ear to ear! Youth being credulous, they are soon received, which you perceiving, straight strive to sow in tender hearts loves amorous passions, from whence adultery doth grow, and vices do increase. You a lady, a bawd. O that honour, the mark of merit, should be placed on such base subjects as you are! Be gone, such bawds as you are not only able to disorder a private family, but to ruin a whole kingdom; you are worse than witches, and do more mischief.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e106950">Lady chastity goes out. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e106960">Lady procurer alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e106970" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e106980">O that I had that power, to make her husband so jealous, as he might hate her!</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e106990">Exit.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="28" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e107000">
            <head>Scene 28.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107010">Enter the lady Hypocondria, and sir William Lovewell.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107020" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocondria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107030">O husband, I am a dead woman: for all my side is numb, nay in a dead palsy, I cannot feel my arm.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107040" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107050">Heaven forbid: let me rub your arm.</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107060">He rubs her arm.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107070">But wife, if it were dead, you could not move it, and you can move it, can you not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107080" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocondria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107090">Yes, but very weakly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107100" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107110">Wrap it up with warm clothes, until such time as the doctor can be sent for. Come into your chamber, and I will send for the doctor straight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107120" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107130">No, pray do not send for the doctor now: for with your rubbing my arm, you have brought the lively spirits into it again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107140" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <pb facs="233" n="443"/>
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107150">I am glad of it; but pray keep your bed.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107160">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="29" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e107170">
            <head>Scene 29.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107180">Enter the lady jealousies waiting-gentlewoman, and her chambermaid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107190" who="A53060_12-gentlewoman">
              <speaker>Gentlewoman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107200">My lady doth not like her caudle: wherefore she will have a sack-posset made her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107210" who="A53060_12-chambermaid">
              <speaker>Chambermaid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107220">Not like it? why she eat a great porringer of it:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107230" who="A53060_12-gentlewoman">
              <speaker>Gentlewoman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107240">That's all one, my lady did not like it; and therefore you must make a sack-posset,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107250" who="A53060_12-chambermaid">
              <speaker>Chambermaid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107260">What fault found she with it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107270" who="A53060_12-gentlewoman">
              <speaker>Gentlewoman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107280">She did not express her particular dislike, but in the general.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107290" who="A53060_12-chambermaid">
              <speaker>Chambermaid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107300">Well, I shall make her a posset straight.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107310">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="30" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e107320">
            <head>Scene 30.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107330">Enter two servant-maids of the lady disagrees.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107340" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107350">Heaven be thanked, my master and lady are perfectly friends again: for she sits in his lap, and he kisses her very lovingly. Lord, what a disquietous house have we had!</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107360">Sir Humphry and his lady make a noise within, as being fallen out again. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107370" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107380">Hark, what noise is that?</p>
              <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107390">They harken, and hear the shovel and tongs slung about.</stage>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107400">Juno bless us, I think they'll fling the house out at the windows.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107410">The lady calls for help.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107420" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107430">Run, run Jane, they are fallen out again, and will kill each other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107440" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107450">O call the chaplin to part them: for we shall never do it: call him, call him.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107460">Exeunt maids in a frighted haste.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="31" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e107470">
            <pb facs="234" n="444"/>
            <head>Scene 31.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107480">Enter the lady Hypocondria's maid in a frighted haste: and enter Roger Trusty, sir William Lovewel's man.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107490" who="A53060_12-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107500">O trusty, where is my master? my lady is so ill, as we think she'll die: for she faith that she is in an apoplexy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107510" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107520">If she were in an apoplexy, she could not speak.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107530" who="A53060_12-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107540">Hold thy prating, fool: for hers is a speaking apoplexy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107550" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107560">You are a slut for calling me fool.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107570" who="A53060_12-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107580">You are a knave for calling me slut.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107590" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107600">Am I so? there's for you for calling me knave.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107610">He kicks her, she cries out; in comes more servants: then follows the lady Hypocondria running after them. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107620" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocondria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107630">What in the name of Juno is the matter? what thieves are entered? or is my house on fire?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107640" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107650">No madam, only Roger and Joan are beating one another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107660" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocondria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107670">May the devil beat them for frighting me so.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107680">Enter sir William Lovewell.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107690" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107700">My dear wife, what is the cause you sent for me in such haste?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107710" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocondria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107720">O husband, I was dying of an apoplexy, my spirits were stopped, and my brain was smothered in a cloud of gross vapours; but your man and my maid falling out, they fell a bearing each other, and she crying out for help, did so affright me, as I came running hither, thinking thieves had broken in, or fire had broken out of our house, which fright hath unstopped the sluice-passages, and dispersed the vapour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107730" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107740">I perceive a bad cause may sometimes produce a good effect, if their fight hath cured you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107750" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocondria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107760">Yes; but I will turn away my maid, for crying, and quarrelling, and making such a noise.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107770" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107780">That were unjust: for should the sick patient, that had been sick to death, when he was restored to health, banish the physician that restored him, without a fee? No, he ought to have his fee doubled or trebled, so you ought not only to keep your maid, but to double or triple her wages.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107790" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107800">It were more just to triple my wages than hers; for I was the cause of the outcry: for when I beat her, she roared, and her voice through her throat, made as great a rumbling noise, as a foul chimney set on fire, and in my conscience as much sooty phlegm fell from her head, as from a cook's chimney; and when she scolded, her words were so harsh, as they creek just so as when a door is taken off the hinges, which made my lady straight apprehend either fire, or thieves, or both.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107810" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107820">No, you deserve nothing, by reason a man ought not to strike a woman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107830" who="A53060_12-roger_trusty">
              <pb facs="234" n="441"/>
              <speaker>Roger trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107840">Why sir? she would sooner have been hanged about my neck, than have cried, if I had kissed her instead of kicking her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107850" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107860">Hold your prating, and learn to be civiller to women.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107870">Exeunt all but Roger and Joan.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107880" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107890">If I had kissed you, Joan, as I perceive my master would have had me done, you had been silent, and in your silence my lady would have died, and then my master had been a lusty widower, and a free wooer, and a fresh man, as one may say, where now he is bound to a sickly wife; and this is the reason my master would not increase my wages: which if I had kissed you, I had been enriched by my master's favour: wherefore Joan, I will kiss thee, but kick thee no more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107900" who="A53060_12-joan">
              <speaker>Joan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107910">Go hang yourself, it is too late now, you should have kissed me before.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107920">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A53060_12-e107930">
          <head>Act iv.</head>
          <div n="32" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e107940">
            <head>Scene. 32.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e107950">Enter the waiting-woman and chambermaid of the lady jealousy.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107960" who="A53060_12-gentlewoman">
              <speaker>Gentlewoman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107970">You are a strange wench, to make the posset-curd so tough, that now my lady hath eat it, it lies so hard, so hard in her stomach, as it cannot digest.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e107980" who="A53060_12-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e107990">Tough, say you? I am sure to my taste it was as tender as cream.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108000" who="A53060_12-gentlewoman">
              <speaker>Gentlewoman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108010">Well, in my lady's stomach it proves as hard as stone: wherefore you must go and burn some claret-wine for her, with cloves, mace, and nutmegs, and make it very sweet with fine loaf-sugar, presently, presently.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108020" who="A53060_12-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108030">But if my lady hath one meat after another so quick, she will not be able to hold all in her stomach, by reason her stomach must of necessity overflow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108040" who="A53060_12-gentlewoman">
              <speaker>Gentlewoman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108050">If the wine make her stomach to overflow, it will be like washing the mouth, and rubbing the teeth after meat, the which will scour her stomach clean.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108060" who="A53060_12-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108070">Nay, if the stomach be not scoured and cleansed sometimes, it would be very foul, by reason it is so often used.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108080" who="A53060_12-gentlewoman">
              <speaker>Gentlewoman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108090">And if it be scoured too often, it will wear it out, as the learned say: but Nan, go your ways and burn the wine, otherwise my lady will chide.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108100">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="33" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e108110">
            <pb facs="235" n="446"/>
            <head>Scene 33.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108120">Enter monsieur amorous, and the lady procurer, as visitants to the lady wanton.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108130" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Lady procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108140">Well monsieur amorous, now I have brought you to this lady, I will leave you to make your compliments, the whilst I will go, madam, to your woman, to mistress Watcher, and chide her for not sending me that you promised me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108150" who="A53060_12-wanton">
              <speaker>Wanton.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108160">She is much ashamed for her forgetfulness, and had rather die than see you.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108170">Exit lady procurer.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108180">Monsieur amorous seems to stagger, as being weak and faint, almost ready to fall into a swoon; then takes his handkerchief, and wipes his face, as if he did sweat. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108190" who="A53060_12-wanton">
              <speaker>Wanton.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108200">Are not you well sir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108210" who="A53060_12-amorous">
              <speaker>Amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108220">A sudden passion hath surrounded my heart, and hath surprised my senses, sending out cold damp sweats over all my body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108230" who="A53060_12-wanton">
              <speaker>Wanton.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108240">Sir, will you drink any cordial water?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108250">He kisses her hand.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108260" who="A53060_12-amorous">
              <speaker>Amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108270">Lady, it was your beauty that struck me with a trembling fear, and made my spirits faint; but this delicious kiss that I have taken from your hand, restores me more, and gives me greater strength than all the spirits chemists can extract.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108280" who="A53060_12-wanton">
              <speaker>Wanton.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108290">I perceive now it was a dissembling fit, and not a real sickness.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108300" who="A53060_12-amorous">
              <speaker>Amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108310">Misconstrue not my admirations and affections, which do adore and worship you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108320" who="A53060_12-wanton">
              <speaker>Wanton.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108330">If we women should believe the words of men, they would make us more conceited of ourselves than yet we are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108340" who="A53060_12-amorous">
              <speaker>Amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108350">There are not thoughts to equal your great beauty, nor words for to express it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108360">Enter the lady procurer in great haste. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108370" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108380">Madam, madam, your husband is coming, your husband is coming.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108390" who="A53060_12-wanton">
              <speaker>Wanton.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108400">For Venus' sake stay by me, madam, that my husband may see I have a woman in my company.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108410">Enter sir Thomas cuckold, sir Thomas and Monsieur amorous congee to one another. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108420" who="A53060_12-amorous">
              <speaker>Amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108430">Sir, my ambition grew impatient to be acquainted, and to render myself, and offer my service to you sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108440" who="A53060_12-cuckold">
              <speaker>Cuckold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108450">Sir, I am your most humble servant, and shall strive by all the ways I can to appear worthy your favours.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108460"><pb facs="235" n="447"/>The ladies speak familiarly. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108470" who="A53060_12-wanton">
              <speaker>Wanton.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108480">Lord, lady procurer, how are you dressed today in a most careless fashion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108490" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108500">It is the mode, it is the mode to go undressed,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108510" who="A53060_12-cuckold">
              <speaker>Cuckold.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108520">Wife, this is not a fit room to entertain this noble gentleman, sir, will you be pleased to walk into another room?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108530" who="A53060_12-amorous">
              <speaker>Amorous.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108540">All rooms are fine sir, where you and your virtuous lady are.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108550">Exeunt sir Thomas cuckold and monsieur amorous.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108560" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108570">I'faith if I had not come running in before your husband, he had catched you.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108580">Lady wanton claps the lady procurer on the clothes. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108590" who="A53060_12-wanton">
              <speaker>Wanton.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108600">I'faith procurer, thou art such another lady-wag, as all the town cannot match thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108610" who="A53060_12-procurer">
              <speaker>Procurer.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108620">I was, I was, but now I am grown old, I am grown old; but I was born to do good offices.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108630">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="34" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e108640">
            <head>Scene 34.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108650">Enter two maids of the lady poverty's.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108660" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108670">I wonder my lady is able to stay in the room with my master: his vomiting hath so fumed the room, as there is such a stink, that by my troth I am almost strangled with the smell of the corrupted drink.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108680" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108690">Alas poor lady! she is forced to stay for fear he should be outrageous in his drunken humour: for if she stirs or speaks, he swears as if he would draw the devils out of hell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108700" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108710">Hell is not so bad, as to be where he is now he is drunk.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108720">Enter another maid.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108730" who="A53060_12-yyyy_3">
              <speaker>3 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108740">My master is asleep, and my lady would have you make less noise, and not to talk so loud, for fear you should awake him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108750" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108760">If he be asleep, we may make what noise we will or can make, he will not wake until such time as the fume or vapour of wine be out of his head, no sound can enter: but I wonder my lady will take such care of him, when he hath no respect to her, but transforms himself from man to beast every day; indeed she sees him only a beast, not a man: for before he is wholly sober, he rises to go to a tavern to be drunk again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108770" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108780">If my master transforms himself into a beast ere that he comes to my lady, he imitates Jove: for he transformed himself into a bull for the sake of fair Europa. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108790" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108800">But not into a drunken roaring bull as my master is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108810" who="A53060_12-yyyy_3">
              <speaker>3 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108820">I'faith if I were my lady, I would hold by his horns, and then let him roar, and drink and whore as much as he will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108830" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <pb facs="236" n="444"/>
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108840">Yes, so she might chance to be drenched in a bathing-tub, as Europa in the sea.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108850">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="35" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e108860">
            <head>Scene 35.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108870">Enter Nan the lady jealousies chambermaid, and her master sir Henry courtly meets her, and kisses her. Enter the lady jealousy, and sees him. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108880" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Lady jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108890">So husband, I perceive Nan is in your favour.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e108900">Nan runs out of the room. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108910" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108920">I'faith wife Nan is a careful and industrious wench! for she strives to serve us both, for she makes you candles and feeds me with kisses.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108930" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Lady jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108940">Or rather husband you feed Nan, and Nan feeds me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108950" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108960">Faith the truth is I need you both.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108970" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Lady jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e108980">But Nan hath the greatest share, that makes her so proud, and I so sickly; but since you are so liberal to her, and so sparing to me, I will board elsewhere, and so as I may carve where I like best.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e108990" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109000">Sure wife you will not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109010" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Lady jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109020">Surely husband I will do my endeavour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109030" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109040">What to be a whore?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109050" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Lady jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109060">Yes, if being a whore will make you a cuckold.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109070">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="36" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e109080">
            <head>Scene. 36.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109090">Enter the lady Hypocondria and her maid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109100" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Lady Hypocondria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109110">My husband hath been a long time abroad, pray Jove he be safe, if he should chance to have a quarrel and fight, a hundred to one but he is killed: for otherwise he would have come home; do you think he is well Joan?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109120" who="A53060_12-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109130">You need not fear, for my master is of so civil a behaviour, and of so sweet a disposition, as he can have no enemies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109140" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Lady Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109150">O but he is a man that is very valiant, and one that is very sensible of disgrace, and affronts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109160" who="A53060_12-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109170">Truly I believe you have no reason to fear.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109180" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Lady Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109190">Do you but believe so, nay then you doubt, and therefore I know he is killed and I will go and find out the murderer, and kill him myself.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109200">The lady Hypocondria offers to run out of the room, as in a frighted passion, the maid stops her. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109210" who="A53060_12-maid">
              <pb facs="236" n="449"/>
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109220">My noble lady, do not run in this passion: for all the idle men, and women, and boys, and girls will run after you, as thinking you mad; for they make no difference betwixt melancholy, and madness.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109230" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Lady Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109240">I am not able to overcome this fear, I shall die.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109250" who="A53060_12-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109260">Pray stay and send out one of our men to inquire where he is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109270" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Lady Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109280">Call Roger trusty. </p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109290">The maid goes out. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109300">The lady alone. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109310" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Lady Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109320">O you defendant gods assist my husband.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109330">Enter Joan, and Roger Trusty.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109340" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Lady Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109350">Trusty go presently, and seek out your master, and bring me word where he is, and how he doth, and be sure if you see a grim looked fellow near him, that you stir not from your master, but wait upon him home, for fear some treachery should beset him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109360" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109370">Who shall bring you word of his health, or sickness, life, or death?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109380" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Lady Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109390">Death do you say, oh you have heard he is killed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109400" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109410">By Pluto I have heard no such thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109420" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Lady Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109430">Why do you talk of death then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109440" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109450">Because you send me to know whether he be dead, or alive.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109460" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Lady Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109470">That is true, wherefore let one of the footboys go along with you to bring me an answer; but be sure you stay with your master.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109480" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109490">I shall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109500" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Lady Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109510">Make all the haste you can to find him.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109520">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="37" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e109530">
            <head>Scene 37.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109540">Enter sir Henry Sage, and the lady chastity.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109550" who="A53060_12-henry_courtly">
              <speaker>Sir Hen. Sage.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109560">Is the lady procurer a bawd say you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109570" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Lady chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109580">A perfect one I think: for she pleaded as earnestly, as lawyers for a fee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109590" who="A53060_12-henry_courtly">
              <speaker>Sir Hen. Sage.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109600">No doubt, but she hath as much reason: for sure she doth it for gain, not out of love to wicked baseness; but I believe poverty persuades her, or rather enforces her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109610" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109620">No surely, it is an inborn, or at least an inbred baseness: for neither death, nor torments can enforce, nor riches, nor preferrments allure a noble mind to such base acts; but some are so unworthy, or rather wicked, as to delight to entice, and to pervert all they can get acquaintance with.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109630" who="A53060_12-henry_courtly">
              <speaker>Sir Hen. Sage.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109640">And some do it to hide their own faults, thinking to bury them under the vices of others, or smother them in the press of a multitude: but let me advise you not to entertain her company any more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109650" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109660">I believe she will not visit me again.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109670">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="38" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e109680">
            <pb facs="237" n="450"/>
            <head>Scene 38.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109690">Enter the lady sprightly, and one of her woman. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109700" who="A53060_12-sprightly">
              <speaker>Lady sprightly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109710">Lord, lord, this nasty love, or rather this beastly lust that doth corrupt all good manners, as gentle civility, free society, lawful recreations, honest friendship, natural affections; it cuts off the feet of obedience, it breaks the knees of duty, it wounds the breast of fidelity, it pulls out the heart of loyalty; it turns away prudence, it banishes temperance, and murder's justice; it breaks peace and makes wars, and turns arms into petticoats. O sweet pure chastity, how amiable thou art, how beautiful thou appearest in women, how heroic in men: for chaste women have such innocent thoughts, such pure, clean, clear, white immaculate minds, such modest countenances, such gentle behaviour, such civil discourses, such noble actions, such discreet entertainments, such cautionary recreations; otherwise they are bold, impudent, rude, flaunting, ranting, romping women: also chastity in men makes them heroic, for propriety, justice constancy, and natural and honest love is the basis, pillars, or foundation whereon true valour is built, when amorous affections make men effeminate, causing them to cast away their hard iron arms to lie in the soft arms of beauty, and stops their cares from loud alarms, with charming notes of music, it takes them from being masters of themselves, and others, and makes them become servants, and slaves; from commanding an army to be commanded by single women, by whom he is checked like a schoolboy, lead like a dog in a string, as after his mistress's humours, her frowns make him crouch like a cur, her smiles make him skip, and make face like a jackanapes , and their beastly appetites make them so rude, and wild, as they regard no civility of behaviour, no gentleness of disposition, no constancy of affection, they keep no friendship, constancy, or vows, they break all decent customs, and disobey all honest laws; but this is a theme too wild to be preached on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109720" who="A53060_12-gentlewoman">
              <speaker>Gentlewoman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109730">Why madam, my lord your father may be a very chaste man although he lieth with his maid, if he hath made her his wife before he made her his bedfellow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109740" who="A53060_12-sprightly">
              <speaker>Lady sprightly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109750">His wife? he scorns the thought, and hates the act?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109760" who="A53060_12-gentlewoman">
              <speaker>Gentlewoman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109770">Pardon me madam, if I offer to lay a wager of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109780" who="A53060_12-sprightly">
              <speaker>Lady sprightly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109790">Are you so confident that you dare lay a wager?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109800" who="A53060_12-gentlewoman">
              <speaker>Gentlewoman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109810">If you inquire more I believe you will find it to be true.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109820">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A53060_12-e109830">
          <pb facs="237" n="451"/>
          <head>Act v.</head>
          <div n="39" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e109840">
            <head>Scene 39.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109850">Enter the lady chastity, and her woman gives her a letter. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109860">Lady reads the letter.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109870" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Lady chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109880">Who brought this letter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109890" who="A53060_12-woman">
              <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109900">A kind of a gentleman servingman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109910" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109920">Pray receive no more letters from that man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109930" who="A53060_12-woman">
              <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109940">He said he would come in the evening to receive an answer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109950" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109960">If he comes, tell him it needs no answer.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e109970">Enter sir Henry Sage.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e109980" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e109990">Husband, will you read a love letter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110000" who="A53060_12-henry_courtly">
              <speaker>Sir Hen. Sage.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110010">From whence comes it, and to whom is it sent?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110020" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110030">You will soon find from whence it comes, and to whom it is sent.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e110040">He reads it.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110050" who="A53060_12-henry_courtly">
              <speaker>Sir Hen. Sage.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110060">So wife, I perceive I am in danger to be made a cuckold.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110070" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110080">Doth the letter beget your faith to that opinion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110090" who="A53060_12-henry_courtly">
              <speaker>Sir Hen. Sage.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110100">But the praises, and professions this letter brings you, raises scruples, and those scruples beget controversies, and those controversies may in time make a convert.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110110" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110120">Rather a pervert husband; but be you constant, and I will warrant you safe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110130" who="A53060_12-henry_courtly">
              <speaker>Sir Hen. Sage.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110140">But youth and beauty wife, when they plead, are greater bawds, and have a more persuasive power than the lady procurer. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110150" who="A53060_12-chastity">
              <speaker>Chastity.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110160">Truly all three, as beauty, youth, or the lady procurer, rather than persuade me, would divert me, had I a wanton nature; as first, for the lady procurer her baseness appeared such as made me hate myself for being of the same sex she was of, and grieved me to see the follies of mankind, the one appearing like a devil, the other like a beast, so seemed the lover and the bawd, when men have reason to govern, as much as appetite to persuade, the one proceeding from the soul, the other from the body; besides, virtue is the natural complexion of the soul, not vice: for vice is bred, not born in man: as for youth, it is so fantastical, extravagant, wild, and self-opinionated, doing such ridiculous actions, putting themselves into such affected postures, as I might be as soon enamoured with a jackanapes: besides, the discourses of youth are so flashy, as it gives the hearers no relish; and their judgement is so shallow, and their understanding so misty, as when reason discourses with them, it is apt to be lost in the darkness of ignorance. Lastly, for beauty in men, it is worse than unhandsomeness in women: for an ill-favoured woman seems masculine, as if she had an heroic spirit,<pb facs="238" n="452"/> though she were a coward; to have a judicious understanding, though she should be a fool; to be chaste, although she were wanton; when on the contrary, a beautiful man appears effeminate, foolish, and cowardly, when (Perchance) he may be wise and valiant, yet 'tis beauty makes him seem otherwise; and (For the most part) a beautiful man is more nice and curious about his person, as in his clothing, dressing, trimming, perfuming, powdering, curling, and some will pomate and pain themselves, all which seems to me preposterous to men, insomuch as I could as soon be amorously affected with my own sex, as those that are accounted beautiful men; and you might sooner be jealous of age than youth, with a sunburnt face and a withered skin, than a face that looks as if it had not seen the sun, or the sun it, nor felt the nipping frost nor parching wind; but I hope you have a better opinion of yourself than to be jealous, as to think I can like any man better, or so well as you: and if you have not so good an opinion of me, us to believe I am constantly honest, yet I have such an assurance of myself, as to know I am not liable to be corrupted, and I am so chaste, as I have not a thought subject to fully the purity of my chaste mind and honest heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110170" who="A53060_12-sage">
              <speaker>Sage.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110180">I believe you.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e110190">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="40" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e110200">
            <head>Scene 40.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e110210">Enter Roger Trusty, as to his master sir William Lovewell.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110220" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110230">What is the matter, Roger, that you are come?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110240" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110250">An't please your worship, my lady hath sent me to know how your worship is in health.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110260" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110270">Why very well. How does she?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110280" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110290">She's well, but that she's afraid your worship's killed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110300" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110310">If I were killed, I were passed sickness or health. But who should kill me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110320" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110330">Nay that her ladyship could not guess.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110340" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110350">Return home to your lady, and tell her I shall be with her within an hour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110360" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110370">I dare not leave your worship: for she hath sent me to guard and protect you from all harm, and to fight in your quarrel, and hath sent one of the footboys to bring her word how your worship doth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110380" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110390">Go you and return back, and tell your lady from me, that honesty, civility, and courage, is a sufficient guard and protection; if not, than my sword, and my skill to use it, will fight, and maintain my quarrel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110400" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110410">If I should go home with that message, you would find her dead at your return.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110420" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110430">Why so?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110440" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110450">Why, sir, the very name of a sword will kill her: I wonder your worship should forget it, and knows her humour so well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110460" who="A53060_12-lovewell">
              <speaker>Lovewell.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110470">Yes, I know she hath a sweet humour, and a tender nature: wherefore return home without any more prating, and tell her that I am safe, and in very good health. Run all the way.</p>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="41" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e110480">
            <pb facs="238" n="453"/>
            <head>Scene 41.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e110490">Enter sir Edward courtly, and his wife the lady jealousy.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110500" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110510">Wife, you may win me from the imbracing of other women, if you have discretion and chastity answerable to your wit and beauty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110520" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110530">But I perceive men love variety; and if so, had I the beauty of Venus, and the wit of Mercury, the wisdom of Pallas, and the chastity of Diana, you would be like Jupiter still, and make love to mortals, which are common wenches: but do not think I will do as Juno did, as to torment myself with vexing and fretting for that which I cannot mend or help; but I will please myself with variety as much as you, and in the clouds of night will hide myself and lovers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110540" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110550">I'faith wife I shall dissolve your clouds into showers of tears, and strike your lover with my thunderbolt, which is my poniard: but wife, let me advise you to be as you ought to be, a good wife: for, as I will not encroach upon my wife's prerogative, so wife, you shall not encroach upon mine, being your husband.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110560" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110570">You will not give me leave to have the variety of courting servants; yet you will take the liberty of variety to court several mistresses.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110580" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110590">It is part of my prerogative.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110600" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110610">What, to have whores?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110620" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110630">Yes; and its part of the wife's duty which she owes to her husband, to be content.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110640" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110650">She is not bound to that duty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110660" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110670">She is bound to obey all duties: for the fundamental laws in marriage, are for the husband to rule, the wife to obey; the husband to cherish, the wife to love; the husband to be valiant to defend and protect her, the wife to be chaste, to suffer and submit; and when I leave to command, you may leave for to obey; when I leave to cherish, you may leave to love; when I am a coward, you may be a whore: for when I basely part with my honour, you are not bound to keep it; but until I do part with my honour, I charge you to keep it as you would do your life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110680" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110690">By these rules married men are not bound to be constant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110700" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110710">Yes, to the sex, but not to his wife, in the case of amorous embracements: for a husband hath liberty for variety, but the wife is refrained to one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110720" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110730">These are laws that neither the gods nor nature have prescribed, but only impartial men which make what laws they please.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110740" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110750">Nature taught men to make them for propriety-sake, and gods command men to keep them, and that men should do their endeavour to force the effeminate sex to obey and practise them strictly, for the sake of civil commonwealths, wherein the gods are best served.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110760" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <speaker>Jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110770">But women are not such fools, to be forced, such asses, to bear such intolerable burdens of troubles, vexations, crosses, and neglects, from their husbands and their whores.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110780" who="A53060_12-courtly">
              <speaker>Courtly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110790">Women are best pleased when they are made asses.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110800" who="A53060_12-jealousie">
              <pb facs="239" n="454"/>
              <speaker>Jealousie.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110810">Indeed husbands make asses of their wives; but in faith you shall not make one of me.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e110820">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="42" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e110830">
            <head>Scene 42.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e110840">Enter two maids of the lady poverties:</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110850" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110860">My poor lady sits so melancholy, and sighs and weeps, as it grieves my soul to see her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110870" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110880">Can you blame her, when she and her children must go a-begging , or sit and starve: for my master hath sold most of his estate at several times, and hath spent the money in drink and whores, and hath lost it at play: and now he hath sent for all his plate to play away, her jewels were pawned before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110890" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110900">But when all is lost and spent, he will be forced to be a good husband.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110910" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110920">When all is gone, it will not be in his power: for none can be good husbands as concerning husbandry, when they have nothing to husband.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110930" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110940">The best of it is, he will suffer as much as my lady.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110950" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110960">No faith: for he will rook, and shark, and cheat, and bawd, to get a poor living, when she, poor lady, must work hard for her living.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110970" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e110980">Alas she cannot work.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e110990" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111000">Then she must get some acquaintance, and turn lady bawd, and show ladies how to dress themselves, and sell paint, pomatums, wax-gloves, oiled-masks, and the like commodities privately; or else she must pretend skill in surgery or physic, and to make plasters, salves, ointments, and the like, or make cordial powders, or cordial waters, and other waters and powders; then persuade old ladies to take thereof, telling them those will make them look as young as one of fifteen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111010" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111020">But those things require cost to make them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111030" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111040">No i'faith, there requires not much charge: for paint, pomatum, and the like commodities, will sell at any price, and will be made at a little charge: and for salves and plasters, and oils and ointments, hogs-grease, turpentine, and bole-armonike, serves for all sorts of those things, and bread, and meal, and milk, and some chopped herbs, and salad-oil, serves for all poultices; and for cordial powders, some hot seeds, as aniseed, caroway-seed, coriander-seed, and the like seeds, with some powder of licorice, and beaten spices, with some sorts of gums, as Mastick, myrrh, and the like, will serve their turn.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111050" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111060">But cordial powders are made of pearl, amber, coral, and the like.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111070" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111080">I'faith a little powder of posts serves as well: for they cannot be distinguished by their taste; but howsoever, it is but putting a grain of musk and ambergrease, and instead of amber, coral, and pearl, 'tis but powdering some shaved hartshorn and chiny, and they will serve as well, and (Perchance work as good effects:) indeed cordial waters are chargeable to<pb facs="239" n="455"/> make: for they require fire to distil them; but there is some remedy for that: for it is but buying several sorts of ordinary hot waters, and mix them together, so as no one of the waters may predominate in taste, and it will pass for rare extracted spirits, so as she shall never need to venture to distil, or lay out money, but just for the present to fetch it from those that sell aquavitae, rosasolus, and the like, which may be had at a cheap rate, and she may sell them at a great price.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111090" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111100">But what shall become of the poor young children?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111110" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111120">Why, he rooking, and she bawding, may make a shift to feed them with bread: and those two trades will never fail as long as mankind lasts: for whoring and knaving will last till doomsday, or for ever.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111130" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111140">But Ursly, my lady hath given us warning to be gone: wherefore we must seek out new services.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111150" who="A53060_12-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111160">My lady is so good a lady, as I wish I could serve her so as to maintain her, since she is not able to maintain a servant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111170" who="A53060_12-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1 maid. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111180">But since we cannot maintain her, nor she us, we must leave her.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e111190">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="43" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e111200">
            <head>Scene 43.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e111210">Enter Roger Trusty to his lady all in a sweat with running: she seeing him come in such haste, cries out. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111220" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocondria.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111230">O help me, help me, you merciful powers, to destroy me, and let me not outlive my husband.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111240" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111250">'Tis like the gods will hear your prayers: for ten to one my master outlives you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111260" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111270">Why, is he alive?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111280" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111290">Yes, and alive's like.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111300" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111310">What makes you sweat so?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111320" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111330">To bring you the good news of his well-being, and to prove the old proverb a liar, which says, bad news hath wings, and good news no legs. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111340" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111350">Where did you meet your master?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111360" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111370">In Westminster-hall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111380" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111390">How did he look?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111400" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111410">Healthful and well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111420" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111430">Did he seem angry or pleased, merry or sad?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111440" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111450">Why he neither seemed angry nor pleased, merry nor sad, which I wondered at: for in lawyer's courts, and places of judicature, I never saw any face but was clothed with a merry green countenance, or a sad black countenance, or a red choleric face, or a pale malicious face; but my master's face appeared like naked truth, and clean temperance, washed white with innocency; being plump with health, and smooth with plenty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111460" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111470">But why did you leave him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111480" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111490">Why he commanded me so to do, and to run every step, to tell you he was coming home, and I chose as the wisest to run, although<pb facs="240" n="456"/> I sweat for it, than stay and have a broken head.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111500" who="A53060_12-hypocondria">
              <speaker>Hypocon.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111510">Well, I give you here a twenty-shilling-piece to dry your sweat with a cup of sack.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e111520">Exi lady.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111530" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111540">May all my labours be rewarded thus.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111550" who="A53060_12-joan">
              <speaker>Maid Joan.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111560">I perceive you take the gift as a due reward, and not as my lady's bounty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111570" who="A53060_12-trusty">
              <speaker>Trusty.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111580">Hold your prating: what need we thank the gods, if saints merit heaven?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e111590">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="44" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_12-e111600">
            <head>Scene 44.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_12-e111610">Enter the lady sprightly, and the lord widower her father. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111620" who="A53060_12-sprightly">
              <speaker>Lady sprightly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111630">Sir, I desire you would not think me undutiful to ask you a question: for I hope I am not so much in your disfavour, as not to resolve me, since it is in your power.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111640" who="A53060_12-widower">
              <speaker>Widower.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111650">Well, what is't that you would know?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111660" who="A53060_12-sprightly">
              <speaker>Sprightly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111670">Whether you are married, or not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111680" who="A53060_12-widower">
              <speaker>Widower.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111690">What if I am? Marriage is lawful.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111700" who="A53060_12-sprightly">
              <speaker>Sprightly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111710">Yes sir, but I doubt whether it be honourable or not: for 'tis said you are married to my chambermaid Dol subtlety. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111720" who="A53060_12-widower">
              <speaker>Widower.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111730">Perchance I am.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111740" who="A53060_12-sprightly">
              <speaker>Sprightly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111750">Then I desire your lordship will let me marry too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111760" who="A53060_12-widower">
              <speaker>Widower.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111770">With all my heart, and I shall do my part towards thy marriage; but to whom would you be married?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111780" who="A53060_12-sprightly">
              <speaker>Sprightly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111790">Your butler sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111800" who="A53060_12-widower">
              <speaker>Widower.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111810">Out upon thee base girl, would you marry a tapster?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111820" who="A53060_12-sprightly">
              <speaker>Sprightly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111830">Why sir, a tapster is as good as a pisspot emptier; besides, they say you have done the fellow wrong: for she (They say) was his by promise, and if conscience hath right, he ought to have her; and perhaps, did not ambition come in the way, affection might prevail: wherefore to gratify him, you ought in justice to bestow me upon him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111840" who="A53060_12-widower">
              <speaker>Widower.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111850">Well, because you shall not marry my butler, I will not marry your maid: for the truth is, I never had so low a thought. But let me tell you, it is in the way of disobedience to question a father's actions, and a presumption for a child to think their father is not wise enough to govern himself; besides, children were ingrateful to parents, to desire that from them, which they cannot, or will not keep to themselves, as neither to suffer a father to marry, or keep a mistress: do children think a father is bound to so many children, and no more?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111860" who="A53060_12-sprightly">
              <speaker>Sprightly.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111870">Sir, I dare answer for the part of children, that they would be well content that their father should have mistresses, but they would be unwilling and grieved that their fathers should be their mistress's slave, whereby they incaptivate their children, or ruin their estates.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_12-e111880" who="A53060_12-widower">
              <speaker>Widower.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_12-e111890">Well then inquire no more after any mistress I shall have, until you are incaptivated.</p>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A53060_12-e111900">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A53060_12"><item xml:id="A53060_12-chastity" n="31">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-chastity</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">31</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A53060_12-hypocondria" n="29">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-hypocondria</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">29</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-yyyy_1" n="27">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">27</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-trusty" n="24">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-trusty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">24</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-inconstant" n="22">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-inconstant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">22</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-procurer" n="22">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-procurer</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">22</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-yyyy_2" n="22">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-yyyy_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">22</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-lovewell" n="20">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-lovewell</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">20</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-lord" n="20">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-lord</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">20</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-disguise" n="18">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-disguise</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">18</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-jealousie" n="17">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-jealousie</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">17</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-courtly" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-courtly</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-forsaken" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-forsaken</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-briget" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-briget</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-maid" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-maid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-hymphrey_disagree</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-sprightly" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-sprightly</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-gentleman" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-gentleman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-gentlewoman" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-gentlewoman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-disagree" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-disagree</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-subtilty" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-subtilty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-wanton" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-wanton</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-henry_courtly" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-henry_courtly</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-skipper" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-skipper</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-lady" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-lady</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-widower" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-widower</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-dotard" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-dotard</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-amorous" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-amorous</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-sage" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-sage</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-hearty" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-hearty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-adviser" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-adviser</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-francis_inconstant" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-francis_inconstant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-servant" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-servant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-thrifty" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-thrifty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-spendall" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-spendall</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-chambermaid" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-chambermaid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-doll_subtilty" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-doll_subtilty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-man" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-man</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-woman" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-woman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-doctor" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-doctor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-yyyy_3" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-yyyy_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-cuckold" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-cuckold</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-joan" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-joan</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-james_hearty" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-james_hearty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-doll" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-doll</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-friend" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-friend</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-roger_trusty" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-roger_trusty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-thomas_cuckold" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-thomas_cuckold</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_12-new_mistris" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_12-new_mistris</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

