<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A19837">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Vision of the Twelve Goddesses (The Masque at Hampton Court) <date type="creation_date">1604</date></title>
        <author>Daniel, Samuel</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nayoon Ahn</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A19837.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The true discription of a royall masque. Presented at Hampton Court, vpon Sunday night, being the eight of Ianuary. 1604. And personated by the Queenes most excellent Majestie, attended by eleuen ladies of honour.</title>
            <author>Daniel, Samuel, 1562-1619.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>8 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2005 December (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99852342</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 6264.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 207(a).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">17658</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19837</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The true discription of a royall masque. Presented at Hampton Court, vpon Sunday night, being the eight of Ianuary. 1604. And personated by the Queenes most excellent Majestie, attended by eleuen ladies of honour.</title>
            <author>Daniel, Samuel, 1562-1619.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[14] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by Edward Allde, and are to be solde at the Long Shoppe, adjoyning vnto S. Mildreds Church in the Poultrye,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1604.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Anonymous. By Samuel Daniel.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>An unauthorized edition according to the epistle in STC 6265.--STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-B4 (-A1, blank?).</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Masques -- Early works to 1800.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A19837-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A19837-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A19837-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A19837-e100040">The true description of a royal masque. </p>
        <p xml:id="A19837-e100050">Presented at Hampton court, upon Sunday night, being the eight of January. 1604.</p>
        <p xml:id="A19837-e100060">And personated by the Queen's most excellent majesty, attended by eleven ladies of honour.</p>
        <p xml:id="A19837-e100070">London printed by Edward Allde, and are to be sold at the long shop, adjoining unto s. Mildred's church in the poultry. 1604.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A19837-e100080">
      <div type="masque" xml:id="A19837-e100090">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>The true description of a royal masque. Presented at Hampton court upon Sunday night being the eight day of January. 1604.</head>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A19837-e100100">
          <stage xml:id="A19837-e100110">The night apparelled in a black vesture set with stars coming from below, and approaching near unto the temple erected toward the upper end of the hall: wakens her son Somnus that there lies sleeping in a cave; with this speech.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19837-e100120" who="A19837-night">
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100130">Awake dark sleep, rouse thee from out thy cave;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100140">Thy mother night, that bred thee in her womb,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100150">And fed thee first with silence and with ease,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100160">Doth here thy shadowed operations crave. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100170">And therefore wake my son, awake and come:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100180">Strike with thy horny wand, the spirits of these</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100190">That here expect some pleasing novelties;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100200">And make their slumber to beget strange sights. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100210"><pb facs="3"/>Strange visions and unusual properties,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100220">Unseen of latter ages, ancient rites;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100230">Of gifts divine, wrapped up in mysteries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100240">Make this to seem a temple in their sight:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100250">Whose main support, holy religion, frame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100260">And wisdom, courage, temperance and right:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100270">Make seem the pillars that sustain the same,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100280">Shadow some sibyl to attend the rites;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100290">And to describe the power that shall resort,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100300">With the interpretation of the benefits</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100310">They bring in clouds, and what they do import,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100320">Yet make them to protend the true desire</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100330">Of those that wish them, waking real things;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100340">Whilst I will hovering here aloof retire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100350">And cover all things with my sable wings. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A19837-e100360" who="A19837-somnus">
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100370">Some. Dear mother night, I your commandment</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100380">Obey, and dreams t'interpret dreams, will make</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100390">As waking curiosity is wont. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100400">Though better dreams asleep, the dreams awake</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100410">And this white horny wand shall work the deed:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100420">Whose power, doth figures of the light present,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100430">When from this sable radius doth proceed</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100440">Naught but confused dark shows to no intent:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100450">And therefore go bright visions, entertain</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100460">All round about, whilst I'll to sleep again. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A19837-e100470">
          <pb facs="3"/>
          <stage xml:id="A19837-e100480">Iris the messenger of the goddesses, descending from the mountain where they were assembled, decked in the colour of the rainbow, speaks as followeth.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19837-e100490" who="A19837-iris">
            <p xml:id="A19837-e100500">I the daughter of wonder, now made the messenger of power; here descended, to signify the coming of a celestial presence of goddesses, determined this fair temple of peace, with holy hands and devout desires, have dedicated to unity and concord: and leaving to themselves in Ouidos Ida Paphos their ancient delighting places of Greece and Asia, now made the seats of barbarism, and spoil, vouchsafe to take their recreation, here, upon the western mount of mighty Brittany, the land of civil music and of rest: and are pleased to appear in the selfsame figures, wherein antiquity hath formerly clothed them; and as they have been cast in the imagination of pity, who hath given mortal shapes to the gifts and effects of an eternal power: for that<pb facs="4"/> those beautiful characters of sense were easier to be read, than their mystical ideas, dispersed in that wide and incomprehensible volume of nature. And well have mortal men apparelled all the virtues, all the graces, all blessings, with that shape wherewith themselves are most delighted, and which work the best motions, and best represent the beauty of heavenly powers. And therefore, reverend prophetess, who here attendest upon the devotions of this place, prepare thyself for those rites that pertain to thy function, and the honour of such deities. And to the end thou mayst have a fore-notion what powers, and who they are that come; take here this prospective, and herein note and tell what thou seest: for well mayst thou there observe their shadows, but their presence will bereave thee of all, save admiration and amazement. For who can look upon such powers and speak? And so I leave thee.</p>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A19837-e100510">
          <pb facs="4"/>
          <stage xml:id="A19837-e100520">Sybilla decked as a nun, in black upon white, having received this message, and the prospective, useth these words.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19837-e100530" who="A19837-sybilla">
            <p xml:id="A19837-e100540">What have I seen? Where am I? Or do I see at all? or am I anywhere ? What? was this Iris the messenger of Juno, or else, but a fantasma or imagination? Will the divine goddesses vouchsafe to visit this poor temple? Shall I be blessed to entertain so great powers? It can be but a dream; yet such great powers have blessed as humble roofs, and use it of no other respect, than their own great favours to shine where they will. But what prospective is this? or what shall I herein see? O admirable powers! what sights are these?</p>
          </sp>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A19837-e100550">
            <pb facs="5"/>
            <head>Juno.</head>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100560">First, here imperial Juno in her chair,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100570">With sceptre of command, for kingdom's large:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100580">Ascends, all clad in colours of the air,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100590">Crowned with bright stars, to signify her charge. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A19837-e100600">
            <head>Pallas.</head>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100610">Next, warlike Pallas, in her helmet dressed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100620">With lance of winning; target of defence:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100630">In whom both wit and courage are expressed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100640">To get with glory, hold with providence. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A19837-e100650">
            <head>Venus.</head>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100660">Then lovely Venus in bright majesty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100670">Appears with mild aspect in dove-like-hue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100680">With th'al combining scarf of amity;</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100690">T'engird strange nations with affections true. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A19837-e100700">
            <head>Diana.</head>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100710">Next, chaste Diana in her robes of green,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100720">With weapons of the wood herself addrests,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100730">To bless the forest where her power is seen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100740">T'hold peace with all the world, but with wild beasts. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A19837-e100750">
            <head>Vesta.</head>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100760">Then comely Vesta with her flames of zeal ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100770">Presents herself, clad in white purity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100780">Whose book the soul's sweet comfort doth reveal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100790">By th'ever burning lamp of piety. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A19837-e100800">
            <pb facs="5"/>
            <head>Proserpina.</head>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100810">Next, rich Proserpina with flames of gold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100820">Whose estate, although within the earth, yet she</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100830">Comes from above, and in her hand doth hold</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100840">The mine of wealth, with cheerful majesty. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A19837-e100850">
            <head>Macaria.</head>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100860">Then all in purple robes, rich happiness:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100870">Next her appears, bearing in either hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100880">Th'ensigns both of wealth and wit; t'express,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100890">That by them both, her majesty doth stand. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A19837-e100900">
            <head>Concordja.</head>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100910">Then all in particoloured robes appears</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100920">In white and crimson-graceful concord, rest</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100930">With knots of union; and in hand she bears</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100940">The happy joined roses of our rest. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A19837-e100950">
            <head>Astraea.</head>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100960">Clear-eyed Astraea next, with reverend brow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100970">Clad in celestial hue, which best she likes:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100980">Comes with her balance, and her sword to show,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e100990">That first her judgement weighs before it strikes. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A19837-e101000">
            <head>Flora.</head>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101010">Then cheerful Flora, all adorned with flowers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101020">Who clothes the earth with beauty and delight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101030">In thousand sundry suits, whilst shining hours,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101040">Will scarce afford a darkness to the night. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A19837-e101050">
            <pb facs="6"/>
            <head>Ceres.</head>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101060">Next, plenteous Ceres in her harvest weed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101070">Crowned with the of what she gave to keep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101080">To gratitude and faith in whom we need:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101090">Who sows on virtue, shall with glory reap. </l>
          </div>
          <div type="section" xml:id="A19837-e101100">
            <head>Tethis.</head>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101110">Lastly comes Tethis, Albion's dearest love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101120">Whom she in faithful arms doth deign t'embrace:</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101130">And brings the trident of her power t'approve</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101140">Her favour and respect to do him grace. </l>
            <lg xml:id="A19837-e101150">
              <l xml:id="A19837-e101160">Thus have I read their shadows, but behold:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19837-e101170">In glory where they come as Iris told. </l>
            </lg>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A19837-e101180">
          <pb facs="6"/>
          <stage xml:id="A19837-e101190">The three graces march before the goddesses, descending down the mountain with loud music, and coming up to the upper end, stay and sing this song, whilst the goddesses go up to the temple with presents, and from them, march down the hall.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19837-e101200" who="A19837-graces">
            <lg type="song" xml:id="A19837-e101210">
              <head>The song.</head>
              <lg xml:id="A19837-e101220">
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101230">Desert, reward, and gratitude,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101240">The graces of society:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101250">Do here with hand in hand conclude,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101260">The blessed chain of amity. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101270">1. For I deserve. 2. I give. 3. I thank:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101280">All. Thanks, gifts, deserts thus join in rank. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19837-e101290">
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101300">We yield the splendent rays of light,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101310">Unto the blessings that descend;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101320">The grace whereof with more delight,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101330">The well disposing doth commend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101340">Whilst gratitude, rewards, deserts,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101350">Please, win, draw on, and couple hearts. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19837-e101360">
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101370">For worth, and power, and due respect,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101380">Deserves, bestows, returns with grace;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101390">The meed, reward, the kind effect,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101400">That gives the world a cheerful face. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101410">And turning in this course of right,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101420">Makes virtue move with true delight. </l>
              </lg>
            </lg>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A19837-e101430">
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <stage xml:id="A19837-e101440">The song being ended, and the maskers in the midst of the hall, disposing themselves to their dance, Sibilla having placed their several presents on the altar, utters these words.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19837-e101450" who="A19837-sybilla">
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101460">O power of powers, grant to our vows we pray,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101470">That these fair blessings which we here arrest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101480">In figures left us here, in substance, may</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101490">Be those great props of glory and respect. </l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101500">Let kingdoms large, let armed policy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101510">Mild love, true zeal, right shooting at the white,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101520">Of brave designs, let wealth, felicity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101530">Justice, and concord, Pleasure, plenty, might</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101540">And power by sea, with grace proportionate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A19837-e101550">Make glorious both this kingdom and estate. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19837-e101560">After this the maskers danced their own measures, which being ended, and they ready to take out the lords, the three graces sing.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19837-e101570" who="A19837-missing">
            <lg type="song" xml:id="A19837-e101580">
              <lg n="1" xml:id="A19837-e101590">
                <head>I.</head>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101600">While worth with honour, make their choice,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101610">For measured motions ordered right:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101620">Now let us likewise give a voice,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101630">Unto the touch of our delight. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg n="2" xml:id="A19837-e101640">
                <head>Ii.</head>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101650">For comforts locked up without sound,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101660">Are th'unborn children of the thought:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101670">Like unto treasures never found,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101680">That buried low, are left forgotten. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg n="3" xml:id="A19837-e101690">
                <head>Iii.</head>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101700">Where words or glory do not show,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101710">There like brave actions without frame,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101720">It seems like plants not set to grow,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19837-e101730">Or as a tomb without a name. </l>
              </lg>
            </lg>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A19837-e101740">
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <stage xml:id="A19837-e101750">The maskers having ended the dancing with the lords: Iris, gives warning of their departure, in this manner, Iris.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A19837-e101760" who="A19837-iris">
            <p xml:id="A19837-e101770">As I was the joyful messenger, to notify the coming of these divine powers; so am I now the same of their departure, who having clothed themselves with these appearances, do now return back spheres of there own being from whence they are. But yet of myself, this much I must reveal, though against the warrant of a messenger, who, I know had better to fail in obedience, than in presumption, that these deities by (The motion of the all-directing Pallas, the glorious patroness of this mighty monarchy) descending in the majesty of their invisible essences, upon yonder mountain; found there the best and most worthy, the best of ladies, disporting herself with the choicest attendants, whose forms they presently took, as delighting to be in the best built temples of beauty and honour, and in them vouchsafed to appear in this manner, being otherwise no objects for mortal eyes.</p>
            <p xml:id="A19837-e101780"><pb facs="8"/>And no doubt, but that in respect or the persons, under whose beautiful coverings they have thus presented themselves? these deities will be pleased, the rather at their invocation, knowing all their desires to be such, as evermore to grace this glorious monarchy, with the royal effects of these blessings represented.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A19837-e101790">After this, they fell to a short parting dance, and so ascended the mountain in the same order as they came down.</stage>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A19837-e101800">Finis.</trailer>
        <pb facs="8"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A19837"><item xml:id="A19837-sybilla" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A19837-sybilla</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19837-iris" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A19837-iris</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19837-graces" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19837-graces</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19837-night" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19837-night</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19837-somnus" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19837-somnus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19837-missing" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19837-missing</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

