<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A18425">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Caesar and Pompey (The Wars of Caesar and Pompey) <date type="creation_date">1605</date></title>
        <author>Chapman, George</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A18425.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Caesar and Pompey a Roman tragedy, declaring their vvarres. Out of whose euents is euicted this proposition. Only a iust man is a freeman. By George Chapman.</title>
            <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>37 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006 June (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99843418</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 4993.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 444(A1*).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">8150</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18425</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Caesar and Pompey a Roman tragedy, declaring their vvarres. Out of whose euents is euicted this proposition. Only a iust man is a freeman. By George Chapman.</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedy of Cæsar and Pompey.</title>
            <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[76] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper, and are to be sold by Godfrey Edmonson, and Thomas Alchorne,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>M.DC.XXXI. [1631]</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-I4 K2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The first leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: The tragedy of Cæsar and Pompey.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>A variant of the edition with title: The warres of Pompey and Caesar (STC 4992).</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Rome -- History -- Civil war, 49-48 B.C. -- Drama.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A18425-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A18425-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A18425-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A18425-e100040">Caesar and Pompey: a Roman tragedy, declaring their wars.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18425-e100050">Out of whose events is evicted this proposition.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18425-e100060">Only a just man is a freeman.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18425-e100070">By George Chapman.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18425-e100080">London: printed by Thomas harper, and are to be sold by Godfrey Emondson, and Thomas Althorus. M.dc.xxxi.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A18425-e100090">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To the right honourable, his exceeding good lord, the Earl of Middlesex, etc.</head>
        <p xml:id="A18425-e100100">Though (My good lord) this martial history suffer the division of acts and scenes, both for the more perspicuity and height of the celebration, yet never touched it at the stage; or if it had (Though some may perhaps causelessly impair it) yet would it, I hope, fall under no exception in your lordship's better-judging estimation, since scenical representation is so far from giving just cause of any least diminution; that the personal and exact life it gives<pb facs="3"/> to any history, or other such delineation of humane actions, adds to them luster, spirit and apprehension, which the only section of acts and scenes makes me stand upon thus much, since that only in some precisianismes will require a little prevention: and the hasty prose the style avoids, obtain to the more temperate and stayed numerous elocution, some assistance to the acceptation and grace of it. Though ingeniously my gratitude confesseth (My lord) it is not such as hereafter i vow to your honour; being written so long since; and had not the timely ripeness of that age that (I thank God) i yet find no fault withal for any old defects.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18425-e100110">Good my lord vouchsafe your idle minutes may admit some slight glances at this, till some work of more novelty and<pb facs="3"/> fashion may confer this the more liking of your honours more worthy deservings; to which his bounden affection vows all services.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A18425-e100120">
          <signed xml:id="A18425-e100130">Ever your lordship's Geo. Chapman.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="argument" xml:id="A18425-e100140">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <head>The argument.</head>
        <p xml:id="A18425-e100150">Pompey and Caesar bring their armies so near Rome, that the senate except against them. Caesar unduly and ambitiously commanding his forces. Pompey more for fear of Caesar's violence to the state, then moved with any affectation of his own greatness. Their opposite pleadings, out of which admirable narrations are made, which yet not conducing to their ends, war ends them. In which at first Caesar is forced to fly, whom Pompey not pursuing with such wings as fitted a speeding conqueror; his victory was prevented, and he unhappily dishonoured. Whose ill fortune his most loving and learned wife Cornelia travailed after, with pains solemn and careful enough; whom the two Lentuli and others attended, till she miserably found him, and saw him monstrously murdered.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18425-e100160">Both the consuls and Cato are slaughtered with their own invincible hands; and Caesar (In spite of all his fortune) without his victory, victor.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A18425-e100170">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A18425-e100180">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <head>Only a just man is a free man.</head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A18425-e100190">
          <head>Act i. scene i.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e100200">Cato, Athenodorus, Porcius, Statilius.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e100210" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100220">Now will the two suns of our Roman heaven</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100230">(Pompey and Caesar) in their tropic burning,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100240">With their contention, all the clouds assemble</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100250">That threaten tempests to our peace and empire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100260">Which we shall shortly see pour down in blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100270">Civil and natural, wild and barbarous turning. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e100280" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e100290">From whence presage you this?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e100300" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100310">From both their armies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100320">Now gathered near our Italy, contending</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100330">To enter severally: Pompey's brought so near</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100340">By Rome's consent; for fear of tyrannous Caesar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100350">Which Caesar fearing to be done in favour</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100360">Of Pompey, and his passage to the empire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100370">Hath brought on his for intervention. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100380">And such a flock of puttocks follow Caesar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100390">For fall of his ill-disposed purse</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100400">(That never yet spared cross to Aquiline virtue)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100410">As well may make all civil spirits suspicious. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100420">Look how against great rains, a standing pool</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100430">Of paddocks, toads, and water-snakes put up</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100440"><pb facs="5"/> their speckled throats above the venomous lake,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100450">Croaking and gasping for some fresh fallen drops</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100460">To quench their poisoned thirst; being near to stifle</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100470">With clottered purgings of their own foul bane;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100480">So still, where Caesar goes, there thrust up head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100490">Impostors, flatterers, favourites, and bawds,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100500">Buffoons, intelligencers, select wits;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100510">Close murderers, mountebanks, and decayed thieves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100520">To gain their baneful lives reliefs from him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100530">From Britain, Belgia, France, and Germany,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100540">The scum of either country, (Chused by him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100550">To be his black guard, and red agents here)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100560">Swarming about him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e100570" who="A18425-porcius">
            <speaker>Porc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100580">And all these are said</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100590">To be suborned, in chief, against yourself;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100600">Since Caesar chiefly fears, that you will sit</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100610">This day his opposite; in the cause for which</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100620">Both you were sent for home; and he hath stolen</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100630">Access so soon here; Pompey: whole rest raised</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100640">To his encounter; and on both sides, Rome</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100650">In general uproar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e100660" who="A18425-stat">
            <speaker>Stat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100670">Which sir, if you saw,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100680">And knew, how for the danger, all suspect</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100690">To this your worthiest friend (For that known freedom</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100700">His spirit will use this day, 'gainst both the rivals,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100710">His wife and family mourn, no food, no comfort</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100720">Allowed them, for his danger) you would use</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100730">Your utmost powers to stay him from the senate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100740">All this day's session. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e100750" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100760">He's too wise, Statilius,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100770">For all is nothing. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e100780" who="A18425-stat">
            <speaker>Stat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100790">Nothing sir? I saw</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100800">Castor and Pollux temple, thrust up full,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100810">With all the damned crew you have lately named ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100820">The market place and suburbs swarming with them:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100830">And where the senate sit, are ruffians pointed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100840">To keep from entering the degrees that go</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100850"><pb facs="5"/> up to the bench; all other but the consuls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100860">Caesar and Pompey, and the senators,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100870">And all for no cause, but to keep out Cato,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100880">With any violence, any villainy;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100890">And is this nothing sir? Is his one life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100900">On whom all good lives, and their goods depend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100910">In Rome's whole empire! All the justice there</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100920">That's free, and simple; all such virtues too,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100930">And all such knowledge; nothing, nothing, all? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e100940" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100950">Away Statilius; how long shall thy love</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100960">Exceed thy knowledge of me, and the gods? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100970">Whose rights thou wrongest for my right? have not? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100980">Their powers to guard me, in a cause of theirs? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e100990">Their justice, and integrity included,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101000">In what I stand for? he that fears the gods,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101010">For guard of any goodness; all things fears;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101020">Earth, seas, and air; heaven, darkness, broad daylight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101030">Rumor, and silence, and his very shade:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101040">And what an aspen soul hath such a creature? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101050">How dangerous to his soul is such a fear? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101060">In whose cold fits, is all heaven's justice shaken</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101070">To his faint thoughts; and all the goodness there</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101080">Due to all good men, by the gods own vows,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101090">Nay, by the firmness of their endless being,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101100">All which shall fail as soon as any one</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101110">Good to a good man in them: for his goodness</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101120">Proceeds from them, and is a beam of theirs. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101130">O never more, Statilius, may this fear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101140">Taint thy bold bosom, for thyself, or friend. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101150">More than the gods are fearful to defend. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101160" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Athen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101170">Come; let him go, Statilius; and your fright;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101180">This man hath inward guard, passed your young sight.<stage xml:id="A18425-e101190">Exeunt</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e101200">Enter Minutius, manet Cato.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101210" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101220">Welcome; come stand by me in what is fit</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101230">For our poor city's safety; nor respect</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101240">Her proudest foes corruption, or our danger</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101250"><pb facs="6"/> of what seen face soever. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101260" who="A18425-min">
            <speaker>Min.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101270">I am yours. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101280">But what alas, sir, can the weakness do</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101290">Against our whole state of us only two? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101300">You know our statists spirits are so corrupt</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101310">And servile to the greatest; that what crosseth</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101320">Them, or their own particular wealth, or honour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101330">They will not enterprise to save the empire. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101340" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101350">I know it; yet let us do like ourselves. <stage xml:id="A18425-e101360">Exeunt.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e101370">Enter some bearing axes, bundles of rods, bare; before two consuls, Caesar and Metellus; Anthonius, and Marcellus in couples; senators, people, soldiers, etc. following. The consuls enter the degrees, with Anthonius, and Marcellus: Caesar staying a while without with Metellus, who hath a paper in his hand.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101380" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101390">Move you for entering only Pompey's army;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101400">Which if you gain for him; for me, all justice</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101410">Will join with my request of entering mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101420" who="A18425-met">
            <speaker>Met.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101430">'Tis like so, and I purpose to enforce it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101440" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101450">But might we not win Cato to our friendship</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101460">By honouring speeches, nor persuasive gifts? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101470" who="A18425-met">
            <speaker>Met.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101480">Not possible.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101490" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101500">Nor by enforcive usage?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101510" who="A18425-met">
            <speaker>Met.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101520">Not all the violence that can be used,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101530">Of power, or set authority can stir him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101540">Much less fair words win, or rewards corrupt him;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101550">And therefore all means we must use to keep him</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101560">From off the bench. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101570" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101580">Give you the course for that,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101590">And if he offer entry, I have fellows</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101600">Will serve your will on him, at my given signal. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e101610">They ascend.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e101620"><pb facs="6"/>Enter Pompey, Gabinius, Vibius, Demetrius, with papers. Enter the lists, ascend and sit. After whom enter Cato, Minutius, Athenodorus, Statilius, Porcius. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101630" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101640">He is the man that sits so close to Caesar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101650">And holds the law there, whispering; see the cowherd</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101660">Hath guards of armed men got, against one naked. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101670">I'll part their whispering virtue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101680" who="A18425-xxxx_1">
            <speaker>1</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101690">Hold, keep out.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101700" who="A18425-xxxx_2">
            <speaker>2</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101710">What? honoured Cato? enter, choose thy place.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101720" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101730">Come in;</l>
            <stage xml:id="A18425-e101740">He draws him in and sits betwixt Caesar and Metelius.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101750">— Away unworthy grooms. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101760" who="A18425-xxxx_3">
            <speaker>3</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101770">No more.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101780" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101790">What should one say to him?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101800" who="A18425-met">
            <speaker>Met.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101810">He will be stoical.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101820" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101830">Where fit place is not given, it must be taken.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101840" who="A18425-xxxx_4">
            <speaker>4</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101850">Do, take it Cato; fear no greatest of them;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101860">Thou seekest the people's good; and these their own. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101870" who="A18425-xxxx_5">
            <speaker>5</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101880">Brave Cato! what a countenance he puts on? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101890">Let's give his noble will, our utmost power. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101900" who="A18425-incomplete">
            <speaker>6</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101910">Be bold in all thy will; for being just,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e101920">Thou mayst defy the gods. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101930" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101940">Said like a God.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101950" who="A18425-met">
            <speaker>Met.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101960">We must endure these people.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101970" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e101980">Do; begin.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e101990" who="A18425-met">
            <speaker>Met.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102000">Consul's, and reverend fathers; and ye people,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102010">Whose voices are the voices of the gods;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102020">I here have drawn a law, by good consent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102030">For entering into Italy, the army</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102040">Of Rome's great Pompey: that his forces here,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102050">As well as he, great Rome, may rest secure</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102060">From danger or the yet still smoking fire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102070">Of Catiline's abhorred conspiracy:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102080">Of which the very chief are left alive,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102090">Only chastised, but with a gentle prison. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e102100" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102110">Put them to death then, and strike dead our fear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102120"><pb facs="7"/> that well you urge, by their unfit survival. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102130">Rather than keep it quick; and two lives give it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102140">By entertaining Pompey's army too. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102150">That gives as great cause of our fear, as they. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102160">For their conspiracy, only was to make</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102170">One tyrant over all the state of Rome. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102180">And Pompey's army, suffered to be entered,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102190">Is, to make him, or give him means to be so. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e102200" who="A18425-met">
            <speaker>Met.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e102210">It follows not.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e102220" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102230">In purpose; clearly sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102240">Which I'll illustrate, with a clear example. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102250">If it be day, the sun's above the earth;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102260">Which follows not (You'll answer) for 'tis day</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102270">When first the morning breaks; and yet is then</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102280">The body of the sun beneath the earth;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102290">But he is virtually above it too,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102300">Because his beams are there, and who then knows not</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102310">His golden body will soon after mount. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102320">So Pompey's army entered Italy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102330">Yet pompey's not in Rome; but Pompey's beams</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102340">Who sees not there? and consequently, he</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102350">Is in all means enthroned in th'empery. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e102360" who="A18425-met">
            <speaker>Met.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102370">Examples prove not, we will have the army</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102380">Of Pompey entered. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e102390" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cato.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102400">We? which we intend you? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102410">Have you already bought the people's voices? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102420">Or bear our consul or our senate here</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102430">So small love to their country; that their wills</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102440">Beyond their countries right are so perverse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102450">To give a tyrant here entire command? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102460">Which I have proved as clear as day, they do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102470">If either the conspirators surviving</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102480">Be let to live; or Pompey's army entered;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102490">Both which, beat one sole path; and threat one danger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e102500" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102510">Consul's, and honoured fathers; the sole entry</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102520">Of Pompey's army, I'll not yet examine:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102530">But for the great conspirators yet living,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102540"><pb facs="7"/> (Which Cato will conclude as one self danger,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102550">To our dear country; and deter all therefore</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102560">That love their country, from their life's defence</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102570">I see no reason why such danger hangs</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102580">On their saved lives; being still safe kept in prison;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102590">And since close prison, to a Roman freedom,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102600">Ten fold torments more, than directest death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102610">Who can be thought to love the less his country,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102620">That seeks to save their lives? And lest myself</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102630">(Thus speaking for them) be unjustly touched</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102640">With any less doubt of my country's love. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102650">Why (Reverend fathers) may it be esteemed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102660">Self praise in me, to prove myself a chief</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102670">Both in my love of her; and in desert</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102680">Of her like love in me? For he that does</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102690">Most honour to his mistress; well may boast</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102700">(Without least question) that he loves her most. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102710">And though things long since done, were long since known,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102720">And so may seem superfluous to repeat;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102730">Yet being forgotten, as things never done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102740">Their repetition needful is, in justice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102750">T'inflame the shame of that oblivion:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102760">For hoping it will seem no less impair</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102770">To others acts, to truly tell mine own;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102780">Put all together; I have passed them all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102790">That by their acts can boast themselves to be</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102800">Their country's lovers: first in those wild kingdoms</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102810">Subdued to Rome, by my unwearied toils. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102820">Which I dissavaged and made nobly civil. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102830">Next, in the multitude of those rude realms</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102840">That so I fashioned; and to Rome's young empire</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102850">Of old have added: then the battles numbered</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102860">This hand hath fought, and won for her, with all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102870">Those infinites of dreadful enemies</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102880">(I slew in them: twice fifteen hundred thousand</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102890">All able soldiers) I have driven at once</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102900">Before my forces: and in sundry onsets,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102910"><pb facs="8"/> a thousand thousand of them, put to sword:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102920">Besides, I took in less than ten years time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102930">By strong assault, above eight hundred cities,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102940">Three hundred several nations, in that space,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102950">Subduing to my country; all which service,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102960">I trust, may interest me in her love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102970">Public, and general enough, to acquit me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102980">Of any self-love; passed her common good:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e102990">For any motion of particular justice</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103000">(By which her general empire is maintained)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103010">That I can make for those accused prisoners,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103020">Which is but by the way; that so the reason</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103030">Metellus makes for entering Pompey's army,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103040">May not more weighty seem, than to agree</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103050">With those imprisoned nobles, vital safeties. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103060">Which granted, or but yielded fit to be,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103070">May well extenuate the necessity</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103080">Of entering Pompey's army. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103090" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103100">All that need</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103110">I took away before; and reasons gave</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103120">For a necessity to keep it out</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103130">Whose entry (I think) he himself affects not. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103140">Since I as well think he affects not th'empire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103150">And both those thoughts hold; since he loves his country,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103160">In my great hopes of him too well to seek</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103170">His sole rule of her, when so many souls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103180">So hard a task approve it; nor my hopes</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103190">Of his sincere love to his country, build</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103200">On sandier grounds than Caesar's; since he can</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103210">As good cards show for it as Caesar did,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103220">And quit therein the close aspersion</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103230">Of his ambition, seeking to employ</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103240">His army in the breast of Italy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103250" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pomp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103260">Let me not thus (Imperial bench and senate)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103270">Feel myself beat about the ears, and tossed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103280">With others breathes to any coast they please:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103290">And not put some stay to my errors in them. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103300"><pb facs="8"/>The gods can witness that not my ambition</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103310">Hath brought to question th'entry of my army;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103320">And therefore not suspected the effect,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103330">Of which that entry is supposed the cause:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103340">Which is a will in me, to give my power</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103350">The rule of Rome's sole empire; that most strangely</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103360">Would put my will in others powers; and powers</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103370">(Unforfeit by my fault) in others wills. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103380">My self-love, out of which all this must rise:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103390">I will not wrong the known proofs of my love</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103400">To this my native city's public good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103410">To quit, or think of; nor repeat those proofs</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103420">Confirmed in those three triumphs I have made;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103430">For conquest of the whole inhabited world;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103440">First Afrique, Europe, and then Asia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103450">Which never consul but myself could boast. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103460">Nor can blind fortune vaunt her partial hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103470">In any part of all my services,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103480">Though some have said, she was the page of Caesar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103490">Both sailing, marching, fighting, and preparing</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103500">His fights in very order of his battles:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103510">The parts she played for him inverting nature,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103520">As giving calmness to th'enraged sea;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103530">Imposing summer's weather on stern winter;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103540">Winging the slowest foot he did command,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103550">And his most cowherd making fierce of hand. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103560">And all this ever when the force of man</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103570">Was quite exceeded in it all; and she</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103580">In th'instant adding her clear deity. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103590">Yet, her for me, I both disclaim and scorn;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103600">And where all fortune is renounced, no reason</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103610">Will think one man transferred with affectation</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103620">Of all Rome's empire; for he must have fortune</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103630">That goes beyond a man; and where so many</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103640">Their handfuls find with it; the one is mad</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103650">That undergoes it: and where that is cleared;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103660">Th'imputed means to it, which is my suit</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103670"><pb facs="9"/> for entry of mine army, I confute. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103680" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e103690">What rests then, this of all parts being disclaimed?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103700" who="A18425-met">
            <speaker>Met.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103710">My part, sir, rests, that let great Pompey bear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103720">What spirit he lists; 'tis needful yet for Rome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103730">That this law be established for his army. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103740" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103750">'Tis then as needful to admit in mine;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103760">Or else let both lay down our arms; for else</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103770">To take my charge off, and leave Pompey his;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103780">You wrongfully accuse me to intend</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103790">A tyranny amongst ye; and shall give</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103800">Pompey full means to be himself a tyrant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103810" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e103820">Can this be answered?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103830" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Cons. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103840">Is it then your wills</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103850">That Pompey shall cease arms? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103860" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e103870">What else?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103880" who="A18425-omnes">
            <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e103890">No, no.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103900" who="A18425-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2 Cons. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e103910">Shall Caesar cease his arms?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103920" who="A18425-omnes">
            <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e103930">Ay, I.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103940" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103950">For shame</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103960">Then yield to this clear equity, that both</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e103970">May leave their arms. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e103980" who="A18425-omnes">
            <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e103990">We indifferent stand.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104000" who="A18425-met">
            <speaker>Met.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104010">Read but this law, and you shall see a difference</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104020">Twixt equity and your indifferency;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104030">All men's objections answered; read it notary. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104040" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e104050">He shall not read it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104060" who="A18425-met">
            <speaker>Met.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e104070">I will read it then.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104080" who="A18425-min">
            <speaker>Min.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104090">Nor thou shalt read it, being a thing so vain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104100">Pretending cause for Pompey's armies entry. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104110">That only by thy complices and thee;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104120">'Tis forged to set the senate in an uproar</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104130" who="A18425-met">
            <speaker>Met.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e104140">I have it sir, in memory, and will speak it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104150" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e104160">Thou shalt be dumb as soon.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104170" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104180">Pull down this Cato,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104190">Author of factions, and to prison with him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104200" who="A18425-unassigned">
            <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e104210">Come down sir. <stage xml:id="A18425-e104220">He draws, and all draw.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104230" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e104240">Hence ye mercenary ruffians.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104250" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <pb facs="9"/>
            <speaker>1 Cons. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104260">What outrage show you? sheath your insolent swords,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104270">Or be proclaimed your countries' foes and traitors. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104280" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104290">How insolent a part was this in you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104300">To offer the imprisonment of Cato? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104310">When there is right in him (Were form so answered</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104320">With terms and place) to send us both to prison? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104330">If, of our own ambitions, we should offer</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104340">Th'entry of our armies; for who knows</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104350">That, of us both, the best friend to his country,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104360">And freest from his own particular ends;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104370">(Being in his power) would not assume the empire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104380">And having it, could rule the state so well</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104390">As now 'tis governed, for the common good? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104400" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104410">Accuse yourself, sir, (If your conscience urge it)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104420">Or of ambition, or corruption,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104430">Or insufficiency to rule the empire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104440">And sound not me with your lead. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104450" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104460">Lead? 'tis gold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104470">And spirit of gold too; to the politic dross</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104480">With which false Caesar sounds men; and for which</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104490">His praise and honour crowns them; who sounds not</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104500">The inmost sand of Caesar? for but sand</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104510">Is all the rope of your great parts affected. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104520">You speak well, and are learned; and golden speech</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104530">Did nature never give man; but to guild</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104540">A copper soul in him; and all that learning</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104550">That heartily is spent in painting speech,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104560">Is merely painted, and no solid knowledge. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104570">But you've another praise for temperance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104580">Which naught commends your free choice to be temperate</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104590">For so you must be; at least in your meals,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104600">Since you've a malady that ties you to it;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104610">For fear of daily falls in your aspirings. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104620">And your disease the gods never gave to man;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104630">But such a one, as had a spirit too great</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104640">For all his bodies passages to serve it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104650">Which notes th'excess of your ambition. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104660"><pb facs="10"/>The malady chancing where the pores and passages</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104670">Through which the spirit of a man is born,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104680">So narrow are, and straight, that oftentimes</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104690">They intercept it quite, and choke it up. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104700">And yet because the greatness of it notes</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104710">A heat mere fleshly, and of bloods rank fire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104720">Goats are of all beasts subject'st to it most. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104730" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104740">Yourself might have it then, if those faults cause it;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104750">But deals this man ingeniously, to tax</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104760">Men with a frailty that the gods inflict? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104770" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pomp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104780">The gods inflict on men, diseases never,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104790">Or other outward maims; but to decipher,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104800">Correct, and order some rude vice within them:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104810">And why decipher they it, but to make</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104820">Men note, and shun, and tax it to th'extreme? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104830">Nor will I see my country's hopes abused,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104840">In any man commanding in her empire;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104850">If my more trial of him, makes me see more</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104860">Into his intricasies; and my freedom</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104870">Hath spirit to speak more, than observers servile. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e104880" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104890">Be free, sir, of your insight and your speech;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104900">And speak, and see more, than the world besides;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104910">I must remember I have heard of one,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104920">That fame gave out, could see thorough oak and stone:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104930">And of another set in Sicily,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104940">That could discern the Carthaginian navy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104950">And number them distinctly, leaving harbour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104960">Though full a day and nights fail distant thence:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104970">But these things (Reverend fathers) I conceive,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104980">Hardly appear to you worth grave belief:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e104990">And therefore since such strange things have been seen</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105000">In my so deep and foul detractions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105010">By only Lyncean Pompey; who was most</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105020">Loved and believed of Rome's most famous whore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105030">Infamous Flora; by so fine a man</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105040">As Galba, or Sarmentus; any jester</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105050">Or flatterer may draw through a lady's ring;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105060"><pb facs="10"/> by one that all his soldiers call in scorn</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105070">Great Agamemnon, or the King of men;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105080">I rest unmoved with him; and yield to you</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105090">To right my wrongs, or his abuse allow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105100" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e105110">My lords, ye make all Rome amazed to hear.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105120" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105130">Away, I'll hear no more; I hear it thunder</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105140">My lords; all you that love the good of Rome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105150">I charge ye, follow me; all such as slay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105160">Are friends to Caesar, and their countries' foes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105170" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e105180">Th'event will fall out contrary, my lords.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105190" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Cons. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105200">Go, thou art a thief to Rome, discharge thine army,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105210">Or be proclaimed, forthwith, her open foe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105220" who="A18425-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2 Cons. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105230">Pompey, I charge thee, help thy injured country</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105240">With what powers thou hast armed, and levy more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105250" who="A18425-ruffians">
            <speaker>The ruffians.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e105260">War, war, oh Caesar. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105270" who="A18425-unassigned">
            <speaker>Senator and Peop.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e105280">Peace, peace, worthy Pompey. </p>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A18425-e105290">
          <head>Act ii. scene i.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e105300">Enter Fronto all ragged, in an over grown red beard, black head, with a halter in his hand, looking about.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105310">Wars, wars, and presses, fly in fire about;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105320">No more can I lurk in my lazy corners,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105330">Nor shifting courses: and with honest means</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105340">To rack my miserable life out, more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105350">The rack is not so fearful; when dishonest</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105360">And villainous fashions fail me; can I hope</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105370">To live with virtuous? or to raise my fortunes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105380">By creeping up in soldierly degrees? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105390">Since villainy varied thorough all his figures,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105400">Will put no better case on me then this;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105410">Despair! come seize me: I had able means;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105420"><pb facs="11"/> and spent all in the swinge of lewd affections;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105430">Plunged in all riot, and the rage of blood;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105440">In full assurance that being knave enough,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105450">Barbarous enough, base, ignorant enough,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105460">I needs must have enough, while this world lasted;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105470">Yet, since I am a poor, and ragged knave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105480">My rags disgace my knavery so, that none</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105490">Will think I am knave; as if good clothes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105500">Were knacks to know a knave; when all men know</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105510">He has no living? which knacks since my knavery</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105520">Can show no more; and only show is all</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105530">That this world cares for; I'll stop out of all</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e105540">The cares 'tis steeped in. <stage xml:id="A18425-e105550">He offers to hang himself.</stage></l>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e105560">Thunder, and the gulf opens, flames issuing; and Ophioneus ascending, with the face, wings, and tail of a dragon; a skin coat all speckled on the throat.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105570" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105580">Hold rascal, hang thyself in these days? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105590">The only time that ever was for a rascal to live in? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105600" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fron.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e105610">How chance I cannot live then?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105620" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105630">Either thou'rt not rascal nor villain enough;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105640">Or else thou dost not pretend honesty</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105650">And piety enough to disguise it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105660" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105670">That's certain, for every ass does that. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105680">What art thou? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105690" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e105700">A villain worse than thou.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105710" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e105720">And dost breathe?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105730" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105740">I speak thou hearest, I move, my pulse beats</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105750">Fast as thine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105760" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e105770">And wherefore liv'st thou?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105780" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105790">The world's out of frame, a thousand rulers</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105800">Wresting it this way, and that, with as many</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105810">Religions; when, as heaven's upper sphere is moved</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105820">Only by one; so should the sphere of earth be, and</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105830">I'll have it so. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105840" who="A18425-fron">
            <pb facs="11"/>
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e105850">How canst thou? what art thou?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105860" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e105870">My shape may tell thee.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105880" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e105890">No man?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105900" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105910">Man? no, spawn of a clot, none of that cursed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105920">Crew, damned in the mass itself; plagued in his birth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105930">Confined to creep below, and wrestle with the elements;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105940">Teach himself tortures; kill himself, hang himself;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105950">No such galley slave, but at war with heaven;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e105960">Spurning the power of the gods, command the elements. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105970" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e105980">What mayst thou be then?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e105990" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106000">An endless friend of thine; an immortal devil.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106010" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106020">Heaven bless us.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106030" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106040">Nay then, forth, go, hang thyself, and thou talkest</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106050">Of heaven once. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106060" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106070">I have done; what devil art thou?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106080" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106090">Read the old Stoic Pherecides, that tells thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106100">Me truly, and says that I Ophioneus (For so is</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106110">My name.) </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106120" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106130">Ophioneus? what's that?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106140" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106150">Devilish serpent, by interpretation; was general</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106160">Captain of that rebellious host of spirits that</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106170">Waged war with heaven. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106180" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106190">And so were hurled down to hell.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106200" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106210">We were so; and yet have the rule of earth; and cares</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106220">Any man for the worst of hell then? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106230" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106240">Why should he?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106250" who="A18425-unassigned">
            <speaker>Oph ▪</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106260">Well said; what's thy name now?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106270" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106280">My name is Fronto. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106290" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106300">Fronto? A good one; and has Fronto lived thus long</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106310">In Rome? lost his state at dice? murdered his</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106320">Brother for his means? spent all? run thorough worse</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106330">Offices since? been a promoter? A purveyor? A pander? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106340">A sumner? A sergeant? an intelligencer? and at last</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106350">Hang thyself? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106360" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106370">How the devil knows he all this?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106380" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106390">Why thou art a most green plover in policy, I</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106400">Perceive; and mayst drink golte-foote, for all thy</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106410"><pb facs="12"/> horsemane beard: 'slight, what need hast</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106420">Thou to hang thyself? as if there were a dearth</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106430">Of hangmen in the land? Thou liv'st in a good cheap</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106440">State, a man may be hanged here for a little, or</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106450">Nothing. What's the reason of thy desperation? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106460" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106470">My idle dissolute life, is thrust out of all his corners</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106480">By this searching tumult now on foot in Rome. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106490">— Caesar now and Pompey</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106500">Are both for battle: Pompey (In his fear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106510">Of Caesar's greater force) is sending hence</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106520">His wife and children, and he bent to fly. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A18425-e106530">Enter Pompey running over the stage with his wife and children, Gabinius, Demetrius, Vibius, pages; other senators, the consuls and all following.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106540">See, all are on their wings; and all the city</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106550">In such an uproar, as if fire and sword</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106560">Were ransacking, and ruining their houses,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106570">No idle person now can lurk near Rome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106580">All must to arms; or shake their heels beneath</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106590">Her martial halters; whose officious pride</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106600">I'll shun, and use mine own swinge: I be forced</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106610">To help my country, when it forceth me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106620">To this past-helping pickle? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106630" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106640">Go to, thou shalt serve me, choose thy profession;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106650">And what cloth thou wouldst wish to have thy coat</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106660">Cut out on. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106670" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106680">I can name none.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106690" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106700">Shall I be thy learned counsel?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106710" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106720">None better.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106730" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106740">Be an archflamen then, to one of the gods.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106750" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106760">Archflamen? what's that?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106770" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106780">A priest.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106790" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106800">A priest? that ne'er was clerk?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106810" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106820">No clerk? what then? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106830">The greatest clerks are not the wisest men. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106840"><pb facs="12"/>Nor skills it for degrees in a knave, or a fool's preferment,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106850">Thou shalt rise by fortune: let desert rise leisurely</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106860">Enough, and by degrees; fortune prefers headlong,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106870">And comes like riches to a man; huge riches being</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106880">Got with little pains; and little with huge pains. And</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106890">For discharge of the priesthood, what thou wantest</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106900">In learning, thou shalt take out in good-fellowship:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106910">Thou shalt equivocate with the sophister, prate with</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106920">The lawyer, scrape with the usurer, drink with the</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106930">Dutchman, swear with the French man, cheat</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106940">With the English man, brag with the scot, and</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106950">Turn all this to religion, hoc est regnum</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e106960">Deorum gentibus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106970" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e106980">All this I can do to a hair.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e106990" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107000">Very good, wilt thou show thyself deeply learned too,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107010">And to live licentiously here, care for nothing hereafter? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107020" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e107030">Not for hell?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107040" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107050">For hell? soft sir; hopest thou to purchase hell</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107060">With only dicing or whoring away thy living? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107070">Murdering thy brother, and so forth? No there</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107080">Remain works of a higher hand and deeper brain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107090">To obtain hell. Thinkst thou earth's great</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107100">Potentates have gotten their places there with</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107110">Any single act of murder, poisoning, adultery,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107120">And the rest? No; 'tis a purchase for all manner</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107130">Of villainy; especially, that may be privileged</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107140">By authority; coloured with holiness, and enjoyed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107150">With pleasure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107160" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e107170">O this were most honourable and admirable.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107180" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107190">Why such an admirable honourable villain shalt</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107200">Thou be. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107210" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e107220">Is't possible?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107230" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e107240">Make no doubt on't; I'll inspire thee.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107250" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e107260">Sacred and puissant. <stage xml:id="A18425-e107270">He kneels.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107280" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107290">Away; companion and friend, give me thy</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107300">Hand; say, dost not love me? art not enamoured</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107310">Of my acquaintance? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107320" who="A18425-fron">
            <pb facs="13"/>
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e107330">Protest I am.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107340" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107350">Well said, protest and 'tis enough. And know for</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107360">Infallible; I have promotion for thee; both here, and</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107370">Hereafter; which not one great one amongst</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107380">Millions shall ever aspire to. Alexander, nor great</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107390">Cyrus, retain those titles in hell, that they did</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107400">On earth:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107410" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e107420">No?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107430" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107440">No: he that sold seacoal here, shall be</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107450">A baron there; he that was a cheating</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107460">Rogue here, shall be a justice of peace there;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107470">A knave here, a knight there. In the mean</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107480">Space, learn what it is to live; and thou shalt</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107490">Have chopines at commandment to any height</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107500">Of life thou canst wish. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107510" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e107520">I fear my fall is too low.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107530" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107540">Too low fool? hast thou not heard of Vulcan's falling</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107550">Out of heaven? Light a thy legs, and no matter</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107560">Though thou haltest with thy best friend ever after; 'tis</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107570">The more comely and fashionable. Better go lame</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107580">In the fashion with Pompey, then never so upright,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107590">Quite out of the fashion with Cato. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107600" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107610">Yet you cannot change the old fashion (They say)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107620">And hide your cloven feet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107630" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107640">No? I can wear roses that shall spread quite</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107650">Over them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107660" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e107670">For love of the fashion do then.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107680" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e107690">Go to; I will hereafter.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107700" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e107710">But for the priesthood you offer me, I affect it not.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107720" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e107730">No? what sayest thou to a rich office then?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107740" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107750">The only second means to raise a rascal</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107760">In the earth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107770" who="A18425-oph">
            <speaker>Oph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107780">Go to; I'll help thee to the best ith' earth then:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107790">And that's in Sicilia; the very storehouse of the</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107800">Romans, where the lord chief censor there</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107810">Lies now a dying; whose soul I will have; and</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107820">Thou shalt have his office. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e107830" who="A18425-fron">
            <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107840">Excellent; was ever great office better supplied? <stage xml:id="A18425-e107850">Exeunt.</stage></l>
            <stage xml:id="A18425-e107860"><pb facs="13"/>Nuntius. </stage>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107870">Now is the mighty empress of the earth</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107880">(Great Rome) fast locked up in her fancied strength,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107890">All broke in uproars; fearing the just gods</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107900">In plagues will drown her so abused blessings. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107910">In which fear, all without her walls, fly in;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107920">By both their jarring champions rushing out;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107930">And those that were within, as fast fly forth;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107940">The consuls both are fled without one rite</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107950">Of sacrifice submitted to the gods,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107960">As ever heretofore their custom was</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107970">When they began the bloody frights of war. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107980">In which our two great soldiers now encountering,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e107990">Since both left Rome, opposed in bitter skirmish,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108000">Pompey (Not willing yet to hazard battle,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108010">By Cato's counsel, urging good cause) fled:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108020">Which firing Caesar's spirit; he pursued</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108030">So home, and fiercely, that great Pompey scorning</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108040">The heart he took, by his aduised flight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108050">Despised advice as much as his pursuit. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108060">And as in Lybia, an aged lion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108070">Urged from his peaceful covert, fears the light</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108080">With his unready and diseased appearance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108090">Gives way to chase a while, and coldly hunts ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108100">Till with the youthful hunter's wanton heat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108110">He all his cool wrath frets into a flame:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108120">And then his sides he swings with his stern,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108130">To lash his strength up, let's down all his brows</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108140">About his burning eyes; erects his mane,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108150">Breaks all his throat in thunders, and to wreak</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108160">His hunter's insolence, his heart even barking;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108170">He frees his fury, turns, and rushes back</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108180">With such a ghastly horror, that in heaps,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108190">His proud foes fly, and he that station keeps:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108200">So Pompey's cool spirits, put to all their heat</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108210"><pb facs="14"/> by Caesar's hard pursuit he turned fresh head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108220">And flew upon his foe with such a rapture</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108230">As took up into furies, all friends fears;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108240">Who fired with his first turning, all turned head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108250">And gave so fierce a charge, their followers fled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108260">Whose instant issue on their both sides, see,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108270">And after set out such a tragedy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108280">As all the princes of the earth may come</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108290">To take their patterns by the spirits of Rome. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e108300">Alarm, after which enter Caesar following Crassinius calling to the soldiers.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108310" who="A18425-crassus">
            <speaker>Crass.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e108320">Stay cowherd, fly ye Caesar's fortunes?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108330" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108340">Forbear foolish Crassinius, we contend in vain</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108350">To stay these vapours, and must raise our camp. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108360" who="A18425-crassus">
            <speaker>Crass.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108370">How shall we rise (My lord) but all in uproars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108380">Being still pursued? </l>
            <stage xml:id="A18425-e108390">Enter Acilius.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108400">The pursuit stays, my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108410">Pompey hath sounded a retreat, resigning</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108420">His time to you to use, in instant raising</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108430">Your ill-lodged army, pitching now where fortune</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108440">May good amends make for her fault today. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108450" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108460">It was not fortune's fault, but mine Acilius,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108470">To give my foe charge, being so near the sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108480">Where well I knew the eminence of his strength,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108490">And should have driven th'encounter further off;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108500">Bearing before me such a goodly country,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108510">So plentiful, and rich, in all things fit</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108520">To have supplied my armies want with victuals,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108530">And th'able cities too, to strengthen it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108540">Of Macedon and Thessaly ▪ where now</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108550">I rather was besieged for want of food,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108560">Then did assault with fighting force of arms. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e108570"><pb facs="14"/>Enter Anthony, Vibius, with others. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108580" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e108590">See, sir, here's one friend of your foes recovered.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108600" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e108610">Vibius? In happy hour.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108620" who="A18425-vib">
            <speaker>Vib.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e108630">For me unhappy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108640" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e108650">What? brought against your will?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108660" who="A18425-vib">
            <speaker>Vib.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e108670">Else had not come.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108680" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108690">Sir, he's your prisoner, but had made you his,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108700">Had all the rest pursued the chase like him;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108710">He drave on like a fury; passed all friends,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108720">But we that took him quick in his engagement. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108730" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108740">O Vibius, you deserve to pay a ransom</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108750">Of infinite rate, for had your general joined</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108760">In your addression, or known how to conquer;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108770">This day had proved him the supreme of Caesar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108780" who="A18425-vib">
            <speaker>Vib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108790">Known how to conquer? His five hundred conquests</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108800">Achieved ere this day, make that doubt unfit</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108810">For him that flies him; for, of issues doubtful</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108820">Who can at all times put on for the best? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108830">If I were mad, must he his army venture</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108840">In my engagement? Nor are generals ever</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108850">Their powers disposers, by their proper angels,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108860">But trust against them, oftentimes, their counsels,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108870">Wherein, I doubt not, Caesar's self hath erred</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108880">Sometimes, as well as Pompey. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108890" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108900">Or done worse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108910">In disobeying my counsel (Vibius)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108920">Of which, this days abused light is witness;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108930">By which I might have seen a course secure</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108940">Of this discomfiture. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e108950" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108960">Amends sits ever</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108970">Above repentance, what's done, wish not undone;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108980">But that prepared patience that you know</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e108990">Best fits a soldier charged with hardest fortunes;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109000">Asks still your use, since powers still temperate kept</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109010">Open still the clearer eyes by one faults sight</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109020"><pb facs="15"/> to place the next act, in the surer right. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109030" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109040">You prompt me nobly sir, repairing in me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109050">Mine own stays practice, out of whose repose</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109060">The strong convulsions of my spirits forced me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109070">Thus far beyond my temper; but good Vibius,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109080">Be ransomed with my love, and haste to Pompey,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109090">Entreating him from me, that we may meet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109100">And for that reason which I know this day</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109110">(Was given by Cato, for his pursuits stay</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109120">Which was prevention of our Roman blood)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109130">Propose my offer of our hearty peace. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109140">That being reconciled, and mutual faith</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109150">Given on our either part, not three days' light</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109160">May further show us foes, but (Both our armies</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109170">Dispersed in garrisons) we may return</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109180">Within that time to Italy, such friends</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109190">As in our country's love, contain our spleens</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109200" who="A18425-vib">
            <speaker>Vib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109210">'Tis offered, sir, 'bove the rate of Caesar</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109220">In other men, but in what I approve</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109230">Beneath his merits: which I will not fail</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109240">T'enforce at full to Pompey, nor forget</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109250">In any time the gratitude of my service. <stage xml:id="A18425-e109260">Vi. salutes Ant. and the other, and exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109270" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e109280">Your love, sir, and your friendship.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109290" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109300">This prepares a good induction to the change of fortune,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109310">In this day's issue, if the pride it kindles</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109320">In Pompey's veins, makes him deny a peace</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109330">So gently offered: for her altered hand</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109340">Works never surer from her ill to good</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109350">On his side she hath hurt, and on the other</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109360">With other changes, then when means are used</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109370">To keep her constant, yet retire refused. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109380" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109390">I try no such conclusion, but desire</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109400">Directly peace. In mean space I'll prepare</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109410">For other issue in my utmost means;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109420">Whose hopes now resting at Brundusium,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109430">In that part of my army, with Sabinus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109440">I wonder he so long delays to bring me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109450"><pb facs="15"/> and must in person haste him, if this even</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109460">I hear not from him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109470" who="A18425-crassus">
            <speaker>Crass.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109480">That (I hope) flies far</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109490">Your full intent, my lord, since Pompey's navy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109500">You know, lies hovering all alongst those seas,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109510">In too much danger, for what aid soever</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109520">You can procure to pass your person safe. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109530" who="A18425-unassigned">
            <speaker>Acil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109540">Which doubt may prove the cause that stays Sabinus;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109550">And, if with shipping fit to pass your army,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109560">He yet strains time to venture, I presume</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109570">You will not pass your person with such convoy</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109580">Of those poor vessels, as may serve you here. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109590" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109600">How shall I help it? shall I suffer this</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109610">Torment of his delay? and rack suspicions</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109620">Worse than assured destructions through my thoughts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109630" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109640">Past doubt he will be here; I left all ordered,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109650">And full agreement made with him to make</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109660">All utmost haste, no least let once suspected. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109670" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109680">Suspected? what suspection should fear a friend</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109690">In such assured straits from his friend's enlargement. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109700">If 'twere his soldier's safeties he so tenders,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109710">Were it not better they should sink by sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109720">Then wrack their number, King and cause ashore? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109730">Their stay is worth their ruin, should we live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109740">If they in fault were? if their leader! he</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109750">Should die the deaths of all; in mean space, I</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109760">That should not, bear all, fly the sight in shame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109770">Thou eye of nature, and abortive night</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109780">Fall dead amongst us: with defects, defects</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109790">Must serve proportion; justice never can</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109800">Be else restored, nor right the wrongs of man. <stage xml:id="A18425-e109810">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e109820">Pompey, Cato, Gabinius, Demetrius, Athenodorus, Porcius, Statilius.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109830" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pomp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109840">This charge of our fierce foe, the friendly gods</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109850">Have in our stregthened spirits beaten back</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109860"><pb facs="16"/> with happy issue, and his forces lessened,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109870">Of two and thirty ensigns forced from him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109880">Two thousand soldiers slain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109890" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109900">O boast not that,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109910">Their loss is yours, my lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109920" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pomp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109930">I boast it not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109940">But only name the number. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e109950" who="A18425-gab">
            <speaker>Gab.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109960">Which right well</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109970">You might have raised so high, that on their tops</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109980">Your throne was offered, ever t'overlook</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e109990">Subverted Caesar, had you been so blessed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110000">To give such honour to your captain's counsels</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110010">As their alacrities did long to merit</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110020">With proof-ful action. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e110030" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e110040">O 'twas ill neglected.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e110050" who="A18425-stat">
            <speaker>Stat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110060">It was deferred with reason, which not yet</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110070">Th'event so clear is to confute. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e110080" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110090">If 'twere,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110100">Our likeliest than was, not to hazard battle,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110110">Th'adventure being so casual; if compared</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110120">With our more certain means to his subversion? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110130">For finding now our army amply stored</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110140">With all things fit to tarry surer time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110150">Reason thought better to extend to length</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110160">The war betwixt us; that his little strength</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110170">May by degrees prove none; which urged now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110180">(Consisting of his best and ablest soldiers)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110190">We should have found at one direct set battle</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110200">Of matchless valours; their defects of victual</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110210">Not tiring yet enough on their tough nerves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110220">Where, on the other part, to put them still</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110230">In motion, and remotion, here and there;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110240">Enforcing them to fortifying still</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110250">Wherever they set down; to siege a wall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110260">Keep watch all night in armour: their most part</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110270">Can never bear it, by their years oppression;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110280">Spent heretofore too much in those steel toils. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e110290" who="A18425-cato">
            <pb facs="16"/>
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110300">I so advised, and yet repent it not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110310">But much rejoice in so much saved blood</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110320">As had been poured out in the stroke of battle,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110330">Whose fury thus prevented, comprehends</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110340">Your countries' good, and empires ▪ in whose care</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110350">Let me beseech you that in all this war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110360">You sack no city, subject to our rule,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110370">Nor put to sword one citizen of Rome;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110380">But when the needful fury of the sword</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110390">Can make no fit distinction in main battle,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110400">That you will please still to prolong the stroke</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110410">Of absolute decision to these jars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110420">Considering you shall strike it with a man</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110430">Of much skill and experience, and one</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110440">That will his conquest sell at infinite rate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110450">If that must end your difference; but I doubt</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110460">There will come humble offer on his part,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110470">Of honoured peace to you, for whose sweet name</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110480">So cried out to you in our late-met senate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110490">Lost no fit offer of that wished treaty. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110500">Take pity on your countries' blood as much</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110510">As possible may stand without the danger</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110520">Of hindering her justice on her foes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110530">Which all the gods to your full wish dispose. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e110540" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110550">Why will you leave us? whither will you go</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110560">To keep your worthiest person in more safety</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110570">Than in my army, so devoted to you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e110580" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110590">My person is the least, my lord, I value;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110600">I am commanded by our powerful senate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110610">To view the cities, and the kingdom's situate</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110620">About your either army, that which side</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110630">Soever conquer, no disordered stragglers</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110640">Puffed with the conquest, or by need impelled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110650">May take their swinge more than the care of one</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110660">May curb and order in these neighbour confines</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110670">My chief pass yet resolves for Utica. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e110680" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110690">Your pass (My truest friend, and worthy father)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110700"><pb facs="17"/> may all good powers make safe, and always answer</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110710">Your infinite merits, with their like protection. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110720">In which, I make no doubt but we shall meet</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110730">With mutual greetings, or for absolute conquest</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110740">Or peace preventing that our bloody stroke,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110750">Nor let our parting be dishonoured so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110760">As not to take into our noblest notice</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110770">Yourself (Most learned and admired father)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110780">Whose merits, if I live, shall lack no honour. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110790">Porcius, Statilius, though your spirits with mine</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110800">Would highly cheer me, yet ye shall bestow them</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110810">In much more worthy conduct; but love me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110820">And wish me conquest, for your countries' sake. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e110830" who="A18425-stat">
            <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110840">Our lives shall seal our loves, sir, with worst death ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110850">Adventured in your service. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e110860" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110870">You're my friends. <stage xml:id="A18425-e110880">Exeunt. Cat. Athen. Por. Sat.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110890">These friends thus gone, 'tis more than time we minded</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110900">Our lost friend Vibius. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e110910" who="A18425-gab">
            <speaker>Gab.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110920">You can want no friends,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110930">See, our two consuls, sir, betwixt them bringing</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110940">The worthy Brutus. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e110950">Enter two consuls leading Brutus betwixt them.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e110960" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Cons. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110970">We attend (My lord)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110980">With no mean friend, to spirit your next encounter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e110990">Six thousand of our choice patrician youths</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111000">Brought in his conduct. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111010" who="A18425-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2 Cons,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111020">And though never yet ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111030">He hath saluted you with any word</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111040">Or look of slenderest love in his whole life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111050">Since that long time since, of his father's death</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111060">By your hand authored; yet see, at your need</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111070">He comes to serve you freely for his country. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111080" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111090">His friendly presence, making up a third</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111100">With both your persons, I as gladly welcome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111110">As if Jones triple flame had guilt this field,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111120"><pb facs="17"/> and lightened on my right hand, from his shield. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111130" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>B●●. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111140">I well assure myself, sir, that no thought</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111150">In your ingenious construction, touches</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111160">At the aspersion that my tendred service</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111170">Proceeds from my despair of elsewhere safety</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111180">But that my countries' safety owning justly</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111190">My whole liabilities of life and fortunes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111200">And you the ablest fautor of her safety,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111210">Her love, and (For your love of her) your own</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111220">Only makes sacred to your use my offering. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111230" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111240">Far fly all other thought from my construction,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111250">And due acceptance of the liberal honour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111260">Your love hath done me, which the gods are witness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111270">I take as stirred up in you by their favours,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111280">Nor less esteem it then an offering holy;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111290">Since, as of all things, man is said the measure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111300">So your full merits measure forth a man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111310" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Cons. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e111320">See yet, my lord, more friends.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111330" who="A18425-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2 Cons. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e111340">Five Kings, your servants.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e111350">Enter five Kings.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111360" who="A18425-hiberia">
            <speaker>Hib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111370">Conquest and all grace crown the gracious Pompey,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111380">To serve whom in the sacred Roman safety,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111390">Myself, Iberia's King, present my forces. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111400" who="A18425-thess">
            <speaker>Thess.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111410">And I that hold the tributary throne</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111420">Of Grecian Thessaly, submit my homage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111430">To Rome, and Pompey. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111440" who="A18425-cilicia">
            <speaker>Cil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e111450">So Cilicia too.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111460" who="A18425-epir">
            <speaker>Epir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e111470">And so Epirus. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111480" who="A18425-thra">
            <speaker>Thra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111490">Lastly I from Thrace</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111500">Present the duties of my power and service. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111510" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111520">Your royal aides deserve of Rome and Pompey</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111530">Our utmost honours. O may now our fortune</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111540">Not balance her broad breast twixt two light wings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111550">Nor on a slippery globe sustain her steps,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111560">But as the Spartans say, the Paphian Queen</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111570"><pb facs="18"/> (The flood Eurotas passing) laid aside </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111580">Her glass, her ceston, and her amorous graces,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111590">And in Lycurgus' favour; armed her beauties</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111600">With shield and javelin, so may fortune now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111610">The flood of all our enemies forces passing</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111620">With her fair ensigns, and arrived as ours,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111630">Displume her shoulders, cast off her winged shoes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111640">Her faithless, and still-rolling stone spurn from her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111650">And enter our powers as she may remain</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111660">Our firm assistant ▪ that the general aids,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111670">Favours, and honours you perform to Rome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111680">May make her build with you her endless home. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111690" who="A18425-omnes">
            <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111700">The gods vouchsafe it; and our causes right</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111710" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111720">What sudden shade is this? observe my lords,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111730">The night, methinks , comes on before her hour. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e111740">Thunder and lightning.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111750" who="A18425-gab">
            <speaker>Gab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e111760">Nor trust me if my thoughts conceive not so.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111770" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111780">What thin clouds fly the winds, like swiftest shafts</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111790">Along airs middle region. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111800" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Cons. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111810">They presage</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111820">Unusual tempests. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111830" who="A18425-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2 Cons. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111840">And 'tis their repair,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111850">That timeless darken thus the gloomy air. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e111860" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111870">Let's force no omen from it, but avoid</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111880">The vapours furies now by Jove employed. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A18425-e111890">Thunder continued, and Caesar enters disguised.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111900">The wrathful tempest of the angry night,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111910">Where hell flies muffled up in clouds of pitch,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111920">Mingled with sulphur, and those dreadful bolts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111930">The Cyclops ram in Jove's artillery,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111940">Hath roused the furies, armed in all their horrors,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111950">Up to the envious seas, in spite of Caesar. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111960">O night, oh jealous night, of all the noblest</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111970">Beauties, and glories, where the gods have stroke</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111980">Their four digestions, from thy ghastly chaos,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e111990"><pb facs="18"/> blush thus to drown them all in this hour signed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112000">By the necessity of fate for Caesar. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112010">I that have ransacked all the world for worth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112020">To form in man the image of the gods,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112030">Must like them have the power to check the worst</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112040">Of all things under their celestial empire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112050">Stoop it, and burst it, or break through it all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112060">With use and safety, till the crown be set</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112070">On all my actions; that the hand of nature</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112080">In all her worst works aiming at an end,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112090">May in a masterpiece of hers be served</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112100">With tops, and state fit for his virtuous crown:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112110">Not lift arts thus far up in glorious frame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112120">To let them vanish thus in smoke and shame. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112130">This river Anius (In whose mouth now lies</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112140">A pinnace I would pass in, to fetch on</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112150">My armies dull rest from Brundusium)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112160">That is at all times else exceeding calm,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112170">(By reason of a purling wind that flies</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112180">Off from the shore each morning, driving up</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112190">The billows far to sea) in this night yet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112200">Bears such a terrible gale; put off from sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112210">As beats the land wind back, and thrusts the flood</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112220">Up in such uproar, that no boat dare stir</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112230">And on it is dispersed all Pompey's navy</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112240">To make my peril yet more envious. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112250">Shall I yet shrink for all? were all, yet more? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112260">There is a certain need that I must give</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112270">Way to my pass; none, known, that I must live. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e112280">Enter master of a ship with sailors</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112290" who="A18425-mast">
            <speaker>Mast.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112300">What battle is there sought now in the air. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112310">That threats the wrack of nature? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112320" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112330">Master? come. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112340">Shall we thrust through it all? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112350" who="A18425-mast">
            <speaker>Mast.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112360">What lost man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112370"><pb facs="19"/> art thou in hopes and fortunes, that dar'st make</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112380">So desperate a motion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112390" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112400">Launch man, and all thy fears freight disavow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112410">Thou carriest Caesar and his fortunes now. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A18425-e112420">
          <head>Act iii. Scene i.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e112430">Pompey, two consuls, five Kings, Brutus, Gabinitis, Demetrius.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112440">Now to Pharsalia, where the smarting strokes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112450">Of our resolved contention must resound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112460">(My lords and friends of Rome) I give you all</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112470">Such welcome as the spirit of all my fortunes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112480">Conquests, and triumphs (Now come for their crown)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112490">Can crown your favours with, and serve the hopes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112500">Of my dear country, to her utmost wish;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112510">I can but set up all my being to give</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112520">So good an end to my forerunning acts;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112530">The powers in me that formed them having lost</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112540">No least time since, in gathering skill to better;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112550">But like so many bees have brought me home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112560">The sweet of whatsoever flowers have grown</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112570">In all the meads, and gardens of the world. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112580">All which hath grown still, as the time increase</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112590">In which 'twas gathered, and with which it stemmed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112600">That what decay soever blood inferred,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112610">Might with my mind's store, be supplied, and cheered,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112620">All which, in one fire of this instant 〈◊〉</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112630">I'll burn, and sacrifice to every cinder</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112640">In sacred offering to my countries' love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112650">And therefore what event soever sort,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112660">As I no praise will look for, but the good</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112670">Freely bestow on all; (If good succeed)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112680"><pb facs="19"/> so if adverse fate fall, I wish no blame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112690">But th'ill befallen me, made my fortune's shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e112700">Not mine, nor my fault. </l>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112710" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Cons. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112720">We too well love Pompey,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112730">To do him that injustice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112740" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112750">Who more thirsts</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112760">The conquest, then resolves to bear the foil? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112770" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112780">Said brutus-like, give several witness all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112790">That you acquit me whatsoever fall. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112800" who="A18425-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2 Cons. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112810">Particular men particular fates must bear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112820">Who feels his own wounds less, to wound another? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112830" who="A18425-thess">
            <speaker>Thess.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112840">Leave him the worst whose best is left undone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112850">He only conquers whose mind still is one. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112860" who="A18425-epir">
            <speaker>Epir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e112870">Free minds, like dice, fall sqare, whate'er the cast.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112880" who="A18425-ibir">
            <speaker>Ibir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e112890">Who on himself sole stands, stands solely fast.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112900" who="A18425-thra">
            <speaker>Thra.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e112910">He's never down, whose mind fights still aloft.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112920" who="A18425-cilicia">
            <speaker>Cil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e112930">Who cares for up or down, when all's but thought.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112940" who="A18425-gab">
            <speaker>Gab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e112950">To things events doth no man's power extend.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112960" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e112970">Since gods rule all, who any thing would mend.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e112980" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e112990">Ye sweetly ease my charge, yourselves unburdening. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113000">Returned not yet our trumpet, sent to know</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113010">Of Vibius' certain state? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113020" who="A18425-gab">
            <speaker>Gab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e113030">Not yet, my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113040" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pomp.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113050">Too long protract we all means to recover</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113060">His person quick or dead, for I still think</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113070">His loss served fate, before we blew retreat;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113080">Though some affirm him seen, soon after fighting. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113090" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e113100">Not after, sir, (I heard) but ere it ended.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113110" who="A18425-gab">
            <speaker>Gab</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113120">He bore a great mind to extend our pursuit</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113130">Much further than it was; and served that day</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113140">(When you had, like the true head of a battle,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113150">Led all the body in that glorious turn)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113160">Upon a far-off squadron that stood fast</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113170">In conduct of the great Marc Anthony,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113180">When all the rest were fled, so passed a man</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113190">That in their tough receipt of him, I saw him</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113200">Thrice break thorough all with ease, and pass as fair</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113210"><pb facs="20"/> as he had all been fire, and they but air. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113220" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e113230">He stuck at last yet, in their midst, it seemed.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113240" who="A18425-gab">
            <speaker>Gab.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113250">So have I seen a fire drake glide at midnight</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113260">Before a dying man to point his grave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113270">And in it stick and hide. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113280" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e113290">He comes yet safe.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e113300">A trumpet sounds, and enters before Vibius, with others.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113310" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113320">O Vibius, welcome, what a prisoner? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113330">With mighty Caesar, and so quickly ransomed? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113340" who="A18425-vib">
            <speaker>Vib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113350">I sir, my ransom, needed little time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113360">Either to gain agreement for the value,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113370">Or the disbursement, since in Caesar's grace</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113380">We both concluded. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113390" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e113400">Was his grace so free</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113410" who="A18425-vib">
            <speaker>Vib.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e113420">For your respect, sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113430" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113440">Nay, sir, for his glory. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113450">That the main conquest he so surely builds on,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113460">(Which ever is forerun with petty fortunes)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113470">Take not effect, by taking any friend</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113480">From all the most, my poor defence can make,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113490">But must be complete, by his perfect own. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113500" who="A18425-vib">
            <speaker>Vib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113510">I know, sir, you more nobly rate the freedom</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113520">He freely gave your friend; then to pervert it</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113530">So passed his wisdom: that knows much too well</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113540">Th'uncertain state of conquest; to raise frames</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113550">Of such presumption on her fickle wings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113560">And chiefly in a loss so late, and grievous ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113570">Besides, your forces far exceeding his,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113580">His whole powers being but two and twenty thousand:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113590">And yours full four and forty thousand strong:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113600">For all which yet, he stood as far from fear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113610">In my enlargement, as the confident glory</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113620">You please to put on him; and had this end</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113630">In my so kind dismission, that as kindly</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113640"><pb facs="20"/> I might solicit a sure peace betwixt you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113650" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e113660">A peace? Is't possible?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113670" who="A18425-vib">
            <speaker>Vib.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e113680">Come, do not show this wanton incredulity too much.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113690" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113700">Believe me I was far from such a thought</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113710">In his high stomach: Cato prophesied then. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113720">What think my lords our consuls, and friend Brutus? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113730" who="A18425-omnes">
            <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e113740">An offer happy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113750" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e113760">Were it plain and hearty.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113770" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e113780">Ay, there's the true inspection to his prospect.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113790" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113800">This straight of his perhaps may need a sleight</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113810">Oh some hid stratagem, to bring him off. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113820" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113830">Devices of a new forge to entrap me? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113840">I rest in Caesar's shades? walk his strow'd paths? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113850">Sleep in his quiet waves? I'll sooner trust</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113860">Hibernian bogs, and quicksands; and hell mouth</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113870">Take for my sanctuary: in bad parts</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113880">That no extremes will better, nature's finger</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113890">Hath marked him to me, to take heed of him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113900">What thinks my Brutus? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113910" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e113920">'Tis your best and safest.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e113930" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113940">This offered peace of his is sure a snare</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113950">To make our war the bloodier, whose fit fear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113960">Makes me I dare not now (In thoughts maturer</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113970">Then late inclined me) put in use the counsel</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113980">Your noble father Cato (Parting) gave me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e113990">Whose much too tender shunning innocent blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114000">This battle hazards now, that must cost more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114010" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Cons. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e114020">It does, and therefore now no more defer it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114030" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e114040">Say all men so?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114050" who="A18425-omnes">
            <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e114060">We do.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114070" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114080">I grieve ye do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114090">Because I rather wish to err with Cato</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114100">Then with the truth go of the world besides;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114110">But since it shall abide this other stroke. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114120">Ye gods that our great Roman genius</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114130">Have made, not give us one day's conquest only,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114140">Nor grow in conquests for some little time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114150"><pb facs="21"/> as did the genius of the Macedons;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114160">Nor be by land great only, like Laconians;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114170">Nor yet by sea alone, as was th'athenians;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114180">Nor slowly stirred up, like the Persian angel;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114190">Nor rocked asleep soon, like the Ionian spirit. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114200">But made our Roman genius, fiery, watchful,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114210">And even from Rome's prime, joined his youth with hers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114220">Grow as she grew, and firm as earth abide,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114230">By her increasing pomp, at sea, and shore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114240">In peace, in battle; against Greece as well</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114250">As our barbarian foes; command yet further</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114260">Ye firm and just gods, our assistful angel</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114270">For Rome, and Pompey, who now fights for Rome;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114280">That all these royal laws, to us, and justice</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114290">Of common safety, may the self-love drown</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114300">Of tyrannous Caesar; and my care for all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114310">Your altars crowned with endless festival. <stage xml:id="A18425-e114320">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e114330">Caesar, Anthony, a soothsayer, Crassinius, Acilius, with others.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114340" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114350">Say (Sacred soothsayer) and inform the truth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114360">What liking hast thou of our sacrifice? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114370" who="A18425-soothsayer">
            <speaker>Soothsayer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114380">Imperial Caesar, at your sacred charge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114390">I drew a milk white ox into the temple,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114400">And turning there his face into the East,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114410">(Fearfully shaking at the shining light)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114420">Down fell his horned forehead to his hoof,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114430">When I began to greet him with the stroke,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114440">That should prepare him for the holy rites,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114450">With hideous roars he laid out such a throat</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114460">As made the secret lurkings of the god</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114470">To answer echo-like, in threatening sounds:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114480">I stroke again at him, and then he slept,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114490">His life-blood boiling out at every wound</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114500">In streams as clear as any liquid ruby,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114510">And there began to alter my presage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114520"><pb facs="21"/> the other ill signs showing th'other fortune,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114530">Of your last skirmish, which far opposite now</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114540">Proves, ill beginnings good events foreshow. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114550">For now the beast cut up, and laid on th'altar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114560">His limbs were all licked up with instant flames,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114570">Not like the elemental fire that burns</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114580">In household uses, lamely struggling up,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114590">This way and that way winding as it rises,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114600">But (Right and upright) reached his proper sphere</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114610">Where burns the fire eternal and sincere. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114620" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e114630">And what may that presage?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114640" who="A18425-soothsayer">
            <speaker>Soothsayer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114650">That even the spirit</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114660">Of heaven's pure flame flew down and ravished up</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114670">Your offerings blaze in that religious instant,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114680">Which shows th'alacrity and cheerful virtue</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114690">Of heaven's free bounty, doing good in time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114700">And with what swiftness true devotions climb. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114710" who="A18425-omnes">
            <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e114720">The gods be honoured.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114730" who="A18425-soothsayer">
            <speaker>Soothsayer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114740">O behold with wonder,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114750">The sacred blaze is like a torch enlightened,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114760">Directly burning just above your camp! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114770" who="A18425-omnes">
            <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e114780">Miraculous.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114790" who="A18425-soothsayer">
            <speaker>Soothsayer</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114800">Believe it, with all thanks:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114810">The Roman genius is altered now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114820">And arms for Caesar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114830" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114840">Soothsayer be for ever</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114850">Reverenced of Caesar. O Marc Anthony,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114860">I thought to raise my camp, and all my tents,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114870">Took down for swift remotion to Scotussa. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114880">Shall now our purpose hold ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114890" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114900">Against the gods? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114910">They grace in th'instant, and in th'instant we</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114920">Must add our parts, and be in th'use as free. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114930" who="A18425-crassus">
            <speaker>Crass.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e114940">See sir, the scouts return. <stage xml:id="A18425-e114950">Enter two scouts.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114960" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e114970">What news, my friends?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e114980" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Scou.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e114990">Arm, arm, my lord; the vanguard of the foe</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115000">Is ranged already:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e115010" who="A18425-yyyy_2">
            <pb facs="22"/>
            <speaker>2 Scou.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115020">Answer them, and arm:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115030">You cannot set your rest of battle up</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115040">In happier hour; for I this night beheld</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115050">A strange confusion in your enemy's camp,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115060">The soldiers taking arms in all dismay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115070">And hurling them again as fast to earth. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115080">Every way routing; as th'alarm were then</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115090">Given to their army. A most causeless fear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115100">Dispersed quite through them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e115110" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115120">Then 'twas Jove himself</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115130">That with his secret finger stirred in them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e115140" who="A18425-crassus">
            <speaker>Crass.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115150">Other presages of success (My lord)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115160">Have strangely happened in th'adjacent cities,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115170">To this your army: for in Tralleis,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115180">Within a temple, built to victory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115190">There stands a statue of your form and name,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115200">Near whose firm base, even from the marble pavement,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115210">There sprang a palm tree up, in this last night,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115220">That seems to crown your statue with his boughs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115230">Spread in wrapped shadows round about your brows. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e115240" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115250">The sign, Crassinius, is most strange and graceful,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115260">Nor could get issue, but by power divine;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115270">Yet will not that, nor all abodes besides</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115280">(Of never such kind promise of success)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115290">Perform it without tough acts of our own. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115300">No care, no nerve the less to be employed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115310">No offering to the gods, no vows, no prayers:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115320">Secure and idle spirits never thrive</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115330">When most the gods for their advancements strive. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115340">And therefore tell me what abodes thou buildest on</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115350">In an spirit to act, inflamed in thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115360">Or in our soldiers seen resolved addresses? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e115370" who="A18425-crassus">
            <speaker>Crass.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115380">Great and fiery virtue. And this day</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115390">Be sure (Great Caesar) of effects as great</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115400">In absolute conquest; to which are prepared</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115410">Enforcements resolute, from this armed hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115420">Which thou shalt praise me for alive or dead. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e115430" who="A18425-caesar">
            <pb facs="22"/>
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115440">Alive (Ye gods vouchsafe) and my true vows</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115450">For life in him (Great heaven) for all my foes</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115460">(Being natural Romans) so far jointly hear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115470">As may not hurt our conquest; as with fear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115480">Which thou already strangely hast diffused</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115490">Through all their army; which extend to flight</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115500">Without one bloody stroke of force and fight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e115510" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e115520">'Tis time, my lord, you put in form your battle.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e115530" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115540">Since we must fight then, and no offered peace</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115550">Will take with Pompey: I rejoice to see</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115560">This long-time looked for, and most happy day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115570">In which we now shall fight, with men, not hunger,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115580">With toils, not sweats of blood through years extended,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115590">This one day serving to decide all jars</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115600">Twixt me and Pompey. Hang out of my tent</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115610">My crimson coat of arms, to give my soldiers</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115620">That ever-sure sign of resolved-for fight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e115630" who="A18425-crassus">
            <speaker>Crass.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e115640">These hands shall give that sign to all their longings.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e115650">Exit Crass.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e115660" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115670">My lord, my army, I think best to order</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115680">In three full squadrons: of which let me pray</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115690">Yourself would take on you the left wings charge;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115700">Myself will lead the right wing, and my place</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115710">Of fight elect in my tenth legion ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115720">My battle by Domitius Calvinus</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115730">Shall take direction. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e115740">The coat of arms is hung out, and the soldier's shout within.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e115750" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>An.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115760">Hark, your soldier's shout</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115770">For joy to see your bloody coat of arms</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115780">Assure their fight this morning. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e115790" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115800">A blessed even</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115810">Bring on them worthy comforts. And ye gods</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115820">Perform your good presages in events</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115830">Of fit crown for our discipline, and deeds</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115840">Wrought up by conquest; that my use of it</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115850"><pb facs="23"/> may wipe the hateful and unworthy slain</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115860">Of tyrant from my temples, and exchange it</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115870">For fautor of my country, ye have given</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115880">That title to those poor and fearful souls</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115890">That every sound puts up, in frights and cries;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115900">Even then, when all Rome's powers were weak and heartless,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115910">When traitorous fires, and fierce barbarian swords,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115920">Rapines, and soul-expiring slaughters filled</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115930">Her houses, temples, all her air, and earth. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115940">To me then (Whom your bounties have informed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115950">With such a spirit as despiseth fear;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115960">Commands in either fortune, knows, and arms</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115970">Against the worst of fate; and therefore can</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115980">Dispose blessed means, encouraged to the best)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e115990">Much more vouchsafe that honour; chiefly now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116000">When Rome wants only this day's conquest given me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116010">To make her happy, to confirm the brightness</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116020">That yet she shines in over all the world;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116030">In empire, riches, strife of all the arts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116040">In gifts of cities, and of kingdoms sent her;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116050">In crowns laid at her feet, in every grace</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116060">That shores, and seas, floods, islands, continents,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116070">Groves, fields, hills, mines, and metals can produce;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116080">All which I (Victor) will increase, I vow</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116090">By all my good, acknowledged given by you. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A18425-e116100">
          <head>Act iiii scene i.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e116110">Pompey in haste, Brutus, Gabinius, Vibius following.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116120">The poison steeped in every vain of empire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116130">In all the world, meet now in only me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116140">Thunder and lighten me to death; and make</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116150">My senses feed the flame, my soul the crack. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116160"><pb facs="23"/>Was ever sovereign captain of so many</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116170">Armies and nations, so oppressed as I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116180">With one hosts headstrong outrage? urging fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116190">Yet fly about my camp in panic terrors;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116200">No reason under heaven suggesting cause. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116210">And what is this but even the gods deterring ▪</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116220">My judgement from enforcing fight this morn? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116230">The new-fled night made day with meteors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116240">Fired over Caesar's camp, and fallen in mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116250">As pointing out the terrible events</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116260">Yet in suspense; but where they threat their fall</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116270">Speak not these prodigies with fiery tongues,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116280">And eloquence that should not move but ravish</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116290">All sound minds, from thus tempting the just gods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116300">And spitting out their fair premonishing flames</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116310">With brackish rheums of ruder and brainsick number,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116320">What's infinitely more, thus wild, thus mad</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116330">For one poor fortune of a beaten few;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116340">To half so many stayed, and dreadful soldiers? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116350">Long trained, long foughten? able, nimble, perfect</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116360">To turn and wind advantage every way? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116370">Increase with little, and enforce with none? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116380">Made bold as lions, gaunt as famished wolves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18425-e116390">With still-served slaughters, and continual toils. </l>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e116400" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116410">You should not, sir, forsake your own wise counsel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116420">Your own experienced discipline, own practice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116430">Own god inspired insight to all changes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116440">Of Protean fortune, and her zany, war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116450">For hosts, and hells of such; what man will think</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116460">The best of them, not mad; to see them range</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116470">So up and down your camp, already suing</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116480">For offices fallen, by Caesars built on fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116490">Before one stroke be struck? Domitius, Spinther,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116500">Your father Scipio new preparing friends</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116510">For Caesar's place of universal Bishop? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116520">Are you th' observed rule, and vouched example;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116530">Whoever would commend physicians,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116540"><pb facs="24"/> that would not follow the diseased desires</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116550">Of their sick patients? yet incur yourself</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116560">The faults that you so much abhor in others. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e116570" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116580">I cannot, sir, abide men's open mouths,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116590">Nor be ill spoken of; nor have my counsels</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116600">And circumspections, turned on me for fears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116610">With mocks and scandals that would make a man</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116620">Of lead, a lightning; in the desperat'st onset</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116630">That ever trampled under death, his life. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116640">I bear the touch of fear for all their safeties. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116650">Or for mine own? enlarge with twice as many</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116660">Self-lives, self-fortunes? they shall sink beneath</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116670">Their own credulities, before I cross them. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116680">Come, haste, dispose our battle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e116690" who="A18425-vib">
            <speaker>Vib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116700">Good my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116710">Against your genius war not for the world. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e116720" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116730">By all worlds he that moves me next to bear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116740">Their scoffs and imputations of my fear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116750">For any cause, shall bear this sword to hell. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116760">Away, to battle; good my lord lead you</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116770">The whole six thousand of our young patricians,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116780">Placed in the left wing to environ Caesar. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116790">My father Scipio shall lead the battle;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116800">Domitius the left wing; I the right</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116810">Against Marc Anthony. Take now your fills</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116820">Ye beastly doters on your barbarous wills. <stage xml:id="A18425-e116830">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e116840">Alarm, excursions, of all: the five Kings driven over the stage, Crassinius chiefly pursuing: at the door enter again the five Kings. The battle continued within.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e116850" who="A18425-epir">
            <speaker>Epir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e116860">Fly, fly, the day was lost before 'twas fought.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e116870" who="A18425-thess">
            <speaker>Thess.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e116880">The Romans feared their shadows.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e116890" who="A18425-cilicia">
            <speaker>Cil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116900">Were there ever</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116910">Such monstrous confidences, as last night</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116920">Their cups and music showed? Before the morning</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116930"><pb facs="24"/> made such amazes ere one stroke was struck? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e116940" who="A18425-iber">
            <speaker>Iber.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116950">It made great Pompey mad, which who could mend? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116960">The gods had hand in it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e116970" who="A18425-tra">
            <speaker>Tra.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116980">It made the consuls</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e116990">Run on their swords to see't. The brave patricians</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117000">Fled with their spoilt faces, arrows sticking</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117010">As shot from heaven at them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e117020" who="A18425-thess">
            <speaker>Thess.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117030">'Twas the charge</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117040">That Caesar gave against them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e117050" who="A18425-epir">
            <speaker>Epir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117060">Come, away,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117070">Leave all, and wonder at this fatal day. <stage xml:id="A18425-e117080">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e117090">The fight nearer; and enter, Crassineus, a sword, as thrust through his face; he falls. To him Pompey and Caesar fighting: Pompey gives way, Caesar follows, and enters at another door.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e117100" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117110">Pursue, pursue; the gods foreshowed their powers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117120">Which we gave issue, and the day is ours. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117130">Crassineus? O look up: he does, and shows</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117140">Death in his broken eyes; which Caesar's hands</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117150">Shall do the honour of eternal closure. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117160">Too well thou keptst thy word, that thou this day</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117170">Wouldst do me service to our victory. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117180">Which in thy life or death I should behold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117190">And praise thee for; I do, and must admire</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117200">Thy matchless valour; ever ever rest</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117210">Thy manly lineaments, which in a tomb</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117220">Erected to thy noble name and virtues,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117230">I'll curiously preserve with balms, and spices,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117240">In eminent place of these Pharsalian fields,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117250">Inscribed with this true soul of funeral,</l>
            <lg xml:id="A18425-e117260">
              <head>Epitaphi</head>
              <l xml:id="A18425-e117270">Crassineus fought for fame, and died for Rome,</l>
              <l xml:id="A18425-e117280">Whose public weal springs from this private tomb. </l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e117290"><pb facs="25"/>Enter some taking him off, whom Caesar helps. Enter Pompey, Demetrius, with black robes in their hands, broad hats, etc. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e117300" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117310">Thus have the gods their justice, men their wills,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117320">And I, by men's wills ruled; myself renouncing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117330">Am by my angel and the gods abhorred;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117340">Who drew me, like a vapour, up to heaven</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117350">To dash me like a tempest 'gainst the earth:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117360">Oh the deserved terrors that attend</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117370">On humane confidence! had ever men</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117380">Such outrage of presumption to be victors</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117390">Before they armed? To send to Rome before</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117400">For houses near the market place, their tents</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117410">Strewed all with flowers, and nosegays; tables covered</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117420">With cups and banquets; bays and myrtle garlands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117430">As ready to do sacrifice for conquest</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117440">Rather than arm them for fit fight t'enforce it;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117450">Which when I saw, I knew as well th'event</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117460">As now I feel it, and because I raged</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117470">In that presage, my genius showing me clearly</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117480">(As in a mirror) all this cursed issue;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117490">And therefore urged all means to put it off</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117500">For this day, or from these fields to some other,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117510">Or from this ominous confidence, till I saw</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117520">Their spirits settled in some graver knowledge</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117530">Of what belonged to such a dear decision;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117540">They spotted me with fear, with love of glory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117550">To keep in my command so many Kings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117560">So great an army; all the hellish blastings</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117570">That could be breathed on me, to strike me blind</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117580">Of honour, spirit and soul: and should I then</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117590">Save them that would in spite of heaven be ruined? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117600">And, in their safeties ruin me and mine</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117610">In everlasting rage of their detraction. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e117620" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117630">Your safety and own honour did deserve</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117640"><pb facs="25"/> respect passed all their values; oh my lord</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117650">Would you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e117660" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e117670">Upbraid me not; go to, go on.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e117680" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117690">No; I'll not rub the wound. The misery is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117700">The gods for any error in a man</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117710">(Which they might rectify, and should; because</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117720">That man maintained the right) should suffer wrong</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117730">To be thus insolent, thus graced, thus blessed? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e117740" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117750">O the strange carriage of their acts, by which</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117760">Men order theirs; and their devotions in them;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117770">Much rather striving to entangle men</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117780">In pathless error, then with regular right</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117790">Confirm their reasons, and their piety's light. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117800">For now sir, whatsoever was foreshown</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117810">By heaven, or prodigy; ten parts more for us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117820">Forewarning us, deterring us, and all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117830">Our blind and brainless frenzies, then for Caesar;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117840">All yet will be ascribed to his regard</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117850">Given by the gods for his good parts, preferring</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117860">Their gloss (Being stark impostures) to the justice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117870">Love, honour, piety, of our laws and country. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117880">Though I think these are arguments enough</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117890">For my acquittal, that for all these fought. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e117900" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e117910">You're clear, my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e117920" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117930">Gods help me, as I am;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117940">Whatever my untouched command of millions</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117950">Through all my eight and fifty years, hath won,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117960">This one day (In the world's esteem) hath lost. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117970">So vile is praise and dispraise by event. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117980">For I am still myself in every worth</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e117990">The world could grace me with, had this days even</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118000">In one blaze joined, with all my other conquests. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118010">And shall my comforts in my well-known self</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118020">Fail me for their false fires, Demetrius? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e118030" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e118040">O no, my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e118050" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118060">Take grief for them, as if</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118070">The rotten-hearted world could steep my soul</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118080"><pb facs="26"/> in filthy putrefaction of their own? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118090">Since their applauses fail me? that are hisses</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118100">To every sound acceptance? I confess,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118110">That till th'affair was past, my passions flamed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118120">But now 'tis helpless, and no cause in me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118130">Rest in these embers my unmoved soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118140">With any outward change, this distich minding;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118150">No man should more allow his own loss, woes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118160">(Being passed his fault) then any stranger does. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118170">And for the world's false loves, and airy honours,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118180">What soul that ever loved them most in life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118190">(Once severed from this breathing sepulchre)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118200">Again came and appeared in any kind</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118210">Their kind admirer still, or did the state</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118220">Of any best man here, associate? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118230">And every true soul should be here so severed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118240">From love of such men, as here drown their souls</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118250">As all the world does? Cato sole accepted,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118260">To whom I'll fly now, and my wife in way</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118270">(Poor lady, and poor children, worse than fatherless)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118280">Visit, and comfort. Come Demetrius ▪<stage xml:id="A18425-e118290">They disguise themselves.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118300">We now must suit our habits to our fortunes</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118310">And since these changes ever chance to greatest. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118320">Nor desire to be</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118330">(Do fortune, to exceed it, what she can)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118340">A Pompey, or a Caesar, but a man. <stage xml:id="A18425-e118350">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e118360">Enter Caesar, Anthony, Acilius, with soldiers.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e118370" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118380">O we have slain, not conquered, Roman blood</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118390">Perverts th'event, and desperate blood let out</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118400">With their own swords. Did ever men before</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118410">Envy their own lives, since another lived</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118420">Whom they would wilfully conceive their foe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118430">And forge a tyrant merely in their fears</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118440">To justify their slaughters? Consul's? furies. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e118450" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118460">Be, sir, their faults their griefs! The greater number</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118470"><pb facs="26"/> were only slaves, that left their bloods to ruth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118480">And altogether, but six thousand slain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e118490" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118500">However many; gods and men can witness</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118510">Themselves enforced it, much against the most</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118520">I could enforce on Pompey for our peace. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118530">Of all slain, yet, if Brutus only lived,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118540">I should be comforted, for his life saved</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118550">Would weigh the whole six thousand that are lost. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118560">But much I fear his death, because the battle</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118570">Full stricken now, he yet abides unfound. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e118580" who="A18425-unassigned">
            <speaker>Acil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118590">I saw him fighting near the battles end,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118600">But suddenly give off, as bent to fly. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e118610">Enter Brutus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e118620" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Anth.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e118630">He comes here, see sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e118640" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118650">I submit to Caesar</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118660">My life and fortunes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e118670" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118680">A more welcome fortune</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118690">Is Brutus, than my conquest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e118700" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118710">Sir, I fought</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118720">Against your conquest, and yourself; and merit</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118730">(I must acknowledge) a much sterner welcome. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e118740" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118750">You fought with me, sir, for I know your arms</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118760">Were taken for your country, not for Pompey:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118770">And for my country I fought, nothing less</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118780">Than he, or both the mighty-stomached consuls;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118790">Both whom (I hear) have slain themselves before</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118800">They would enjoy life in the good of Caesar. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118810">But I am nothing worse, how ill soever</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118820">They, and the great authority of Rome</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118830">Would fain enforce me by their mere suspicions. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118840">Loved they their country better than her Brutus? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118850">Or knew what fitted noblesse, and a Roman</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118860">With freer souls than Brutus. Those that live</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118870">Shall see in Caesar's justice. and whatever </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118880">Might make me worthy both their lives and loves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118890"><pb facs="27"/> that I have lost the one without my merit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118900">And they the other with no Roman spirit. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118910">Are you impaired to live, and joy my love? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118920">Only requite me, Brutus, love but Caesar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118930">And be in all the powers of Caesar, Caesar. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118940">In which free wish, I join your father Cato;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118950">For whom I'll haste to Utica, and pray</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e118960">His love may strengthen my success today. <stage xml:id="A18425-e118970">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e118980">Porcius in haste, Marcillius bore, following. Porcius discovers a bed, and a sword hanging by it, which he takes down.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e118990" who="A18425-marcus">
            <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e119000">To what use take you that (My lord?)</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119010" who="A18425-porcius">
            <speaker>Por.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119020">Take you</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119030">No note that I take it, nor let any servant,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119040">Besides yourself, of all my father's nearest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119050">Serve any mood he serves, with any knowledge</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119060">Of this or any other, Caesar comes</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119070">And gives his army wings to reach this town. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119080">Not for the town's sake, but to save my father. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119090">Whom justly he suspects to be resolved</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119100">Of any violence to his life, before</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119110">He will preserve it by a tyrant's favour. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119120">For Pompey hath miscarried, and is fled. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119130">Be true to me, and to my father's life;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119140">And do not tell him; nor his fury serve</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119150">With any other. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119160" who="A18425-marcus">
            <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119170">I will die, my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119180">Ere I observe it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119190" who="A18425-porcius">
            <speaker>Por.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e119200">O my lord and father.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e119210">Cato, Athenodorus, Statilius. Cato with a book in his hand.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119220" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119230">What fears fly here on all sides? what wild looks</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119240">Are squinted at me from men's mere suspicions</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119250"><pb facs="27"/> that I am wild myself, and would enforce</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119260">What will be taken from me by the tyrant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119270" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119280">No: would you only ask life, he would think</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119290">His own life given more strength in giving yours</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119300" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e119310">I ask my life of him?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119320" who="A18425-stat">
            <speaker>Stat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119330">Ask what's his own? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119340">Of him he scorns should have the least drop in it</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119350">At his disposure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119360" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119370">No, Statilius. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119380">Men that have forfeit lives by breaking laws,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119390">Or have been overcome, may beg their lives,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119400">But I have ever been in every justice</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119410">Better than Caesar, and was never conquered,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119420">Or made to fly for life, as Caesar was. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119430">But have been victor ever, to my wish,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119440">'Gainst whomsoever ever hath opposed;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119450">Where Caesar now is conquered in his conquest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119460">In the ambition, he till now denied;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119470">Taking upon him to give life, when death</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119480">Is tenfold due to his most tyrannous self. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119490">No right, no power given him to raise an army,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119500">Which in despite of Rome he leads about</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119510">Slaughtering her loyal subjects, like an outlaw,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119520">Nor is he better. Tongue, show, falsehood are,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119530">To bloodiest deaths his parts so much admired,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119540">Vainglory, villainy; and at best you can,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119550">Fed with the parings of a worthy man. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119560">My fame affirm my life received from him? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119570">I'll rather make a beast my second father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119580" who="A18425-stat">
            <speaker>Stat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119590">The gods avert from every Roman mind</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119600">The name of slave to any tyrant's power. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119610">Why was man ever just, but to be free,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119620">'Gainst all injustice? and to bear about him</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119630">As well all means to freedom every hour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119640">As every hour he should be armed for death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119650">Which only is his freedom? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119660" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119670">But Statilius'</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119680"><pb facs="28"/> death is not free for any man's election,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119690">Till nature, or the law, impose it on him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119700" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119710">Must a man go to law then, when he may</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119720">Enjoy his own in peace? If I can use</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119730">Mine own myself, must I of force, reserve it</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119740">To serve a tyrant with it? All just men</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119750">Not only may enlarge their lives, but must,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119760">From all rule tyrannous, or live unjust. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119770" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e119780">By death must they enlarge their lives?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119790" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e119800">By death.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119810" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e119820">A man's not bound to that.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119830" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119840">I'll prove he is. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119850">Are not the lives of all men bound to justice? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119860" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e119870">They are.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119880" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119890">And therefore not to serve injustice:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119900">Justice itself ought ever to be free,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119910">And therefore every just man being a part</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119920">Of that free justice, should be free as it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119930" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e119940">Then wherefore is there law for death?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e119950" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119960">That all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119970">That know not what law is, nor freely can</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119980">Perform the fitting justice of a man</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e119990">In kingdom's common good, may been forced. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120000">But is not every just man to himself</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120010">The perfectest law ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120020" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e120030">Suppose.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120040" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120050">Then to himself</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120060">Is every just man's life subordinate. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120070">Again, sir; is not our free soul infused</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120080">To everybody in her absolute end</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120090">To rule that body? in which absolute rule</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120100">Is she not absolutely empress of it? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120110">And being empress, may she not dispose</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120120">It, and the life in it, at her just pleasure? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120130" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e120140">Not to destroy it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120150" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120160">No; she not destroys it</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120170">When she dislives it; that their freedoms may</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120180"><pb facs="28"/> go firm together, like their powers and organs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120190">Rather than let it live a rebel to her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120200">Profaning that divine conjunction</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120210">Twixt her and it; nay, a disjunction making</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120220">Betwixt them worse than death; in killing quick</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120230">That which in just death lives: being dead to her</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120240">If to her rule dead; and to her alive,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120250">If dying in her just rule. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120260" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120270">The body lives not</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120280">When death hath rest it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120290" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120300">Yet 'tis free, and kept</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120310">Fit for rejunction in man's second life;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120320">Which dying rebel to the soul, is far</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120330">Unfit to join with her in perfect life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120340" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e120350">It shall not join with her again.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120360" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e120370">It shall.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120380" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e120390">In reason shall it?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120400" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120410">In apparent reason;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120420">Which I'll prove clearly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120430" who="A18425-stat">
            <speaker>Stat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e120440">Hear, and judge it sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120450" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120460">As nature works in all things to an end,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120470">So in th'appropriate honour of that end,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120480">All things precedent have their natural frame;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120490">And therefore is there a proportion</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120500">Betwixt the ends of those things and their primes:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120510">For else there could not be in their creation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120520">Always, or for the most part, that firm form</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120530">In their still like existence; that we see</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120540">In each full creature. What proportion then</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120550">Hath an immortal with a mortal substance? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120560">And therefore the mortality to which</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120570">A man is subject; rather is asleep ,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120580">Then bestial death; since sleep and death are called</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120590">The twins of nature. For if absolute death</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120600">And bestial seize the body of a man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120610">Then is there no proportion in his parts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120620">His soul being free from death, which otherwise</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120630"><pb facs="29"/> retains divine proportion for as sleep</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120640">No disproportion holds with humane souls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120650">But aptly quickens the proportion</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120660">Twixt them and bodies, making bodies fitter ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120670">To give up forms to souls, which is their end:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120680">So death (Twin-born of sleep) resolving all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120690">Man's bodies heavy parts; in lighter nature</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120700">Makes a reunion with the sprightly soul;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120710">When in a second life their beings given,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120720">Holds their proportion firm, in highest heaven. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120730" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120740">Hold you our bodies shall revive, resuming</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120750">Our souls again to heaven? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120760" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120770">Past doubt, though others</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120780">Think heaven a world too high for our low reaches. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120790">Not knowing the sacred sense of him that sings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120800">Jove can let down a golden chain from heaven,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120810">Which tied to earth, shall fetch up earth and seas;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120820">And what's that golden chain, but our pure souls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120830">A golden beam of him, let down by him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120840">That governed with his grace, and drawn by him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120850">Can hoist this earthy body up to him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120860">The sea, and air, and all the elements</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120870">Compressed in it: not while 'tis thus concrete,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120880">But fined by death, and then given heavenly heat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120890" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120900">Your happy exposition of that place</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120910">(Whose sacred depth I never heard so sounded)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120920">Evicts glad grant from me you hold a truth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120930" who="A18425-stat">
            <speaker>Stat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e120940">Is't not a manly truth, and mere divine?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e120950" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120960">'Tis a good cheerful doctrine for good men. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120970">But (Son and servants) this is only argued</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120980">To spend our dear time well, and no life urgeth</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e120990">To any violence further than his owner</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121000">And graver men hold fit. Let's talk of Caesar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121010">He's the great subject of all talk, and he</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121020">Is hotly hasting on. Is supper ready? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121030" who="A18425-marcus">
            <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e121040">It is, my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121050" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121060">Why then let's in and eat;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121070"><pb facs="29"/> our cool submission will quench Caesar's heat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121080" who="A18425-stat">
            <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e121090">Submission? here's for him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121100" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121110">Statilus ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121120">My reasons must not strengthen you in error,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121130">Nor learned Athenodorus gentle yielding. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121140">Talk with some other deep philosophers. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121150">Or some divine priest of the knowing gods,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121160">And hear their reasons; in mean time come sup. <stage xml:id="A18425-e121170">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e121180">Cato going out arm in arm betwixt Athen. and Statilius.</stage>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A18425-e121190">
          <head>Act v. scene i.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e121200">Enter ushers, with the two Lentuli, and Septimius before Cornelia; Cyris, Telesilla, Lelia, Drusus, with others, following. Cornelia; Septimius and the two Lentuli reading letters. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121210" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121220">So may my comforts for this good news thrive</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121230">As I am thankful for them to the gods. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121240">Joys unexpected, and in desperate plight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121250">Are still most sweet, and prove from whence they come;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121260">When earth's still moonlike confidence, in joy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121270">Is at her full. True joy descending far</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121280">From passed her sphere, and from that highest heaven</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121290">That moves and is not moved: how far was I</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121300">From hope of these events, when fearful dreams</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121310">Of harpies tearing out my heart? of armies</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121320">Terribly joining? Cities, kingdoms falling,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121330">And all on me? proved sleep, not twin to death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121340">But to me, death itself? yet making then,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121350">These letters; full of as much cheerful life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121360">I found closed in my hand. O gods how justly</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121370">Ye laugh at all things earthly? at all fears</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121380"><pb facs="30"/> that rise not from your judgements? at all joys,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121390">Not drawn directly from yourselves, and in ye,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121400">Distrust in man is faith, trust in him ruin. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121410">Why write great learned men? men merely rapt</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121420">With sacred rage, of confidence, belief? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121430">Undaunted spirits? inexorable fate</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121440">And all fear treading on? 'tis all but air,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121450">If any comfort be, 'tis in despair. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121460" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Len. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e121470">You learned ladies may hold any thing.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121480" who="A18425-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2 Lent.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121490">Now madam is your walk from coach come near</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121500">The promontory, where you late commanded</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121510">A sentinel should stand to see from thence</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121520">If either with a navy, brought by sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121530">Or train by land; great Pompey comes to greet you</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121540">As in your letters, he near this time promised. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121550" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121560">O may this isle of Lesbos, compassed in</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121570">With the Aegaean sea, that doth divide</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121580">Europe from Asia. (The sweet literate world</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121590">From the barbarian) from my barbarous dreams</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121600">Divide my dearest husband and his fortunes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121610" who="A18425-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2 Len. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121620">He's busied now with ordering offices. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121630">By this time, madam, sits your honoured father<stage xml:id="A18425-e121640">He looks in his letter.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121650">In Caesar's chair of universal Bishop. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121660">Domitius Aenobarbas, is made consul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121670">Spinther his consort; and Phaonius</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121680">Tribune, or praetor. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e121690">Septimius with a letter.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121700" who="A18425-sept">
            <speaker>Sep.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121710">These were only sought</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121720">Before the battle, not obtained; nor moving</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121730">My father but in shadows. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121740" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Corn.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121750">Why should men</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121760">Tempt fate with such firm confidence? seeking places</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121770">Before the power that should dispose could grant them? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121780">For then the stroke of battle was not struck. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121790" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Len. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121800">Nay, that was sure enough. Physicians know</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121810"><pb facs="30"/> when sick men's eyes are broken, they must die. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121820">Your letters telling you his victory</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121830">Lost in the skirmish, which I know hath broken</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121840">Both the eyes and heart of Caesar: for as men</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121850">Healthful through all their lives to greyhaired age,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121860">When sickness takes them once, they seldom scape:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121870">So Caesar victor in his general fights</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121880">Till this late skirmish, could no adverse blow</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121890">Sustain without his utter overthrow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121900" who="A18425-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2 Lent.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e121910">See, madam, now; your sentinel: inquire.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121920" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121930">Seest thou no fleet yet (Sentinel) nor train</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121940">That may be thought great Pompey's? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121950" who="A18425-senator">
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e121960">Not yet, madam.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e121970" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Len. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121980">Seest thou no travellers addressed this way? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e121990">In any number on this Lesbian shore? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122000" who="A18425-senator">
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122010">I see some not worth note; a couple coming</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122020">This way, on foot, that are not now far hence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122030" who="A18425-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2 Lent.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122040">Come they apace? like messengers with news?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122050" who="A18425-senator">
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122060">No, nothing like (My lord) nor are their habits</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122070">Of any such men's fashions; being long mantles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122080">And sable hewed; their heads all hid in hats</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122090">Of parching Thessaly, broad brimmed, high crowned. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122100" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122110">These serve not our hopes.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122120" who="A18425-senator">
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122130">Now I see a ship,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122140">A kenning hence; that strikes into the haven. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122150" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122160">One only ship?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122170" who="A18425-senator">
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122180">One only, madam, yet.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122190" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122200">That should not be my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122210" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Lent.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122220">Your lord? no madam.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122230" who="A18425-senator">
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122240">She now lets out armed men upon the land.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122250" who="A18425-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2 Lent.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122260">Armed men? with drum and colours?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122270" who="A18425-senator">
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122280">No, my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122290">But bright in arms, yet bear half pikes, or beadhookes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122300" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Lent.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122310">These can be no plumes in the train of Pompey. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122320" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122330">I'll see him in his letter, once again.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122340" who="A18425-senator">
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122350">Now, madam, come the two I saw on foot.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e122360"><pb facs="31"/>Enter Pompey and Demetrius:</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122370" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122380">See your Princess, sir, come thus far from the</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122390">City in her coach, to encounter your promised coming</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122400">About this time in your last letters. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122410" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122420">The world is altered since Demetrius;<stage xml:id="A18425-e122430">Offer to go by.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122440" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Lent.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122450">See, madam, two Thessalian augurs it seems</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122460">By their habits. Call, and inquire if either by their</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122470">Skills or travels, they know no news of your husband. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122480" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122490">My friends? A word.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122500" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122510">With us, madam?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122520" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122530">Yes. Are you of Thessaly? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122540" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122550">Ay, madam, and all the world besides.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122560" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122570">Your country is great.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122580" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122590">And our portions little.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122600" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122610">Are you augurs?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122620" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122630">Augurs, madam? yes a kind of augurs, alias</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122640">Wizards, that go up and down the world, teaching</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122650">How to turn ill to good. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122660" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122670">Can you do that?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122680" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122690">Ay, madam, you have no work for us, have you? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122700">No ill to turn good, I mean? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122710" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122720">Yes; the absence of my husband.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122730" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122740">What's he?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122750" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122760">Pompey the great.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122770" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122780">Wherein is he great?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122790" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122800">In his command of the world.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122810" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122820">Then he's great in others. Take him without his</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e122830">Addition (Great) what is he then? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122840" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122850">Pompey. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122860" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122870">Not your husband then?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122880" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122890">Nothing the less for his greatness.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122900" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122910">Not in his right; but in your comforts he is.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122920" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122930">His right is my comfort.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122940" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122950">What's his wrong?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122960" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122970">My sorrow.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e122980" who="A18425-dem">
            <pb facs="31"/>
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e122990">And that's ill.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123000" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123010">Yes.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123020" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123030">You're come to the use of our profession, madam,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123040">Would you have that ill turned good? that</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123050">Sorrow turned comfort? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123060" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123070">Why is my lord wronged.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123080" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123090">We profess not that knowledge, madam:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123100">Suppose he were. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123110" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123120">Not I. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123130" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123140">You'll suppose him good.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123150" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123160">He is so.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123170" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123180">Then must you needs suppose him wronged; for</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123190">All goodness is wronged in this world. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123200" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123210">What call you wrong?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123220" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123230">Ill fortune, affliction.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123240" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123250">Think you my lord afflicted?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123260" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123270">If I think him good (Madam) I must. Unless he</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123280">Be worldly good, and then, either he is ill, or has ill:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123290">Since, as no sugar is without poison: so is no worldly</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123300">Good without ill. Even naturally nourished in it, like a</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123310">Household thief, which is the worst of all thieves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123320" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123330">Then he is not worldly, but truly good.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123340" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123350">He's too great to be truly good; for worldly greatness</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123360">Is the chief worldly goodness; and all worldly goodness</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123370">(I proved before) has ill in it: which true good has not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123380" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123390">If he rule well with his greatness, wherein is he ill?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123400" who="A18425-dem">
            <speaker>Dem.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123410">But great rulers are like carpenters that wear their</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123420">Rules at their backs still: and therefore to make good your</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123430">True good in him, y'ad better suppose him little, or mean. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123440">For in the mean only is the true good. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123450" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123460">But every great lady must have her husband</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123470">Great still, or her love will be little. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123480" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123490">I am none of those great ladies.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123500" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Len. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123510">She's a philosophress augur, and can turn</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123520">Ill to good as well as you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123530" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123540">I would then, not honour, but adore her: could you</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123550">Submit yourself cheerfully to your husband,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123560"><pb facs="32"/> supposing him fallen? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123570" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123580">If he submit himself cheerfully to his fortune ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123590" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123600">'Tis the greatest greatness in the world you undertake.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123610" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123620">I would be so great, if he were.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123630" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123640">In supposition.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123650" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123660">In fact.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123670" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123680">Be no woman, but a goddess then; and make good thy greatness;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123690">I am cheerfully fallen; be cheerful. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123700" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123710">I am: and welcome, as the world were closed</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123720">In these embraces. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123730" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123740">Is it possible? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123750">A woman, losing greatness, still as good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123760">As at her greatest? O gods, was I ever</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123770">Great till this minute? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123780" who="A18425-unassigned">
            <speaker>Amb.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123790">Len. Pompey? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123800" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123810">View me better.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123820" who="A18425-unassigned">
            <speaker>Amb.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123830">Len. conquered by Caesar? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123840" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123850">Not I, but mine army. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123860">No fault in me, in it: no conquest of me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123870">I tread this low earth as I trod on Caesar. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123880">Must I not hold myself, though lose the world? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123890">Nor lose I less; a world lost at one clap,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123900">'Tis more than Jove ever thundered with. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123910">What glory is it to have my hand hurl</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123920">So vast a volley through the groaning air? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123930">And is't not great, to turn griefs thus to joys,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123940">That break the hearts of others? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123950" who="A18425-unassigned">
            <speaker>Amb.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e123960">Len. oh 'tis jove-like.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e123970" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123980">It is to imitate Jove, that from the wounds</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e123990">Of softest clouds, beats up the terriblest sounds. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124000">I now am good, for good men still have least,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124010">That twixt themselves and God might rise their rest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124020" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e124030">O Pompey, Pompey: never great till now.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124040" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124050">O my Cornelia: let us still be good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124060">And we shall still be great: and greater far</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124070">In every solid grace, then when the tumour</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124080">And boil of rotten observation swelled us.</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124090"><pb facs="32"/> griefs for wants outward, are without our cure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124100">Greatness, not of itself, is never sure. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124110">Before, we went upon heaven, rather treading</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124120">The virtues of it underfoot, in making</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124130">The vicious world our heaven; then walking there</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124140">Even here, as knowing that our home; contemning</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124150">All forged heavens here raised; setting hills on hills. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124160">Vulcan from heaven fell, yet on's feet did light,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124170">And stood no less a god then at his height;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124180">At lowest things lie fast ▪ we now are like</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124190">The two poles propping heaven, on which heaven moves;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124200">And they are fixed, and quiet, being above</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124210">All motion far; we rest above the heavens. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124220" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124230">O, I more joy, t'embrace my lord thus fixed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124240">Than he had brought me ten inconstant conquests. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124250" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Len</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124260">Miraculous standing in a fall so great,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124270">Would Caesar knew, sir, how you conquered him</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124280">In your conviction. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124290" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124300">'Tis enough for me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124310">That Pompey knows it. I will stand no more</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124320">On others legs: nor build one joy without me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124330">If ever I be worth a house again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124340">I'll build all inward: not a light shall open</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124350">The common outway: no expense, no art,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124360">No ornament, no door will I use there,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124370">But raise all plain, and rudely, like a rampire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124380">Against the false society of men</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124390">That still batters</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124400">All reason piecemeal. And for earthy greatness</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124410">All heavenly comforts ratifies to air,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124420">I'll therefore live in dark, and all my light,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124430">Like ancient temples, let in at my top. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124440">This were to turn ones back to all the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124450">And only look at heaven. Empedocles</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124460">Recured a mortal plague through all his country,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124470">With stopping up the yawning of a hill,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124480">From whence the hollow and unwholesome South</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124490"><pb facs="33"/> exhaled his venomed vapour. And what else</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124500">Is any King, given over to his lusts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124510">But even the poisoned cleft of that cracked mountain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124520">That all his kingdom plagues with his example? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124530">Which I have stopped now, and so cured my country</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124540">Of such a sensual pestilence:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124550">When therefore our diseased affections</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124560">Harmful to humane freedom; and stormlike</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124570">Inferring darkness to th'infected mind</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124580">Oppress our comforts: 'tis but letting in</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124590">The light of reason, and a purer spirit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124600">Take in another way; like rooms that fight</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124610">With window against the wind, yet let in sight. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124620" who="A18425-unassigned">
            <speaker>Amb. Len.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e124630">My lord, we served before, but now adore you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124640" who="A18425-senator">
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124650">My lord, the armed men I discovered lately</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124660">Unshipped, and landed; now are trooping near. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124670" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e124680">What armed men are they?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124690" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Len. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124700">Some, my lord, that lately</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124710">The sentinel discovered, but not knew ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124720" who="A18425-senator">
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124730">Now all the sea (My lords) is hid with ships,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124740">Another promontory flanking this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124750">Some furlong hence, is climbed, and full of people,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124760">That easily may see hither; it seems looking</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124770">What these so near intend: take heed, they come. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e124780">Enter Achillas, Septius, Saluius, with soldiers,</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124790" who="A18425-achillas">
            <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124800">Haile to Rome's great commander; to whom Egypt</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124810">(Not long since seated in his kingdom by thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124820">And sent to by thee in thy passage by)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124830">Sends us with answer: which withdraw and hear. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124840" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e124850">I'll kiss my children first.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124860" who="A18425-sept">
            <speaker>Sep.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e124870">Bless me, my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124880" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124890">I will, and Cyris, my poor daughter too. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124900">Even that high hand that hurled me down thus low,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124910">Keep you from rising high: I hear: now tell me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124920">I think (My friend) you once served under me:</l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e124930">Septius only nods with his head.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124940" who="A18425-pompey">
            <pb facs="33"/>
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124950">Nod only? not a word deign? what are these? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e124960">Cornelia? I am now not worth men's words. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124970" who="A18425-achillas">
            <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e124980">Please you receive your aid, sir?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e124990" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e125000">Ay, I come. <stage xml:id="A18425-e125010">Exit Pom. they draw and follow.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125020" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e125030">Why draw they? See, my lords; attend them ushers.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125040" who="A18425-senator">
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e125050">O they have slain great Pompey. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125060" who="A18425-cornelia">
            <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e125070">O my husband.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125080" who="A18425-unassigned">
            <speaker>Sept. cyr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125090">Mother, take comfort. <stage xml:id="A18425-e125100">Enter Pompey bleeding.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125110">O my lord and father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125120" who="A18425-pompey">
            <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125130">See heavens your sufferings, is my country's love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125140">The justice of an empire; piety;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125150">Worth this end in their leader: last yet life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125160">And bring the gods off fairer: after this</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125170">Who will adore, or serve the deities? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e125180">He hides his face with his robe.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e125190">Enter the murderers.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125200" who="A18425-achillas">
            <speaker>Ach.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e125210">Help hale him off: and take his head for Caesar. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125220" who="A18425-sept">
            <speaker>Sep.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e125230">Mother? O save us; Pompey? O my father.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e125240">Enter the two Lentuli and Demetrius bleeding, and kneel about Cornelia.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125250" who="A18425-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1 Len. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125260">Yet falls not heaven? Madam, oh make good</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125270">Your late great spirits; all the world will say,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125280">You know not how to bear adverse events,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125290">If now you languish. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125300" who="A18425-omnes">
            <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125310">Take her to her coach. <stage xml:id="A18425-e125320">They bear her out.</stage></l>
            <stage xml:id="A18425-e125330">Cato with a book in his hand.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125340">O beastly apprehenders of things manly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125350">And merely heavenly: they with all the reasons</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125360">I used for just men's liberties, to bear</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125370">Their lives and deaths up in their own free hands;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125380">Fear still my resolution though I seem</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125390"><pb facs="34"/> to give it off like them: and now am won</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125400">To think my life in law's rule ▪ not mine own,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125410">When once it comes to death; as if the law</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125420">Made for a sort of outlaws, must bound me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125430">In their subjection; as if I could</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125440">Be racked out of my veins, to live in others;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125450">As so I must, if others rule my life;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125460">And public power keep all the right of death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125470">As if men needs must serve the place of justice;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125480">The form, and idol, and renounce itself? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125490">Ourselves, and all our rights in God and goodness? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125500">Our whole contents and freedoms to dispose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125510">All in the joys and ways of arrant rogues? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125520">No stay but their wild errors, to sustain us? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125530">No forges but their throats to vent our breathes? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125540">To form our lives in, and repose our deaths? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125550">See, they have got my sword. Who's there? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e125560">Enter Marcillius bare.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125570" who="A18425-marcus">
            <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e125580">My lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125590" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125600">Who took my sword hence? Dumb? I do not ask</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125610">For any use or care of it: but hope</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125620">I may be answered. Go sir, let me have it. <stage xml:id="A18425-e125630">Exit Mar.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125640">Poor slaves, how terrible this death is to them? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125650">If men would sleep, they would be wroth with all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125660">That interrupt them physic take to take</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125670">The golden rest it brings: both pay and pray</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125680">For good, and soundest naps all friends consenting</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125690">In those kind invocations; praying all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125700">Good rest, the gods vouchsafe you; put when death</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125710">(Sleeps natural brother) comes; (That's nothing worse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125720">But better; being more rich; and keeps the store;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125730">Sleep ever fickle, wayward still, and poor)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125740">Oh how men grudge, and shake, and dear, and fly</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125750">His stern approaches? all their comforts taken</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125760">In faith, and knowledge of the bliss and beauties</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125770"><pb facs="34"/> that watch their wakings in an endless life:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125780">Drowned in the pains and horrors of their sense</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125790">Sustained but for an hour; be all the earth</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125800">Rapt with this error, lie pursue my reason,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125810">And hold that as my light and fiery pillar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125820">Th'eternal law of heaven and earth no firmer. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125830">But while I seek to conquer conquering Caesar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125840">My soft-spleened servants overrule and curb me. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A18425-e125850">He knocks, and Brutus enters.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125860">Where's he I sent to fetch and place my sword</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125870">Where late I left it? Dumb to? Come another! </l>
            <stage xml:id="A18425-e125880">Enter Cleanthes.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125890">Where's my sword hung here? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125900" who="A18425-cleopatra">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125910">My lord, I know not,<stage xml:id="A18425-e125920">Ent. Marcilius.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e125930" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125940">The rest come in there. Where's the sword I charged you</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125950">To give his place again? I'll break your lips open,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125960">Spite of my freedom; all my servants, friends;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125970">My son and all, will needs betray me naked</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125980">To th' armed malice of a foe so fierce</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e125990">And bear-like, mankind of the blood of virtue. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126000">O gods, whoever saw me thus contemned? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126010">Go call my son in; tell him, that the less</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126020">He shows himself my son, the less I'll care</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126030">To live his father. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e126040">Enter Athenodorus, Porcius ▪ Porcius kneeling; Brutus, Cleanthes and Marcilius by him.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e126050" who="A18425-porcius">
            <speaker>Por.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126060">I beseech you, sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126070">Rest patient of my duty, and my love;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126080">Your other children think on, our poor mother,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126090">Your family, your country. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e126100" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126110">If the gods</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126120">Give over all, I'll fly the world with them. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126130">Athenodorus, I admire the changes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126140">I note in heavenly providence. When Pompey</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126150">Did all things out of course, past right, past reason,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126160"><pb facs="35"/> he stood invincible against the world:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126170">Yet, now his cares grew pious, and his powers</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126180">Set all up for his country, he is conquered. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e126190" who="A18425-athenodorus">
            <speaker>Ath.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126200">The gods wills secret are, nor must we measure</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126210">Their chaste-reserved deeps by our dry shallows. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126220">Sufficeth us, we are entirely such</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126230">As twixt them and our consciences we know</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126240">Their graces, in our virtues, shall present</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126250">Unspotted with the earth; to'th high throne</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126260">That overlooks us: for this giant world</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126270">Let's not contend with it, when heaven itself</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126280">Fails to reform it: why should we affect</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126290">The least hand over it, in that ambition? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126300">A heap 'tis of digested villainy;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126310">Virtue in labour with eternal chaos</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126320">Pressed to a living death, and racked beneath it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126330">Her throws unpitied; every worthy man</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126340">Limb by limb sawn out of her virgin womb,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126350">To live here piecemeal tortured, fly life then;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126360">Your life and death made presidents for men. <stage xml:id="A18425-e126370">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e126380" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126390">Ye hear (My masters) what a life this is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126400">And use much reason to respect it so. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126410">But mine shall serve ye. Yet restore my sword,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126420">Lest too much ye presume, and I conceive</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126430">Ye front me like my fortunes. Where's Statilius? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e126440" who="A18425-porcius">
            <speaker>Por.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126450">I think sir, gone with the three hundred Romans</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126460">In Lucius Caesar's charge, to serve the victor. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e126470" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126480">And would not take his leave of his poor friend? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126490">Then the philosophers have stooped his spirit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126500">Which I admire, in one so free, and knowing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126510">And such a fiery hater of base life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126520">Besides, being such a vowed and noted foe</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126530">To our great conqueror. But I advised him</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126540">To spare his youth, and live. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e126550" who="A18425-porcius">
            <speaker>Por.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126560">My brother Brutus</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126570">Is gone to Caesar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e126580" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126590">Brutus? Of mine honour</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126600"><pb facs="35"/> (Although he be my son in law) I must say</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126610">There went as worthy, and as learned a precedent</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126620">As lives in Rome's whole rule, for all life's actions;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126630">And yet your sister Porcia (His wife)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126640">Would scarce have done this. But (For you my son)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126650">However Caesar deals with me; be counseled</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126660">By your experienced father, not to touch</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126670">At any action of the public weal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126680">Nor any rule bear near her politic stern:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126690">For, to be upright, and sincere therein</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126700">Like Cato's son, the time's corruption</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126710">Will never bear it: and, to soothe the time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126720">You shall do basely, and unworthy your life;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126730">Which, to the gods I wish, may outweigh mine</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126740">In every virtue; howsoever ill</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126750">You thrive in honour. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e126760" who="A18425-porcius">
            <speaker>Por.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126770">Ay, my lord, shall gladly</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126780">Obey that counsel. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e126790" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126800">And what needed you</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126810">Urge my kind care of any charge that nature</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126820">Imposes on me? have I ever shown</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126830">Love's least defect to you? or any dues</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126840">The most indulgent father (Being discreet)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126850">Could do his dearest blood? do you me right</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126860">In judgement, and in honour; and dispense</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126870">With passionate nature: go, neglect me not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126880">But send my sword in. Go, 'tis I that charge you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e126890" who="A18425-porcius">
            <speaker>Por.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e126900">O my lord, and father, come, advise me. <stage xml:id="A18425-e126910">Exeunt.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e126920" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126930">What have I now to think on in this world? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126940">No one thought of the world, I go each minute</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126950">Discharged of all cares that may fit my freedom. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126960">The next world, and my soul, then let me serve</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126970">With her last utterance, that my body may</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126980">With sweetness of the passage drown the sour</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e126990">That death will mix with it: the consul's souls</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127000">That slew themselves so nobly, scorning life</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127010">Led under tyrants sceptres, mine would see. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127020"><pb facs="36"/>For we shall know each other; and passed death</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127030">Retain those forms of knowledge learned in life;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127040">Since, if what here we learn, we there shall lose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127050">Or immortality were not life, but time. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127060">And that our souls in reason are immortal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127070">Then natural and proper objects prove;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127080">Which immortality and knowledge are. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127090">For to that object ever is referred</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127100">The nature of the soul, in which the acts</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127110">Of her high faculties are still employed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127120">And that true object must her powers obtain</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127130">To which they are in natures aim directed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127140">Since 'twere absurd to have her sit an object</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127150">Which possibly she never can aspire. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e127160">Enter a page with his sword taken out before.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127170" who="A18425-page">
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e127180">Your sword, my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127190" who="A18425-cato">
            <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127200">O is it found? lay down</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127210">Upon the bed (My boy)<stage xml:id="A18425-e127220">Exit pa.</stage>poor men; a boy</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127230">Must be presenter; manhood at no hand</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127240">Must serve so foul a fact; for so are called</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127250">(In common mouths) men's fairest acts of all. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127260">Unsheathe; is't sharp? 'tis sweet. Now I am safe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127270">Come Caesar, quickly now, or lose your vassal. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127280">Now wing thee, dear soul, and receive her heaven. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127290">The earth, the air, and seas I know, and all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127300">The joys, and horrors of their peace and wars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127310">And now will see the god's state, and the stars. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e127320">He falls upon his sword, and enter Statilius at another side of the stage with his sword drawn, Porcius, Brutus, Cleanthes and Marcilius holding his hands.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127330" who="A18425-stat">
            <speaker>Stat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e127340">Cato? my lord?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127350" who="A18425-porcius">
            <speaker>Por.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127360">I swear (Statilius)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127370"><pb facs="36"/> he's forth, and gone to seek you, charging me</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127380">To seek elsewhere, lest you had slain yourself;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127390">And by his love entreated you would live. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127400" who="A18425-stat">
            <speaker>Sta.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e127410">I swear by all the gods, I'll run his fortunes.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127420" who="A18425-porcius">
            <speaker>Por.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127430">You may, you may; but shun the victor now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127440">Who near is, and will make us all his slaves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127450" who="A18425-stat">
            <speaker>Sta</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e127460">He shall himself be mine first, and my slaves. <stage xml:id="A18425-e127470">Exit.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127480" who="A18425-porcius">
            <speaker>Por.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127490">Look, look in to my father, oh (I fear)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127500">He is no sight for me to bear and live. <stage xml:id="A18425-e127510">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127520" who="A18425-all">
            <speaker>Omn. 3</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e127530">O ruthful spectacle ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127540" who="A18425-cleopatra">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e127550">He hath ripped his entrails.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127560" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e127570">Search, search; they may be sound.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127580" who="A18425-cleopatra">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127590">They may, and are. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127600">Give leave, my lord, that I may sew them up</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127610">Being yet unperished. <stage xml:id="A18425-e127620">He thrusts him back, and plucks out his entrails.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127630" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127640">Stand off; now they are not. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127650">Have he my curse that my life's least part saves. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127660">Just men are only free, the rest are slaves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127670" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e127680">Mirror of men.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127690" who="A18425-marcus">
            <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e127700">The gods envied his goodness.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A18425-e127710">Enter Caesar, Anthony, Brutus, Acilius, with lords and citizens of Utica.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127720" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127730">Too late, too late; with all our haste. O Cato,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127740">All my late conquest, and my life's whole acts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127750">Most crowned, most beautified, are basted all</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127760">With thy grave life's expiring in their scorn. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127770">Thy life was rule to all lives, and thy death</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127780">(Thus forcibly despising life) the quench</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127790">Of all life's glories. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127800" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127810">Unreclaimed man? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127820">How censures Brutus his stern father's fact? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127830" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e127840">'Twas not well done.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127850" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127860">O censure not his acts;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127870">Who knew as well what fitted man, as all men. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A18425-e127880"><pb facs="37"/>Enter Achilius, Septimius, Salvius, with Pompey's head. </stage>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127890"><stage xml:id="A18425-e127900">All kneeling.</stage>your enemy's head great Caesar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e127910" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127920">Cursed monsters,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127930">Wound not mine eyes with it, nor in my camp</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127940">Let any dare to view it; far as noblesse</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127950">The den of barbarism flies, and bliss</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127960">The bitterest curse of vexed and tyrannised nature,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127970">Transfer it from me. Born the plagues of virtue</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127980">How durst ye poison thus my thoughts? to torture</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e127990">Them with instant rapture. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e128000" who="A18425-all">
            <speaker>Omn. 3.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e128010">Sacred Caesar. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e128020" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128030">Away with them; I vow by all my comforts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128040">Who slack seems, or not fiery in my charge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128050">Shall suffer with them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e128060" who="A18425-all">
            <speaker>All the soldiers.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128070">Out base murderers;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128080">Tortures, tortures for them:<stage xml:id="A18425-e128090">Bale them out. </stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e128100" who="A18425-omnes">
            <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e128110">Cruel Caesar. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e128120" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e128130">Too mild with any torture.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e128140" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128150">Let me crave</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128160">The ease of my hate on their one cursed life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e128170" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128180">Good Brutus take it; oh you cool the poison</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128190">These villain's flaming poured upon my spleen</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128200">To suffer with my loathings. If the blood</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128210">Of every common roman touched so near;</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128220">Shall I confirm the false brand of my tyranny</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128230">With being found a fautor of his murder</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128240">Whom my dear country choosed to fight for her? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e128250" who="A18425-antony">
            <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e128260">Your patience sir, their tortures well will quit you ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e128270" who="A18425-brutus">
            <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A18425-e128280">Let my slaves use, sir, be your precedent.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A18425-e128290" who="A18425-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128300">It shall, I swear: you do me infinite honour. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128310">O Cato, I envy thy death, since thou</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128320">Enviedst my glory to preserve thy life. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128330">Why fled his son and friend Statilius? </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128340">So far I fly their hurt, that all my good</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128350">Shall fly to their desires. And (For himself)</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128360"><pb facs="37"/> my lords and citizens of Utica,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128370">His much renown of you, quit with your most. </l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128380">And by the sea, upon some eminent rock,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128390">Erect his sumptuous tomb; on which advance</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128400">With all fit state his statue; whose right hand</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128410">Let hold his sword, where, may to all times rest</l>
            <l xml:id="A18425-e128420">His bones as honoured as his soul is blessed. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A18425-e128430">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A18425"><item xml:id="A18425-pompey" n="55">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-pompey</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">55</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-caesar" n="49">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-caesar</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">49</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-cato" n="48">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-cato</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">48</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-cornelia" n="37">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-cornelia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">37</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A18425-fron" n="32">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-fron</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">32</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-oph" n="31">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-oph</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">31</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-dem" n="30">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-dem</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">30</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-yyyy_1" n="19">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">19</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-athenodorus" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-athenodorus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-antony" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-antony</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-brutus" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-brutus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-yyyy_2" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-yyyy_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-met" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-met</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-stat" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-stat</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-porcius" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-porcius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-senator" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-senator</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-unassigned" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-omnes" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-omnes</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-vib" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-vib</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-gab" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-gab</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-crassus" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-crassus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-marcus" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-marcus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-epir" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-epir</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-thess" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-thess</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-soothsayer" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-soothsayer</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-achillas" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-achillas</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-cilicia" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-cilicia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-cleopatra" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-cleopatra</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-all" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-sept" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-sept</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-mast" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-mast</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-min" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-min</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-thra" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-thra</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-xxxx_3" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-xxxx_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-hiberia" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-hiberia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-xxxx_2" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-xxxx_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-incomplete" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-incomplete</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-iber" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-iber</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-page" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-page</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-xxxx_4" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-xxxx_4</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-ruffians" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-ruffians</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-xxxx_1" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-xxxx_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-xxxx_5" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-xxxx_5</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-tra" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-tra</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18425-ibir" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18425-ibir</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

