<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A09221">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Battle of Alcazar <date type="creation_date">1589</date></title>
        <author>Peele, George</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Madeline Burg</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A09221.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The battell of Alcazar fought in Barbarie, betweene Sebastian king of Portugall, and Abdelmelec king of Marocco. With the death of Captaine Stukeley. As it was sundrie times plaid by the Lord high Admirall his seruants.</title>
            <author>Peele, George, 1556-1596.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>26 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99845899</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 19531.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 127.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">10830</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09221</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The battell of Alcazar fought in Barbarie, betweene Sebastian king of Portugall, and Abdelmelec king of Marocco. With the death of Captaine Stukeley. As it was sundrie times plaid by the Lord high Admirall his seruants.</title>
            <title type="alt">Battle of Alcazar.</title>
            <author>Peele, George, 1556-1596.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[52] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>By Edward Allde for Richard Bankworth, and are to be solde at his shoppe in Pouls Churchyard at the signe of the Sunne,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1594.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Anonymous. By George Peele.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-E F4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A09221-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A09221-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A09221-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A09221-e100040"><pb facs="1"/>The battle of Alcazar, fought in Barbary, between Sebastian King of Portugal, and Abdelmelec King of Morocco. With the death of captain Stukeley. As it was sundry times played by the lord high admiral his servants.</p>
        <p xml:id="A09221-e100050">Imprinted at London by Edward Allde for Richard Bankworth, and are to be sold at his shop in Paul's churchyard at the sign of the sun. 1594.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A09221-e100060">
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A09221-e100070">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>The tragical battle of Alcazar in Barbary. With the death of three Kings, and captain Stukeley an Englishman.</head>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e100080" who="A09221-presenter">
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e100090">Enter the presenter.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100100">Honour the spur that pricks the princely mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100110">To follow rule and climb the stately chair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100120">With great desire inflames the Portingal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100130">An honourable and courageous King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100140">To undertake a dangerous dreadful war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100150">And aid with christian arms the barbarous Moor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100160">The negro Muly Hamet that withholds</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100170">The kingdom from his uncle Abdelmelec,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100180">Whom proud Abdallas wronged,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100190">And in his throne installs his cruel son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100200">That now usurps upon this prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100210">This brave barbarian lord Muly Molocco. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100220">The passage to the crown by murder made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100230">Abdallas dies, and reigns this tyrant King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100240">Of whom we treat sprung from the Arabian Moor</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100250">Black in his look, and bloody in his deeds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100260">And in his shirt stained with a cloud of gore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100270">Presents himself with naked sword in hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100280">Accompanied as now you may behold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100290">With devils coted in the shapes of men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e100300" who="A09221-presenter">
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e100310"><pb facs="3"/>The first dumb show. Enter Muly Mahamet and his son, and his two young brothers, the Moor showeth them the bed, and then takes his leave of them, and they betake them to their rest. And then the presenter speaketh.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100320">Like those that were by kind of murder mummed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100330">Sit down and see what heinous stratagems</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100340">These damned wits contrive. And lo alas</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100350">How like poor lambs prepared for sacrifice;</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100360">This traitor King hales to their longest home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100370">These tender lords his younger brothers both. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e100380" who="A09221-presenter">
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e100390">The second dumb show. Enter the Moor and two murderers bringing in his uncle Abdelmunen, then they draw the curtains and smother the young princes in the bed. Which done, in sight of the uncle they strangle him in his chair, and then go forth. And then the presenter saith.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100400">His brothers thus in fatal bed behearsed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100410">His father's brother of too light belief. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100420">This negro puts to death by proud command. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100430">Say not these things are feigned, for true they are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100440">And understand how eager to enjoy</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100450">His father's crown this unbelieving Moor</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100460">Murdering his uncle and his brothers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100470">Triumphs in his ambitious tyranny,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100480">Till Nemesis high mistress of revenge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100490">That with her scourge keeps all the world in awe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100500">With thundering drums awakes the god of war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100510">And calls the furies from Avernus' crags,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100520">To range and rage and vengeance to inflict</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100530">Vengeance on this accursed Moor for sin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100540">And now behold how Abdelmelec comes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100550">Uncle to this unhappy traitor King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100560"><pb facs="3"/> armed with great aid that Amurath had sent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100570">Great Amurath emperor of the East,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100580">For service done to sultan Soliman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100590">Under whose colours he had served in field,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100600">Flying the fury of this negro's father,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100610">That wronged his brothers to install his son. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100620">Sit you and see this true and tragic war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100630">A modern matter full of blood and ruth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100640">Where three bold Kings confounded in their height,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100650">Fell to the earth contending for a crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100660">And call this war the battle of Alcazar. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e100670">Exit.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e100680">Sound drums and trumpets, and enter Abdelmelec with Calsepius bassa and his guard, and Zareo a Moor with soldiers.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e100690" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100700">All-hail Argerd Zareo and ye Moors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100710">Salute the frontiers of your native home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100720">Cease rattling drums, and Abdelmelec here</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100730">Throw up thy trembling hands to heaven's throne</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100740">Pay to thy god due thanks and thanks to him</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100750">That strengthens thee with mighty gracious arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100760">Against the proud usurper of thy right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100770">The royal seat and crown of Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100780">Great Amurath great emperor of the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100790">The world bear witness how I do adore</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100800">The sacred name of Amurath the great. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100810">Calsepius bassa, bassa Calcepius</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100820">To thee and to thy trusty band of men</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100830">That carefully attend us in our camp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100840">Picked soldiers comparable to the guard</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100850">Of Myrmidons, that kept Achilles' tent</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100860">Such thanks we give to thee and to them all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100870">As may concern a poor distressed King</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100880">In honour and in princely courtesy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e100890" who="A09221-bassa">
          <speaker><pb facs="4"/>Bassa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100900">Courteous and honourable Abdelmelec,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100910">We are not come at Amurath's command,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100920">As mercenary men to serve for pay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100930">But as sure friends by our great master sent</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100940">To gratify and to remunerate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100950">Thy love, thy loyalty, and forwardness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100960">Thy service in his father's dangerous war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100970">And to perform in view of all the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100980">The true office of right and royalty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e100990">To see thee in thy kingly chair enthroned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101000">To settle and to seat thee in the same,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101010">To make thee emperor of this Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101020">Are come the viceroys and sturdy janissaries</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101030">Of Amurath, son to sultan Soliman. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e101040">Enter Muly Mahamet Xeque, Rubin arches, Abdil rays, with others.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e101050" who="A09221-raye">
          <speaker>Abdil rays</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101060">Long live my lord the sovereign of my heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101070">Lord Abdelmelech whom the god of Kings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101080">The mighty Amurath hath happy made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101090">And long live Amurath for this good deed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e101100" who="A09221-muly-mahomet">
          <speaker>Muly Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101110">Our Moors have seen the silver moons to wane,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101120">In banners bravely spreading over the plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101130">And in this semicircles have descried</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101140">All in a golden field a star to rise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101150">A glorious comet that begins to blaze,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101160">Promising happy sorting to us all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e101170" who="A09221-rubin">
          <speaker>Rubyn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101180">Brave man at arms whom Amurath hath sent</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101190">To sow the lawful true succeeding seed</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101200">In Barbary, that bows and groans withal</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101210">Under a proud usurping tyrant's mace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101220">Right thou the wrongs this rightful King hath born. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e101230" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker><pb facs="4"/>Abdilm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101240">Distressed ladies and ye dames of Fez,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101250">Sprung from the true Arabian Muly Xarif</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101260">The lodestar and the honour of our line,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101270">Now clear your watery eyes, wipe tears away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101280">And cheerfully give welcome to these arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101290">Amurath hath sent scourges by his men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101300">To whip that tyrant traitor King from hence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101310">That hath usurped from us, and maimed you all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101320">Soldier's sith rightful quarrels aid</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101330">Successful are, and men that manage them</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101340">Fight not in fear as traitors and their fers</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101350">That you may understand what arms we bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101360">What lawful arms against our brother's son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101370">In sight of heaven, even of mine honour's worth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101380">Truly I will deliver and discourse</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101390">The sum of all. Descended from the line</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101400">Of Mahomet, our grandsire Mulizaref</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101410">With store of gold and treasure leaves Arabia,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101420">And strongly plants himself in Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101430">And of the Moors that now with us do wend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101440">Our grandsire Mulizaref was the first,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101450">From him well wot ye Muly Mahamet Xeque,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101460">Who in his life time made a perfect law,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101470">Confirmed with general voice of all his peers</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101480">That in his kingdom should successively</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101490">His sons succeed. Abdullas was the first</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101500">Eldest of four Abdelmenen the second,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101510">And we the rest my brother and myself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101520">Abdullas reigned his time. But see the change,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101530">He labours to invest his son in all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101540">To disannul the law our father made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101550">And disinherit us his brothers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101560">And in his life time wrongfully proclaims,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101570">His son for King that now contends with us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101580">Therefore I crave to reobtain my right</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101590"><pb facs="5"/> that Muly Mahamet the traitor holds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101600">Traitor and bloody tyrant both at once,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101610">That murdered his younger brothers both,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101620">But on this damned wretch, this traitor King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101630">The gods shall pour down showers of sharp revenge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101640">And thus a matter not to you unknown</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101650">I have delivered. Yet for no distrust</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101660">Of loyalty my well-beloved friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101670">But that the occasions fresh in memory</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101680">Of these encounters, so may move your minds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101690">As for the lawful true succeeding prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101700">Ye neither think your lives nor honours dear</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101710">Spent in a quarrel just and honourable. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e101720" who="A09221-bassa">
          <speaker>Bassa.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101730">Such and no other we repute the cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101740">That forwardly for thee we undertake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101750">Thrice puissant and renowned Abdelmelec,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101760">And for thine honour, safety and crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101770">Our lives and honours frankly to expose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101780">To all the dangers that our war attends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101790">As freely and as resolutely all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101800">As any Moor whom thou commandest most. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e101810" who="A09221-muly_xe">
          <speaker>Muly Xe.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101820">And why is Abdelmelec then so slow</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101830">To chastise him with fury of the sword,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101840">Whose pride doth swell to sway beyond his reach,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101850">Follow this pride then with fury of revenge. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e101860" who="A09221-rubin">
          <speaker>Rub. Ar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101870">Of death, of blood, of wreak, and deep revenge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101880">Shall Rubin archis frame her tragic songs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101890">In blood, in death, in murder and misdeed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101900">This heaven's malice did begin and end. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e101910" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdilm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101920">Rubin these rights to Abdelmunen's ghost,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101930">Have pierced by this to Pluto's grave below,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101940">The bells of Pluto ring revenge amain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101950">The furies and the fiends conspire with thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101960">War bids me draw my weapons for revenge</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101970"><pb facs="5"/> of my deep wrongs, and my dear brother's death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e101980" who="A09221-muly_xe">
          <speaker>Muly Xe.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e101990">Sheath not your swords you soldiers of Amurath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102000">Sheath not your swords you Moors of Barbary</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102010">That fight in right of your anointed King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102020">But follow to the gates of death and hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102030">Pale death and hell to entertain his soul. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102040">Follow I say to burning Phlegethon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102050">This traitor tyrant and his companies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e102060" who="A09221-bassa">
          <speaker>Bas</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102070">Heave up your swords against these stony holds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102080">Wherein these barbarous rebels are enclosed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102090">Called for is Abdelmelec by the gods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102100">To sit upon the throne of Barbary. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e102110" who="A09221-raye">
          <speaker>Abd. Ra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102120">Bassa great thanks the honour of the Turks. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102130">Forward brave lords unto this rightful war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102140">How can this battle but successful be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102150">Where courage meeteth with a rightful cause? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e102160" who="A09221-rubin">
          <speaker>Rub.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102170">Go in good time my best beloved lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102180">Successful in thy work thou undertakes. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e102190">Exit.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e102200">Enter the Moor in his chariot, attended with his son. Pisano his captain with his guard and treasure.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e102210" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker>Moore.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102220">Pisano, take a cornet of our horse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102230">As many argolets and armed pikes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102240">And with our carriage march away before</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102250">By Scyras, and those plots of ground</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102260">That to Moroccus leads the lower way. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102270">Our enemies keep upon the mountain tops,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102280">And have encamped themselves not far from Fez,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102290">Madam, gold is the glue, sinews, and strength of war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102300">And we must see our treasure may go safe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102310">Away. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102320">Now boy what's the news? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e102330" who="A09221-muly-mahomet">
          <speaker>Muly Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102340">The news my lord is war, war and<pb facs="6"/> revenge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102350">And if I shall declare the circumstance. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102360">'Tis thus. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102370">Rubyn our uncle's wife that wrings her hands</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102380">For Abdelmunen's death, accompanied</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102390">With many dames of Fez in mourning weeds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102400">Near to Argier encountered Abdelmelec,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102410">That bends his force puffed up with Amurath's aid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102420">Against your holds and castles of defence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102430">The younger brother Muly Mahamet Seth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102440">Greets the great bassa, that the King of Turks. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102450">Sends to invade your right and royal realm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102460">And basely beg revenge, archrebels all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102470">To be inflict upon our progeny. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e102480" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker>Moore.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102490">Why boy, is Amurath's bassa such a bug,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102500">That he is marked to do this doughty deed? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102510">Then bassa lock the winds in wards of brass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102520">Thunder from heaven damn wretched men to death</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102530">Bar all the offices of Saturn's sons,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102540">Be Pluto then in hell and bar the fiends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102550">Take Neptune's force to thee and calm the seas,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102560">And execute Jove's justice on the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102570">Convey Tamburlaine into our Afrique here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102580">To chastise and to menace lawful Kings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102590">Tamburlaine triumph not, for thou must die</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102600">As Philip did, Caesar, and Caesar's peers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e102610" who="A09221-muly-mahomet">
          <speaker>Muly Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102620">The bassa grossly flattered to his face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102630">And Amurath's praise advanced above the sound</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102640">Upon the plains, the soldiers being spread,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102650">And that brave guard of sturdy janissaries,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102660">That Amurath to Abdelmelec gave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102670">And bade him boldly be to them as safe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102680">As if he slept within a walled town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102690">Who take them to their weapons threatening revenge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102700">Bloody revenge, bloody revengeful war. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e102710" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker><pb facs="6"/>Moore.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102720">Away, and let me hear no more of this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102730">Why boy, are we successors to the great Abdelmelec,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102740">Descended from the Arabian Muly Zarif,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102750">And shall we be afraid of bassas and of bugs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102760">Raw head and bloody bone? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102770">Boy, seest here this scimitar by my side,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102780">Sith they begin to bathe in blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102790">Blood be the theme whereon our time shall tread,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102800">Such slaughter with my weapon shall I make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102810">As through the stream and bloody channels deep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102820">Our Moors shall sail in ships and pinnaces,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102830">From Tangier shore unto the gates of Fez. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e102840" who="A09221-muly-mahomet">
          <speaker>Muly Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102850">And of those slaughtered bodies shall thy son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102860">A hugy tower erect like Nimrod's frame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102870">To threaten those unjust and partial gods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102880">That to Abdallas' lawful seed deny,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102890">A long, a happy, and triumphant reign. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e102900">Sound an alarum within, and enter a messenger.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e102910" who="A09221-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102920">Fly King of Fez, King of Moroccus fly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102930">Fly with thy friends emperor of Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102940">Oh fly the sword and fury of the foe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102950">That rageth as the ramping lioness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102960">In rescue of her younglings from the bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102970">Thy towns and holds by numbers basely yield,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102980">Thy land to Abdilmelec's rule resigns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e102990">Thy carriage and thy treasure taken is</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103000">By Amurath's soldiers, that have sworn thy death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103010">Fly Amurath's power, and Abdilmelec's threats,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103020">Or thou and thine look here to breathe your last. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e103030" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker>More.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103040">Villain, what dreadful sound of death and fight</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103050">Is this, where with thou dost afflict our ears? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103060">But if there be no safety to abide</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103070"><pb facs="7"/> the favour, fortune, and success of war. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103080">Away in haste, roll on my chariot wheels</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103090">Restless, till I be safely set in shade</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103100">Of some unhaunted place, some blasted grove</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103110">Of deadly hue, or dismal cypress tree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103120">Far from the light or comfort of the sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103130">There to curse heaven, and he that heaves me hence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103140">To seek as envy at cecropes' gate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103150">And pine the thought and terror of mishaps,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103160">Away. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e103170">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A09221-e103180">
        <head>Actus secunda. Scaena prima.</head>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e103190" who="A09221-presenter">
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e103200">Alarum. And then the presenter speaketh.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103210">Now war begins his rage and ruthless reign,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103220">And Nemesis with bloody whip in hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103230">Thunders for vengeance on this negro Moor. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103240">Nor may the silence of the speechless night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103250">Dire architects of murders and misdeeds. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103260">Of tragedies, and tragic tyrannies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103270">Hide or contain this barbarous cruelty</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103280">Of this usurper to his progeny. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e103290">Three ghosts crying Vindicta.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103300">Hark lords, as in a hollow place afar ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103310">The dreadful shrieks and clamours that resound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103320">And sound revenge upon this traitor's soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103330">Traitor to kin and kind, to gods and men. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103340">Now Nemesis upon her doubling drum,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103350">Moved with this ghastly moan, this sad complaint,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103360">Larums aloud into Allecto's ears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103370">And with her thundering wakes whereas they lie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103380">In cave as dark as hell, and beds of steel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103390">The furies just imps of dire revenge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103400"><pb facs="7"/> revenge cries Abdilmelec's grieved ghost,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103410">And rouseth with the terror of this noise</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103420">These nymphs of Erebus. Wreak and revenge</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103430">Ring out the souls of his unhappy brothers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103440">And now start up these torments of the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103450">Waked with the thunder of Rhamnusia's drum,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103460">And fearful echoes of these grieved ghosts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103470">Allecto with her brand and bloody torch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103480">Megaera with her whip and snaky hair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103490">Tisiphone with her fatal murdering iron,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103500">These three conspire, these three complain and moan,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103510">Thus Muly Mahamet is a counsel held,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103520">To wreak the wrongs and murders thou hast done. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103530">By this imagine was this barbarous Moor</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103540">Chased from his dignity and his diadem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103550">And lives forlorn among the mountain shrubs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103560">And makes his food the flesh of savage beasts. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103570">Amurath's soldiers have by this installed</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103580">Good Abdelmelec in his royal seat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103590">The dames of Fez and ladies of the land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103600">In honour of the son of Soliman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103610">Erect a statue made of beaten gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103620">And sing to Amurath songs of lasting praise. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103630">Muly Mahamet's fury overruled,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103640">His cruelty controlled, and pride rebuked,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103650">Now at last when sober thoughts removed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103660">Care of his kingdom and desired crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103670">The aid that once was offered and refused</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103680">By messengers, he furiously employs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103690">Sebastian's aid brave King of Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103700">He forward in all arms and chivalry</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103710">Hearkens to his ambassadors, and grants</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103720">What they in letters and by words entreat. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103730">Now listen lordings now begins the game,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103740"><pb facs="8"/> Sebastian's tragedy in this tragic war. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e103750">Alarum within, and then enter Abdelmelec, Muly Mahamet Seth, Calsepius bassa, with Moors and janissaries, and the ladies.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e103760" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103770">Now hath the sun displayed his golden beams,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103780">And dusky clouds dispersed, the welkin clears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103790">Wherein the twenty coloured rainbow shows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103800">After this fight happy and fortunate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103810">Wherein our Moors have lost the day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103820">And victory adorned with fortunes plumes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103830">Alights on Abdelmelech's glorious crest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103840">Here find we time to breath, and now begin</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103850">To pay thy due and duties thou dost owe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103860">To heaven and earth, to gods and Amurath. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e103870">Sound trumpets.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103880">And now draw near, and heaven and earth give ear</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103890">Give ear and record heaven and earth with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103900">Ye lords of Barbary hearken and attend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103910">Hark to the words I speak, and vow I make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103920">To plant the true succession of the crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103930">Lo lords, in our seat royal to succeed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103940">Our only brother here we do install,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103950">And by the name of Muly Mahamet Seth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103960">Entitle him true heir unto the crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103970">Ye gods of heaven gratulate this deed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103980">That men on earth may therewith stand content. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e103990">Lo thus my due and duty is done, I pay</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104000">To heaven and earth, to gods and Amurath. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e104010">Sound trumpets.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e104020" who="A09221-muly-mahomet">
          <speaker>Muly Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104030">Renowned bassa, to remunerate</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104040">Thy worthiness and magnanimity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104050">Behold the noblest ladies of the land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104060">Bring present tokens of their gratitude. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e104070" who="A09221-rubin">
          <speaker><pb facs="8"/>Rub. Ar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104080">Rubin that breathes but for revenge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104090">Bassa by this commends herself to thee</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104100">Resign the token of her thankfulness</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104110">To Amurath the god of earthly Kings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104120">Doth Rubin give and sacrifice her son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104130">Not with sweet smoke of fire, or sweet perfume,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104140">But with his father's sword, his mother's thanks</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104150">Doth Rubin give her son to Amurath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e104160" who="A09221-queen">
          <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104170">As Rubin gives her son, so we ourselves</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104180">To Amurath give, and fall before his face. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104190">Bassa, wear thou the gold of Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104200">And glister like the palace of the sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104210">In honour of the deed that thou hast done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e104220" who="A09221-bassa">
          <speaker>Bas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104230">Well worthy of the aid of Amurath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104240">Is Abdelmelec and these noble dames,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104250">Rubin thy son I shall ere long bestow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104260">Where thou dost him bequeath in honour's fee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104270">On Amurath, mighty emperor of the East,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104280">That shall receive the imp of royal race,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104290">With cheerful looks and gleams of princely grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104300">This chosen guard of Amurath's jenizaries,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104310">I leave to honour and attend on thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104320">King of Morocco conqueror of thy foes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104330">True King of Fez, emperor of Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104340">Muly Molocco live and keep thy seat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104350">In spite of fortune's spite or enemies threats,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104360">Ride bassa now, bold bassa homeward ride,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104370">As glorious as great Pompey in his pride. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e104380">Exit omnes.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e104390">Enter Diego Lopis governor of Lisborne, the Irish Bishop, Stukeley, Jonas, and Hercules.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e104400" who="A09221-diego">
          <speaker>Dieg.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104410">Welcome to Lisbon valiant Catholics,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104420">Welcome brave Englishmen to Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104430">Most reverent primate of the Irish church. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104440"><pb facs="9"/>And noble Stukeley famous by thy name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104450">Welcome, thrice welcome to Sebastian's town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104460">And welcome English captains to you all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104470">It joyeth us to see his holiness' fleet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104480">Cast anchor happily upon our coast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e104490" who="A09221-bishop">
          <speaker>Bishop.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104500">These welcomes worthy governor of Lisbon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104510">Argue an honourable mind in thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104520">But treat of our misfortune therewithal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104530">To Ireland by Pope Gregory's command,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104540">Were we all bound, and therefore thus embarked,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104550">To land our forces there at unawares,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104560">Conquering the land for his holiness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104570">And so restore it to the Roman faith,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104580">This was the cause of our expedition,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104590">And Ireland long ere this had been subdued,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104600">Had not foul weather brought us to this bay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e104610" who="A09221-diego">
          <speaker>Diego.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104620">Under correction, are ye not all Englishmen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104630">And longs not Ireland to that kingdom lords? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104640">Then may I speak my conscience in the cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104650">Sans scandal to the holy see of Rome,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104660">Unhonorable is this expedition,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104670">And misbeseeming you to meddle in. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e104680" who="A09221-stukeley">
          <speaker>Stuk.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104690">Lord governor of Lisbon understand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104700">As we are Englishmen, so are we men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104710">And I am Stukeley so resolved in all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104720">To follow rule, honour and empery,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104730">Not to be bent so strictly to the place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104740">Wherein at first I blew the fire of life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104750">But that I may at liberty make choice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104760">Of all the continents that bounds the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104770">For why? I make it not so great desert</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104780">To be begotten or born in any place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104790">Sith that's a thing of pleasure and of ease,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104800">That might have been performed elsewhere as well. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e104810" who="A09221-diego">
          <speaker><pb facs="9"/>Die.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104820">Follow what your good pleasure will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104830">Good captain Stukeley be it far from me</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104840">To take exceptions beyond my privilege. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e104850" who="A09221-bishop">
          <speaker>Bishop</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104860">Yet captain give me leave to speak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104870">We must affect our country as our parents,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104880">And if at any time we alienate</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104890">Our love or industry from doing it honour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104900">It must respect effects and touch the soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104910">Matter of conscience and religion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104920">And not desire of rule or benefit. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e104930" who="A09221-stukeley">
          <speaker>Stuk.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104940">Well said Bishop, spoken like yourself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104950">The reverent lordly Bishop of saint Asaph's. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e104960" who="A09221-hercules">
          <speaker>Herc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104970">The Bishop talks according to his coat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104980">And takes not measure of it by his mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e104990">You see he hath it made thus large and wide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105000">Because he may convert it as he list,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105010">To any form may fit the fashion best,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e105020" who="A09221-bishop">
          <speaker>Bishop</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105030">Captain you do me wrong to descant thus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105040">Upon my coat or double conscience,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105050">And cannot answer it in another place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e105060" who="A09221-diego">
          <speaker>Die.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105070">'Tis but in jest, lord Bishop put it up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105080">And all as friends deign to be entertained,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105090">As my ability here can make provision,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105100">Shortly shall I conduct you to the King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105110">Whose welcomes evermore to strangers are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105120">Princely and honourable as his state becomes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e105130" who="A09221-stukeley">
          <speaker>Stuk.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105140">Thanks worthy governor, come Bishop come</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105150">Will you show fruits of quarrel and of wrath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105160">Come let us in with my lord of Lisbon here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105170">And put all conscience into one carouse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105180">Letting it out again, as we may live. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105190">There shall no action pass my hand or sword,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105200">That cannot make a step to gain a crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105210">No word shall pass the office of my tongue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105220">That sounds not of affection to a crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105230"><pb facs="10"/> no thought have being in my lordly breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105240">That works not every way to win a crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105250">Deeds, words and thoughts shall all be as a King's,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105260">My chiefest company shall be with Kings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105270">And my deserts shall counterpoise a King's,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105280">Why should not I then look to be a King? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105290">I am the marquess how of Ireland made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105300">And will be shortly King of Ireland,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105310">King of a molehill had I rather be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105320">Than the richest subject of a monarchy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105330">Huff it brave mind, and never cease t'aspire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105340">Before thou reign sole King of thy desire</l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e105350">Exeunt.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e105360">Enter the Moor, with Calypolis his wife, Muly Mahamet his son, and two others.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e105370" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker>Moore.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105380">Where art thou boy, where is Calypolis? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105390">O deadly wound that passeth by mine eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105400">The fatal prison of my swelling heart! </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105410">O fortune constant in unconstancy! </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105420">Fight earthquakes in the entrails of the earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105430">And Eastern whirlwinds in the hellish shades,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105440">Some foul contagion of the infected heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105450">Blast all the trees, and in their cursed tops,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105460">The dismal night raven and tragic owl</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105470">Breed, and become foretellers of my fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105480">The fatal ruin of my name and me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105490">Adders and serpents hiss at my disgrace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105500">And wound the earth with anguish of their stings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105510">Now Abdelmelech, now triumph in Fez,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105520">Fortune hath made thee King of Barbary. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e105530" who="A09221-calypolis">
          <speaker>Caly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105540">Alas my lord, what boots these huge exclaims</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105550">To advantage us in this distressed estate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105560">O pity our perplexed estate my lord;</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105570">And turn all curses to submiss complaints,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105580">And those complaints to actions of relief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105590">I faint my lord, and naught may cursing plaints</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105600"><pb facs="10"/> refresh the fading substance of my life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e105610" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker>Moore.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105620">Faint all the world, consume and be accursed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105630">Since my state faints and is accursed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e105640" who="A09221-calypolis">
          <speaker>Calyp.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105650">Yet patience lord to conquer sorrows so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e105660" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker>More.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105670">What patience is for him that lacks his crown</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105680">There is no patience where the loss is such,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105690">The shame of my disgrace hath put on wings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105700">And swiftly flies about this earthly ball,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105710">Carest thou to live then fond Calypolis,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105720">When he that should give essence to thy soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105730">He on whose glory all thy joy should stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105740">Is soulless, gloryless, and desperate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105750">Crying for battle, famine, sword and fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105760">Rather than calling for relief or life. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105770">But be content, thy hunger shall have end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105780">Famine shall pine to death and thou shalt live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105790">I will go hunt these cursed solitaries,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105800">And make the sword and target here my hound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105810">To pull down lions and untamed beasts. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e105820">Exit.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e105830" who="A09221-mah">
          <speaker>Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105840">Tush mother, cherish your unhearty soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105850">And feed with hope of happiness and ease,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105860">For if by valour or by policy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105870">My kingly father can be fortunate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105880">We shall be Jove's commanders once again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105890">And flourish in a threefold happiness. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e105900" who="A09221-zareo">
          <speaker>Zareo</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105910">His majesty hath sent Sebastian</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105920">The good and harmless King of Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105930">A promise to resign the royalty</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105940">And kingdom of Morocco to his hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105950">But when this haughty offer takes effect,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105960">And works affiance in Sebastian,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105970">My gracious lord warned wisely to advise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105980">I doubt not but will watch occasion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e105990">And take her foretop by the slenderest hair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106000">To rid us of this miserable life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e106010" who="A09221-mah">
          <speaker><pb facs="11"/>Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106020">Good madam cheer yourself, my father's wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106030">He can submit himself and live below,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106040">Make show of friendship, promise, vow and swear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106050">Till by the virtue of his fair pretence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106060">Sebastian trusting his integrity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106070">He makes himself possessor of such fruits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106080">As grow upon such great advantages. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e106090" who="A09221-calypolis">
          <speaker>Calip.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106100">But more dishonour hangs on such misdeeds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106110">Than all the profit their return can bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106120">Such secret judgements hath the heavens imposed</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106130">Upon the drooping state of Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106140">As public merits in such lewd attempts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106150">Hath drawn with violence upon our heads. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e106160">Enter Muly Mahamet with lion's flesh upon bis sword.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e106170" who="A09221-muly-mahomet">
          <speaker>Mu Ma.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106180">Hold thee Calypolis feed and faint no more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106190">This flesh I forced from a lioness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106200">Meat of a Princess, for a Princess meet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106210">Learn by her noble stomach to esteem</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106220">Penury plenty, in extremest dearth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106230">Who when she saw her foragement bereft,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106240">Pined not in melancholy or childish fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106250">But as brave minds are strongest in extremes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106260">So she redoubling her former force</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106270">Ranged through the woods, and rent the breeding vaults</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106280">Of proudest savages to save herself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106290">Feed then and faint not fair Calypolis,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106300">For rather than fierce famine shall prevail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106310">To gnaw thy entrails with her thorny teeth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106320">The conquering lioness shall attend on thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106330">And lay huge heaps of slaughtered carcases</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106340"><pb facs="11"/> as bulwarks in her way to keep her back. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106350">I will provide thee of a princely osprey,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106360">That as she flieth over fish in pools,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106370">The fish shall turn their glistering bellies up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106380">And thou shalt take thy liberal choice of all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106390">Jove's stately bird with wide commanding wings</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106400">Shall hover still about thy princely head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106410">And beat down fowl by shoals into thy lap,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106420">Feed then and faint not fair Calypolis. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e106430" who="A09221-calypolis">
          <speaker>Calyp.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106440">Thanks good my lord, and though my stomach be</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106450">Too queasy to digest such bloody meat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106460">Yet strength I it with virtue of my mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106470">I doubt no whit but I shall live my lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e106480" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker>Moore.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106490">Into the shades then fair Calypolis,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106500">And make thy son and negroes here good cheer,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106510">Feed and be fat that we may meet the foe</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106520">With strength and terror to revenge our wrong. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e106530">Enter Sebastian King of Portugal, the Duke of Avero, the Duke of Barceles, leves de Silva, Christophero de Tavera</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e106540" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106550">Call forth those Moors, those men of Barbary. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106560">That came with letters from the King of Fez. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e106570">Exit one.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106580">Ye warlike lords and men of chivalry,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106590">Honourable ambassadors of this high regent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106600">Hark to Sebastian King of Portugal:</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106610">These letters sent from your distressed lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106620">Torn from his throne by Abdilmelec's hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106630">Strengthened and raised by furious Amurath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106640">Imports a kingly favour at our hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106650">For aid to reobtain his royal seat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106660">And place his fortunes in their former height. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106670"><pb facs="12"/>For 'quital of which honourable arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106680">By these his letters he doth firmly vow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106690">Wholly to yield and to surrender up</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106700">The kingdom of Moroccus to our hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106710">And to become to us contributary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106720">And to content himself with the realm of Fez,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106730">These lines my lords writ in extremity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106740">Contain therefore but during fortune's date,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106750">How shall Sebastian then believe the same? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e106760" who="A09221-ambassador">
          <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106770">Viceroys, and most christian King of Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106780">To satisfy thy doubtful mind herein,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106790">Command forthwith a blazing brand of fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106800">Be brought in presence of thy majesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106810">Then shalt thou see by our religious vows</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106820">And ceremonies most inviolate</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106830">How firm our sovereign's protestations are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106840">Behold my lord, this binds our faith to thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106850">In token that great Muly Mahamet's hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106860">Hath writ no more than his stout heart allows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106870">And will perform to thee and to thine heirs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106880">We offer here our hands into this flame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106890">And as this flame doth fasten on this flesh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106900">So from our souls we wish it may consume</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106910">The heart of our great lord and sovereign</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106920">Muly Mahamet King of Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106930">If his intent agree not with his words. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e106940" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106950">These ceremonies and protestations</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106960">Sufficeth us ye lords of Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106970">Therefore return this answer to your King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106980">Assure him by the honour of my crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e106990">And by Sebastian's true unfeigned faith</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107000">He shall have aid and succour to recover,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107010">And seat him in his former empery,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107020">Let him rely upon our princely word,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107030"><pb facs="12"/> tell him by August we will come to him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107040">With such a power of brave impatient minds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107050">As Abdelmelec and great Amurath</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107060">Shall tremble at the strength of Portugal. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e107070" who="A09221-ambassador">
          <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107080">Thanks to the renowned King of Portugal</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107090">On whose stout promises our state depend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e107100" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107110">Barbarians go glad your distressed King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107120">And say Sebastian lives to right his wrong,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e107130">Exit.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107140">Duke of Avero call in those Englishmen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107150">Don Stukeley, and those captains of the fleet</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107160">That lately landed in our bay of Lisbon. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107170">Now breath Sebastian, and in breathing blow</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107180">Some gentle gale of thy new formed joys,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107190">Duke of Avero, it shall be your charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107200">To take the muster of the Portugals,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107210">And bravest bloods of all our country,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107220">Lewes de Sylva you shall be dispatched</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107230">With letters unto Philip King of Spain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107240">Tell him we crave his aid in this behalf,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107250">I know our brother Philip nill deny</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107260">His furtherance in this holy christian war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107270">Duke of Barceles as thy ancestors</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107280">Have always loyal been to Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107290">So now in honour of thy towards youth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107300">Thy charge shall be to Antwerp speedily,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107310">To hire us mercenary men at arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107320">Promise them princely pay, and be thou sure</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107330">Thy word is ours, Sebastian speaks the word. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e107340" who="A09221-christopher">
          <speaker>Chri.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107350">I beseech your majesty employ me in this war. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e107360" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107370">Christopher de Tavera, next unto myself</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107380">My good Hephaestion, and my bedfellow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107390">Thy cares and mine shall be alike in this,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e107400">Enter Stukeley and the rest.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107410">And thou and I will live and die together. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107420">And now brave Englishmen to you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107430"><pb facs="13"/> whom angry storms have put into our bay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107440">Hold not your fortune e'er the worse in this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107450">We hold our strangers' honours in our hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107460">And for distressed frank and free relief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107470">Tell me then Stukeley, for that's thy name I trow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107480">Wilt thou in honour of thy country's fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107490">Hazard thy person in this brave exploit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107500">And follow us to fruitful Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107510">With these six thousand soldiers thou hast brought</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107520">And choicely picked through wanton Italy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107530">Thou art a man of gallant personage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107540">Proud in thy looks, and famous every way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107550">Frankly tell me, wilt thou go with me? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e107560" who="A09221-stukeley">
          <speaker>Stuk</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107570">Courageous King, the wonder of my thoughts</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107580">And yet my lord, with pardon understand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107590">Myself and these, whom weather hath enforced,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107600">To lie at road upon thy gracious coast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107610">Did bend our course and made amain for Ireland. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e107620" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107630">For Ireland Stukeley, thou mistakst me wondrous much,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107640">With seven ships, two pinnaces, and six thousand men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107650">I tell thee Stukeley, they are far too weak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107660">To violate the Queen of Ireland's right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107670">For Ireland's Queen commandeth England's force,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107680">Were every ship ten thousand on the seas,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107690">Manned with the strength of all the Eastern Kings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107700">Conveying all the monarchs of the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107710">To invade the island where her highness reigns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107720">'Twere all in vain, for heavens and destinies</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107730">Attend and wait upon her majesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107740">Sacred, imperial, and holy is her seat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107750">Shining with wisdom, love and mightiness. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107760">Nature that every thing imperfect made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107770">Fortune that never yet was constant found,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107780"><pb facs="13"/> time that defaceth every golden show,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107790">Dare not decay, remove, or be impure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107800">Both nature, time and fortune, all agree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107810">To bless and serve her royal majesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107820">The wallowing ocean hems her round about,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107830">Whose raging floods do swallow up her foes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107840">And on the rocks their ships in pieces split,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107850">And even in Spain where all the traitors dance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107860">And play themselves upon a sunny day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107870">Securely guard the West part of her isle,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107880">The South the narrow Britain sea begirts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107890">Where Veptune sits in triumph, to direct</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107900">Their course to hell that aim at her disgrace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107910">The German seas alongst the East do run,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107920">Where Nenus banquets all her water nymphs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107930">That with her beauty glancing on the waves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107940">Disdains the check of fair Proserpina,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107950">Advise thee then proud Stukeley ere thou pass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107960">To wrong the wonder of the highest god,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107970">Sith danger, death and hell doth follow thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107980">Thee and them all that seek to danger her. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e107990">If honour be the mark whereat thou aim'st,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108000">Then follow me in holy christian wars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108010">And leave to seek thy country's overthrow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108020" who="A09221-stukeley">
          <speaker>Stuk.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108030">Rather my lord, let me admire these words,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108040">Then answer to your firm objections,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108050">His holiness Pope Gregory the seventh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108060">Hath made us four the leaders of the rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108070">Amongst the rest my lord, I am but one,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108080">If they agree Stukeley will be the first</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108090">To die with honour for Sebastian. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108100" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108110">Tell me lord Bishop, captains tell me all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108120">Are you content to leave this enterprise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108130">Against your country and your country men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108140">To aid Mahamet King of Barbary? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108150" who="A09221-bishop">
          <speaker><pb facs="14"/>Bishop</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108160">To aid Mahamet King of Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108170">'Tis 'gainst our vows great King of Portugal. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108180" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108190">Then captains what say you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108200" who="A09221-jonas">
          <speaker>Jonas</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108210">I say my lord as the Bishop said,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108220">We may not turn from conquering Ireland. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108230" who="A09221-hercules">
          <speaker>Herc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108240">Our country and our countrymen will condemn</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108250">Us worthy of death, if we neglect our vows. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108260" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108270">Consider lords you are now in Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108280">And I may now dispose of you and yours. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108290">Hath not the wind and weather given you up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108300">And made you captives to our royal will? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108310" who="A09221-jonas">
          <speaker>Jonas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108320">It hath my lord, and willingly we yield</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108330">To be commanded by your majesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108340">But if you make us voluntary men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108350">Our course is then direct for Ireland. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108360" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108370">That course will we direct for Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108380">Follow me lords, Sebastian leads the way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108390">To plant the christian faith in Africa. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108400" who="A09221-stukeley">
          <speaker>Stuk.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108410">Saint George for England, and Ireland now adieu,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108420">For here Tom Stukeley shapes his course anew. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e108430">Exit.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e108440">Enter the presenter and speaks.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108450" who="A09221-presenter">
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108460">Lo thus into a lake of blood and gore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108470">The brave courageous King of Portugal</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108480">Hath drenched himself, and now prepares amain</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108490">With sails and oars to cross the swelling seas,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108500">With men and ships, courage and cannon shot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108510">To plant this cursed Moor in fatal hour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108520">And in this Catholic case the King of Spain</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108530">Is called upon by sweet Sebastian. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108540">Who surfeiting in prime time of his youth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108550"><pb facs="14"/> upon ambitious poison dies thereon. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108560">By this time is the Moor to Tangier come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108570">A city longing to the Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108580">And now doth Spain promise with holy face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108590">As favouring the honour of the cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108600">His aid of arms, and levies men apace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108610">But nothing less than King Sebastian's good</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108620">He means, yet at sucor de Tupea. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108630">He met some say in person with the Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108640">And treateth of a marriage with the King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108650">But beware ambitious wiles and poisoned eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108660">There was nor aid of arms nor marriage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108670">For on his way without those Spaniards King Sebastian went. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e108680">Enter the King of Portugal and his lords, Lewes de Sylva, and the ambassadors of Spain.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108690" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108700">Honourable lords, ambassadors of Spain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108710">The many favours by our meetings done</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108720">From our beloved and renowned brother,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108730">Philip the Catholic King of Spain</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108740">Say therefore good my lord ambassador,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108750">Say how your mighty master minded is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108760">To propagate the fame of Portugal. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108770" who="A09221-ambassador">
          <speaker>Ambassador</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108780">To propagate the fame of Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108790">And plant religious truth in Africa,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108800">Philip the great and puissant King of Spain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108810">For love and honour of Sebastian's name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108820">Promiseth aid of arms and swears by us</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108830">To do your majesty all the good he can,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108840">With men, munition, and supply of war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108850">Of Spaniards proud in King Sebastian's aid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108860"><pb facs="15"/> to spend their bloods in honour of their Christ. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e108870" who="A09221-legate">
          <speaker>Legate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108880">And farther to manifest unto your majesty</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108890">How much the Catholic King of Spain affects</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108900">This war with Moors and men of little faith,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108910">The honour of your everlasting praise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108920">Behold to honour and enlarge thy name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108930">He maketh offer of his daughter Isabel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108940">To link in marriage with the brave Sebastian,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108950">And to enrich Sebastian's noble wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108960">His majesty with promise to resign</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108970">The titles of the islands of Moloccus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108980">That by his royalty in Judah he commands</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e108990">These favours with unfeigned love and zeal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109000">Voweth King Philip to King Sebastian. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e109010" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109020">And God so deal with King Sebastian's soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109030">As justly he intends to fight for Christ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109040">Nobles of Spain, sith our renowned brother,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109050">Philip the King of honour and of zeal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109060">By you the chosen orators of Spain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109070">The offer of the holds he makes</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109080">Are not so precious in our account,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109090">As is the peerless dame whom we adore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109100">His daughter, in whose loyalty consists</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109110">The life and honour of Sebastian. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109120">As for the aid of arms he promiseth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109130">We will expect, and thankfully receive</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109140">At Cardis, as we sail alongst the coast. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109150">Sebastian clap thy hands for joy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109160">Honoured by this meeting and this match,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109170">Go lords and follow to the famous war</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109180">Your King, and be his fortune such in all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109190">As he intends to manage arms in right. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e109200">Exeunt.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e109210">Manet Stubley and another.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e109220" who="A09221-stukeley">
          <speaker>Stuk.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109230">Sit fast Sebastian, and in this work</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109240"><pb facs="15"/> God and good men labour for Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109250">For Spain disguising with a double face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109260">Flatters thy youth and forwardness good King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109270">Philip whom some call the Catholic King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109280">I fear me much thy faith will not be firm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109290">But disagree with thy profession. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e109300" who="A09221-other">
          <speaker>The other.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109310">What then shall of these men of war become,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109320">Those numbers that do multiply in Spain? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e109330" who="A09221-stukeley">
          <speaker>Stuk.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109340">Spain hath a vent for them and their supplies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109350">The Spaniard ready to embark himself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109360">Here gathers to a head, but all too sure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109370">Flanders I fear shall feel the force of Spain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109380">Let Portugal fare as he may or can,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109390">Spain means to spend no powder on the Moors. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e109400" who="A09221-other">
          <speaker>The other.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109410">If Kings do dally so with holy oaths,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109420">The heavens will right the wrongs that they sustain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109430">Philip if these forgeries be in thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109440">Assure thee King, 'twill light on thee at last,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109450">And when proud Spain hopes soundly to prevail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109460">The time may come that thou and thine shall fail. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e109470">Exit.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e109480">Enter Abdelmelec, Muly Mahamet. Seth, Zareo and their train.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e109490" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdelm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109500">The Portugal lead with decoining hope,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109510">Hath raised his power, and received our foe</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109520">With honourable welcomes and regard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109530">And left his country bounds, and hither bends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109540">In hope to help Mahamet to a crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109550">And chase us hence, and plant this negro Moor</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109560">That clads himself in coat of hammered steel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109570">To heave us from the honour we possess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109580">But for I have myself a soldier been,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109590"><pb facs="16"/> I have in pity to the Portugal</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109600">Sent secret messengers to counsel him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109610">As for the aid of Spain whereof they hoped,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109620">We have dispatched our letters to their prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109630">To crave that in a quarrel so unjust,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109640">He that entitled is the Catholic King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109650">Would not assist a careless christian prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109660">And as by letters we are let to know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109670">Our offer of the seven holds we made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109680">He thankfully receives, with all conditions,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109690">Differing in mind far from all his words</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109700">And promises to King Sebastian,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109710">As we would wish, or you my lords desire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e109720" who="A09221-zareo">
          <speaker>Zareo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109730">What resteth then but Abdelmelec may</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109740">Beat back this proud invading Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109750">And chastise this ambitious negro Moor</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109760">With thousand deaths for thousand damned deeds. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e109770" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdilm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109780">Forward Zareo and ye manly Moors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109790">Sebastian see in time unto thyself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109800">If thou and thine misled do thrive amiss,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109810">Guiltless is Abdelmelec of thy blood. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e109820">Exeunt.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e109830">Enter don de Mevysis governor of Tangar, with his company speaking to the captain.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e109840" who="A09221-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109850">Captain, we have received letters from the King. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109860">That with such signs and arguments of love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109870">We entertain the King of Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109880">That marcheth towards Tangier with his men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109890">The poor remainders of those that fled from Fez,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109900">When Abdelmelec got the glorious day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109910">And stalled himself in his imperial throne. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e109920" who="A09221-captain">
          <speaker>Captain</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109930">Lord governor, we are in readiness</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109940">To welcome and receive this hapless King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109950"><pb facs="16"/> chased from his land by angry Amurath ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109960">And if the right rest in this lusty Moor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109970">Bearing a princely heart unvanquishable,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109980">A noble resolution than it is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e109990">In brave Sebastian our christian King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110000">To aid this Moor with his victorious arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110010">Thereby to propagate religious truth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110020">And plant his springing praise in Africa. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e110030" who="A09221-captain_2">
          <speaker>Ano. Capt.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110040">But when arrives this brave Sebastian,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110050">To knit his forces with this manly Moor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110060">That both in one, and one in both may join</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110070">In this attempt of noble consequence? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110080">Our men of Tangier long to see their King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110090">Whose princely face that like the summer's son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110100">Glads all these hither parts of Barbary. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e110110" who="A09221-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110120">Captains, he cometh hitherward amain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110130">Top and top gallant, all in brave array</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110140">The 26. day of June he left the bay of Lisbon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110150">And with all his fleet at Cardis happily he</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110160">Arrived in Spain the eight of July, tarrying for the aid</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110170">That Philip King of Spain had promised,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110180">And fifteen days he there remained aboard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110190">Expecting when this Spanish force would come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110200">Nor stepped ashore as he were going still:</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110210">But Spain that meant and minded nothing less,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110220">Pretends a sudden fear and care to keep</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110230">His own from Amurath's fierce invasion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110240">And to excuse his promise to our King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110250">For which he storms as great Achilles erst. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110260">Lying for want of wind in Aulis' gulf,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110270">And hoisteth up his sails and anchors weighs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110280">And hitherward he comes, and looks to meet</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110290">This manly Moor, whose case he undertakes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110300">Therefore go we to welcome and rescue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110310">With cannon shot, and shouts of young and old,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110320"><pb facs="17"/> this fleet of Portugals and troop of Moors. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e110330">Exit.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e110340">The trumpets sound the chambers are discharged. Then enter the King of Portugal and the Moor, with all their train.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e110350" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110360">Muly Mahamet King of Barbary</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110370">Well met, and welcome to our town of Tangier,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110380">After this sudden shock and hapless war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110390">Welcome brave Queen of Moors, repose thee here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110400">Thou and thy noble son, and soldiers all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110410">Repose you here in King Sebastian's town. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110420">Thus far in honour of thy name and aid</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110430">Lord Mahamet, we have adventured</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110440">To win for thee a kingdom, for ourselves</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110450">Fame, and performance of those promises,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110460">That in thy faith and royalty thou hast</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110470">Sworn to Sebastian King of Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110480">And thrive it so with thee as thou dost mean,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110490">And mean thou so as thou dost wish to thrive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110500">And if our Christ for whom in chief we fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110510">Hereby to enlarge the bounds of Christendom,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110520">Favour this war, and as I do not doubt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110530">Send victory to light upon my crest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110540">Brave Moor I will advance thy kingly son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110550">And with a diadem of pearl and gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110560">Adorn thy temples and enrich thy head,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e110570" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker>Moor</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110580">O brave Sebastian noble Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110590">Renowned and honoured ever mayst thou be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110600">Triumpher over those that menace thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110610">The hellish prince grim Pluto with his mace</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110620">Ding down my soul to hell, and with this soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110630">This son of mine the honour of my house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110640">But I perform religiously to thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110650"><pb facs="17"/> that I have holily erst undertaken,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110660">And that thy lords and captains may perceive</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110670">My mind in this single and pure to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110680">As pure as is the water of the brook,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110690">My dearest son to thee I do engage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110700">Receive him lord in hostage of my vow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110710">For even my mind presageth to myself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110720">That in some slavish sort I shall behold</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110730">Him dragged along this running river shore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110740">A spectacle to daunt the pride of those</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110750">That climb aloft by force, and not by right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e110760" who="A09221-moor_son">
          <speaker>The Moors son.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110770">Nor can it otherwise befall the man</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110780">That keeps his seat and sceptre all in fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110790">That wears his crown in eye of all the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110800">Reputed theft and not inheritance. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110810">What title then hath Abdelmelec here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110820">To bar our father or his progeny,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110830">Right royal prince, hereof you make no doubt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110840">Agreeing with your wholesome christian laws,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110850">Help then courageous lord with hand and sword,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110860">To clear his way, whose lets are lawless men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110870">And for this deed ye all shall be renowned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110880">Renowned and chronicled in books of fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110890">In books of fame and characters of brass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110900">Of brass may beaten gold, fight then for fame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110910">And find the Arabian Muly Hamet here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110920">Adventurous, bold, and full of rich reward. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e110930" who="A09221-stukeley">
          <speaker>Stuk.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110940">Brave boy, how plain this princely mind in thee</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110950">Argues the height and honour of thy birth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110960">And well have I observed thy forwardness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110970">Which being tendered by your majesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110980">No doubt the quarrel opened by the mouth</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e110990">Of this young prince unpartially to us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111000">May animate and hearten all the host,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111010"><pb facs="18"/> to fight against the devil for lord Mahamet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111020" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111030">True Stukeley, and so freshly to my mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111040">Hath this young prince reduced his father's wrong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111050">That in good time I hope this honour's fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111060">Kindled already with regard of right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111070">Bursts into open flames, and calls for wars,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111080">Wars, wars to plant the true succeeding prince. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111090">Lord Mahamet, I take thy noble son</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111100">A pledge of honour, and shall use him so. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111110">Lord Lodowick, and my good lord of Avero</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111120">See this young prince conveyed safe to Messegon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111130">And there accompanied as him fitteth best,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111140">And to this war prepare ye more and less,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111150">This rightful war, that Christians God will bless. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e111160">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A09221-e111170">
        <head>Actus 4.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A09221-e111180">The presenter speaketh.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111190" who="A09221-presenter">
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111200">Now hardened is this hapless heathen prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111210">And strengthened by the arms of Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111220">This Moor, this murderer of his progeny. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111230">And war and weapons now, and blood and death</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111240">Wait on the counsels of this cursed King:</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111250">And to a bloody banquet he invites</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111260">The brave Sebastian and his noble peers. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e111270">Enter to the bloody banquet.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111280">In fatal hour arrived this peerless prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111290">To lose his life, his life and many lives</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111300">Of lusty men, courageous Portugals,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111310">Drawn by ambitious golden looks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111320">Let fame of him no wrongful censure sound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111330"><pb facs="18"/> honour was object of his thoughts, ambition was his ground. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e111340">Exit.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e111350">Enter Abdelmelec and his train.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111360" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdilm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111370">Now tell me Celybin, what doth the enemy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111380" who="A09221-celybin">
          <speaker>Celybin.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111390">The enemy dread lord, hath left the town</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111400">Of Arzil, with a thousand soldiers armed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111410">To guard his fleet of thirteen hundred sail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111420">And mustering of his men before the walls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111430">He found he had two thousand armed horse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111440">And fourteen thousand men that serve on foot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111450">Three thousand pioneers, and a thousand coachmen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111460">Besides a number almost numberless</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111470">Of drudges, negroes, slaves and muleteers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111480">Horseboys, laundresses and courtesans,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111490">And fifteen hundred waggons full of stuff</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111500">For noble men, brought up in delicate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111510" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111520">Alas good King, thy foresight hath been small</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111530">To come with women into Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111540">With laundress, with baggage, and with trash,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111550">Numbers unfit to multiply thy host. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111560" who="A09221-celybin">
          <speaker>Cely.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111570">Their payment in the camp is passing slow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111580">And victuals scarce, that many faint and die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111590" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdilm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111600">But whither marcheth he in all this haste? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111610" who="A09221-celybin">
          <speaker>Cely.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111620">Some thinks he marcheth hitherward,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111630">And means to take this city of Alcazar. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111640" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111650">Unto Alcazar, oh unconstant chance! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111660" who="A09221-celybin">
          <speaker>Cely.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111670">The brave and valiant King of Portugal</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111680">Quarters his power in four batallions,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111690">A-front the which, to welcome us withal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111700">Are six and thirty roaring pieces placed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111710">The first consisting of light armed horse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111720">And of the garrisons from Tangier brought</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111730"><pb facs="19"/> is led by Alvaro Peres de Tavero,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111740">The left or middle battle of Italians,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111750">And German horsemen Stukeley doth command,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111760">A warlike Englishman sent by the Pope,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111770">That vainly calls himself marquess of Ireland. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111780">Alonjo Aquilaz conducts the third,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111790">That wing of German soldiers most consists. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111800">The fourth legion is none but Portugals,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111810">Of whom Lodevico Caesar hath the chiefest charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111820">Besides there stand six thousand horse</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111830">Bravely attired, pressed where need requires. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111840">Thus have I told your royal majesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111850">How he is placed to brave his fight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111860" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111870">But where's our nephew Muly Mahamet? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111880" who="A09221-celybin">
          <speaker>Cely</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111890">He marcheth in the middle, guarded about</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111900">With full five hundred harquebus on foot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111910">And twice three thousand needless armed pikes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e111920" who="A09221-zareo">
          <speaker>Zareo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111930">Great sovereign, vouchsafe to hear me speak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111940">And let Zareo's counsel now prevail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111950">Whilst time doth serve, and that these Christians dare</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111960">Approach the field with warlike ensigns spread,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111970">Let us in haste with all our forces meet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111980">And hem them in, that not a man escape,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e111990">So will they be advised another time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112000">How they do touch the shore of Barbary. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e112010" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdilm.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112020">Zareo, hear our resolution,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112030">And thus our forces we will first dispose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112040">Hamet my brother with a thousand shot</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112050">On horseback, and choice harquebusiers all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112060">Having ten thousand with spear and shield,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112070">Shall make the right wing of the battle up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112080">Zareo you shall have in charge the left,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112090">Two thousand argolets and ten thousand horse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112100">The main battle of harquebus on foot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112110">And twenty thousand horsemen in their troops,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112120"><pb facs="19"/> myself environed with my trusty guard</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112130">Of janissaries, fortunate in war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112140">And towards Arzil will we take our way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112150">If then our enemy will balk our force,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112160">In god's name let him, it will be his best,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112170">But if he level at Alcazar walls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112180">Then beat him back with bullets as thick as hail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112190">And make him know and rue his oversight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112200">That rashly seeks the ruin of this land. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e112210">Exeunt.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e112220">Enter Sebastian King of Portugal, the Duke of Avero, Stukeley, and others.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e112230" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112240">Why tell me lords, why left ye Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112250">And crossed the seas with us to Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112260">Was it to see the country and no more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112270">Or else to slay before ye were assailed? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112280">I am ashamed to think that such as you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112290">Whose deeds have been renowned heretofore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112300">Should slack in such an act of consequence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112310">We come to fight, and fighting vow to die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112320">Or else to win the thing for which we came,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112330">Because Abdelmelec as pitying us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112340">Sends messages to counsel quietness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112350">You stand amazed and think it sound advice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112360">As if our enemy would wish us any good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112370">No, let him know we scorn his courtesy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112380">And will resist his forces whatsoe'er . </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112390">Cast fear aside, myself will lead the way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112400">And make a passage with my conquering sword</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112410">Knee deep in blood of these accursed Moors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112420">And they that love my honour follow me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112430"><pb facs="20"/>Were you as resolute as is your King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112440">Alcazar walls should fall before your face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112450">And all the force of this barbarian lord</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112460">Should be confounded, were it ten times more. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e112470" who="A09221-avero">
          <speaker>Avero</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112480">So well become these words a kingly mouth</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112490">That are of force to make a coward fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112500">But when advice and prudent foresight</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112510">Is joined with such magnanimity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112520">Troops of victory and kingly spoils</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112530">Adorn his crown, his kingdom, and his fame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e112540" who="A09221-hercules">
          <speaker>Herc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112550">We have descried upon the mountain tops</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112560">A hugy company of invading Moors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112570">And they my lord, as thick as winter's hail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112580">Will fall upon our heads at unawares,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112590">Best then betimes t'avoid this gloomy storm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112600">It is in vain to strive with such a stream. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e112610">Enter Muly Mahamet.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e112620" who="A09221-muly-mahomet">
          <speaker>Muly Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112630">Behold thrice noble lord, uncalled I come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112640">To counsel where necessity commands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112650">And honour of undoubted victory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112660">Makes me exclaim upon this dastard flight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112670">Why King Sebastian, wilt thou now foreslow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112680">And let so great a glory slip thy hands? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112690">Say you do march unto Larissa now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112700">The forces of the foe are come so nigh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112710">That he will let the passage of the river,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112720">So unawares you will be forced to fight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112730">But know oh King, and you thrice valiant lords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112740">Few blows will serve, I ask but only this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112750">That with your power you march into the field,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112760">For now is all the army resolute,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112770">To leave the traitor helpless in the fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112780"><pb facs="20"/> and fly to me as to their rightful prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112790">Some horsemen have already led the way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112800">And vow the like for their companions,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112810">The host is full of tumult and of fear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112820">Then as you come to plant me in my seat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112830">And to enlarge your fame in Africa,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112840">Now, now or never bravely execute</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112850">Your resolution sound and honourable,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112860">And end this war together with his life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112870">That doth usurp the crown with tyranny. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e112880" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112890">Captains, you hear the reasons of the King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112900">Which so effectually have pierced wine ears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112910">That I am fully resolute to fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112920">And who refuseth now to follow me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112930">Let him be ever counted cowardly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e112940" who="A09221-avero">
          <speaker>Avero</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112950">Shame be his share that flies when Kings do fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112960">Avero lays his life before your feet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e112970" who="A09221-stukely">
          <speaker>Stukeley</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112980">For my part lords, I cannot sell my blood</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e112990">Dearer than in the company of Kings. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e113000">Exeunt.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e113010">Manet Muly Mahamet.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e113020" who="A09221-muly-mahomet">
          <speaker>Muly Ma.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113030">Now have I set these Portugals a work,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113040">To hew a way for me unto the crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113050">Or with your weapons here to dig your graves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113060">You dastards of the night and Erebus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113070">Fiends, fairies, hags that fight in beds of steel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113080">Range through this army with your iron whips,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113090">Drive forward to this deed this christian crew,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113100">And let me triumph in the tragedy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113110">Though it be sealed and honoured with my blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113120">Both of the Portugal and barbarous Moor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113130">Ride Nemesis, ride in thy fiery cart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113140"><pb facs="21"/> and sprinkle gore amongst these men of war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113150">That either party eager of revenge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113160">May honour thee with sacrifice of death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113170">And having bathed thy chariot wheels in blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113180">Descend and take to thy tormenting hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113190">The mangled body of that traitor King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113200">That scorns the power and force of Portugal. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113210">Then let the earth discover to his ghost,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113220">Such tortures as usurpers feel below,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113230">Racked let him be in proud Ixion's wheel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113240">Pined let him be with Tantalus endless thirst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113250">Pray let him be to Tison's greedy bird,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113260">Wearied with Sisyphus immortal toil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113270">And lastly for revenge, for deep revenge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113280">Whereof thou goddess and deviser art,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113290">Damned let him be, damned and condemned to bear</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113300">All torments, tortures, plagues and pains of hell. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e113310">Exit.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e113320">Enter the presenter before the last dumb show, and speaketh.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e113330" who="A09221-presenter">
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113340">Ill be to him that so much ill bethinks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113350">And ill betide this foul ambitious Moor,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113360">Whose wily trains with smoothest course of speech. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113370">Hath tide and tangled in a dangerous war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113380">The fierce and manly King of Portugal. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e113390">Lightning and thunder.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113400">Now throw the heavens forth their lightning flames,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113410">And thunder over Afrique's fatal fields,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113420">Blood will have blood, foul murder scape no scourge. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e113430">Enter fame like an angel, and hangs the crowns upon a tree.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113440">At last descendeth fame as Iris,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113450"><pb facs="21"/> to finish fainting Dido's dying life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113460">Fame from her stately bout doth descend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113470">And on the tree as fruit new ripe to fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113480">Placeth the crowns of these unhappy Kings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113490">That erst she kept in eye of all the world. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e113500">Here the blazing star.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113510">Now fiery stars and streaming comets blaze,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113520">That threat the earth and princes of the same. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e113530">Fire works.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113540">Fire, fire about the axletree of heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113550">Who whirls round, and from the foot of Casyopa</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113560">In fatal hour consumes these fatal crowns,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e113570">One falls.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113580">Down falls the diadem of Portugal,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e113590">The other falls.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113600">The crowns of Barbary and kingdom's fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113610">Ay me, that kingdoms may not stable stand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113620">And now approaching near the dismal day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113630">The bloody day wherein the battles join,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113640">Monday the fourth of August seventy eight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113650">The sun shines wholly on the parched earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113660">The brightest planet in the highest heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113670">The heathens eager bent against their foe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113680">Give onset with great ordnance to the war. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113690">The Christians with great noise of cannon shot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113700">Send angry onsets to the enemy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113710">Give ear and hear how war begins his song,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113720">With dreadful clamours, noise, and trumpets sound. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e113730">Exit.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113740">Alarms within, let the chambers be discharged, then enter to the battle, and the Moors fly. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113750">Skirmish still then enter ab dilmelec in his chair, Zareo and their train. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e113760" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113770">Say on Zareo, tell me all the news,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113780">Tell me what fury rangeth in our camp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113790"><pb facs="22"/> that hath enforced our Moors to turn their backs. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113800">Zareo say, what chance did bode this ill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113810">What ill enforced this dastard cowardice? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e113820" who="A09221-zareo">
          <speaker>Zareo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113830">My lord, such chance as wilful war affords</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113840">Such chances and misfortunes as attend</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113850">On him, the god of battle and of arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113860">My lord, when with our ordnance fierce we sent</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113870">Our Moors with smaller shot as thick as hail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113880">Follows apace to charge the Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113890">The valiant Duke the devil of Avero,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113900">The bane of Barbary, fraughted full of ire</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113910">Breaks through the ranks, and with five hundred horse</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113920">All men at arms, forward and full of might,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113930">Assaults the middle wing, and puts to flight</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113940">Eight thousand harquebus that served on foot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113950">And twenty thousand Moors with spear and shield:</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113960">And therewithal the honour of the day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e113970" who="A09221-abdilmelec">
          <speaker>Abdel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113980">Ah Abdelmelec dost thou live to hear</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e113990">This bitter process of this first attempt? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114000">Labour my lords to renew our force,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114010">Of fainting Moors, and fight it to the last. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114020">My horse Zareo, oh the goal is lost,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114030">The goal is lost, thou King of Portugal</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114040">Thrice happy chance it is for thee and thine</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114050">That heavens abates my strength and calls me hence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114060">My sight doth fail, my soul, my feeble soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114070">Shall be released from prison on this earth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114080">Farewell vain world for I have played my part. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e114090">He dyeth.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e114100">A long Skirmidge, and then enter his brother Muly Mahomet Seth.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e114110" who="A09221-muly">
          <speaker>Muly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114120">Brave Abdelmelec, thou thrice noble lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114130">Not such a wound was given to Barbary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114140"><pb facs="22"/> had twenty hosts of men been put to sword</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114150">As death, pale death with fatal shaft hath given. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114160">Lo dead is he, my brother and my King</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114170">Whom I might have revived with news I bring. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e114180" who="A09221-zareo">
          <speaker>Zareo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114190">His honours and his types he hath resigned</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114200">Unto the world, and of a manly man</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114210">Lo, in a twinkling a senseless stock we see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e114220" who="A09221-muly">
          <speaker>Muly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114230">You trusty soldiers of this warlike King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114240">Be counsel de now by us in this advice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114250">Let not his death be bruited in the camp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114260">Lest with the sudden sorrow of the news,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114270">The army wholly be discomfited. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114280">My lord Zareo thus I comfort you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114290">Our Moors have bravely born themselves in fight</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114300">Likely to get the honour of the day</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114310">If ought may gotten be where loss is such. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114320">Therefore in this apparel as he died</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114330">My noble brother will we here advance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114340">And set him in his chair with cunning props,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114350">That our barbarians may behold their King</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114360">And think he doth repose him in his tent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e114370" who="A09221-zareo">
          <speaker>Zareo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114380">Right politic and good is your advice. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114390">Go then to see it speedily performed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114400">Brave lord, if Barbary recover this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114410">Thy soul with joy will sit and see the sight. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e114420">Exeunt.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e114430">Alarms. Enter to the battle, and the Christians fly. The Duke of Avero slain.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e114440">Enter Sebastian and Stukeley.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e114450" who="A09221-sebastian">
          <speaker>Sebast.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114460">Seest thou not Stukeley, oh Stukeley seest thou not</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114470">The great dishonour done to Christendom? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114480"><pb facs="23"/>Our cheerful onset crossed in springing hope,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114490">The brave and mighty prince, Duke of Avero</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114500">Slain in my sight, now joy betide his ghost,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114510">For like a lion did he bear himself. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114520">Our battles are all now disordered,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114530">And by our horses strange retiring back,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114540">Our middle wing of footmen over-rode. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114550">Stukeley, alas I see my oversight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114560">False hearted Mahamet, now to my cost,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114570">I see thy treachery, warned to beware</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114580">A face so full of fraud and villainy. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e114590">Alarms within, and they run out, and two set upon Stukeley, and he driveth them in. Then enter the Moor and his boy flying.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e114600" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker>Moore.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114610">Villain, a horse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e114620" who="A09221-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114630">O my lord, if you return you die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e114640" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker>Moore.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114650">Villain I say, give me a horse to fly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114660">To swim the river villain, and to fly. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e114670">Exit boy.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114680">Where shall I find some unfrequented place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114690">Some uncouth walk where I may curse my fill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114700">My stars, my dam, my planets and my nurse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114710">The fire, the air, the water, and the earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114720">All causes that have thus conspire in one,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114730">To nourish and preserve me to this shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114740">Thou that wert at my birth predominate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114750">Thou fatal star, what planet ere thou be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114760">Spit out thy poison bad, and all the ill</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114770">That fortune, fate or heaven may bode a man. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114780">Thou nurse infortunate, guilty of all:</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114790">Thou mother of my life that broughtest me forth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114800">Cursed mayst thou be for such a cursed son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114810">Cursed be thy son with every curse thou hast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114820">Ye elements of whom consists this clay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114830"><pb facs="23"/> this mass of flesh, this cursed crazed corpses,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114840">Destroy, dissolve, disturb, and dissipate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114850">What water, earth, and air congealed. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e114860">Alarms and enter the boy.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e114870" who="A09221-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114880">O my lord, these ruthless Moors pursue you at the heels,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114890">And come amain to put you to the sword. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e114900" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker>Moore.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114910">A horse, a horse, villain a horse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114920">That I may take the river straight and fly,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e114930" who="A09221-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114940">Here is a horse my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114950">As swiftly paced as Pegasus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114960">Mount thee thereon, and save thyself by flight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e114970" who="A09221-moor">
          <speaker>Moore.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114980">Mount me I will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e114990">But may I never pass the river till I be</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115000">Revenged upon thy soul accursed Abdelmelec,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115010">If not on earth, yet when we meet in hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115020">Before grim Minos, Rodamant, and Aeacus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115030">The combat will I crave upon thy ghost,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115040">And drag thee through the loathsome pools,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115050">Of Lethe's, Styx, and fiery Phlegethon. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e115060">Exit.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e115070">Alarms. Enter Stukeley with two Italians.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e115080" who="A09221-hercules">
          <speaker>Herc.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115090">Stand traitor, stand ambitious Englishman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115100">Proud Stukeley stand, and stir not ere thou die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115110">Thy forwardness to follow wrongful arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115120">And leave our famous expedition erst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115130">Intended by his holiness for Ireland,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115140">Foully hath here betrayed, and tide us all</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115150">To ruthless fury of our heathen foe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115160">For which as we are sure to die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115170">Thou shalt pay satisfaction with thy blood. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e115180" who="A09221-stukeley">
          <speaker><pb facs="24"/>Stuk.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115190">A vaunt base villains, twit ye me with shame</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115200">Or infamy of this injurious war? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115210">When he that is the judge of right and wrong</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115220">Determines battle as him pleaseth best. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115230">But sith my stars bode me this tragic end</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115240">That I must perish by these barbarous Moors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115250">Whose weapons have made passage for my soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115260">That breaks from out the prison of my breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115270">Ye proud malicious dogs of Italy</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115280">Strike on, strike down this body to the earth</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115290">Whose mounting mind stoops to no feeble stroke. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e115300">Stab him.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e115310" who="A09221-jonas">
          <speaker>Jonas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115320">Why suffer we this English man to live? </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115330">Villain bleed on, thy blood in channels run</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115340">And meet with those whom thou to death hast done</l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e115350">Exeunt.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e115360" who="A09221-stukeley">
          <speaker>Stuk.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115370">Thus Stukeley slain with many a deadly stab,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115380">Dies in these desert fields of Africa. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115390">Hark friends, and with the story of my life</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115400">Let me beguile the torment of my death. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115410">In England's London lordings was I born,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115420">On that brave bridge, the bar that thwarts the Thames. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115430">My golden days, my younger careless years,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115440">Were when I touched the height of fortune's wheel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115450">And lived in affluence of wealth and ease. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115460">Thus in my country carried long aloft,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115470">A discontented humour drave me thence</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115480">To cross the seas to Ireland, then to Spain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115490">There had I welcome and right royal pay</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115500">Of Philip, whom some call the Catholic King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115510">There did Tom Stukeley glitter all in gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115520">Mounted upon his jennet white as snow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115530">Shining as Phoebus in King Phillip's court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115540">There like a lord, famous don Stukeley lived,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115550"><pb facs="24"/> for so they called me in the court of Spain</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115560">Till for a blow I gave a Bishop's man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115570">A strife 'gan rise between his lord and me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115580">For which, we both were banished by the King. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115590">From thence, to Rome rides Stukeley all aflaunt </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115600">Received with royal welcomes of the Pope. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115610">There was I graced by Gregory the great,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115620">That then created me marquis of Ireland. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115630">Short be my tale, because my life is short,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115640">The coast of Italy and Rome I left. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115650">Then was I made lieutenant general</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115660">Of those small forces that for Ireland went,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115670">And with my companies embarked at Austria</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115680">My sails I spread, and with these men of war</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115690">In fatal hour at Lisbon we arrived. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115700">From thence to this, to this hard exigent</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115710">Was Stukeley driven to fight or else to die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115720">Dared to the field, that never could endure</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115730">To hear God Mars his drum, but he must march. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115740">Ah sweet Sebastian, hadst thou been well advised</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115750">Thou mightst have managed arms successfully. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115760">But from our cradles we were marked all</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115770">And destinate to die in Afrique here. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115780">Stukeley, the story of thy life is told,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115790">Here breathe thy last and bid thy friends farewell. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115800">And if thy country's kindness be so much,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115810">Then let thy country kindly ring thy knell. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115820">Now go, and in that bed of honour die</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115830">Where brave Sebastian's breathless course doth lie. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115840">Here endeth fortune, rule, and bitter rage:</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115850">Here ends Tom Stukeley pilgrimage. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e115860">He dyeth</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e115870">Enter muly Mahometh and his train, with drums and trumpets.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e115880" who="A09221-muly">
          <speaker>Muly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115890">Retreat is sounded through our camp, and now</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115900"><pb facs="25"/> from battles fury cease our conquering Moors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115910">Pay thanks to heaven with sacrificing fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115920">Alcazar and ye towns of Barbary. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115930">Now hast thou sit as in a trance and seen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115940">To thy soul's joy and honour of thy house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115950">The trophies and the triumphs of thy men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115960">Great Abdelmelec and the god of Kings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115970">Hath made thy war successful by thy right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115980">His friends whom death and fates hath ta'en from thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e115990">Lo this was he that was the people's pride,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116000">And cheerful sunshine to his subjects all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116010">Now have him hence, that royally he may</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116020">Be buried and embalmed, as is meet. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116030">Zareo, have you through the camp proclaimed</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116040">As erst we gave in charge? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116050" who="A09221-zareo">
          <speaker>Zareo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116060">We have my lord, and rich rewards proposed</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116070">For them that find the body of the King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116080">For by those guard that had him in their charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116090">We understand that he was done to death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116100">And for his search two prisoners Portugals</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116110">Are set at large to find their royal King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116120" who="A09221-muly-mahomet">
          <speaker>Muly Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116130">But of the traitorous Moor you hear no news. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116140">That fled the field and sought to swim the ford? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116150" who="A09221-zareo">
          <speaker>Zareo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116160">Not yet my lord, but doubtless God will tell</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116170">And with his finger point out where he haunts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116180" who="A09221-muly-mahomet">
          <speaker>Muly Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116190">So let it rest, and on this earth bestow</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116200">This princely corse, till further for his funerals</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116210">We provide. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116220" who="A09221-zareo">
          <speaker>Zareo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116230">From him to thee as true succeeding prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116240">With all allegiance, and with honour's tips,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116250">In name of all thy people and thy land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116260">We give this kingly crown and diadem. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116270" who="A09221-muly">
          <speaker>Muly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116280">We thank you all, and as my lawful right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116290"><pb facs="25"/> with god's defence and yours shall I keep. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e116300">Enter two Portugals with the body of the King.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116310" who="A09221-portugal">
          <speaker>Port.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116320">As gave your grace in charge, right royal prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116330">The fields and sandy plains we have surveyed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116340">And even among the thickest of his lords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116350">The noble King of Portugal we found</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116360">Wrapped in his colours coldly on the earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116370">And done to death with many a mortal wound. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116380" who="A09221-mah">
          <speaker>Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116390">Lo here my lords, this is the earth and clay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116400">Of him that erst was mighty King of Portugal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116410">There let him lie, and you for this be free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116420">To make return from hence to Christendom. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A09221-e116430">Enter two bringing in the Moor.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116440" who="A09221-one">
          <speaker>One.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116450">Long live the mighty King of Barbary. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116460" who="A09221-mah">
          <speaker>Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116470">Welcome my friend, what body hast thou there? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116480" who="A09221-one">
          <speaker>One.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116490">The body of the ambitious enemy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116500">That squandered all this blood in Africa,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116510">Whose malice sent so many souls to hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116520">The traitor Muly Mahamet do I bring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116530">And for thy slave I throw him at thy feet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116540" who="A09221-mah">
          <speaker>Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116550">Zareo give this man a rich reward,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116560">And thanked be the god of just revenge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116570">That he hath given our foe into our hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116580">Beastly, unarmed, slavish, full of shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116590">But say, how came this traitor to his end? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116600" who="A09221-one">
          <speaker>One,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116610">Seeking to save his life by shameful flight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116620">He mounteth on a hot barbarian horse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116630">And so in purpose to have passed the stream,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116640">His headstrong stead throws him from out his seat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116650">Where diving oft for lack of skill to swim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116660"><pb facs="26"/> it was my chance alone to see him drowned. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116670">Whom by the heels I dragged from out the pool,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116680">And hither have him brought thus filled with mud. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A09221-e116690" who="A09221-mah">
          <speaker>Mah.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116700">A death too good for such a damned wretch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116710">But sith our rage and rigor of revenge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116720">By violence of his end prevented is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116730">That all the world may learn by him to avoid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116740">To hall on princes to injurious war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116750">His skin we will be parted from his flesh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116760">And being stiffened out and stuffed with straw,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116770">So to deter and fear the lookers on. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116780">From any such soul fact or bad attempt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116790">Away with him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116800">And now my lords, for this christian King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116810">My lord Zareo, let it be your charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116820">To see the soldiers tread a solemn march. </l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116830">Trailing their pikes and ensigns on the ground,</l>
          <l xml:id="A09221-e116840">So to perform the princes funerals. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer xml:id="A09221-e116850">Here endeth the tragical battle of Alcazar.</trailer>
        <pb facs="26"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A09221"><item xml:id="A09221-sebastian" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-sebastian</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-abdilmelec" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-abdilmelec</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-moor" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-moor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-stukeley" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-stukeley</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-muly-mahomet" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-muly-mahomet</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-zareo" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-zareo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-presenter" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-presenter</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-mah" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-mah</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-celybin" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-celybin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-muly" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-muly</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-diego" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-diego</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-bassa" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-bassa</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-rubin" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-rubin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-calypolis" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-calypolis</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-bishop" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-bishop</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-hercules" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-hercules</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-boy" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-boy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-ambassador" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-ambassador</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-jonas" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-jonas</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-one" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-one</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-governor" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-governor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-avero" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-avero</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-other" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-other</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-raye" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-raye</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-muly_xe" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-muly_xe</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-messenger" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-captain_2" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-captain_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-legate" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-legate</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-queen" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-queen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-stukely" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-stukely</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-captain" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-captain</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-portugal" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-portugal</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-christopher" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-christopher</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A09221-moor_son" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A09221-moor_son</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

