<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A04959">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Corona Minervae <date type="creation_date">1635</date></title>
        <author>Kynaston, Francis (?) </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A04959.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Corona Minervæ. Or A masque presented before Prince Charles His Highnesse, the Duke of Yorke his brother, and the Lady Mary his sister, the 27th of February, at the Colledge of the Museum Minervæ.</title>
            <author>Kinnaston, Francis, Sir, 1587-1642.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>15 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2011 April (TCP phase 2)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99843843</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 15100.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 503.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">8602</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04959</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Corona Minervæ. Or A masque presented before Prince Charles His Highnesse, the Duke of Yorke his brother, and the Lady Mary his sister, the 27th of February, at the Colledge of the Museum Minervæ.</title>
            <title type="alt">Corona Minervæ</title>
            <title type="alt">Masque presented before Prince Charles His Highnesse, the Duke of Yorke his brother, and the Lady Mary his sister, the 27th of February, at the Colledge of the Museum Minervæ.</title>
            <author>Kinnaston, Francis, Sir, 1587-1642.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[28] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed for William Sheares,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1635.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Anonymous. By Sir Francis Kinnaston.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-C4 D2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Variant: with an added leaf, "To the reader", inserted after title page.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Masques.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A04959-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A04959-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A04959-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A04959-e100040">Corona minervae. Or a masqve presented before prince Charles his highness, the Duke of York his brother, and the lady Mary his sister, the 27thof February, at the college of the museum minervae.</p>
        <p xml:id="A04959-e100050">London, printed for William Sheares. 1635.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A04959-e100060">
      <div type="masque" xml:id="A04959-e100070">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>Corona minervae. A masque presented before prince Charles his highness, the Duke of York his brother, and the lady Mary his sister, the 27th. of February, at the college of the museum minervae. </head>
        <p xml:id="A04959-e100080">A curtain being drawn, there is discovered a frontispiece, whereon the image of Minerva is seen sitting upon a stone, placed between two returns of a broken arch, supported by two brass statues of Mars, and Mercury, standing in niches of Corinthian work: under, within<pb facs="3"/> a prospective is seen, a paved gallery environed on either side and terminated with Doric columns, which flying away, Minerva presents herself attired in her proper habit.</p>
        <p xml:id="A04959-e100090">Over the entrance in a square was written</p>
        <p xml:id="A04959-e100100">
          <quote xml:id="A04959-e100110">Corona minervae.</quote>
        </p>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e100120" who="A04959-minerva">
          <speaker>Minerva.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100130">What rare unvalued jewels are here sent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100140">As if the gods themselves strived to present</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100150">Minerva with their choicest gems, and grace</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100160">Her cabinet, as yet too mean a place</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100170">To hold such deities, who more adorn</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100180">This presence, than the rosy fingered morn</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100190">(Guiding the East for the uprising sun)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100200">Doth beautify his car, ready to run</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100210">His daily circle round. It hath been said,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100220">The friends and servants of the jove-born maid</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100230">Are poor, except those, whom Bellona's hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100240">Enrolls for soldiers of Mars warlike band,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100250">Who sometimes want their pay too: but now see</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100260">A treasure here deposited with me,</l>
          <pb facs="3"/>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100270">Outvaluing all the riches of the earth;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100280">Three pledges of sweet peace, whose happy birth</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100290">Blesseth this present age, and crown's it so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100300">That former ages passed, could they but know</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100310">How fortunate this is, they all would mourn</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100320">They passed so soon, or else would back return,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100330">To see an age, wherein both arms and arts</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100340">Flourish at height, and both share equal parts. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e100350">Time enters here to Minerva in a party coloured robe half white, half black, fringed with silver, with one wing of a swan, another of a bat. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e100360" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100370">Great mistress of both arms and arts, 'tis true,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100380">Your exploration of their praises due,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100390">They are the blessings, which the ages passed</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100400">Fell ignorant, and unworthy-of to taste. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100410">And I old time, that of those ages saw</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100420">The first, and last, till now could never draw</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100430">Air, that so pleased me, as in this blessed clime,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100440">That crown's with youth the old-old head of time. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100450">All breath's panchaian here: nay only this</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100460">Is the clear western that Favonian is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100470">Perpetual spring creating. God's here</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100480">Your twofold discipline, in which you were</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100490">So late distracted by the world's neglect,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100500">Shall reassume it's ancient fair respect. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e100510" who="A04959-minerva">
          <speaker>Minerva.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e100520">Time, you speak comfort to me.</p>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e100530" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100540">And no more</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100550">Than my glad daughter truth is spreading o'er</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100560">This happy monarchy, whose supreme head</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100570">(In highest heaven his name is registered)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100580">By power and wisdom, will the use advance</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100590">Of arms and arts, above despite and chance. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e100600" who="A04959-minerva">
          <speaker>Minerva.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e100610">Time, thou hast made me happy.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e100620" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100630">No, 'tis he</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100640">That hath felicitated you and me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100650">Who hath already by defensive arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100660">Beat back the boasts, that were intended harms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100670">Which industry is crowned with a peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100680">That daily will bring forth the arts increase;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100690">You may observe th' assurance of it here</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100700">In these, who he is pleased (To grace your sphere)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100710">Should leave their own; each an illustrious gem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100720">Proper to his imperial diadem;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100730">I could with joy and wonder dwell an age</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100740">Under their smiles; from an old man, turn page</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100750">To wait upon their persons: break my glass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100760">And pick up sand by sand, ere I would pass</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100770">From their divine aspects; use all delay</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100780">Had not the fates decreed time must away. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e100790" who="A04959-minerva">
          <speaker>Minerva.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100800">But not so fast, good time, your haste may make</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100810">Their grace's leave me too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e100820" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100830">I'll undertake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100840">Sacred Minerva, they will not, but grace</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100850">You and your arts, whilst there is time and place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100860">Yet ere I go, for I must stay a while</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100870">In this fair presence, and my haste beguile</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100880">With a report of an unlooked for crew,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100890">Coming to see your princely guests and you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e100900" who="A04959-minerva">
          <speaker>Minerva.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e100910">Time, what are they?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e100920" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100930">The seasons of the year</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100940">Having discovered the convention here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100950">All equally possessed with an ambition,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100960">To see and to be seen without commission</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100970">From me, or from the months, or powerful sol,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100980">That wont is to infranchise, or control</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e100990">Them at his pleasure, now are altogether</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101000">Broke loose, and filled with gladness, posting hither. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101010">Cold winter stretching out his cramped up nerves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101020">Strives to outstrip the jolly spring, who serves</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101030">Summer the like, and with her nimble feet</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101040">Runs through her heat, till they with autumn meet;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101050">At last, they all conjoined come on their way,</l>
          <pb facs="5"/>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101060">Like the whole year contracted in this day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101070">Each season hath a several present too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101080">In which they strive each other to outdo,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101090">As if by general warrant from their fate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101100">They all were always to attend this state. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101110" who="A04959-minerva">
          <speaker>Minerva.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e101120">'Tis welcome news.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e101130">A confusion is here heard of several voices of birds, and beasts, such as are peculiar to every season.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e101140">Again here several noises and voices are heard confusedly of birds and beasts, as exactly performed to the life, that no man could distinguish them.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e101150">Upon which,</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101160" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101170">Hark, they are all at hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101180">And all their heralds, both by air and land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101190">The birds and beasts of every season met,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101200">In a most singular discord; hark how they set</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101210">Throat against throat; the wren and redbreast swell</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101220">To be above the lark and Philomell. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101230">The cuckoo with the owlet strives, and now</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101240">The bleating lamb joys 'gainst the lowing cow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101250">All in confusion, and so shall you see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101260">Will the contention of the seasons be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101270">Till I be stickler. See they come, stand by. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e101280">Here enter the four seasons rushing in, winter, spring pulling him back, spring, summer, autumn, and winter striving for precedence. </stage>
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e101290">Spring's habit was of green taffeta, fringed with silver; and figured with flowers, a chaplet of several flowers upon her head. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101300" who="A04959-spring">
          <speaker>Spring.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e101310">Winter, keep back, I claim priority.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e101320">Winter in a long gown of freeze, his hair and beard all made of icicles, a garland of hollies and ivy entwined upon his head. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101330" who="A04959-winter">
          <speaker>Winter.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101340">No wanton girl, I must have first access,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101350">My age and honour can require no less. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e101360">Summer in a straw coloured robe of taffeta, with a garland of cornflowers, and blue bottles upon his head. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101370" who="A04959-summer">
          <speaker>Summer.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e101380">I claim it from you both.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e101390">Autumn his garment of peuke-colour, a pruning knife in his hand, as a Vintiger, a chaplet of grapes and damosens upon his head. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101400" who="A04959-autumn">
          <speaker>Autumn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101410">Why, summer you? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101420">The place to autumn properly is due. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101430" who="A04959-spring">
          <speaker>Spring.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101440">How can that be? Look into every race,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101450">Do you not find, that youth takes the first place. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101460">Was not the whole world young before 'twas old? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101470" who="A04959-winter">
          <speaker>Winter.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101480">And what of that, proud girl? thy reason's cold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101490">Colder than is my frost. Did not the spring</l>
          <pb facs="6"/>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101500">Of the old world rise from an elder thing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101510">What else was chaos? hah? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101520" who="A04959-spring">
          <speaker>Spring.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e101530">I mind not that.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101540" who="A04959-winter">
          <speaker>Winter.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e101550">Fond lass, thou mindest, say'st, dost, thou knowest not what.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101560" who="A04959-summer">
          <speaker>Summer.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101570">I do: for summer's strength is at full growth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101580">Like middle age in man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101590" who="A04959-autumn">
          <speaker>Autumn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101600">I would be loath</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101610">To give the knowledge of declining age</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101620">Which autumn shadows, for the summer's rage. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101630" who="A04959-winter">
          <speaker>Winter.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101640">You're all against me, and yet it doth appear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101650">None is another's friend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101660" who="A04959-spring">
          <speaker>Spring.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101670">Yet to the year</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101680">We all do grateful service, thou dost none. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101690" who="A04959-winter">
          <speaker>Winter.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e101700">I would hear that.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101710" who="A04959-spring">
          <speaker>Spring.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101720">In me the spring, 'tis known,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101730">The grass, the grain, the leaf, the flower, the fruit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101740">The birds that sing, the beasts, the fishes mute</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101750">Take their beginnings. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101760" who="A04959-summer">
          <speaker>Summer.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101770">Make no tedious tale,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101780">You begin well, I ripe and perfect all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101790" who="A04959-spring">
          <speaker>Spring.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101800">In that you wrong me summer: for you do</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101810">Out of my hands take work and credit too. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="6"/>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101820" who="A04959-summer">
          <speaker>Summer.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101830">I wrong not you so much as autumn me;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101840">For he gets all the crop from me and thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101850" who="A04959-autumn">
          <speaker>Autumn.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101860">But all the store I gather for the year,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101870">Winter devours, or spoils. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e101880" who="A04959-winter">
          <speaker>Winter.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101890">Pray sirs forbear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101900">You increase all, you ripen all you say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101910">You gather all, I spend all, and best may. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101920">I am the careful husband of the earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101930">That gives her comforts after every birth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101940">In which you wear her out, or bring her low</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101950">Past hope, that from her teeming womb should grow</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101960">Ever more timely fruits: I kindly then</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101970">(That she may live and propagate again)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101980">Quench her faint thirst with plenteous showers of rain</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e101990">Wherewith I fill her veins, and drown her pain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102000">Then having made her bed as soft below,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102010">I cover her with swan down, you call snow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102020">Which keeps her warm, so lay I her to rest:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102030">And for her lying-in make many a feast</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102040">Of her late store, for mortals that do pray</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102050">To see her blithe again another day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e102060" who="A04959-spring">
          <speaker>Spring.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e102070">Which day would never come, were't not with me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e102080" who="A04959-winter">
          <speaker>Winter.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e102090">Nor thou with it, did not I set her free.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e102100" who="A04959-summer">
          <speaker>Summer.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e102110">This strife will grow unto an endless fit.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e102120" who="A04959-autumn">
          <speaker>Autumn.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e102130">Would we had time here to determine it.</p>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="7"/>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e102140" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102150">Time is at hand, who gives an instant charge</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102160">Distinctly, that each one of you enlarge</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102170">Himself by practice, show what you can do,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102180">Before the presence you aspire unto. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102190">What presents, or what pastimes you have brought</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102200">To please these glories, whom all you have sought</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102210">T'endear your service to. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e102220" who="A04959-all">
          <speaker>All four.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e102230">I have the best.</p>
          <stage xml:id="A04959-e102240">Here every one offered baskets of fresh fruits and flowers.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e102250" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102260">Nay one at once, for whilst you all contest</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102270">Each to be first, you but confusion make;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102280">Let time then govern you, for order's sake:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102290">Seasons, I promise you both first and last,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102300">And all shall equally their favours taste. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e102310" who="A04959-all">
          <speaker>All four.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e102320">We all obey.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e102330" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102340">Then thus I order ye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102350">Out of your discord to raise harmony,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102360">Presents you've brought I see of fruits, and flowers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102370">Leave them with me; whilst from their caves and bowers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102380">Each season summon forth and here advance</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102390">A pair of his attendance in a dance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102400">To move delight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e102410" who="A04959-all">
          <speaker>All four.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A04959-e102420">Immediately 'tis done.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e102430">Here as time speaketh, the seasons go off. First, spring, then summer, autumn next, and last winter, and immediately, as they depart, the several voices are heard distinctly, and in order according to the words of time.</stage>
        <pb facs="7"/>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e102440" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A04959-e102450">
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102460">First spring lead you the way, than every one</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102470">In order follow, let your herald's sound</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102480">Each to his season, as the year goes round:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102490">The spring begins her part already, hark! </l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102500">The evening lamb, and morning early lark</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102510">Lead her her way, the merry cuckoo too</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102520">Busy in's office; summer, now go you,</l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A04959-e102530">
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102540">Now mark the joy the fawn and swallow takes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102550">Of which there's more than one a summer makes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102560">To welcome her; now autumn take your turn,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102570">Lest Sommers too long reign your harvest burn:</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102580">The thrush now chants her notes at his approach,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102590">And the glad boar-pig having scaped the broach</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102600">At the last fair, runs wild about to taste</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102610">The scattered grain, and the sweet fatting mast. </l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102620">Now follow winter whilst your robin sings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102630">Over the half dead earth, to wake the springs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102640">In her cold veins, hark how the hoarse grown cow</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102650">Lows for her fodder, and to whit to whoo</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102660">Madge owlet cries, for cold she as in her feet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A04959-e102670">But other music now for dancers meet. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e102680">Here enter to dance,<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" xml:id="A04959-e102690">emblem of the spring. </note>a frog followed by a fisherman. To them,<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" xml:id="A04959-e102700">of the summer. </note>a sheepsherer leading a ram. To them,<note anchored="true" n="3" place="margin" xml:id="A04959-e102710">of the autumn. </note>a drunken butcher holding a big by the tail. <note anchored="true" n="4" place="margin" xml:id="A04959-e102720">of winter. </note>to them a chimneysweeper and a cat. All to several strains of agreeing music. At length all being entered, they join in a dance. The dance ended. </stage>
        <pb facs="8"/>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e102730" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102740">Creatures be gone, and let your muses meet</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102750">With fluent numbers, and harmonious sweet</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102760">Voices, to sing, of all their presents here</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102770">The worth and rarity, and let the near</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102780">Adjoining woods, rocks, valleys, caves, and hills</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102790">Resound their echoing helps to grace their skills,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102800">While I their several presents overview,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102810">The spring brings here all that is rare, and new,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102820">Of early flowers and fruits, such as to name</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102830">In other seasons might beget a blame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102840">For longing ladies' sakes. The summer brings</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102850">Gifts no less dainty, for her offerings;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102860">So autumn, and so winter, so all bear</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102870">At once, the rarities of all the year. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102880">Yet let not my dull talk attempt to wrong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102890">T'anticipate the subject of their song,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e102900">But let the woods, rocks, etc. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e102910">Here are sung the several songs by several voices, with symphonies betwixt, and a chorus: during which, time peruseth the several presents, as he discovers them orderly: all which are expressed in the song. </stage>
        <floatingText xml:id="A04959-e102920">
          <body xml:id="A04959-e102930">
            <div type="song" xml:id="A04959-e102940">
              <head>The seasons song.</head>
              <sp xml:id="A04959-e102950" who="A04959-spring">
                <speaker>Spring.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e102960">Those flowers your infancy did crown,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e102970">Spring doth again to you resign,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e102980">Which now are yours, no more her own,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e102990">The primrose, and sweet eglantine,</l>
                <pb facs="8"/>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103000">The daisy, pink, and violet blew,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103010">All which received their scents from you. </l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103020">May blossoms now shall never fade,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103030">You have may everlasting made. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A04959-e103040" who="A04959-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <lg xml:id="A04959-e103050">
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103060">All hearts rejoice, which now behold</l>
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103070">Again the happy age of gold. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103080">For time to us hath brought far more</l>
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103090">True joys, then feigned were heretofore. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103100">Three royal blossoms to us he doth bring,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103110">Whose looks and sweetness, make eternal spring. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg xml:id="A04959-e103120">
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103130">May cherries plashed up to the wall,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103140">The dew-berries, that in valleys grows,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103150">Kept in your lips, shall never fall,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103160">The lady grass, and the musk rose,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103170">Which were your mantle swathing band</l>
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103180">You make yet flourish freshly, and</l>
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103190">Sweet fennel, for court flatterers fit</l>
                  <l xml:id="A04959-e103200">Lives under you, you above it. </l>
                </lg>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A04959-e103210" who="A04959-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103220">All hearts rejoice, etc. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A04959-e103230" who="A04959-summer">
                <speaker>Summer.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103240">To keep the summer's heat away,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103250">Which earth from the young sun receives. </l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103260">The elm, the sycamore, and bay</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103270">Still shade you with their lasting leaves. </l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103280">The lilies, and the damask rose,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103290">The sheets and bed, when you repose,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103300">More white, more sweet, more soft have been</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103310">Since they did touch your whiter skin. </l>
                <pb facs="9"/>
                <pb facs="9"/>
                <pb facs="10"/>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103320">To sleep when your fair eyes incline,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103330">Hiding from men their dearest light,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103340">Let hearts ease, flowers of jasmine,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103350">And rosemary your couches dight. </l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103360">The holy thistle down shall fill</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103370">Your pillows, bolsters, and until</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103380">You rise like gemini, arm in arm,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103390">Levander cotton keep you warm. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A04959-e103400" who="A04959-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103410">All hearts rejoice, etc. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A04959-e103420" who="A04959-autumn">
                <speaker>Autumn.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103430">Rising from beds of July flowers</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103440">With Hyacinthus, and Narcissus spread</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103450">Into your lap autumnus powers,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103460">The mulberries, and raspis red,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103470">Pomona in her basket bears</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103480">Apricots, and bon Christian pears. </l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103490">And Bacchus forth his hand will reach</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103500">To pluck the damson, fig, and peach. </l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103510">And for digestion, Candian wines</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103520">Will skink out of his Indian gourd</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103530">Mellecottons, and nectarines</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103540">He brings you from his mellow hoard,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103550">That you shall wish, while you them taste,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103560">Autumn and spring may ever last:</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103570">Or, that, except them two, there were</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103580">No other seasons of the year. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A04959-e103590" who="A04959-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103600">All hearts rejoice, etc. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A04959-e103610" who="A04959-winter">
                <speaker>Winter.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103620">Cold winter brings to crown your age</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103630">Many happy years are told. </l>
                <pb facs="10"/>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103640">The myrtle, Savory, and sage,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103650">The semper viva, never old,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103660">To crown your high victorious brows</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103670">Green laurel garlands, arbute boughs</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103680">With palms, and olives, whose increase</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103690">Are emblems of your lasting peace. </l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103700">Nor is cold winter yet at all</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103710">Less frolic, than the wanton spring:</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103720">The robin red breast in the hall</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103730">Picking up crumbs at Christmas sing</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103740">When winds blow cold, and ways be fowl</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103750">In barns, and sheep coats sits the owl,</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103760">Whose note the husbandman delights</l>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103770"> whenas she hoots in frosty nights. </l>
              </sp>
              <sp xml:id="A04959-e103780" who="A04959-chorus">
                <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                <l xml:id="A04959-e103790">All hearts, etc. </l>
                <stage xml:id="A04959-e103800">The songs being ended.</stage>
              </sp>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e103810" who="A04959-minerva">
          <speaker>Minerva.</speaker>
          <stage xml:id="A04959-e103820">Here is discovered the temple of Minerva supported upon Doric columns standing in a grove, before the temple gate an antic Greek altar whereon was a crown placed.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103830">Seasons I thank you, that have all so well</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103840">Strived by your loves each others to excel</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103850">In honour of these princes. Now by you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103860">Time, let my service be presented too. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e103870" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103880">Time takes your charge, and swiftly will declare</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103890">What the devotions of Minerva are. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103900">To you great prince, and to each blessed bud</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103910">Of the same royal stock, and linked in blood</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103920">With you, Minerva gratefully imparts</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103930">Full knowledge, and true use of arms, arts,</l>
          <pb facs="11"/>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103940">And that she, bound unto this gratitude</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103950">I by fame's trumpet will make understood</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103960">Her reason through the world, for thus she says,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103970">Whereas of old she was sole patroness</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103980">Of arms, and arts, and former ages through</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e103990">Had reverence, and adoration due</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104000">To her divinity; she by blind chance</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104010">Hath been of late, and blinder ignorance</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104020">Rudely opposed, oppressed, and lastly thrown</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104030">By violence from her proper mansion</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104040">Altars, and temples, that were dedicate</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104050">To her of old, are now laid ruinate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104060">And she forlorn to give the world a view</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104070">Was all to seek of house, and patron too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104080">Labouring with that distress, unto this I'll</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104090">More gracious made by the most gracious smile</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104100">Of its most royal sovereign, than the day</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104110">In other lands, by Phoebus brightest ray,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104120">She bent her course, and here she was received</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104130">By the most gracious, bounteous King relieved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104140">Planted, and raised to a magnific state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104150">Above the reach of her malignant fate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104160">For which unequal grace, she can no less</l>
          <stage xml:id="A04959-e104170">Here a Cupid descending with a light in his hand shows unto the prince a crown, which is placed on Minerva's altar, and reserved by her for his highness. </stage>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104180">Then yield herself to be his votaress,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104190">Of all her gifts devoting the renown</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104200">A due addition to his fourfold crown. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104210">In pledge whereof, first branch of that fair stem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104220">High prince, here is a royal diadem</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104230">Brought from her old, here to her Athens new</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104240">By your propitious fate reserved for you</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104250">Upon Minerva's altar, 'tis no slight</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104260">Or fabulous thing that time shall now recite;</l>
          <pb facs="11"/>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104270"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A04959-e104280">Hippocrates divinanatura preditus nonus a chrisamide rege, decimus et octavus ab Aesculapio. Vigesimus a looe ex patre heraclida, ex matre Paxithea Phaenaretes silia ex familia he aclidarum, quare ex utroque se. mine a diis ortum habet divinus Hippocrates, ut qui a patre quidem asclepiades est, a matre heraclides. didicit artātuma patre heraclidatum ab avo Hippocrate et proinde iustissime, in multis terrae locis divinos honores etiam ipse consequutus est, et tisdem donariis cum hercule et aescula pioab atheniensi bus dignus factus est. paetus in epistola ad regem regum magnum Artaxerxem. Heraclidae erant gigantes, in oration Thessaliad athenienses. Hippocrates genere et arte conjunctus est Aesculapio, hic vero herculis est ex fratre nepos. in epistola senatus populique abderitarum.</note> 'tis found in my records 'mongst ancient rules</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104290">That were observed in Minerva's schools</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104300">That those of physic were not held the least</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104310">But rather most divine of all the rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104320">And that of old physicians had relation</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104330">Amongst princes, and the gods, and adoration</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104340">Given to their person, and their memories. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104350">Then shined Minerva's altar, when her wise</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104360">Athenians there, to add his renown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104370">Gave Hercules an Aesculapian crown:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104380">And after him, when by the same decree</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104390">Great skilled Hippocrates upon his knee</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104400">Received the like, and was sent crowned thence</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104410">Physicians, and philosophers, high prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104420">This crown still reserves in store</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104430">Great sir, to add unto your future four. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104440">To this, as to the rest, you're princely heir</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104450">Prince of physicians born your titles fair</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104460">And I find it (Time shall do no wrong)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104470">In rendering truth, though his discourse be long. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104480">In Florence the first Dukes to crown the name</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104490">Of Cosmus, who most piously became</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104500">Patron of christian cures successively,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104510">Were (The physician's art to dignify)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104520">Through many reigns called Cosmus, latter days</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104530">Have crowned the Medici with flourishing bays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104540">All of them still employing, that they are</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104550">Patrons of all physicians regular:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104560">And from the illustrious Florence Medici</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104570">You draw a line from France to Brittany</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104580">'Twas first the honour of the Florence crown</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104590">To take its fair denomination</l>
          <pb facs="12"/>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104600">From physics art, and that but rational</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104610">In France to physic supernatural. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104620">That titles linked, and both in one brought o'er</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104630">Met the miraculous cure was here before</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104640">In the thrice happy England, so you are</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104650">By virtue of descent apparent heir</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104660">To the physician's crown, who both inherit</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104670">Of rational, and miraculous cures the spirit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104680"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A04959-e104690">that those of physic. Hippocrates divina natura praeditus est, nonus quidem a crisamide rege: etc., Hippocrates is endowed with a divine nature the ninth truly by descent from King Crisamides, the eighteenth from Esculapius, the twentieth from Jupiter: by his mother Praxithea the daughter of Phaenaretes. he is of the family of the Heraclides, by his father an Asclepiad, so that by both his parents divine Hippocrates hath his offspring from the gods, and for his art most justly hath in many places of the earth obtained divine honours and with Hercules and Esculapius, he hath by the Athenians been made worthy of the same gifts etc.: Petus proconsul in his epistle to the great King of Kings Artaxerxes. </note>for which, and for the favours done to her</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104700">Minerva must on you this crown confer. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e104710" who="A04959-minerva">
          <speaker>Minerva.</speaker>
          <stage xml:id="A04959-e104720">Here the music sounds for the dance of the 4. Nations of England Scotland, France and Ireland. </stage>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104730">Time while you strive to show my gratitude</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104740">I fear you are thought tedious if not rude</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104750">To press so far. But hark this music says</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104760">Each nation, that subjectingly obeys</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104770">Their majesties, and you are come to show</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104780">With nimble feet the duty, that they owe</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104790"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A04959-e104800">visum est, ac decretum senatui et populo atheniensium ut gratiam condignam hippocrati pro benefactis referat, ipsum publicè magnis mysteriis initiare quemadmodum herculem fusum lovis, et coronare ipsum Corona aurea mille anreorum, et ipsam coronam quatriis magnis Minerva festis, in gertamine gymnico per praeconem proclamare. in decreto Atheni, ensium. Ab initio dei unde genus nostrum esse gloriamur Aesculapius et Hercules in hominum utilitatem prognatisunt. Et hos proptervirtutem quam exercuerunt, omnes de●rumloco habent oratio thèssali and athenienses.</note> all in their kind t'express their skill in dance. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104810">Glad England first, blithe Scotland, sprightly France</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104820">And civilised Ireland shall in order trace</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104830">And do their best to gain a greater grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e104840">Enter the dancers who having ended their dance Minerva speaks to the princes. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e104850" who="A04959-minerva">
          <speaker>Minerva.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104860">Now princely ones may't please you to advance</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104870">And your aspects on fresher objects glance</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104880">Of arms, and arts. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="12"/>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e104890" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104900">Pray you be pleased to walk</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104910">And pardon time, old folks are full of talk. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A04959-e104920">The prince, and the rest are here conducted by Minerva, and time towards the chamber of arts, and arms, by the way Minerva turning to the prince speaks.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e104930" who="A04959-minerva">
          <speaker>Minerva.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104940">Great Britain's prince, since that your innate love</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104950">To learning doth so soon your highness move</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104960">To view Minerva's mansion, and to be</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104970">Admitted one of hers. Behold, and see</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104980">How I begin (Out of a tender care</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e104990">Complying with your years) books to prepare</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105000">Fit for your studies, now from which by sense</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105010">You may extract the sweetest quintessence</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105020"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A04959-e105030">ego nunc cum mea sobole, oleaeramulis coronotus ad minerva aram supplex consisto. Oratio hippocratis ad aram consistentis Coro. illa aurea in theatro vestro i● posita ad sum. ām aemulationēac felicitatem patrem meum evexit: sed et hoc beneficium superastis, dum et patrem et me publicè cereris et proserpinae mysteriis ac sacris initiastis. Thessalus in ora●. ad athenienses. Thessalus filius hippocratis aurea corona coronatus ab atheniensibus Theodoret.</note> had by allusion to each authors name</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105040">To sweeten learning's root so as the same</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105050">To others bitter might prove sweet to you</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105060">Then freely taste, and tasting cast your view</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105070">Upon each authors name, whereby you may</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105080">Be more acquainted with them day by day. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105090">And, as your better part shall shine more clear</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105100">I'll from themselves still make you better cheer. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e105110">The princes, and the rest being entered.</stage>
        <pb facs="13"/>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e105120" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105130">How now, what mystery is this? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105140">How dare you use the prince thus, schoolmistress? </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105150">Are th'arms, and arts you promised to his view</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105160">To be picked out of books? This is a new</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105170">And a course way of entertainment too. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105180">A banquet had been fitter. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e105190" who="A04959-minerva">
          <speaker>Minerva.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105200">Such is this</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105210">Time, if you knew but what sweet learning is</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105220">Composed in these plain books, yourself would say</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105230">Both for delight, and health his highness may</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105240">Not only taste, but as his meat devour them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105250">And so become a helluo librorum. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e105260" who="A04959-time">
          <speaker>Time.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105270">Yet by your learned leave, Minerva, let</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105280">Before his taster here the books be set</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105290">What author's this? pray let us here begin</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105300">Suetonius says his out side: but within</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105310">All sweet meats. O sweet Suetonius! </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105320">What's his next neighbour? Aulus Gellius,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105330">All jellies, as I am true time. What lurks</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105340">Here in this volume? 'tis friar bacons works</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105350">Most sweetly interlarded. And here's Cato</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105360">In biscuit cakes, and sugar plates in Plato. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105370">Erasmus full of preserved raspices,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105380">Delicate authors all. Now what are these</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105390">Damesins in Damascenus, and preserved</l>
          <pb facs="13"/>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105400">Lemons here in Levinus Lemnius served. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105410">Apples in Apuleius. All's good cheer. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105420">But stay Minerva, what good drink ha' ye here</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105430">To wash it down? o here I see are brought</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105440">Nine amphoras of glass; in each a draught</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105450">Of several waters, sent from several wells</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105460">And fountains, where the sacred muses dwells,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105470">As their nine names, which are inscribed thereon</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105480">Do plainly show. See first from Helicon</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105490">Clio a clear immortal liquor sends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105500">Urania Eridanus commends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105510">Thalia of Ionian pleasant streams</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105520">A drink hath sent. The ancient poet's themes</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105530">Bacchus Minerva's bottleman did bring</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105540">This sweetest nectar from the Thespian spring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105550">A present from Erato: this pure clean</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105560">Fresh water seems to come from Hippocrene</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105570">Euterpe's gift: and here, and please you, sip ye</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105580">Of the clear brook, that runs from Aganippe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105590">Sent by Melpomene, so of the rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105600">Whose liquours come to dignify the feast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105610">So may you eat, and drink, and carry more</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105620">Of learning hence then Pallas keeps in store. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A04959-e105630">The banquet being ended Minerva turning to the prince speaks for a conclusion thus.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A04959-e105640" who="A04959-minerva">
          <speaker>Minerva.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105650">Now (Royal prince) with thanks let Pallas say;</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105660">She's by your brightness had a glorious day:</l>
          <pb facs="14"/>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105670">But you declining your Phoebean light</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105680">Will leave her shrouded in perpetual night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105690">Unless to show you're pleased you leave for grace</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105700">A smile, which may illuminate the place. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105710">So shall Minerva give a glad adieu</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105720">Withal her arms, and arts to wait on you. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e105730">For the banquet were provided little angels holding candles to give light unto the princes: which hung in the air could no way be discerned.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e105740">The banquet which Minerva gave was enclosed in artificial books, so handsomely made that no man could know but that they were very books indeed, disposed and placed according to their several volumes: between which by these nine several amphoras of glass were placed, full of 9 several sorts of wines as sent from the 9 muses. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="A04959-e105750">The authors that Minerva showed the princes were many, but the first that fell into the prince's hands were these, which follow named: and in the frontispeece of them were found these verses following. </stage>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e105760">
          <head>In Suetonius these</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105770">My title is Suetonius, but within</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105780">A history of sweet meats doth begin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105790">Which so may please (Illustrious prince) your taste</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105800">As your life may all Caesar's acts out last. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e105810">
          <head>Aulus Gellius.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105820">Let the lamp wasting student, who delights</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105830">In reading Aulus Gellius Attic nights,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105840">Make himself pale: here for a courtier's wit</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105850">Is nourishing strong jelly much more fit. </l>
        </lg>
        <pb facs="14"/>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e105860">
          <head>Friar bacons works.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105870">Friar bacons works my inside well may be</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105880">Now conjured into Collops: and yet see</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105890">There is no Puritan but would desire</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105900">Like to the devil to devour this friar. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e105910">
          <head>Lucius Florus.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105920">See Lucius Florus from his history</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105930">Renders you nothing but a prophecy</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105940">Upon your flower deluces, which he says</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105950">Shall grace your crown 'bove all his emperor's bays. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e105960">
          <head>Levinus Lemnius de occultis naturae miraculis.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105970">If for Levinus Lemnius you do find</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105980">Dried candied lemons, or a citron rind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e105990">Here soon read over: for at once you look</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106000">On all the hidden secrets of his book. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e106010">
          <head>Apuleius.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106020">Not Apuleius golden ass's story</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106030">(Glory of princes) here is set before ye:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106040">But golden apples of the hesperides</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106050">Are brought your taste, as well as sight to please. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e106060">
          <head>Quintus Curtius.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106070">My outside's Quinius Curtius' (Gracious princes)</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106080">But see within my leaves are curious quinces</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106090">This transposition well excused may be:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106100">Books and their titles do not still agree. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e106110">
          <head>Origen.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106120">If (Curious reader) you desire to know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106130">Why the inside and the title differ so:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106140">As Origen and Orang, make no doubt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106150">The anagrams within of what's without. </l>
        </lg>
        <pb facs="15"/>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e106160">
          <head>Damascenus.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106170">Old Damascenus says you are too young,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106180">Sweet prince, to read or taste of physic strong:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106190">Therefore which better may your palate suit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106200">Prescribes you damsens your liege country fruit. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e106210">
          <head>Erasmus roterodamus.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106220">When with Erasmus you hereafter meet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106230">You'll find him like this raspis sharp and sweet</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106240">Sweet like almond butter, which never came</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106250">From any butter box of Roterdame. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e106260">
          <head>Cato.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106270">Cato from sugar cakes not differs far,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106280">Since into distickes both divided are. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e106290">
          <head>Plato.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106300">Vouchsafe of Plato's works to taste a piece,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106310">Though not of greek, yet full of ambergris. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e106320">
          <head>Manuscripti.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106330">Among so many books 'tis not o'er slipped,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106340">That you have here a manuscript. </l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106350">You may well see by what you do find in't,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106360">'Twas done by hand and never yet in print. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e106370">
          <head>Hermolaus barbarus.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106380">Of Hermolaus barbarus the sense</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106390">Is harmless; barberies, like eloquence:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106400">Which though 'tis sweet, hath tartness mixed among</l>
          <pb facs="15"/>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106410">Witness each wanton witty woman's tongue. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e106420">
          <head>Cardanus.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106430">Cardanus works these are, as some do say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106440">But it seems rather that they were his play. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A04959-e106450">
          <head>Littleton.</head>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106460">Here Littleton is set before your eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106470">Because law's common, little shall suffice:</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106480">Yet is that little much to be regarded,</l>
          <l xml:id="A04959-e106490">Because an old coke hath it interlarded. </l>
        </lg>
        <trailer xml:id="A04959-e106500">Finis</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A04959"><item xml:id="A04959-time" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A04959-time</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04959-minerva" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A04959-minerva</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04959-winter" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A04959-winter</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04959-spring" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A04959-spring</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A04959-summer" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A04959-summer</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04959-autumn" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A04959-autumn</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04959-chorus" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A04959-chorus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A04959-all" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A04959-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

