<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A01502">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Antonius<date type="creation_date">1590</date></title>
        <author>Garnier, Robert</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nayoon Ahn</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A01502.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The tragedie of Antonie. Doone into English by the Countesse of Pembroke.</title>
            <author>Garnier, Robert, 1544-1590.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>56 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99841427</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 11623.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 108(b).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">6008</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01502</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The tragedie of Antonie. Doone into English by the Countesse of Pembroke.</title>
            <title type="alt">Marc Antoine. English</title>
            <title type="alt">Marc Antoine.</title>
            <title type="alt">Antonius.</title>
            <author>Garnier, Robert, 1544-1590.</author>
            <author>Pembroke, Mary Sidney Herbert, 1561-1621,</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[112] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>[By P. Short] for William Ponsonby,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1595.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>A translation of: Garnier, Robert. Marc Antoine.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Colophon reads "Printed at London by P.S. for William Ponsonby. 1595."; printer's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-G.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The last leaf is blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: Antonius.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>First published with Philippe de Mornay's "A discourse of life and death", 1592.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Variant: title page has "Done into englishe".</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Antonius, Marcus, -- 83?-30 B.C. -- Drama.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A01502-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A01502-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A01502-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A01502-e100040">The tragedy of Antony.</p>
        <p xml:id="A01502-e100050">Done into English by the countess of Pembroke</p>
        <p xml:id="A01502-e100060">Imprinted at London for William Ponsonby 1595.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="argument" xml:id="A01502-e100070">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>¶ The argument.</head>
        <p xml:id="A01502-e100080">After the overthrow of Brutus and Cassius, the liberty of Rome being now utterly oppressed, and the empire settled in the hands of Octavius Caesar and Marcus Antonius, (Who for knitting a straiter bond of amity between them, had taken to wife Octavia the sister of Caesar) Antonius undertook a journey agàinst the Parthians, with intent to regain on them the honour won by them from the Romans, at the discomfiture and slaughter of Crassus. But coming in his journey into Siria the places renewed in his remembrance<pb facs="3"/> the long intermitted love of Cleopatra Queen of Egypt: who before time had both in Cilicia and at Alexandria, entertained him with all the exquisite delights and sumptuous pleasures, which a great prince and voluptuous lover could to the uttermost desire. Whereupon omitting his enterprise, he made his return to Alexandria, again falling to his former loves, without any regard of his virtuous wife Octavia, by whom nevertheless he had excellent children. This occasion Octavius took of taking arms against him: and preparing a mighty fleet, encountered him at Actium, who also had assembled to that place a great number of galleys of his own, beside, 60. which Cleopatra brought with her from Egypt, but at the very beginning of the battle Cleopatra with all her galleys betook her to flight, which Antony seeing could not but follow: by his departure<pb facs="3"/> to Octavius the greatest victory which in any seabattell hath been hard off. Which he not negligent to pursue, follows them the next spring and besiegeth them with in Alexandria, where Antony finding all that he trusted to fail him, beginneth to grow jealous and to suspect Cleopatra. She thereupon enclosed herself with two of her women in a monument she had before caused to be built, thence sends him word she was dead: which he believing for truth, gave himself with his sword a deadly wound: but died not until a messenger came from Cleopatra to have him brought to her to the tomb. Which she not daring to open lest she should be made a prisoner to the Romans, and carried in Caesar's triumph, cast down a cord from an high window, by the which (Her women helping her) she trussed up Antonius half dead, and so got him into the monument. The stage supposed Alexandria: the chorus first Egyptians, and after Roman soldiers: the history to be read at large in Plutarch in the life of Antonius. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A01502-e100090">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <head>¶ The actors.</head>
        <list xml:id="A01502-e100100">
          <item xml:id="A01502-e100110">Antonius.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01502-e100120">Cleopatra.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01502-e100130">Eras and Charmion. Cleopatra's women</item>
          <item xml:id="A01502-e100140">Philostratus a philosopher. </item>
          <item xml:id="A01502-e100150">Lucilius.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01502-e100160">Diomed secretary to Cleopatra.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01502-e100170">Octavius Caesar.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01502-e100180">Agrippa.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01502-e100190">Euphron, teacher of Cleopatra's children. </item>
          <item xml:id="A01502-e100200">Children of Cleopatra,</item>
          <item xml:id="A01502-e100210">Dircetus the messenger. </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A01502-e100220">
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A01502-e100230">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <head>Antonius</head>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e100240" who="A01502-antoniud">
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100250">Since cruel heavens against me obstinate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100260">Since all mishaps of the round engine do</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100270">Conspire my harm: since men, since powers divine</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100280">Air, earth, and sea are all injurious:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100290">And that my Queen herself, in whom I lived,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100300">The idol of my heart, doth me pursue;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100310">It's meet I die. For her have I forgone</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100320">My country, Caesar unto war provoked</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100330">(For just revenge of sisters wrong my wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100340">Who moved my Queen (Ay me!) to jealousy)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100350">For love of her, in her allurements caught</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100360">Abandoned life, I honour have despised,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100370">Disdained my friends, and of the stately Rome</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100380">Despoiled the empire of her best attire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100390">Contemned that power that made me so much feared,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100400"><pb facs="5"/> a slave become unto her feeble face. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100410">O cruel, traitress, woman most unkind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100420">Thou dost, forsworn, my love and life betray:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100430">And givest me up to rageful enemy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100440">Which soon (O fool!) will plague thy perjury. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100450">Yielded Pelusium on this country's shore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100460">Yielded thou hast my ships and men of war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100470">That naught remains (So destitute am I)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100480">But these same arms which on my back I wear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100490">Thou shouldst have had them too, and me unarmed</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100500">Yielded to Caesar naked of defence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100510">Which while I bear let Caesar never think</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100520">Triumph of me shall his proud chariot grace</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100530">Not think with me his glory to adorn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100540">On me alive to use his victory. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100550">Thou only Cleopatra triumph haste,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100560">Thou only hast my freedom's servile made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100570">Thou only hast me vanquished: not by force</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100580">(For forced I cannot be) but by sweet baits</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100590">Of thy eyes graces, which did gain so fast</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100600"><pb facs="5"/> upon my liberty, that naught remained. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100610">None else henceforth, but thou my dearest Queen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100620">Shall glory in commanding Antony. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100630">Have Caesar fortune and the gods his friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100640">To him have Jove and fatal sisters given</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100650">The sceptre of the earth: he never shall</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100660">Subject my life to his obedience. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100670">But when that death, my glad refuge, shall have</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100680">Bounded the course of my unsteadfast life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100690">And frozen corpse under a marble cold</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100700">Within tomb's bosom widow of my soul:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100710">Then at his will let him it subject make:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100720">Then what he will let Caesar do with me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100730">Make me limb after limb be rent: make me</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100740">My burial take in sides of Thracian wolte. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100750">Poor Antony! alas what was the day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100760">The days of loss that gained thee thy love! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100770">Wretch Antony! since Maegaera pale</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100780">With snaky hairs enchained thy misery. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100790">The fire thee burned was never Cupid's fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100800"><pb facs="6"/> (For Cupid bears not such a mortal brand)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100810">It was some furies torch, Orestes torch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100820">Which sometimes burned his mother-murdering soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100830">(When wand'ring mad, rage boiling in his blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100840">He fled his fault which followed as he fled)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100850">Kindled within his bones by shadow pale</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100860">Of mother slain returned from Stygian lake. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100870">Antony, poor Antony! since that day</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100880">Thy old good hap did far from thee retire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100890">Thy virtue dead: thy glory made alive</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100900">So oft by martial deeds is gone in smoke:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100910">Since then the bays so well thy forehead knew</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100920">To Venus' myrtles yielded have their place:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100930">Trumpets to pipes: field tents to courtly bowers:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100940">Lances and pikes to dances and to feasts. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100950">Since then, o wretch! in stead of bloody wars</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100960">Thou shouldst have made upon the Parthian Kings</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100970">For Roman honour filled by Crassus' foil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100980">Thou threw'st thy cuirass off, and fearful helm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e100990">With coward courage unto Egypt's Queen</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101000"><pb facs="6"/> in haste to run, about her neck to hang</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101010">Languishing in her arms thy I doll made:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101020">In sum given up to Cleopatra's eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101030">Thou breakest at length from thence, as one encharmed</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101040">Breaks from th'enchanter that him strongly held. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101050">For thy first reason (Spoiling of their force</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101060">The poisoned cups of thy fair sorceress)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101070">Recured thy spirit: and then on every side</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101080">Thou madest again the earth with soldiers swarm</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101090">All Asia hid: Euphrates banks do tremble</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101100">To see at once so many Romans there</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101110">Breath horror, rage, and with a threatening eye</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101120">In mighty squadrons cross his swelling streams. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101130">Naught seen but horse, and fire sparkling arms:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101140">Naught heard but hideous noise of muttering troops,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101150">The Parth, the Mede, abandoning their goods</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101160">Hide them for fear in hills of Hyrcany,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101170">Redoubting thee. Then willing to besiege</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101180">The great Phraate head of Media,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101190">Thou campedst at her walls with vain assault,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101200"><pb facs="7"/> thy engines fit (Mishap!) not thither brought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101210">So long thou stayest, so long thou dost thee rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101220">So long thy love with such things nourished</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101230">Reframes, reforms itself and stealingly</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101240">Retakes his force and rebecomes more great. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101250">For of thy Queen the looks, the grace, the words,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101260">Sweetness, allurements, amorous delights,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101270">Entered again thy soul, and day and night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101280">In watch, in sleep, her image followed thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101290">Not dreaming but of her, repenting still</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101300">That thou for war hadst such a goddess left. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101310">Thou carest no more for Parth, nor Parthian bow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101320">Sallies, assaults, encounters, shocks, alarms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101330">For ditches, rampiers, wards, entrenched grounds:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101340">Thy only care is sight of Nilus' streams,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101350">Sight of that face whose guileful semblant doth</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101360">(Wand'ring in thee) infect thy tainted heart. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101370">Her absence thee besots: each hour, each hour</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101380">Of stay, to thee impatient seems an age. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101390">Enough of conquest, praise thou deemest enough,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101400"><pb facs="7"/> if soon enough the bristled fields thou see</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101410">Of fruitful Egypt, and the stranger flood</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101420">Thy Queen's fair eyes (Another Pharos) lights. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101430">Returned lo, dishonoured, despised,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101440">In wanton love a woman thee misleads</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101450">Sunk in foul sink: meanwhile respecting naught</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101460">Thy wife Octavia and her tender babes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101470">Of whom the long contempt against thee whets</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101480">The sword of Caesar now thy lord become. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101490">Lost thy great empire, all those goodly towns</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101500">Reverenced thy name as rebels now thee leave:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101510">Rise against thee, and to the ensigns flock</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101520">Of conquering Caesar, who enwalls thee round</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101530">Caged in thy hold, scarce master of thyself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101540">Late master of so many nations. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101550">Yet, yet, which is of grief extremest grief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101560">Which is yet of mischief highest mischief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101570">It's Cleopatra alas! alas, it's she,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101580">It's she augments the torment of thy pain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101590">Betrays thy love, thy life alas!) betrays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101600"><pb facs="8"/> Caesar to please, whose grace she seeks to gain:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101610">With thought her crown to save and fortune make</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101620">Only thy foe which common ought have been. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101630">If her I always loved, and the first flame</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101640">Of her heart-killing love shall burn me last:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101650">Justly complain I she disloyal is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101660">Nor constant is, even as I constant am,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101670">To comfort my mishap, despising me</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101680">No more, than when the heavens favoured me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101690">But ah! by nature women wavering are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101700">Each moment changing and rechanging minds. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101710">Unwise, who blind in them, thinks loyalty</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101720">Ever to find in beauty's company. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e101730" who="A01502-chorus">
          <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101740">The boiling tempest still</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101750">Makes not sea waters foam:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101760">Nor still the Northern blast</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101770">Disquiets quiet streams:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101780"><pb facs="8"/> nor who his chest to fill</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101790">Sails to the morning beams,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101800">On waves wind tosseth fast</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101810">Still keeps his ship from home. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101820">Nor Jove still down doth cast</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101830">Inflamed with bloody ire</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101840">On man, on tree, on hill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101850">His darts of thundering fire.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101860">Nor still the heat doth last</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101870">On face of parched plain.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101880">Nor wrinkled cold doth still</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101890">On frozen furrows reign. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101900">But still as long as we</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101910">In this low world remain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101920">Mishaps our daily mates</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101930">Our lives do entertain:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101940">And woes which bear no dates</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101950">Still perch upon our heads,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101960">None go but straight will be</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101970">Some greater in their steads. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101980"><pb facs="9"/>Nature made us not free</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e101990">When first she made us live:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102000">When we began to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102010">To be begun our woe:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102020">Which growing evermore</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102030">As dying life doth grow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102040">Do more and more us grieve,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102050">And tire us more and more. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102060">No stay in fading states,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102070">For more to height they reach,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102080">Their fellow miseries. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102090">The more to height do stretch. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102100">They cling even to the crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102110">And threatening furious wise</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102120">From tirannizing pates</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102130">Do often pull it down. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102140">In vain on waves untried</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102150">To shun them go we should</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102160">To Scythes and Massagetes</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102170">Who near the pole reside:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102180"><pb facs="9"/> in vain to boiling sands</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102190">Which Phoebus' battery beats,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102200">For with us still they would</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102210">Cut seas and compass lands. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102220">The darkness no more sure</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102230">To join with heavy night:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102240">The light which guilds the days</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102250">To follow Titan pure:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102260">No more the shadow light</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102270">The body to ensue:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102280">Then wretchedness always</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102290">Us wretches to pursue. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102300">O blessed who never breathed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102310">Or whom with pity moved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102320">Death from his cradle reaved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102330">And swaddled in his grave:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102340">And blessed also he</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102350">(As curse may blessing have)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102360">Who low and living free</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102370">No princes charge hath proved. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102380"><pb facs="10"/>By stealing sacred fire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102390">Prometheus then unwise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102400">Provoking gods to ire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102410">The heap of ills did stir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102420">And sickness pale and cold</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102430">Our end which onward spur,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102440">To plague our hands too bold</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102450">To filch the wealth of skies. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102460">In heaven's hate since then</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102470">Of ill with ill enchained</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102480">We raze of mortal men</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102490">Full fraught our breasts have born</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102500">And thousand thousand woes</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102510">Our heavenly souls now thorn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102520">Which free before from those</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102530">No! earthly passion pained. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102540">War and wars bitter cheer</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102550">Now long time with us stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102560">And fear of hated foe</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102570">Still still increaseth sore:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102580"><pb facs="10"/> our harms worse daily grow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102590">Less yesterday they were</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102600">Then now, and will be more</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102610">Tomorrow then today. </l>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A01502-e102620">
        <head>Act. 2.</head>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e102630" who="A01502-philostratus">
          <speaker>Philostratus.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102640">What horrible fury, what cruel rage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102650">Oh Egypt so extremely thee torments? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102660">Hast thou the gods so angered by thy fault? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102670">Hast thou against them some such crime conceived. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102680">That their engrained hand lift up in threats</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102690">They should desire in thy heart blood to bathe? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102700">And that their burning wrath which naught can quench</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102710">Should pitiless on us still lighten down? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102720">We are not hewn out of the monstrous mass</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102730">Of giants those, which heaven's wrack conspired:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102740">Ixion's race, false prater of his loves:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102750"><pb facs="11"/> nor yet of him who feigned lightnings found:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102760">Nor cruel Tantalus, nor bloody Atreus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102770">Whose cursed banquet for Thyestes plague</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102780">Made the beholding sun for horror turn</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102790">His back, and backward from his course return:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102800">And hastening his wing-footed horse's race</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102810">Plunge him in sea for shame to hide his face:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102820">While sullen night upon the wondering world</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102830">For midday's light her starry mantle cast. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102840">But what we be, whatever wickedness</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102850">By us is done, alas! with what more plagues,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102860">More eager torments could the gods declare</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102870">To heaven and earth that us they hateful hold? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102880">With soldiers, strangers, horrible in arms</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102890">Our land is hid, our people drowned in tears. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102900">But terror here and horror, naught is seen:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102910">And present death prising our life each hour. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102920">Hard at our ports and at our porches waits</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102930">Our conquering foe: hearts fail us, hopes are dead:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102940">Our Queen laments: and this great emperor</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102950"><pb facs="11"/> sometime (Would now they did) whom worlds did fear</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102960">Abandoned, betrayed, now minds no more</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102970">But from his evils by hastened death to pass. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102980">Come! you poor people tired with ceaseless plaints</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e102990">With tears and sighs make mournful sacrifice</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103000">On Isis' altars: not ourselves to save,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103010">But soften Caesar and him piteous make</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103020">To us, his prey: that so his lenity</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103030">May change our death into captivity. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103040">Strange are the evils the fates on us have brought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103050">Oh but alas! how far more strange the cause! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103060">Love, love (Alas, whoever would have thought?) </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103070">Hath lost this realm inflamed with his fire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103080">Love, playing love, which men say kindles not</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103090">But in soft hearts, hath ashes made our towns. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103100">And his sweet shafts, with whose shot none are killed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103110">Which ulcer not, with deaths our lands have filled,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103120">Such was the bloody, murdering, hellish love</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103130">Possessed thy heart fair false guest Priam's son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103140">Firing a brand which after made to burn</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103150"><pb facs="12"/> the Trojan towers by Grecians ruinate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103160">By this love, Priam, Hector, Troilus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103170">Memnon, Deiphobus, Glaucus, thousands more. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103180">Whom red Scamander's armour clogged streams</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103190">Rolled into seas, before their dates are dead. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103200">So plaguy he, so many tempests raiseth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103210">So murdering he, so many cities raiseth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103220">When insolent, blind, lawless, orderless,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103230">With made delights our sense he entertains. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103240">All knowing gods our wracks did us foretell</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103250">By signs in earth, by signs in starry spheres,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103260">Which should have moved us, had not destiny</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103270">With too strong hand warped our misery. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103280">The comets flaming through the scattered clouds</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103290">With fiery beams, most like unbroaded hairs:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103300">The fearful dragon whistling at the banks:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103310">And holy Apis ceaseless bellowing</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103320">(As never erst) and shedding endless tears:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103330">Blood raining down from heaven in unknown showers:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103340">Our god's dark faces over cast with woe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103350"><pb facs="12"/> and dead men's ghosts appearing in the night. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103360">Yea even this night while all the city stood</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103370">Oppressed with terror, horror, servile fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103380">Deep silence over all: the sounds were heard</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103390">Of divers songs, and divers instruments,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103400">Within the void of air: and howling noise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103410">Such as mad Bacchus' priests in Bacchus' feasts</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103420">On Nisa make: and (Seemed) the company,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103430">Our city lost, went to the enemy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103440">So we forsaken both of gods and men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103450">So are we in the mercy of our foes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103460">And we henceforth obedient must become</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103470">To laws of them who have us overcome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e103480" who="A01502-chorus">
          <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103490">Lament we our mishaps,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103500">Drown we with tears our woe:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103510">For lamentable haps</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103520">Lamented easy grow:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103530"><pb facs="13"/> and much less torment bring</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103540">Then when they first did spring. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103550">We want that woeful song,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103560">Wherewith woodmusic's Queen</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103570">Doth ease her woes, among,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103580">Fresh spring-time's bushes green,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103590">On pleasant branch alone</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103600">Renewing ancient moan. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103610">We want that moanful sound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103620">That prattling Progne makes</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103630">On fields of Thracian ground,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103640">Or streams of Thracian lakes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103650">To empt her breast of pain</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103660">For Itys by her slain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103670">Though halcyons do still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103680">Bewailing Ceyx's lot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103690">The seas with plainings fill</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103700">Which his dead limbs have got,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103710">Not ever other grave</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103720">Than tomb of waves to have:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103730"><pb facs="13"/> and though the bird in death</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103740">That most Meander loves:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103750">So sweetly sighs his breath</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103760">When death his fury proves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103770">As almost softs his heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103780">And almost blunts his dart:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103790">Yet all the plaints of those,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103800">Nor all their tearful larmes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103810">Cannot content our woes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103820">Nor serve to wail the harms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103830">In soul which we, poor we.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103840">To feel enforced be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103850">Nor they of Phoebus bred</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103860">In tears can do so well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103870">They for their brother shed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103880">Who into Padus fell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103890">Rash guide of chariot clear</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103900">Surveyor of the year. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103910">Nor she whom heavenly powers</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103920">To weeping rock did turn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103930"><pb facs="14"/> whose tears distil in showers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103940">And show she yet doth mourn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103950">Wherewith his top to skies</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103960">Mount Sipylus doth rise. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103970">Nor weeping drops which flow</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103980">From bark of wounded tree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e103990">That Myrrha's shame doth show</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104000">With ours compared may be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104010">To quench her loving fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104020">Who durst embrace her fire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104030">Nor all the howlings made</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104040">On Cybel's sacred hill</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104050">By eunuchs of her trade,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104060">Who Atys, Atys still</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104070">With doubled cries resound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104080">Which echo makes rebound. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104090">Our plaints no limits stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104100">Nor more than do our woes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104110">Both infinitely stray</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104120">And neither measure knows</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104130"><pb facs="14"/> in meam sure let them plain:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104140">Who measured griefs sustain. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A01502-e104150">Cleopatrra. Eras. Charmton. Diomede.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e104160" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cleopatra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104170">That I have thee betrayed, dear Antony,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104180">My life, my soul, my sun? I had such thought? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104190">That I have thee betrayed my lord, my King? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104200">That I would break my vowed faith to thee? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104210">I have thee? deceive thee? yield thee to the rage</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104220">Of mighty foe? I ever had that heart? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104230">Rather sharp lightning lighten on my head:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104240">Rather may I to deepest mischief fall:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104250">Rather the opened earth devour me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104260">Rather fierce tigers feed them on my flesh:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104270">Rather, o rather let our Nilus send,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104280">To swallow me quick, some weeping crocodile. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104290">And didst thou then suppose my royal heart</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104300"><pb facs="15"/> had hatched, thee to ensnare, a faithless love? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104310">And changing mind, as fortune changed cheer,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104320">I would weak thee, to win the stronger, loose? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104330">O wretch! O caitiff! O too cruel hap! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104340">And did not I sufficient loss sustain</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104350">Losing my realm, losing my liberty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104360">My tender offspring, and the joyful light</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104370">Of beamy sun, and yet, yet losing more</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104380">Thee Antony my care, if I lose not</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104390">What yet remained? thy love alas! thy love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104400">More dear than sceptre, children, freedom, light</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104410">So ready I to row in Charon's barge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104420">Shall lose the joy of dying in thy love:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104430">So the sole comfort of my misery</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104440">To have one tomb with thee is me bereft. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104450">So I in shady plains shall plain alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104460">Not (As I hoped) companion of thy moan,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104470">Oh height of grief! Eras why with continual cries</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104480">Your griefful harms do you exasperate? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104490">Torment yourself with murdering complaints;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104500"><pb facs="15"/> strain your weak breast so oft, so vehemently? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104510">Water with tears this fair alabaster? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104520">With sorrow's sting so many beauties wound? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104530">Come of so many Kings want you the heart</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104540">Bravely, stoutly, this tempest to resist? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e104550" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104560">My evils are wholly unsupportable,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104570">No human force can them withstand, but death. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e104580" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Eras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104590">To him that strives naught is impossible. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e104600" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104610">In striving lies no hope of my mishaps. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e104620" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Eras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104630">All things do yield to force of lovely face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e104640" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104650">My face too lovely caused my wretched case. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104660">My face hath so entrapped, so cast us down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104670">That for his conquest Caesar may it thank,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104680">Causing that Antony one army lost</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104690">The other wholly did to Caesar yield. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104700">For not enduring (So his amorous sprite</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104710">Was with my beauty fired) my shameful flight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104720">Soon as he saw from rank wherein he stood</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104730">In hottest fight, my galleys making sail:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104740">Forgetful of his charge (As if his soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104750"><pb facs="16"/> unto his lady's soul had been enchained)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104760">He left his men, who so courageously</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104770">Did leave their lives to gain him victory. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104780">And careless both of fame and army's loss</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104790">My oared galleys followed with his ship's</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104800">Companion of my flight, by this base part</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104810">Blasting his former flourishing renown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e104820" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Eras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104830">Are you therefore cause of his overthrow? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e104840" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104850">I am sole cause: I did it, only I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e104860" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Er.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104870">Fear of a woman troubled so his sprite? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e104880" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104890">Fire of his love was by my fear inflamed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e104900" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Er.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104910">And should he then to war have led a Queen? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e104920" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104930">Alas! this was not this offence, but mine. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104940">Antony (Ay me! who else so brave a chief!) </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104950">Would not I should have taken seas with him:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104960">But would have left me fearful woman far</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104970">From common hazard of the doubtful war. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104980">O that I had believed! now, now of Rome</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e104990">All the great empire at our beck should bend. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105000">All should obey, the vagabonding Scythes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105010"><pb facs="16"/> the feared Germans, back-shooting Parthians,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105020">Wand'ring Numidians, Britons far removed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105030">And tawny nations scorched with the sun. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105040">But I cared not: so was my soul possessed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105050">(To my great harm) with burning jealousy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105060">Fearing lest in my absence Antony</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105070">Should leaving me retake Octavia. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e105080" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Char.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105090">Such was the rigour of your destiny. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e105100" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105110">Such was my error and obstinacy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e105120" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105130">But since gods would not, could you do withal? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e105140" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105150">Always from god's good haps, not harms, do fall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e105160" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105170">And have they not all power on men's affairs? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e105180" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105190">They never bow so low, as worldly cares. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105200">But leave to mortal men to be disposed</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105210">Freely on earth whatever mortal is. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105220">If we therein sometimes some faults commit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105230">We may them not to their high majesties,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105240">But to ourselves impute; whose passions</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105250">Plunge us each day in all afflictions. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105260">Wherewith when we our souls do thorned feel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105270"><pb facs="17"/> flattering ourselves we say they destinies are:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105280">That gods would have it so, and that our care</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105290">Could not impeach but that it must be so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e105300" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Char.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105310">Things here below are in the heavens begot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105320">Before they be in this our world born:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105330">And never can our weakness turn awry</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105340">The stayless course of powerful destiny. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105350">Naught here force, reason, human providence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105360">Holy devotion, noble blood prevails:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105370">And Jove himself whose hand doth heavens rule,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105380">Who both to gods and men as King commands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105390">Who earth (Our firm support) with plenty stores,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105400">Mouses air and sea with twinkling of his eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105410">Who all can do, yet never can undo</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105420">What once hath been by their hard laws decreed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105430">When Trojan walls, great Neptune's workmanship. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105440">Environed were with Greeks, and fortunes wheel</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105450">Doubtful ten years now to the camp did turn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105460">And now again towards the town returned. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105470">How many times did force and fury swell</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105480"><pb facs="17"/> in Hector's veins egging him to the spoil</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105490">Of conquered foes, which at his blows did fly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105500">As fearful sheep at feared wolves approach:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105510">To save (In vain: for why? it would not be)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105520">Poor walls of Troy from adversary's rage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105530">Who died them in blood, and cast to ground</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105540">Heaped them with bloody burning carcases. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105550">No, madam, think, that if the ancient crown</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105560">Of your progenitors that Nilus ruled,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105570">Force take from you; the gods have willled it so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105580">To whom oft times princes are odious. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105590">They have to every thing an end ordained;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105600">All worldly greatness by them bounded is:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105610">Some sooner, later some, as they think best:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105620">None their decree is able to infringe. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105630">But, which is more, to us disastered men</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105640">Which subject are in all things to their will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105650">Their will is hid: nor while we live, we know</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105660">How, or how long we must in life remain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105670">Yet must we not for that feed on despair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105680"><pb facs="18"/> and make us wretched ere we wretched be:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105690">But always hope the best, even to the last,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105700">That from ourselves the mischief may not grow. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105710">Then, madam, help yourself, leave of in time</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105720">Antony's wrack, left it your wrack procure:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105730">Retire you from him, save from wrathful rage</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105740">Of angry Caesar both your realm and you. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105750">You see him lost, so as your amity</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105760">Unto his evils can yield no more relief. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105770">You see him ruined, so as your support</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105780">No more henceforth can him with comfort raise. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105790">Withdraw you from the storm: persist not still</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105800">To lose yourself: this royal diadem</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105810">Regain of Caesar. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e105820" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105830">Sooner shining light</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105840">Sall leave the day, and darkness leave the night:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105850">Sooner moist currents of tempestuous seas</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105860">Shall wave in heaven, and the nightly troops</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105870">Of stars shall shine within the foaming waves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105880">Than I thee, Antony, leave in deep distress. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105890">I am with thee, be it thy worthy soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105900"><pb facs="18"/> lodge in thy breast, or from that lodging part</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105910">Crossing the joyless lake to take her place</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105920">In place prepared for men demigods. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105930">Live, if thee please, if life be loathsome die:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105940">Dead and alive, Antony, thou shalt see</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105950">Thy Princess follow thee, follow, and lament,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105960">Thy wrack, no less her own then was thy weal. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e105970" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Char.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e105980">What helps his wrack this everlasting love?. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e105990" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106000">Help, or help not, such must, such ought I prove. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106010" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106020">Ill done to lose yourself, and to no end. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106030" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106040">How ill think you to follow such a friend? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106050" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106060">But this your love naught mitigates his praine. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106070" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106080">Without this love I should be inhuman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106090" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106100">Inhuman he, who his own death pursues. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106110" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106120">Not inhuman who miseries eschews. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106130" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106140">Live for your sons. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106150" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106160">Nay for their father die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106170" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106180">Hard-hearted mother! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106190" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106200">Wife kindhearted I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106210" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106220">Then will you them deprive of royal right? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106230" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106240">Do I deprive them? no, it's destiny's might. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106250" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106260">Do you not them deprive of heritage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106270"><pb facs="19"/> that give them up to adversary's hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106280">A man forsaken fearing to forsake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106290">Whom such huge numbers hold environed? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106300">T'abandon one 'gainst whom the frowning world</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106310">Banded with Caesar makes conspiring war. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106320" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106330">The less ought I to leave him lest of all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106340">A friend in most distress should most assist. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106350">If that when Antony great and glorious</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106360">His legions led to drink Euphrates streams,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106370">So many Kings in train redoubting him;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106380">In triumph raised as high as highest heaven;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106390">Lordlike disposing as him pleased best,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106400">The wealth of Greece, the wealth of Asia:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106410">In that fair fortune had I him exchanged</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106420">For Caesar, then, men would have counted me</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106430">Faithless, unconstant, light: but now the storm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106440">And blustering tempest driving on his face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106450">Ready to drown, alas! what would they say? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106460">What would himself in Plato's mansion say? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106470">If, I whom always more than life he loved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106480"><pb facs="19"/> if I, who am his heart, who was his hope,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106490">Leave him, forsake him (And perhaps in vain)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106500">Weakly to please who him hath overthrown? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106510">Not light, unconstant, faith less should I be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106520">But vile, forsworn, of treacherous cruelty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106530" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106540">Cruelty to shun you self-cruel are:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106550" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106560">Self-cruel him from cruelty to spare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106570" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106580">Our first affection to ourself is due. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106590" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106600">He is myself. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106610" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106620">Next it extends unto</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106630">Our children, friends, and to our country soil. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106640">And you for some respect of wifely love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106650">(Albe scarce wifely) lose your native land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106660">Your children, friends, and (Which is more) your life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106670">With so strong charms doth love bewitch our wits:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106680">So fast in us this fire once kindled flames. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106690">Yet if his harm by yours redress might have,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106700" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106710">With mine it may be closed in darksome grave. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106720" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106730">And that, as Alcest to herself unkind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106740">You might exempt him from the laws of death. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106750">But he is sure to die: and now his sword</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106760"><pb facs="20"/> already moisted is in his warm blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106770">Helpless for any succour you can bring</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106780">Against death's sting, which he must shortly feel. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106790">Then let your love be like the love of old</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106800">Which Carian Queen did nourish in her heart</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106810">Of her Mausolus: build for him a tomb</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106820">Whose stateliness a wonder new may make. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106830">Let him, let him have sumptuous funerals:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106840">Let grave thereon the horror of his fights:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106850">Let earth be buried with unburied heaps. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106860">Frame their Pharsaly, and discoloured streams</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106870">Of deep Enipeus: frame the grassy plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106880">Which lodged his camp at siege of Mutina. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106890">Make all his combats, and courageous acts:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106900">And yearly plays to his praise institute:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106910">Honour his memory: with doubled care</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106920">Breed and bring up the children of you both</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106930">In Caesar's grace: who as a noble prince</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106940">Will leave them lords of this most glorious realm. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e106950" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106960">What shame were that? ah gods! what infamy? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106970"><pb facs="20"/>With Antony in his good haps to share,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106980">And overlive him dead: deeming enough</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e106990">To shed some tears upon a widow tomb? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107000">The after-livers justly might report</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107010">That I him only for his empire loved</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107020">And high estate: and that in hard estate</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107030">I for another did him lewdly leave? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107040">Like to those birds wafted with wand'ring wings. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107050">From foreign lands in spring-time here arrive:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107060">And live with us so long as summer's heat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107070">And their food lasts, then seek another soil. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107080">And as we see with ceaseless fluttering</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107090">Flocking of silly flies a brownish cloud</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107100">To vintaged wine yet working in the ton:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107110">Not parting thence while they sweet liquor taste:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107120">After, as smoke, all vanish in the air,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107130">And of the swarm not one so much appear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107140" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Eras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107150">By this sharp death what profit can you win? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107160" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107170">I neither gain nor profit seek therein. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107180" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Er.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107190">What praise shall you of after-ages get? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107200" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <pb facs="21"/>
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107210">Nor praise, nor glory in my cares are set. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107220" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Eras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107230">What other end ought you respect, than this? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107240" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107250">My only end my only duty is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107260" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Eras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107270">Your duty must upon some good be founded? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107280" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107290">On virtue it, the only good, is grounded. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107300" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Er.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107310">What is that virtue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107320" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107330">That which us beseems. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107340" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Er.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107350">Outrage ourselves? who that beseeming deems? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107360" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107370">Finish I will my sorrows dying thus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107380" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Er.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107390">Minish you will your glories doing thus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107400" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107410">Good friends I pray you seek not to revoke</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107420">My fixed intent of following Antony. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107430">I will die. I will die: must not his life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107440">His life and death by mine be followed? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107450">Meanwhile , dear sisters, live: and while you live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107460">Do often honour to our loved tombs. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107470">Straw them with flowers: and sometimes happily</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107480">The tender thought of Antony your lord</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107490">And me poor soul to tears shall you invite,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107500">And our true loves to doleful voice commend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107510" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107520">And think you madam, we from you will part? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107530"><pb facs="21"/>Think you alone to feel deaths ugly dart? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107540">Think you to leave us? and that the same sun</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107550">Shall see at once you dead, and us alive? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107560">We'll die with you: and Clotho pitiless</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107570">Shall us with you in hellish boat embark:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107580" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107590">Ah live, I pray you: this disastered woe</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107600">Which racks my heart, alone to me belongs:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107610">My lot longs not to you: servants to be</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107620">No shame, no harm to you, as is to me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107630">Live sisters, live, and sing his suspect</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107640">Hath causeless me in sea of sorrows drowned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107650">And that I cannot live, if so I would,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107660">Nor yet would leave this life, if so I could,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107670">Without his love: procure me, Diomed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107680">That 'gainst poor me he be no more incensed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107690">Wrest out of his conceit that harmful doubt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107700">That since his wrack he hath of me conceived</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107710">Though wrong conceived: witness you reverent gods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107720">Barking Anubis, Apis bellowing. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107730">Tell him, my soul burning, impatient,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107740"><pb facs="22"/> forlorn with love of him, for certain seal</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107750">Of her true loyalty my corpse hath left,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107760">T'increase of dead the number numberless,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107770">Go then, and if as yet he me bewail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107780">If yet for me his heart one sigh fourth breathe</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107790">Blessed shall I be: and far with more content</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107800">Depart this world, where so I me torment. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107810">Mean season us let this sad tomb enclose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107820">Attending here till death conclude our woes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107830" who="A01502-diomede">
          <speaker>Diom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107840">I will obey your will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107850" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107860">So the desert</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107870">The gods repay of thy true faithful heart. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e107880" who="A01502-diomede">
          <speaker>Diomed.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107890">And is't not pity, gods, ah gods of heaven</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107900">To see from love such hateful fruits to spring? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107910">And is't not pity that this firebrand so</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107920">Lays waste the trophies of Phillippi fields? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107930">Where are those sweet allurements, those sweet looks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107940">Which gods themselves right heart sick would have made</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107950"><pb facs="22"/> what doth that beauty, rarest gift of heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107960">Wonder of earth? Alas! what do those eyes? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107970">And that sweet voice all Asia understood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107980">And sunburnt Afrique wide in deserts spread? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e107990">Is their force dead? have they no further power? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108000">Can not by them Octavius be surprised? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108010">Alas! if Jove in midst of all his ire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108020">With thunderbolt in hand some land to plague,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108030">Had cast his eyes on my Queen, out of hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108040">His plaguing bolt had fallen out of his hand:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108050">Fire of his wrath into vain smoke should turn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108060">And other fire within his breast should burn. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108070">Naught lives so fair. Nature by such a work</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108080">Herself, should seem, in workmanship hath passed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108090">She is all heavenly: never any man</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108100">But seeing her was ravished with her sight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108110">The alablaster covering of her face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108120">The coral colour her two lips engrains,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108130">Her beamy eyes, two suns of this our world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108140">Of her fair hair the fine and flaming gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108150"><pb facs="23"/> her brave straight stature, and her winning parts</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108160">Are nothing else but fierce, fetters, darts. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108170">Yet this is nothing th'enchanting skills</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108180">Of her celestial spirit, her training speech,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108190">Her grace, her majesty, and forcing voice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108200">Whither she it with finger's speech consort,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108210">Or hearing sceptred Kings ambassadors</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108220">Answer to each in his own language make. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108230">Yet now at need it aids her not at all</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108240">With all these beauties, so her sorrow stings. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108250">Darkened with woe her only study is</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108260">To weep, to sigh, to seek for loneliness. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108270">Careless of all, her hair disordered hangs:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108280">Her charming eyes whence murdering looks did fly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108290">Now rivers grown ', whose wellspring anguish is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108300">Do trickling wash the marble of her face. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108310">Her fair discovered breast with sobbing swollen</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108320">Self cruel she still martyreth with blows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108330">Alas! It's our ill hap, for if her tears</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108340">She would convert into her loving charms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108350"><pb facs="23"/> to make a conquest of the conqueror,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108360">(As well she might, would she her force employ)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108370">She should us safety from these ills procure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108380">Her crown to her, and to her race assure. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108390">Unhappy he, in whom self-succour lies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108400">Yet self-forsaken wanting succour dies. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e108410" who="A01502-chorus">
          <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108420">O sweet fertile land, wherein</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108430">Phoebus did with breath inspire</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108440">Man who men did first begin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108450">Formed first of Nilus' mire.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108460">Whence of arts the eldest kinds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108470">Earth's most heavenly ornament,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108480">Were as from their fountain sent</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108490">To enlight our misty minds.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108500">Whose gross sprite from endless time</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108510">As in darkened prison penned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108520">Never did to knowledge climb. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108530"><pb facs="24"/>Where the Nile, our father good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108540">Fatherlike doth never miss</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108550">Yearly us to bring such food,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108560">As to life required is:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108570">Visiting each year this plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108580">And with fat slime covering it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108590">Which his seven mouths do spit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108600">As the season comes again.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108610">Making thereby greatest grow</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108620">Busy reapers joyful pain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108630">When his floods do highest flow. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108640">Wand'ring prince of rivers thou,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108650">Honour of the Aethiops land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108660">Of a lord and master now</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108670">Thou a slave in awe must stand.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108680">Now of Tiber which is spread</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108690">Less in force, and less in fame</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108700">Reverence thou must the name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108710">Whom all other river's dread,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108720">For his children swollen in pride,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108730"><pb facs="24"/> who by conquest seek to tread</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108740">Round this earth on every side. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108750">Now thou must begin to send</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108760">Tribute of thy watery store,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108770">As sea paths thy steps shall bend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108780">Yearly presents more and more.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108790">Thy fat scum, our fruitful corn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108800">Peeled from hence with thievish hands</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108810">All unclothed shall leave our lands</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108820">Into foreign country born.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108830">Which puffed up with such a prey</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108840">Shall thereby the praise adorn</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108850">Of that sceptre Rome doth sway. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108860">Naught thee helps thy horns to hide</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108870">Far from hence in unknown grounds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108880">That thy waters wander wide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108890">Yearly breaking banks, and bounds.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108900">And that thy sky-coloured brooks</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108910">Through a hundred people's pass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108920">Drawing plots for trees and grass</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108930"><pb facs="25"/> with a thousand turns and crooks.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108940">Whom all weary of their way</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108950">Thy throats which in wideness pass</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108960">Power into their mother sea. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108970">Naught so happy hapless life</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108980">In this world as freedom finds:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e108990">Naught wherein more sparks are rise</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109000">To inflame courageous minds.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109010">But if force must us enforce</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109020">Needs a yoke to undergo,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109030">Under foreign yoke to go</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109040">Still it proves a bondage worse.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109050">And doubled subjection</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109060">See we shall, and feel, and know</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109070">Subject to a stranger grown. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109080">From hence forward for a King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109090">Whose first being from this place</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109100">Should his breast by nature bring</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109110">Care of country to embrace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109120">We at surly face must quake</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109130"><pb facs="25"/> of some Roman madly bent:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109140">Who our terror to augment.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109150">His proconsuls axe will shake.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109160">Driving with our Kings from hence</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109170">Our established government,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109180">Justice sword, and law's defence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109190">Nothing worldly of such might</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109200">But more mighty destiny,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109210">By swift times unbridled flight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109220">Makes in end his end to see.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109230">Every thing time overthrows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109240">Naught to end doth steadfast stay.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109250">His great scythe mows all away</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109260">As the stalk of tender rose.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109270">Only immortality</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109280">Of the heavens doth it oppose</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109290">'Gainst his powerful deity. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109300">One day there will come a day</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109310">Which shall quail they fortune's flower</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109320">And thee ruined low shall lay</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109330"><pb facs="26"/> in some barbarous prince's power.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109340">When the pity-wanting fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109350">Shall, oh Rome, thy beauties burn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109360">And to humble ashes turn</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109370">Thy proud wealth and rich attire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109380">Those guilt roofs which turretwise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109390">Justly making envy mourn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109400">Threaten now to pierce skies. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109410">As thy forces fill each land</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109420">Harvests making here and there,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109430">Reaping all with ravening hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109440">They find growing anywhere :</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109450">From each land so to thy fall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109460">Multitudes repair shall make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109470">From the common spoil to take</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109480">What to each man's share may fall.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109490">Fingered all thou shalt behold:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109500">No jot left for tokens sake</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109510">That thou wert so great of old. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109520">Like unto the ancient Troy</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109530"><pb facs="26"/> whence derived thy founders be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109540">Conquering foe shall thee enjoy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109550">And a burning pray in thee.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109560">For within this turning ball</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109570">This we see, and see each day:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109580">All things fixed ends do stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109590">Ends to first beginnings fall. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109600">And that naught, how strong or strange</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109610">Changeless doth endure alway,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109620">But endureth fatal change. </l>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A01502-e109630">
        <stage xml:id="A01502-e109640">M. Antonius. Lucilius.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e109650" who="A01502-antony">
          <speaker>M. Ant.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109660">Lucil. sole comfort of my bitter case,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109670">The only trust, the only hope I have,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109680">In last despair: ah is not this the day</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109690">That death should me of life and love bereave? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109700">What wait I for that have no refuge left,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109710"><pb facs="27"/> but am sole remnant of my fortune left? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109720">All leave me, fly me: none, no not of them</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109730">Which of my greatness greatest good received,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109740">Stands with my fall: they seem as now ashamed</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109750">That heretofore they did me ought regard:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109760">They draw them back, showing they followed me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109770">Not to partake my harms, but cozen me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e109780" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109790">In this our world nothing is steadfast found,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109800">In vain he hopes, who here his hopes doth ground. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e109810" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109820">Yet naught afflicts me, nothing kills me so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109830">As that I so my Cleopatra see</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109840">Practice with Caesar, and to him transport</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109850">My flame, her love, more dear than life to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e109860" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109870">Believe it not: too high a heart she bears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109880">Too princely thoughts. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e109890" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109900">Too wise a head she wear</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109910">Too much inflamed with greatness, evermore</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109920">Gaping for our great empire's government. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e109930" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109940">So long time you her constant love have tried. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e109950" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109960">But still with me good fortune did abide. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e109970" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e109980">Her changed love what token makes you know? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e109990" who="A01502-antonius">
          <pb facs="27"/>
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110000">Pelusium lost, and Actium overthrow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110010">Both by her fraud: my well appointed fleet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110020">And trusty soldiers in my quarrel armed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110030">Whom she, false she, in stead of my defence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110040">Came to persuade, to yield them to my foe:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110050">Such honour there done, such welcome given,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110060">Their long close talks I neither knew, nor would,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110070">And treacherous wrong Alexas hath me done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110080">Witness too well her perjured love to me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110090">But you oh gods (If any faith regard)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110100">With sharp revenge her faithless change reward. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e110110" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110120">The dole she made upon our overthrow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110130">Her realm given up for refuge to our men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110140">Her poor attire when she devoutly kept</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110150">The solemn day of her nativity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110160">Again the cost and prodigal expense</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110170">Showed when she did your birth day celebrate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110180">Do plain enough her heart unfeigned prove,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110190">Equally touched, you loving, as you love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e110200" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110210">Well; be her love to me or false, or true,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110220"><pb facs="28"/> once in my soul a cureless wound I feel. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110230">I Jove: nay burn in fire of her love:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110240">Each day, each night her image haunts my mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110250">Herself my dreams: and still I tired am,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110260">And still I am with burning pincers nipped. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110270">Extreme my harm: yet sweeter to my sense</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110280">Then boiling torch of jealous torments fire:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110290">This grief, nay rage, in me such stir doth keep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110300">And thorns me still, both when I wake and sleep. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110310">Take Caesar conquest, take my goods, take he</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110320">Th'honour to be lord of the earth alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110330">My sons, my life bent headlong to mishaps:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110340">No force, so not my Cleopatra take. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110350">So foolish I, I cannot her forget,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110360">Though better were I banished her my thought. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110370">Like to the sick whose throat the fevers's fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110380">Hath vehemently with thirsty drought inflamed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110390">Drinks still, albe the drink he still desires</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110400">Be nothing else but fuel to his flame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110410">He cannot rule himself: his health's respect</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110420"><pb facs="28"/> yieldeth to his distempered stomach's heat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e110430" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110440">Leave of this love, that thus renews your woe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e110450" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110460">I do my best, but ah! can not do so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e110470" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110480">Think how you have so brave a captain bene,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110490">And now are by this vain affection fallen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e110500" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110510">The ceaseless thought of my felicity</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110520">Plunges me more in this adversity. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110530">For nothing so a man in ill torments,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110540">As who to him his good state represents. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110550">This makes my rack, my anguish, and my woe</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110560">Equal unto the hellish passions grow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110570">When I to mind my happy puissance call</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110580">Which erst I had by warlike conquest won,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110590">And that good fortune which me never left,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110600">Which hard disaster now hath me bereft. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110610">With terror tremble all the world I made</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110620">At my sole word, as rushes in the streams</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110630">At waters will: I conquered Italy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110640">I conquered Rome, that nations so redoubt. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110650">I bore ( meanwhile besieging Mutina)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110660"><pb facs="29"/> two consuls armies for my ruin brought. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110670">Bathed in their blood, by their deaths witnessing</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110680">My force and skill in matters martial. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110690">To wreak thy uncle, unkind Caesar, I</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110700">With blood of enemies the banks embrued</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110710">Of stained Enipeus, hindering his course</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110720">Stopped with heaps of piled carcases:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110730">When Cassius and Brutus ill betide</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110740">Marched against us, by us twice put to flight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110750">But by my sole conduct: for all the time</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110760">Caesar heart-sick with fear and fever lay. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110770">Who knows it not? and how by every one</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110780">Fame of the fact was given to me alone. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110790">There sprang the love, the never changing love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110800">Wherein my heart hath since to yours been bound:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110810">There was it, my Lucill, you Brntus saved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110820">And for your Brutus Antony, you found. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110830">Better my hap in gaining such a friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110840">Then in subduing such an enemy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110850">Now former virtue dead doth me forsake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110860"><pb facs="29"/> fortune engulfs me in extreme distress:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110870">She turns from me her smiling countenance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110880">Casting on me mishap upon mishap,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110890">Left and betrayed of thousand thousand friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110900">Once of my suit, but you Lucill are left</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110910">Remaining to me steadfast as a tower</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110920">In holy love, in spite of fortunes blasts. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110930">But if of any God my voice be heard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110940">And be not vainly scattered in the heavens,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110950">Such goodness shall not gloryless be lost. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110960">But coming ages still there of shall boast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e110970" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110980">Men in their friendship ever should be one,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e110990">And never ought with fickle fortune shake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111000">Which still removes, nor will, nor knows the way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111010">Her rolling bowl in one sure state to stay. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111020">Wherefore we ought as borrowed things receive</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111030">The goods light she lends us to pay again:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111040">Not hold them sure, nor on them build our hopes</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111050">As on such goods as cannot fail, and fall:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111060">But think again, nothing is durable,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111070"><pb facs="30"/> virtue except, our never failing host:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111080">So bearing sail when favouring winds do blow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111090">As frowning tempests may us least dismay</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111100">When they on us do fall: not overglad</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111110">With good estate, nor over-grieved with bad. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111120">Resist mishap. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e111130" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111140">Alas! it is too strong. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111150">Mishaps oft times are by some comfort born:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111160">But these, ay me! whose weights oppress my heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111170">Too heavy lie, no hope can them relieve. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111180">There rests no more, but that with cruel blade</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111190">For lingering death a hasty way be made. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e111200" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111210">Caesar, as heir unto his father's state. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111220">So will his father's goodness imitate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111230">To you ward: whom he knows allied in blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111240">Allied in marriage, ruling equally</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111250">Th' empire with him, and with him making war</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111260">Have purged the earth of Caesar's murderers. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111270">You into portions parted have the world</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111280">Even like coheirs their heritage's part:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111290">And now with one accord so many years</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111300"><pb facs="30"/> in quiet peace both have your charges ruled. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e111310" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111320">Blood and alliance nothing do prevail</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111330">To cool the thirst of hot ambitious breasts:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111340">The son his father hardly can endure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111350">Brother his brother, in one common realm. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111360">So fervent this desire to command:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111370">Such jealousy it kindleth in our hearts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111380">Sooner will men permit another should</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111390">Love her they love then wear the crown they wear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111400">All laws it breaks, turns all things upside down:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111410">Amity, kindred, naught so holy is</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111420">But it defiles. A monarchy to gain</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111430">None cares which way, so he may it obtain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e111440" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111450">Suppose he monarch be and that this world</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111460">No more acknowledge sundry emperors,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111470">That Rome him only fear, and that he join</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111480">The East with West, and both at once do rule:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111490">Why should he not permit you peaceably</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111500">Discharged of charge and empire's dignity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111510">Private to live reading philosophy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111520"><pb facs="31"/> in learned Greece, Spain, Asia, any land? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e111530" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111540">Never will he his empire think assured</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111550">While in this world mark Antony shall live. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111560">Sleepless suspicion, pale distrust, cold fear</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111570">Always to prince's company do bear</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111580">Bred of reports: reports which night and day</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111590">Perpetual guests from court go not away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e111600" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111610">He hath not slain your brother Lucius,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111620">Nor shortened hath the age of Lepidus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111630">Albeit both into his hands were fallen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111640">And he with wrath against them both inflamed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111650">Yet one, as lord in quiet rest doth bear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111660">The greatest sway in great Iberia:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111670">The other with his gentle prince retains</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111680">Of highest priest the sacred dignity. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e111690" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111700">He fears not them, their feeble force he knows. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e111710" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111720">He fears no vanquished overfilled with woes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e111730" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111740">Fortune may change again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e111750" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>L.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111760">A downcast foe</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111770">Can hardly rise, which once is brought so low. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e111780" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111790">All that I can is done: for last assay</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111800"><pb facs="31"/> (When all means failed) I to entreaty fell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111810">(Ah coward creature!) whence again repulsed</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111820">Of combat I unto him proffer made:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111830">Though he in prime, and I by feeble age</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111840">Mightily weakened both in force and skill. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111850">Yet could not he his coward heart advance</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111860">Basely afraid to try so praiseful chance. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111870">This makes me plain, makes me myself accuse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111880">Fortune in this her spiteful force doth use</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111890">'Gainst my grey hairs: in this unhappy I</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111900">Repine at heavens in my haps pitiless. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111910">A man, a woman both in might and mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111920">In Mars his school who never lesson learned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111930">Should me repulse, chase, overthow, destroy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111940">Me of such fame, bring to so low an ebb? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111950">Alcides blood, who from my infancy</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111960">With happy prowess crowned have my praise</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111970">Witness thou Gaul unused to servile yoke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111980">Thou valiant Spain, you fields of Thessaly</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e111990">With millions of mourning cries bewailed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112000"><pb facs="32"/> twice watered now with blood of Italy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e112010" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112020">Witness may Afrique, and of conquered world</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112030">All four quarters witnesses may be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112040">For in what part of earth inhabited,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112050">Hungry of praise have you not ensigns spread? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e112060" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112070">Thou knowest rich Egypt (Egypt of my deeds</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112080">Fair and foul subject) Egypt ah! thou knowest</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112090">How I behaved me fighting for thy King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112100">When I regained him his rebellious realm:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112110">Against his foes in battle showing force,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112120">And after fight in victory remorse. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112130">Yet if to bring my glory to the ground,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112140">Fortune had made me overthrown by one</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112150">Of greater force, of better skill than I:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112160">One of those captains feared so of old,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112170">Camill, Marcellus, worthy Scipio,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112180">This late great Caesar, honour of our state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112190">Or that great Pompey aged grown in arms;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112200">That after harvest of a world of men</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112210">Made in a hundred battles, fights, assaults,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112220"><pb facs="32"/> my body thorough pierced with push of pike</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112230">Had vomited my blood, in blood my life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112240">In midst of millions fellows in my fall:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112250">The less her wrong, the less should my woe:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112260">Nor she should pain, nor I complain me so. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112270">No, no, whereas I should have died in arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112280">And vanquished oft new armies should have armed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112290">New battles given, and rather lost with me</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112300">All this whole world submitted unto me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112310">A man who never saw enlaced pikes</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112320">With bristled points against his stomach bent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112330">Who fears the field, and hides him cowardly</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112340">Dead at the very noise the soldiers make. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112350">His virtue, fraud, deceit, malicious guile,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112360">His arms the arts that false Ulysses used,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112370">Known at Modena, where the consuls both</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112380">Death-wounded were, and wounded by his men</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112390">To get their army, war with it to make</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112400">Against his faith, against his country soil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112410">Of Lepidus, which to his succours came,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112420"><pb facs="33"/> to honour whom he was by duty bound,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112430">The empire he usurped: corrupting first</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112440">With baits and bribes the most part of his men. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112450">Yet me hath overcome, and made his prey,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112460">And state of Rome, with me hath overcome. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112470">Strange! one disordered act at Actium</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112480">The earth subdued, my glory hath obscured. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112490">For since, as one whom heaven's wrath attaints</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112500">With fury caught, and more than furious</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112510">Vexed with my evils, I never more had care</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112520">My armies lost, or lost name to repair:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112530">I did no more resist. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e112540" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112550">All wars affairs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112560">But battles most, daily have their success</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112570">Now good, now ill: and though that fortune have</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112580">Great force and power in every worldly thing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112590">Rule all, do all, have all things fast enchained</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112600">Unto the circle of her turning wheel:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112610">Yet seems it more than any practice else</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112620">She doth frequent Bellona's bloody trade:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112630">And that her favour, wavering as the wind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112640"><pb facs="33"/> her greatest power therein doth oftenest show. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112650">Whence grows, we daily see, who in their youth</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112660">Get honour there, do lose it in their age,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112670">Vanquished by some less warlike than themselves:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112680">Whom yet a meaner man shall overthrow. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112690">Her use is not to lend us still her hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112700">But sometimes headlong back a gain to throw,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112710">When by her favour she hath us extolled</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112720">Unto the top of highest happiness. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e112730" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112740">Well ought I curse within my grieved soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112750">Lamenting day and night, this senseless love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112760">Whereby my fair enticing foe entrapped</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112770">My heedless reason, could no more escape. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112780">It was not fortunes ever changing face:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112790">It was not destiny's changeless violence</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112800">Forged my mishap. Alas! who doth not know</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112810">They make, nor mar, nor any thing can do. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112820">Fortune, which men so fear, adore, detest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112830">Is but a chance whose cause unknown doth rest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112840">Although oft times the cause is well perceived,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112850"><pb facs="34"/> but not th'effect the same that was conceived. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112860">Pleasure, naught else, the plague of this our life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112870">Our life which still a thousand plagues pursue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112880">Alone hath me this strange disaster spun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112890">Fallen from a soldier to a chamberer,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112900">Careless of virtue, careless of all praise. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112910">Nay, as the fatted swine in filthy mire</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112920">With glutted heart I wallowed in delights,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112930">All thoughts of honour trodden under foot. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112940">So I me lost: for finding this sweet cup</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112950">Pleasing my taste, unwise I drunk my fill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112960">And through the sweetness of that poison's power</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112970">By steps I drave my former wits astray. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112980">I made my friends, offended me forsake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e112990">I holp my foes against myself to rise. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113000">I robbed my subjects, and for followers</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113010">I saw myself be set with flatterers. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113020">Mine idle arms fair wrought with spider's work,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113030">My scattered men without their ensigns strayed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113040">Caesar meanwhile who never would have dared</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113050"><pb facs="34"/> to cope with me, me suddenly despised,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113060">Took heart to fight, and hoped for victory</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113070">On one so gone, who glory had forgone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e113080" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113090">Enchanting pleasure Venus sweet delights</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113100">Weaken our bodies, overcloud our sprights,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113110">Trouble our reason, from our hearts out chase</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113120">All holy virtue's lodging in their place:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113130">Like as the cunning fisher takes the fish</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113140">By traitor bait whereby the hooks is hid:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113150">So pleasure serves to vice in steed of food</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113160">To bait our souls thereon too liquorish. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113170">This poison deadly is alike to all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113180">But on great Kings doth greatest outrage work,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113190">Taking the royal sceptres from their hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113200">Thence forward to be by some stranger born:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113210">While that their people charged with heavy loads</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113220">Their flatterers pill, and suck their marry dry,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113230">Not ruled but left to great men as a prey,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113240">While this fond prince himself in pleasures drowns</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113250">Who hears naught, sees naught, doth naught of a King</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113260"><pb facs="35"/> seeming himself against himself conspire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113270">Then equal justice wandreth banished,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113280">And in her seat sits greedy tyranny. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113290">Confused disorder troubleth all estates,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113300">Crimes without fear and outrages are done. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113310">Then mutinous rebellion shows her face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113320">Now hid with this, and now with that pretence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113330">Provoking enemies, which on each side</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113340">Enter at ease, and make them lords of all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113350">The hurtful works of pleasure here behold,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e113360" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113370">The wolf is not so hurtful to the fold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113380">Frost to the grapes, to ripened fruits the rain:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113390">As pleasure is to princes full of pain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e113400" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113410">There needs no proof, but by th' Assyrian King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113420">On whom that monster woeful wrack did bring. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e113430" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113440">There needs no proof, but by unhappy I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113450">Who lost my empire, honour, life thereby,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e113460" who="A01502-lucilius">
          <speaker>Lu</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113470">Yet hath this ill so much the greater force,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113480">As scarcely any do against it stand:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113490">No not the demigods the old world knew,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113500"><pb facs="35"/> who all subdued, could pleasure's power subdue. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113510">Great Hercules, Hercules once that was</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113520">Wonder of earth and heaven, matchless in might,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113530">Who Anteus, Lycus, Geryon overcame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113540">Who drew from hell the triple-headed dog,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113550">Who Hydra killed, vanquished Achelous,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113560">Who heaven's weight on his strong shoulders bore;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113570">Did he not under pleasure's burden bow? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113580">Did he not captive to this passion yield,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113590">When by his captive, so he was inflamed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113600">As now yourself in Cleopatra burn? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113610">Slept in her lap, her bosom kissed and kissed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113620">With base unseemly service bought her love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113630">Spinning at distaff, and with sinewy hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113640">Winding on spindle's thread, in maid's attire? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113650">His conquering club at rest on wall did hang:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113660">His bow unstringed he bent not as he used:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113670">Upon his shafts the weaving spider's spun:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113680">And his hard cloak the fretting moths did pierce. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113690">The monsters free and fearless all the time</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113700"><pb facs="36"/> throughout the world the people did torment. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113710">And more and more increasing day by day</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113720">Scorned his weak heart become a mistress play. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e113730" who="A01502-antonius">
          <speaker>An.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113740">In only this like Hercules am I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113750">In this I prove me of his lineage right:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113760">In this himself, his deeds I show in this:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113770">In this, naught else, my ancestor he is. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113780">But go we: die I must, and with brave end</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113790">Conclusion make of all foregoing harms:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113800">Die, die I must: I must a noble death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113810">A glorious death unto my succour call:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113820">I must deface the shame of time abused,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113830">I must adorn the wanton loves I used,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113840">With some courageous act: that my last day</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113850">By mine own hand my spots may wash away. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113860">Come dear Lucill: alas! why weep you thus! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113870">This mortal lot is common to us all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113880">We must all die, each doth in homage owe</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113890">Unto that God that shared the realms below</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113900">Ah sigh no more: alas! appease your woes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113910"><pb facs="36"/> for by your grief my grief more eager grows,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e113920" who="A01502-chorus">
          <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113930">Alas, with what tormenting fire</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113940">Us martyreth this blind desire</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113950">To stay our life from flying! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113960">How ceaselessly our minds doth rack,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113970">How heavy lies upon our back</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113980">This dastard fear of dying! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e113990">Death rather healthful succour gives,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114000">Death rather all mishaps relieves</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114010">That life upon us throweth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114020">And ever to us death unclose</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114030">The door whereby from cureless woes</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114040">Our weary soul out goeth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114050">What goddess else more mild than she</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114060">To bury all our pain can be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114070">What remedy more pleasing? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114080">Our pained hearts when dolour stings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114090"><pb facs="37"/> and nothing rest, or respite brings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114100">What help have we more easing? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114110">Hope which to us doth comfort give,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114120">And doth our fainting hearts revive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114130">Hath not such force in anguish:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114140">For promising a vain relief</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114150">She oft us fails in midst of grief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114160">And helpless let's us languish. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114170">But death who call on her at need</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114180">Doth never with vain semblant feed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114190">But when them sorrow paineth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114200">So rids their souls of all distress</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114210">Whose heavy weight did them oppress,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114220">That not one grief remaineth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114230">Who fearless and with courage bold</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114240">Can Acheron's black face behold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114250">Which muddy water beareth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114260">And crossing over in the way</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114270">Is not amazed at perruque grey</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114280">Old rusty Charon weareth? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114290"><pb facs="37"/>Who void of dread can look upon</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114300">The dreadful shades that Rome alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114310">On banks where sound no voices:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114320">Whom with her firebrands and her snakes</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114330">No whit afraid Allecto makes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114340">Nor triple-barking noises:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114350">Who freely can himself dispose</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114360">Of that last hour which all must close,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114370">And leave this life at pleasure:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114380">This noble freedom more esteems,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114390">And in his heart more precious deems,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114400">Then crown and kingly treasure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114410">The waves which Boreas blasts turmoil</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114420">And cause with foaming fury boil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114430">Make not his heart to tremble:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114440">Nor brutish broil, when with strong head</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114450">A rebel people madly led</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114460">Against their lords assemble:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114470">Nor fearful face of tyrant wood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114480">Who breathes but threats, and drinks but blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114490"><pb facs="38"/> no, nor the hand which thunder,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114500">The hand of Jove which thunder bears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114510">And ribs of rocks in sunder tears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114520">Tears mountains sides in sunder:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114530">Nor bloody Mars's butchering bands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114540">Whose lightnings desert lay the lands</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114550">Whom dusty clouds do cover:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114560">From of whose armour sunbeams fly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114570">And under them make quaking lie</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114580">The plains whereon they hover:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114590">Nor yet the cruel murth'ing blade</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114600">Warm in the moisty bowels made</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114610">Of people pell-mell dying</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114620">In some great city put to sack</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114630">By savage tyrant brought to wrack,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114640">At his cold mercy lying. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114650">How abject him, how base think I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114660">Who wanting courage can not die</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114670">When need him thereto calleth? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114680">From whom the dagger drawn to kill</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114690"><pb facs="38"/> the cureless griefs that vex him still</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114700">For fear and faintness falleth? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114710">O Antony with thy dear mate</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114720">Both in misfortunes fortunate! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114730">Whose thoughts to death aspiring </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114740">Shall you protect from victor's rage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114750">Who on each side doth you encage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114760">To triumph much desiring. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114770">That Caesar may you not offend</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114780">Naught else but death can you defend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114790">Which his weak force derideth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114800">And all in this round earth contained,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114810">Powerless on them whom once enchained</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114820">Avernus' prison hideth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114830">Where great Psammetique's ghost doth rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114840">Not with infernal pain possessed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114850">But in sweet fields detained:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114860">And old Amasis' soul likewise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114870">And all our famous Ptolemy's</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114880">That whilom on us reigned. </l>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A01502-e114890">
        <pb facs="39"/>
        <head>Act. 4</head>
        <stage xml:id="A01502-e114900">Caesar. Agrippa. Dircetus. the messenger.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e114910" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Caesar.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114920">You everliving gods which all things hold</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114930">Within the power of your celestial hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114940">By whom heat, cold, the thunder, and the wind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114950">The properties of enter changing months</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114960">Their course and being have; which do set down</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114970">Of empires by your destinied decree</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114980">The force, age, time, and subject to no change</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e114990">Change all, reserving nothing in one state:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115000">You have advanced, as high as thundering heaven</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115010">The Romans greatness by Bellona's might:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115020">Mastering the world with fearful violence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115030">Making the world widow of liberty. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115040">Yet at this day this proud exalted Rome</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115050"><pb facs="39"/> despoiled, captived, at one man's will doth bend:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115060">Her empire mine, her life is in my hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115070">As monarch I both world and Rome command;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115080">Do all, can all; forth my commandment cast</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115090">Like thundering fire from one to other pole</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115100">Equal to Jove: bestowing by my word</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115110">Haps and mishaps, as fortune's King and lord. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115120">No town there is, but up my image sets,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115130">But sacrifice to me doth daily make:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115140">Whither where Phoebus join his mourning steeds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115150">Or where the night them weary entertains,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115160">Or where the heat the Garamants doth scorch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115170">Or where the cold from Boreas breast is blown:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115180">All Caesar do both awe and honour bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115190">And crowned Kings his very name doth fear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115200">Antony knows it well, for whom not one</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115210">Of all the princes all this earth do rule,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115220">Arms against me: for all redoubt the power</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115230">Which heavenly powers on earth have made me bear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115240">Antony, he poor man with fire inflamed</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115250"><pb facs="40"/> a woman's beauties kindled in his heart. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115260">Rose against me, who longer could not bear</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115270">My sisters wrong he did so ill entreat:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115280">Sing her left while that his lewd delights</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115290">Her husband with his Cleopatra took</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115300">In Alexandria, where both nights and days</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115310">Their time they passed in naught but loves and plays</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115320">All Asia's forces into one he drew,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115330">And forth he set upon the azured waves</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115340">A thousand and a thousand ships, which filled</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115350">With soldiers, pikes, with targets, arrows, darts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115360">Made Neptune quake, and all the watery troops</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115370">Of Glauques, and Tritons lodged at Actium,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115380">But mighty gods, who still the force withstand</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115390">Of him, who causeless doth another wrong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115400">In less than moment's space reduced to naught</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115410">All that proud power by sea or land he brought. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e115420" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Agr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115430">Presumptuous pride of heigh and haughty sprite,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115440">Voluptuous care of fond and foolish love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115450">Have justly wrought his wrack: who thought he held</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115460"><pb facs="40"/> (By overweening) fortune in his hand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115470">Of us he made no count, but as to play,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115480">So fearless came our forces to assay. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115490">So sometimes fell to sons of mother earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115500">Which crawled to heaven war on the god to make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115510">Olymp on Pelion, Ossa on Olymp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115520">Pindus on Ossa loading by degrees:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115530">That at hand strokes with mighty clubs the might</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115540">On mossy rocks the gods make tumble down:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115550">When mighty Jove with burning anger chafed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115560">Disbrained with him Gyges and Briareus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115570">Blunting his darts upon their bruised bones. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115580">For no one thing the gods can less abide</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115590">In deeds of men, than arrogance and pride. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115600">And still the proud, which too much takes in hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115610">Shall foulest fall, where best he thinks to stand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e115620" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115630">Right as some palace, or some stately tower,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115640">Which overlooks the neighbour buildings round</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115650">In scorning wise, and to the stars up grows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115660">Which in short time his own weight overthrows. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115670"><pb facs="41"/>What monstrous pride, nay what impiety</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115680">Incensed him onward to the god's disgrace? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115690">When his two children, Cleopatra's bats,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115700">To Phoebe and her brother he compared,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115710">Latona's race, causing them to be called</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115720">The sun and moon? Is not this folly right</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115730">And is not this the gods to make his foes? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115740">And is not this himself to work his woes? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e115750" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Agr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115760">In like proud sort he caused his head to lose</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115770">The Jewish King Antigonus, to have</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115780">His realm for balm, that Cleopatra loved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115790">As though on him he had some treason proved. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e115800" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Caes</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115810">Lidia to her, and Siria he gave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115820">Cyprus of gold, Arabia rich of smells:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115830">And to his children more Cilicia,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115840">Parth's, Medes, Armenia, Phoenicia:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115850">The Kings of Kings proclaiming them to be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115860">By his own word, as by a sound decree. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e115870" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Agr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115880">What? Robbing his own country of her due</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115890">Triumphed he not in Alexandriae,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115900"><pb facs="41"/> of Artabasus the Armenian King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115910">Who yielded on his perjured word to him? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e115920" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115930">Nay, never Rome more injuries received,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115940">Since thou, o Romulus, by flight of birds</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115950">With happy hand the Roman walls didst build,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115960">Than Antony's fond loves to it hath done. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115970">Nor ever war more holy, nor more just,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115980">Nor undertaken with more hard constraint,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e115990">Then is this war: which were it not, our state</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116000">Within small time all dignity should lose:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116010">Though I lament (Thou sun my witness art,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116020">And thou great Jove) that it so deadly proves:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116030">That Roman blood should in such plenty flow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116040">Watering the fields and pastures where we go. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116050">What Carthage in old hatred obstinate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116060">What Gaul still barking at our rising state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116070">What rebel Samnite, what fierce Pyrrhus' power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116080">What cruel mithridate, what Parth hath wrought</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116090">Such woe to Rome? whose common wealth he had,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116100">(Had he been victor) into Egypt brought. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116110" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <pb facs="42"/>
          <speaker>Agr.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116120">Surely the gods, which have this city built</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116130">Steadfast to stand as long as time endures,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116140">Which keep the Capitol, of us take care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116150">And care will take of those shall after come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116160">Have made you victor, that you might redress</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116170">Their honour grown by passed mischieves less. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116180" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116190">The silly man when all the Greekish sea</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116200">His fleet had hid, in hope me sure to drown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116210">Me battle gave: where fortune in my stead,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116220">Repulsing him his forces disarrayed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116230">Himself took flight, soon as his love he saw</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116240">All won through fear with full sails fly away. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116250">His men, though lost, whom none did now direct,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116260">With courage fought fast grappled ship with ship,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116270">Charging, resisting, as their oars would serve,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116280">With darts, with swords, with pikes, with fiery flames. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116290">So that the darkened night her starry veil</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116300">Upon the bloody sea had overspread,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116310">Whilst yet they held: and hardly, hardly then</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116320">They fell to flying on the wavy plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116330"><pb facs="42"/> all full of soldiers overwhelmed with waves. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116340">The air throughout with cries and groans did sound:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116350">The sea did blush with blood: the neighbour shores</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116360">Groaned, so they with shipwracks pestered were,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116370">And floating bodies left for pleasing food</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116380">To birds, and beasts, and fishes of the sea,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116390">You know it well Agrippa. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116400" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116410">Meet it was</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116420">The Roman empire so should ruled be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116430">As heaven is ruled: which turning over us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116440">All under things by his example turns. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116450">Now as of heaven one only lord we know:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116460">One only lord should rule this earth below. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116470">When one self power is common made to two</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116480">Their duties they nor suffer will, nor do. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116490">In quarrel still, in doubt, in hate, in fear;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116500"> meanwhile the people all the smart do bear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116510" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116520">Then to the end none, while my days endure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116530">Seeking to raise himself may succours find,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116540">We must with blood mark this our victory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116550">For just example to all memory</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116560"><pb facs="43"/> murder we must, until not one we leave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116570">Which may hereafter us of rest be . </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116580" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116590">Mark it with murders? Who of that can like? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116600" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116610">Murders must use, who doth assurance seek. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116620" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116630">Assurance call you enemies to make? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116640" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116650">I make no such, but such away I take. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116660" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116670">Nothing so much as rigour doth displease. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116680" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116690">Nothing so much doth make me live at ease. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116700" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116710">What ease to him that feared is of all? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116720" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116730">Feared to be, and see his foes to fall. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116740" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116750">Commonly fear doth breed and nourish hate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116760" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116770">Hate without power comes commonly too late. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116780" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116790">A feared prince hath oft his death desired</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116800" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116810">A prince not feared hath oft his wrong conspired. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116820" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116830">No guard so sure, no fort so strong doth prove. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116840">No such defence, as is the people's love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116850" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116860">Naught more unsure more weak, more like the wind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116870">Than people's favour still to change inclined. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116880" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116890">Good gods! what love to gracious prince men bear! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116900" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116910">What honour to the prince that is severe! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116920" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <pb facs="43"/>
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116930">Naught more divine then is benignity. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116940" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116950">Naught likes the gods as doth severity. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116960" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116970">Gods all forgive. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e116980" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e116990">On faults they pains do lay. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117000" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117010">And give their goods. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117020" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>C.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117030">Oft times they take away</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117040" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117050">They wreak them not, o Caesar, at each time</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117060">That by our sins they are to wrath provoked. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117070">Neither must you (Believe, I humbly pray)</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117080">Your victory with cruelty defile. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117090">The gods it gave, it must not be abused,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117100">But to the good of all men mildly used,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117110">And they be thanked: that having given you grace</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117120">To reign alone, and rule this earthly mass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117130">They may henceforward hold it still in rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117140">All scattered power united in one breast. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117150" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117160">But what is he that breathless comes so fast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117170">Approaching us, and going in such haste? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117180" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117190">He seems afraid: and under his arm I</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117200">(But much I err) a bloody sword espy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117210" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117220">I long to understand what it may be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117230" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117240">He hither comes: it's best we stay and see. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117250" who="A01502-dircetus">
          <pb facs="44"/>
          <speaker>Dirce.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117260">What good God now my voice will reinforce,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117270">That tell I may to rocks, and hills, and woods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117280">To waves of sea, which dash upon the shore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117290">To earth, to heaven, the woeful news I bring? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117300" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>A.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117310">What sudden chance thee towards us hath brought</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117320" who="A01502-dircetus">
          <speaker>Dir.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117330">A lamentable chance. O wrath of heavens! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117340">O gods too pitiless! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117350" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117360">What monstrous hap</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117370">Wilt thou recount? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117380" who="A01502-dircetus">
          <speaker>Dir.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117390">Alas too hard mishap! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117400">When I but dream of what mine eyes beheld,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117410">My heart doth freeze, my limbs do quivering quake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117420">I senseless stand, my breast with tempest tossed</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117430">Kills in my throat my words, ere fully born. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117440">Dead, dead he is: be sure of what I say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117450">This murdering sword hath made the man away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117460" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117470">Alas my heart doth cleave, pity me racks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117480">My breast doth pant to hear this doleful tale. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117490">Is Antony then dead? to death, alas! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117500">I am the cause despair him so compelled. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117510">But soldior of his death the manner show,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117520">And how he did this living light forgo. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117530" who="A01502-dircetus">
          <pb facs="44"/>
          <speaker>Dir.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117540">When Antony no hope remaining saw</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117550">How war he might, or how agreement make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117560">Saw him betrayed by all his men of war</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117570">In every fight as well by sea, as land;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117580">That not content to yield them to their foes</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117590">They also came against himself to fight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117600">Alone in court he 'gan himself torment,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117610">Accuse the Queen, himself of her lament,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117620">Called her untrue and traitress, as who sought</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117630">To yield him up she could no more defend:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117640">That in the harms which for her sake he bore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117650">As in his blissful state, she might not share. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117660">But she again, who much his fury feared,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117670">Got to the tombs, dark horrors dwelling place:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117680">Made lock the doors, and pull the hearses down. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117690">Then fell she wretched, with herself to fight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117700">A thousand plaints, a thousand sobs she cast</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117710">From her weak breast which to the bones was torn. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117720">Of women her the most unhappy called,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117730">Who by her love, her woeful love, had lost</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117740"><pb facs="45"/> her realm, her life, and more the love of him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117750">Who while he was, was all her woes support. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117760">But that she faultless was she did invoke</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117770">For witness heaven, and air, and earth, and sea. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117780">Then sent him word, she was no more alive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117790">But lay enclosed dead within her tomb. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117800">This he believed; and fell to sigh and groan,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117810">And crossed his arms, than thus began to moan. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117820" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>C.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117830">Poor hopeless man! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e117840" who="A01502-dircetus">
          <speaker>D.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117850">What dost thou more attend</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117860">Ah Antony! why dost thou death defer. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117870">Since fortune thy professed enemy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117880">Hath made to die, who only made thee live? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117890">Soon as with sighs he had these words up closed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117900">His armour he unlaced and cast it off,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117910">Then all disarmed he thus again did say:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117920">My Queen, my heart, the grief that now I feel. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117930">Is not that I your eyes, my sun, do lose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117940">For soon again one tomb shall us conjoin:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117950">I grieve, whom men so valorous did deem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117960">Should now, than you, of lesser valour seem. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117970"><pb facs="45"/>So said, forthwith he Erisychthon to him called,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117980">Erisychthon his man; summoned him on his faith</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e117990">To kill him at his need. He took the sword,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118000">And at that instant stabbed therewith his breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118010">And ending life fell dead before his feet. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118020">O Erisychthon thanks (Quoth Antony) for this</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118030">Most noble act, who powerless me to kill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118040">On thee hast done, what I on me should do. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118050">Of speaking thus he scarce had made an end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118060">And taken up the bloody sword from ground,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118070">But he his body pierced; and of red blood</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118080">A gushing fountain all the chamber filled. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118090">He staggered at the blow, his face grew pale,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118100">And on a couch all feeble down he fell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118110">Sounding with anguish: deadly cold him took,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118120">As if his soul had then his lodging left</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118130">But he revived, and marking all our eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118140">Bathed in tears, and how our breasts we beat</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118150">For pity, anguish, and for bitter grief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118160">To see him plunged in extreme wretchedness:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118170"><pb facs="46"/> he prayed us all to haste his lingering death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118180">But no man willing, each himself withdrew. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118190">Then fell he new to cry and vex himself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118200">Until a man from Cleopatra came,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118210">Who said from her he had commandment</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118220">To bring him to her to the monument. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118230">The poor soul at these words even rapt with joy</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118240">Knowing she lived, prayed us him to convey</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118250">Unto his lady. Then upon our arms</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118260">We bore him to the tomb, but entered not. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118270">For she who feared captive to be made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118280">And that she should to Rome in triumph go,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118290">Kept close the gate but from a window high</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118300">Cast down a cord, wherein he was impact. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118310">Then by her women's help the corpse she raised,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118320">And by strong arms into her window drew. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118330">So pitiful a sight was never seen. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118340">Little and little Antony was pulled,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118350">Now breathing death: his beard was all unkempt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118360">His face and breast all bathed in his blood. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118370"><pb facs="46"/>So hideous yet, and dying as he was,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118380">His eyes half-closed upon the Queen he cast:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118390">Held up his hands, and holp himself to raise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118400">But still with weakness back his body fell. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118410">The miserable lady with moist eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118420">With hair which careless on her forehead hung,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118430">With breast which blows had bloodily benumbed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118440">With stooping head, and body downward bent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118450">Enlaced her in the cord, and with all force</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118460">This life-dead man courageously upraised,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118470">The blood with pain into her face did flow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118480">Her sinews stiff, herself did breathless grow. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118490">The people which beneath in flocks beheld,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118500">Assisted her with gesture, speech, desire:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118510">Cried and encouraged her, and in their souls</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118520">Did sweat, and labour, no whit less than she. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118530">Who never tired in labour, held so long</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118540">Helped by her women, and her constant heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118550">That Antony was drawn into the tomb,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118560">And there (I think) of dead augments the sum. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118570"><pb facs="47"/>The city all to tears and sighs is turned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118580">To plaints and outcries horrible to hear:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118590">Men, women, children, hoary-headed age</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118600">Do all pell-mell in house and street lament,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118610">Scratching their faces, tearing of their hair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118620">Wringing their hands, and martyring their breasts</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118630">Extreme their dole: and greater misery</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118640">In sacked towns can hardly ever be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118650">Not if the fire had scaled the highest towers:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118660">That all things were of force and murder full;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118670">That in the streets the blood in rivers streamed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118680">The son his sire saw in his bosom slain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118690">The sire his son: the husband and rest of breath</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118700">In his wife's arms, who furious runs to death. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118710">Now my breast wounded with their piteous plaints</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118720">I left their town, and took with me this sword,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118730">Which I took up at what time Antony</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118740">Was from his chamber carried to the tomb:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118750">And brought it you, to make his death more plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118760">And that thereby my words may credit gain. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e118770" who="A01502-caesar">
          <pb facs="47"/>
          <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118780">Ah gods what cruel hap! poor Antony,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118790">Alas hast thou this sword so long time born</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118800">Against thy foe, that in the end it should</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118810">Of thee his lord the cursed murderer be? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118820">O death how I bewail thee! we (Alas!) </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118830">So many wars have ended, brothers, friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118840">Companions, cozens, equals in estate:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118850">And must it now to kill thee be my fate? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e118860" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118870">Why trouble you yourself with bootless grief? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118880">For Antony why spend you tears in vain? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118890">Why darken you with dole your victory? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118900">Me seems yourself your glory do envy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118910">Enter the town, give thanks unto the gods. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e118920" who="A01502-caesar">
          <speaker>Cae.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118930">I cannot but his tearful chance lament,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118940">Although not I, but his own pride the cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118950">And unchaste love of this Egyptian. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e118960" who="A01502-agrippa">
          <speaker>Agt.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118970">But best we sought into the tomb to get,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118980">Lest she consume in this amazed case</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e118990">So much rich treasure, with which happily</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119000">Despair in death may make her feed the fire:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119010"><pb facs="48"/> suffering the flames her jewels to deface,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119020">You to defraud, her funeral to grace. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119030">Send then to her, and let some mean be used</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119040">With some device so hold her still alive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119050">Some fair large promises: and let them mark</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119060">Whither they may by some fine cunning slight</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119070">Enter the tombs. Caesar. Let Proculeius go,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119080">And feed with hope her soul disconsolate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119090">Assure her so, that we may wholly get</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119100">Into our hands her treasure and herself. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119110">For this of all things most I do desire</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119120">To keep her safe until our going hence:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119130">That by her presence beautified may be</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119140">The glorious triumph Rome prepares for me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e119150" who="A01502-chorus">
          <speaker>Chorus of Roman soldiers.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119160">Shall ever civil bate</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119170">Gnaw and devour our state?</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119180"><pb facs="48"/> shall never we this blade,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119190">Our blood hath bloody made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119200">Lay down? these arms down lay</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119210">As robes we wear always?</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119220">But as from age to age.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119230">So pass from rage to rage? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119240">Our hands shall we not rest</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119250">To bathe in our own breast?</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119260">And shall thick in each land</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119270">Our wretched trophies stand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119280">To tell posterity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119290">What mad impiety</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119300">Our stony stomachs led</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119310">Against the place us bred? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119320">Then still must heaven view</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119330">The plagues that us pursue.</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119340">And everywhere descry</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119350">Heaps of us scattered lie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119360">Making the stranger plains</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119370">Fat with our bleeding rains,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119380"><pb facs="49"/> proud that on them their grave</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119390">So many legions have. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119400">And without fleshes still</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119410">Neptune his fishes fill</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119420">And drunk with blood from blue</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119430">The sea take blushing hue:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119440">As juice of Tyrian shell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119450">When clarified well</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119460">To wool of finest fields</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119470">A purple gloss it yields. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119480">But since the rule of Rome,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119490">To one man's hand is come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119500">Who governs without mate</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119510">Her now united state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119520">Late jointly ruled by three</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119530">Envying mutually,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119540">Whose triple yoke much woe</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119550">On Latins necks did throw:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119560">I hope the cause of jar,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119570">And of this bloody war,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119580"><pb facs="49"/> and deadly discord gone</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119590">By what we last have done:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119600">Our banks shall cherish now</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119610">The branchy pale-hewed bow</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119620">Of olive, Pallas praise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119630">In stead of barren bays. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119640">And that his temple door,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119650">Which bloody Mars before</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119660">Held open, now at last</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119670">Old Janus shall make fast:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119680">And rust the sword consume,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119690">And spoilt of waving plume,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119700">The useless morion shall</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119710">On crook hang by the wall. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119720">At least if war return</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119730">It shall not here sojourn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119740">To kill us with those arms</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119750">Were forged for others harms:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119760">But have their points addressed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119770">Against the Germans breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119780"><pb facs="50"/> the Parthians feigned flight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119790">The Biscayne's martial might. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119800">Old memory doth there</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119810">Painted on forehead wear</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119820">Our father's praise: thence torn</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119830">Our triumphs bays have worn:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119840">Thereby our matchless Rome</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119850">Whilom of shepherds come</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119860">Raised to this greatness stands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119870">The Queen of foreign lands. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119880">Which now even seems to face</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119890">The heavens, her glory's place:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119900">Naught resting under skies</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119910">That dares affront her eyes. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119920">So that she needs but fear</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119930">The weapons Jove doth bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119940">Who angry at one blow</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119950">May her quite overthrow. </l>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A01502-e119960">
        <pb facs="50"/>
        <head>Act. 5,</head>
        <stage xml:id="A01502-e119970">Cleopatra. Euphron. Children of Cleopatra. Charmion. Eras.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e119980" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cleop.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e119990">O cruel fortune! O accursed lot! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120000">O plaguy love! O most detested brand! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120010">O wretched joys! O beauties miserable! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120020">O deadly state! O deadly royalty! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120030">O hateful life! O Queen most lamentable! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120040">O Antony by my fault buriable! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120050">O hellish work of heaven! alas! the wrath</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120060">Of all the gods at once on us is fallen. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120070">Unhappy Queen! O would I in this world</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120080">The wand'ring light of day had never seen? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120090">Alas! of mine the plague and poison I</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120100">The crown have lost my ancestors me left,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120110">This realm I have to strangers subject made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120120"><pb facs="51"/> and robbed my children of their heritage. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120130">Yet this is naught (Alas!) unto the price</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120140">Of you dear husband, whom my snares entrapped:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120150">Of you, whom I have plagued, whom I have made</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120160">With bloody hand a guest of mouldy tomb:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120170">Of you, whom I destroyed, of you, dear lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120180">Whom I of empire, honour, life have spoiled. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120190">O hurtful woman! and can I yet live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120200">Yet longer live in this ghost-haunted tomb? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120210">Can I yet breath! can yet in such annoy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120220">Yet can my soul within this body dwell? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120230">O sisters you that spin the threads of death! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120240">O Styx! O Plegethon! you brooks of hell! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120250">O imps of night! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120260" who="A01502-euphron">
          <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120270">Live for your children's sake:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120280">Let not your death of kingdom them deprive. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120290">Alas what shall they do who will have care? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120300">Who will preserve this royal race of yours? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120310">Who pity take? even now me seems I see</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120320">These little souls to servile bondage fallen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120330">And born in triumph. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120340" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120350">Ah most miserable! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120360" who="A01502-euphron">
          <pb facs="51"/>
          <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120370">Their tender arms with cursed cord fast bound</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120380">At their weak backs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120390" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120400">Ah gods what pity more! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120410" who="A01502-euphron">
          <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120420">Their silly necks to ground with weakness bend</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120430" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120440">Never on us, good gods, such mischief send. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120450" who="A01502-euphron">
          <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120460">And pointed at with fingers as they go. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120470" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120480">Rather a thousand deaths. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120490" who="A01502-euphron">
          <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120500">Lastly his knife</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120510">Some cruel caitiff in their blood imbrue. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120520" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120530">Ah my heart breaks. By shady banks of hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120540">By fields whereon the lonely ghosts do tread,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120550">By my soul, and the soul of Antony</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120560">I you beseech, Euphron, of them have care. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120570">Be their good father, let your wisdom let</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120580">That they fall not into this tyrants hands. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120590">Rather conduct them where their freezed locks</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120600">Black Aethiops to neighbour sun do show;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120610">On wavy ocean at the waters will;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120620">On barren cliffs of snowy Caucasus;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120630">To tigers swift, to lions, and to bears;</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120640">And rather, rather unto every coast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120650">To every land and sea: for naught I fear</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120660"><pb facs="52"/> as rage of him, whose thirst no blood can quench. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120670">Adieu dear children, children dear adieu:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120680">Good Isis you to place of safety guide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120690">Far from our foes, where you your lives may lead</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120700">In free estate devoid of servile dread. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120710">Remember not, my children, you were born</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120720">Of such a princely race: remember not</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120730">So many brave Kings which have Egypt ruled</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120740">In right descent your ancestors have been:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120750">That this great Antony your father was,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120760">Hercules' blood, and more than he in praise. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120770">For your high courage such remembrance will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120780">Sing your fall with burning rages fill. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120790">Who knows if that your hands false destiny</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120800">The sceptres promised of imperious Rome,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120810">In stead of them shall crooked sheephooks bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120820">Needles or forks, or guide the cart, or plough? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120830">Ah learn t'endure: your birth and high estate</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120840">Forget, my babes, and bend to force of fate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120850">Farewell, my babes, farewell my heart is closed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120860"><pb facs="52"/> with pity and pain, myself with death enclosed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120870">My breath doth fail. Farewell for evermore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120880">Your sire and me you shall see never more. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120890">Farewell sweet care, farewell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120900" who="A01502-children">
          <speaker>Chil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120910">Madam adieu. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120920" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120930">Ah this voice kills me. Ah good gods! I swoon. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120940">I can no more, I die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120950" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Eras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120960">Madam, alas! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120970">And will you yield to woe? Ah speak to us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e120980" who="A01502-euphron">
          <speaker>Eu,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e120990">Come children. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121000" who="A01502-children">
          <speaker>Chil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121010">We come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121020" who="A01502-euphron">
          <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121030">Follow we our chance. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121040">The gods shall guide us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121050" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Char.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121060">O too cruel lot! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121070">O too hard chance! Sister what shall we do,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121080">What shall we do, alas! if murdering dart</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121090">Of death arrive while that in slumbering swoon</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121100">Half dead she lie with anguish overgone? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121110" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Er,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121120">Her face is frozen. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121130" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121140">Madam for God's love</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121150">Leave us not thus: bid us yet first farewell. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121160">Alas! weep over Antony: let not</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121170">His body be without due rites entombed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121180" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121190">Ah, ah. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121200" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Char.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121210">Madam. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121220" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121230">Ay me! </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121240" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121250">How faint she is? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121260" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121270">My sisters, hold me up. How wretched I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121280">How cursed am: and was there ever one</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121290"><pb facs="53"/> by fortune's hate into more dolours thrown? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121300">Ah, weeping Niobe, although thy heart</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121310">Beholds itself enwrapped in causeful woe</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121320">For thy dead children, that a senseless rock</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121330">With grief become, on Sipylus thou standest</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121340">In endless tears: yet didst thou never feel</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121350">The weights of grief that on my heart do lie. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121360">Thy children thou, mine I poor soul have lost,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121370">And lost their father, more than them I wail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121380">Lost this fair realm; yet me the heaven's wrath</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121390">Into a stone not yet transformed hath. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121400">Phaeton's sisters, daughters of the sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121410">Which wail your brother fallen into the streams</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121420">Of stately Po: the gods upon the banks</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121430">Your bodies to bank-loving alders turned. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121440">For me, I sigh, I ceaseless weep, and wail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121450">And heaven pitiless laughs at my woe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121460">Revives, renews it still: and in the end</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121470">(O cruelty!) doth death for comfort lend. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121480">Die Cleopatra then no longer stay</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121490"><pb facs="53"/> from Antony, who thee at Styx attends:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121500">Go join thy ghost with his, and sob no more</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121510">Without his love within these tombs enclosed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121520" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Eras.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121530">Alas! yet let us weep, lest sudden death</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121540">From him our tears, and those last duties take</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121550">Unto his tomb we owe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121560" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121570">Ah let us weep</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121580">While moisture lasts, then die before his feet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121590" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121600">Who furnish will mine eyes with streaming tears</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121610">My boiling anguish worthily to wail,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121620">Wail thee Antony, Antony my heart? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121630">Alas, how much I weeping liquor want! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121640">Yet have mine eyes quite drawn their conduits dry</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121650">By long beweeping my disastered harms. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121660">Now reason is that from my side they suck</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121670">First vital moisture, than the vital blood. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121680">Then let the blood from my sad eyes outflow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121690">And smoking yet with thine in mixture grow. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121700">Moist it, and heat it new, and never stop,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121710">All watering thee, while yet remains one drop. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121720" who="A01502-charmion">
          <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121730">Antony take our tears: this is the last</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121740"><pb facs="54"/> of all the duties we to thee can yield,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121750">Before we die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121760" who="A01502-eras">
          <speaker>Er.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121770">These sacred obsequies</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121780">Take Antony, and take them in good part. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01502-e121790" who="A01502-cleopatra">
          <speaker>Cl.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121800">O goddess thou whom Cyprus doth adore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121810">Venus of Paphos, bent to work us harm</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121820">For old Julus' brood, if thou take care</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121830">Of Caesar, why of us takest thou no care? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121840">Antony did descend, as well as he,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121850">From thine own son by long enchained line:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121860">And might have ruled by one and self same fate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121870">True Trojan blood, the stately Roman state. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121880">Antony, poor Antony, my dear soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121890">Now but a block, the booty of a tomb,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121900">Thy life thy heat is lost, thy colour gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121910">And hideous paleness on thy face hath seized. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121920">Thy eyes, two suns, the lodging place of love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121930">Which yet for tents to warlike Mars did serve,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121940">Locked up in lids (As fair days cheerful light</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121950">Which darkness flies) do winking hide in night. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121960">Antony by our true loves I thee beseech,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121970"><pb facs="54"/> and by our hearts sweet sparks have set on fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121980">Our holy marriage, and the tender ruth</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e121990">Of our dear babes, knot of our amity:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122000">My doleful voice thy ear let entertain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122010">And take me with thee to the hellish plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122020">Thy wife, thy friend: hear Antony, o hear</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122030">My sobbing sighs, if here thou be, or there. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122040">Lived thus long, the winged race of years</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122050">Ended I have as destiny decreed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122060">Flourished and reigned, and taken just revenge</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122070">Of him who me both hated and despised. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122080">Happy, alas too happy: if of Rome</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122090">Only the fleet had hither never come. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122100">And now of me an image great shall go</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122110">Under the earth to bury there my woe. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122120">What say I? where am I? O Cleopatra,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122130">Poor Cleopatra, grief thy reason reaves. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122140">No, no, most happy in this hapless case,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122150">To die with thee, and dying thee embrace:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122160">My body joined with thine, my mouth with thine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122170"><pb facs="55"/> my mouth, whose moisture burning sighs have dried</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122180">To be in one self tumble, and one self chest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122190">And wrapped with thee in one self sheet to rest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122200">The sharpest torment in my heart I feel</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122210">Is that I stay from thee, my heart, this while. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122220">Die will I straight now, now straight will I die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122230">And straight with thee a wand'ring shade will be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122240">Under the cypress trees thou hauntest alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122250">Where brooks of hell do falling seem to moan. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122260">But yet I stay, and yet thee overlive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122270">That ere I die due rites I may thee give. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122280">A thousand sobs I from my breast will tear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122290">With thousand plaints thy funerals adorn:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122300">My hair shall serve for thy oblations,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122310">My boiling tears for thy effusions,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122320">Mine eyes thy fire: for out of them the flame</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122330">(Which burned thy heart on me enamoured) came. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122340">Weep my companions, weep, and from your eyes</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122350">Rain down on him of tears a brinish stream. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122360">Mine can no more, consumed by the coals</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122370"><pb facs="55"/> which from my breast, as from a furnace rise. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122380">Martyr your breasts with multiplied blows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122390">With violent hands tear of your hanging hair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122400">Outrage your face: alas! why should we seek</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122410">(Since now we die) our beauties more to keep? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122420">I spent in tears, not able more to spend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122430">But kiss him now, what rests me more to do? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122440">Then let me kiss you, you fair eyes, my light,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122450">Front seat of honour, face most fierce, most fair! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122460">O neck, o arms, o hands, o breast where death</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122470">(Oh mischief) comes to choke up vital breath. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122480">A thousand kisses, thousand thousand more</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122490">Let you my mouth for honour's farewell give:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122500">That in this office weak my limbs may grow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01502-e122510">Fainting on you, and fourth my soul may flow. </l>
        </sp>
        <closer xml:id="A01502-e122520">
          <dateline xml:id="A01502-e122530">at rams bury. <date xml:id="A01502-e122540">26. of November. 1590.</date></dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A01502-e122550">
      <div type="colophon" xml:id="A01502-e122560">
        <pb facs="56"/>
        <p xml:id="A01502-e122570">Printed at London by P. s. for William Ponsonby. 1595.</p>
        <pb facs="56"/>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A01502"><item xml:id="A01502-cleopatra" n="44">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-cleopatra</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">44</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-caesar" n="24">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-caesar</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">24</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-charmion" n="23">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-charmion</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">23</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-agrippa" n="22">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-agrippa</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">22</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-lucilius" n="18">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-lucilius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">18</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-antonius" n="18">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-antonius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">18</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-eras" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-eras</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-euphron" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-euphron</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-chorus" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-chorus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-dircetus" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-dircetus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-diomede" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-diomede</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-children" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-children</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-philostratus" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-philostratus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-antony" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-antony</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01502-antoniud" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01502-antoniud</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

