<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A01853">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Lodovick Sforza <date type="creation_date">1628</date></title>
        <author>Gomersall, Robert</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Madeline Burg</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A01853.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The tragedie of Lodouick Sforza Duke of Millan. By Robert Gomersall.</title>
            <author>Gomersall, Robert, 1602-1646?</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>45 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2007 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99838982</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 11995.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 418(a).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">3375</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01853</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The tragedie of Lodouick Sforza Duke of Millan. By Robert Gomersall.</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedie of Lodovick Sforza Duke of Millan</title>
            <title type="alt">Sforza.</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedie of Lodovick Sforza Duke of Millan.</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedy of Sforza.</title>
            <author>Gomersall, Robert, 1602-1646?</author>
            <author>Cecil, Thomas, fl. 1630,</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[18], 70, [2] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>[By Miles Flesher for John Marriott],</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>in the yeare M DC XXVIII. [1628]</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>With an additional title page, engraved, signed "Tho: Cecill. sculp.": Sforza by Rob: Gomersall. London. Printed for Iohn Marriott. 1628.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The first two leaves are blank except for signature-mark on A2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: The tragedy of Sforza.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Ludovico Sforza, -- Duke of Milan, -- 1452-1508 -- Drama.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A01853-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A01853-e100020">
      <div type="frontispiece" xml:id="A01853-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <lg xml:id="A01853-e100040">
          <head>The explanation of the frontispiece.</head>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100050">It was when industry did sleep</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100060">The wolf was tutor to the sheep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100070">And to amaze a plainer man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100080">The thief was made the guardian. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100090">But can a wolf forget to prey? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100100">Can night be lightened into day? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100110">Without respect of laws or blood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100120">His charge he makes to be his food. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100130">With that triumphant be sits down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100140">Oppressed, not honoured with a crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100150">And on the lesser beasts does try</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100160">A most authentic tyranny:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100170">This the French lion hears, and when</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100180">He's thought fast sleeping in his den,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100190">Vengeance and he at once do wake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100200">And on the wolf their fury slake. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100210">Bad acts may bloom sometimes, but ne'er grow high,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100220">Nor do they live so sure, as they shall die. </l>
        </lg>
        <p xml:id="A01853-e100230">
          <pb facs="3"/>
          <figure xml:id="A01853-e100240">
            <head>Sforza</head>
            <signed xml:id="A01853-e100250">By Rob: Gomersall</signed>
            <p xml:id="A01853-e100260">London printed for 〈…〉</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A01853-e100270">
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <pb facs="4"/>
        <p xml:id="A01853-e100280">The tragedy of Lodovick Sforza Duke of Milan. </p>
        <p xml:id="A01853-e100290">By Robert Gomersall. </p>
        <p xml:id="A01853-e100300">Imprinted at London in the year m dc xxviii.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A01853-e100310">
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <head>To his most worthy friend Mr. Francis hide proctor of Oxford. </head>
        <p xml:id="A01853-e100320">Having resolved what to print, I could not be long doubtful unto whom: it had been an unfriendly absurdity not to have entitled him to my second, who might not unjustly have challenged the patronage of my first labour. But if until this time I had had no reason for such a dedication, if the same most fruitful college had not for these many years known us of the same time and friendship, if in all offices of life I had not still found you most inseparably one with me: yet this work at this time could not offer itself to any so justly as to you. It is to your name that I owe whatever fruits of my spent time shall be preserved, it is to your name that I owe whatever fruits of my former time, being unhappily lost, may have a possibility of recovery. And could I dedicate any of my remaining labours with<pb facs="6"/> more justice unto any, then to him, by whose friendly care, I dare almost assure myself of them which are remaining? But some perhaps may say for this, that it had been better if it had been lost, or at least that these kind of labours are more judiciously suppressed then published. Sermons had been fitter for my setting forth, and to preach more proper than to write. But is not this to preach? I have heard divers speak an hour, who preach not, and there are many, who effectually preach, that are more sparing of their breath. If I make the ambitious see that he climbs but to a fall, the usurper to acknowledge, that blood is but a slippery foundation of power, all men in general to confess that the most glorious is not the most safe place: is not this to cry down ambition and usurpation? or is it less to show, than to threaten? and are not men so much moved with the event itself, as with the commination of the event? And yet in this age, wherein only heresy or sedition prefer a book, wherein contradiction is called learning, and zeal wonders that she is become faction, I can expect but a few readers, whose small number shall be no discouragement at all to me if that your judgement shall counterpoise them, which is the only desired crown of</p>
        <closer xml:id="A01853-e100330">
          <signed xml:id="A01853-e100340">Your true friend, R. G.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="argument" xml:id="A01853-e100350">
        <pb facs="6"/>
        <head>The argument.</head>
        <p xml:id="A01853-e100360">Lodovic Sforza, after he had cunningly supplanted the Duchess from the wardship of her son Galeazzo, as cunningly practiseth to be the murderer of him, of whom he would seem to be the protector. To this end he was to remove this impediment. Isabella daughter to the prince of Calabria, and grandchild unto Ferdinand King of Naples, was wife to Galeazzo. A woman of a spirit as high as her birth, and equal to Sforza in all things but the sex: she perceiving the stupidity of her husband, and how that whatsoever she projected for his safety, he discovered to his uncle, for his overthrow, makes her father secretly acquainted with all the passages, desiring him to vindicate his son in law from the usurpation of his protector. This could not be so privately dispatched, but that Sforza had an incling of it, whether out of his own reach he guessed it: or by his nephew's sottishness he understood it. To prevent then his own ruin, whilst he intends his nephews, he ventures on those remedies which the height of fear rather rusheth on, then chooseth,<pb facs="7"/> which more express and exchange, then remove, or avoid a danger. He knew the French claim to Naples, to the prosecution of which he solicits the young King; whom either his right, or inconsiderateness quickly arms unto the action. But before his coming, he by continual messengers deludes the old King, and makes him believe that there was no purpose of his coming, and that the French journey unto Naples, as it was only the child of rumor, and had no being but from fame, so in a very short space, in the age of a wonder it would vanish and expire. Thus was Ferdinand persuaded from his necessary defence, till having certainly understood that all defence would be too late, the French being already very strong upon his frontiers, cheated, not conquered, he dies and leaves his son Alphonso heir of his kingdom, and his troubles. The French King being now entered in person into Italy, Galeazzo dies of a poison at Pavia, when Sforza has brought this worse poison into his country. But the French growing prodigiously victorious, and almost by the very seeing over coming their opposites, Sforza begins to be apprehensive of his own danger, and strives to rid himself of these encumbrances, in the which a too much providence had entangled him. A consideration<pb facs="7"/> without doubt necessary, but almost past the season, it being near unto an impossibility to expel him now, whom it was far from any difficulty at the first not to admit. So that this second resolution did only proclaim the folly of the first, which either in wisdom he should not have ventured on, or, in honesty not have altered. But howsoever, he enters into a new league with the Venetians, and gives the French after their victorious return from Naples half an overthrow at Taro. And now when he thinks himself confirmed in his dukedom, when he as little feared ruin, as he deserved preservation; the French King dies suddenly, to whom Lewis, the true Duke of Orleans, and titular Duke of Milan, succeeded, with him Sforza's late friend, the Venetians conclude a league. Thus Sforza being left alone, raiseth two armies under the conduct of the two sanseverins, men, whom he had highly favoured and advanced. But it is scarce seen, that a faithless master should have a trusty servant, and he that hath no respect to his own word, shall in the extremest of his necessities, find all others promises but words. The elder revolts, and the younger, without the least show of resistance, flies, and Sforza himself is so closely pursued, that he can scarce get away safe into Germany. The French<pb facs="8"/> abusing their late victory, the Millanesi with a general consent, recall Sforza; who, like a melting snow, overflows all before him, and recovers most of his duchy, with the same easiness that he had lost it. The strength of his army consisted especially of Swissers, whom the late overthrow of the warlike Duke of Burgundy, and these Italian wars, had raised to the height of admiration. But to be valiant is not to have all virtues: these were as strong in treachery, as in battle, they lead Sforza in the habit of a Swisser into the French camp, through which in the same habit they had promised to conduct him. Thus having been twice betrayed, and now a prisoner, after a ten years harsh confining he dies in France, having lived in his misery, longer than in his duchy, and leaving instruction to succeeding princes that height should not be their aim, but integrity; and that they would not (That I may use the words of our poet) tempt their stars beyond their light.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A01853-e100370">
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A01853-e100380">
        <pb facs="8"/>
        <head>The names of the actors.</head>
        <list xml:id="A01853-e100390">
          <item xml:id="A01853-e100400">Giovanni Galeazzo the young Duke.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01853-e100410">Lodovick Sforza his protector, afterwards Duke. <list xml:id="A01853-e100420"><head>Two brothers of the house of Sanseverin, Sforza's favourites.</head><item xml:id="A01853-e100430">Galeazzo</item><item xml:id="A01853-e100440">Count Caiazzo</item></list></item>
          <item xml:id="A01853-e100450">
            <list xml:id="A01853-e100460">
              <head>Two of the nobility.</head>
              <item xml:id="A01853-e100470">Lucio Malvezzo</item>
              <item xml:id="A01853-e100480">Carlo Burbiano count Belgiosa</item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item xml:id="A01853-e100490">
            <list xml:id="A01853-e100500">
              <head>Two old courtiers.</head>
              <item xml:id="A01853-e100510">Juliano</item>
              <item xml:id="A01853-e100520">Picinino</item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item xml:id="A01853-e100530">
            <list xml:id="A01853-e100540">
              <head>Poisoners.</head>
              <item xml:id="A01853-e100550">Vitellio</item>
              <item xml:id="A01853-e100560">Malatesta</item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item xml:id="A01853-e100570">Ascanio Sforza's brother, a Cardinal.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01853-e100580">Triulcio the French general.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01853-e100590">The captain of the Swissers.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01853-e100600">Isabella Galeazzo's wife.</item>
          <item xml:id="A01853-e100610">Julia. </item>
          <item xml:id="A01853-e100620">Beatrice wife to Sforza. </item>
          <item xml:id="A01853-e100630">Ambassadors, soldiers, servants.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue_to_drama" xml:id="A01853-e100640">
        <pb facs="9"/>
        <head>The prologue.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A01853-e100650">
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100660">Can horror have an auditory? can</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100670">Man love the spectacle of ruined man? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100680">We feared we should have been alone, that hence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100690">The actors should have been the audience. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100700">Are you not frighted yet? do you not rise? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100710">Can that invite, which should dismay your eyes? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100720">We show near murders, and in that degree</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100730">Where marriage is unlawful, then, the free</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100740">Progress of crimes, by nimble justice met,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100750">Equally horrid, this we show, but yet</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100760">Unless your courtesy, your judgement sway,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e100770">We suffer a worse torture, than we play. </l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="text_of_drama" xml:id="A01853-e100780">
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A01853-e100790">
          <pb facs="9" n="1"/>
          <head>Actus primi</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e100800">
            <head>Scaena prima.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e100810">Galeazzo Duke of Millane, Isabella his wife.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e100820" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e100830">Why weeps my dear?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e100840" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e100850">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e100860">Ask why I do not weep:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e100870">(Poor Isabella are thy tears denied thee?) </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e100880">Ask why thus long such a succession</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e100890">Of sorrow clogs my bosom, and does rob</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e100900">So much of woman from me, as complaints. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e100910">Ask why I do not rave, tear my hair, thus,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e100920">Create a grief, which fate would spare me, than</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e100930">Cloud the sad air with sighs, and at the last,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e100940">With a bold stab take from insulting fortune</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e100950">The miserable object of her sport:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e100960">Ask why I do not this, not, why I weep. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e100970" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 l.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e100980">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e100990">Or stint thy tears, or mingle them with mine</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101000">By a relation of their cause: these eyes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101010">Trust me, my Isabella, are not dry,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101020">Nor has strong sorrow ere exhausted them,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101030">To make them bankrupt of a friendly tear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101040">Do thou but prove it once a friendly tear</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101050">And not a fond one. Why, my Isabella,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101060">Why dost thou hasten those that come too fast,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101070"><pb facs="10" n="2"/> sorrow, and age? If it be true, I heard</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101080">Of Sforza, my dear Sforza, there's no joy</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101090">But either past, or fleeting, and poor man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101100">Grows up but to the experience of grief,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101110">And then is truly past minority</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101120">When he is passed all happiness:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e101130" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Jsab.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e101140">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101150">My lord,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101160">My sorrow dares not argue with your love,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101170">This smile expels it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e101180" who="A01853-galeazzo">
              <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e101190">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101200">Be it banished far,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101210">Eternally, or to the years of age. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101220">Ay, those unclouded looks become my dear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101230">And give me joy too. I must hunt today</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101240">With my dear uncle: oh he is a man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101250">That alters all those fond relations,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101260">Which nature gives, who in an uncle's name</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101270">Out loves a father: I could praise him still,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101280">But that I stay too long from him: farewell. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e101290">〈…〉</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e101300" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Jsab.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e101310">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101320">O Galeazzol o not Galeazzo! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101330">How has man fled thee! how thy soul has fled thee! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101340">Only thy lineaments belly a man. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101350">Thou hunt; alas as poor prince, thou art the game:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101360">Thy uncle hunts: and yet he does not neither,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101370">But stands a glad, and idle looker on,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101380">Whilst thou ensnarest thyself, sinfully fooled,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101390">Flattering thy executioner, and so</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101400">Dost not prevent thy misery, nor yet know. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e101410">Enter g 〈…〉</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e101420" who="A01853-galeazzo">
              <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e101430">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101440">I am returned once more; before I'm gone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101450">To see if thy fond grief be not returned;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101460">What joy is there in a forbidden grief? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101470">What comfort in the eyes sad flux? once 〈…〉</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101480">Is it my fault gives you these tears? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e101490" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Jsab ▪</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e101500">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101510">My 〈…〉 ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101520"><pb facs="10" n="3"/> for which so strange a sadness seizes me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101530">That it increaseth when I strive with it,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101540">And makes my face rebellious to my lord,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101550">When my heart yields. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e101560" who="A01853-galeazzo">
              <speaker>●al</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e101570">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101580">Then once again, adieu,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101590">Forsake your grief, or grief will forsake you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e101600">Exit.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e101610" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Flab</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e101620">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101630">Forsake my grief — oh bid me forsake heaven,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101640">My reason, and mine honour: only sighs</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101650">Doc keep me in opinion of being,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101660">And without them I were a stupid corse. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101670">Shall I obey impossibilities? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101680">Forsake the sorrow, and retain the cause? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101690">How can I think that yet the untired sun</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101700">Has journeyed but a twelvemonth, since I was</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101710">In Ferdinando's court, the paragon</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101720">Of happy Naples, when his palace seemed</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101730">Guarded with princely suitors, and mine eye,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101740">Caught with so many rarities of men,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101750">Taught me that too much choice did hinder choice,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101760">That Galeazzo then must carry me? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101770">This Galeazzo, neither prince, nor man,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101780">Fooled out of both by Sforza, his dear uncle. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101790">Can I think this, and think of joy again? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101800">Can I think this, and dare to think again? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101810">Why should some toys of after-torment fright</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101820">A resolution of easing me</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101830">From present ones? O 'tis the curse of man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101840">To be unhappy at arbitrement,<stage xml:id="A01853-e101850">Enter Julia.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101860">Till heaven please to relent ▪ my Julia,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101870">Breathes Naples any comfort? quickly speak. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e101880" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>●al</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e101890">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101900">None, madam, and your courteous grandfather</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101910">In stead of armies sends you patience. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e101920" who="A01853-galeazzo">
              <speaker>Flab</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e101930">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101940">What patience? he should have sent me rage,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101950">Aided my anger, if not my revenge:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101960"><pb facs="11" n="4"/> patience? O God! can grief be patient? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101970">Can thunder whisper? or chafed sea not roar? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101980">In me is sea and thunder, I will be</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e101990">A pattern of revenge not misery. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e102000">
            <head>Scaena secunda.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e102010" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sforza.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e102020">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102030">Sforza as yet thou but beginst to act,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102040">And yet beginst to stagger: wert thou not</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102050">A prince's son? why art thou not a prince? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102060">Protectors are but subjects, and this staff</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102070">But shows me under whose command I am. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102080">Is this our hindrance that our mother first</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102090">Swelled with another? what her womb denied</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102100">Our head shall give, or we will lose our head,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102110">What was her labour to a crown? Perhaps</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102120">A monster might have filled her first, a thing</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102130">Of royal prodigy, and should this thing</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102140">Grow to be hooted to a crown before us? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102150">Or if that crowns be due to the most years,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102160">Why should the nephew be the uncle's lord? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102170">And laws of nations conquer those of nature? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102180">Nature intended sovereignty to them</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102190">Of sovereign understanding; to the rest,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102200">However aged, but subjection,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102210">Which Isabella would detain us in:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102220">And whilst she trusts to Naples, our sad brow</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102230">May sooner wear willow, than diadems. <stage xml:id="A01853-e102240">Enter Belgiosa</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102250">Returned so soon, my Belgiosa? thanks,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102260">Before I hear thy message, for thy haste. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e102270" who="A01853-belgiosa">
              <pb facs="11" n="5"/>
              <speaker>●el</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e102280">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102290">My lord, our sudden coming into France,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102300">Left fame behind us, where arrived, we craved</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102310">A private audience? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e102320" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>●f</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e102330">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102340">But had you it? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102350">Did not our enemies sharp espies descry</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102360">The depth of our hid counsels? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e102370" who="A01853-belgiosa">
              <speaker>●el</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e102380">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102390">They might first</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102400">Descry the subtle path of a swift ship,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102410">The voyage of a bullet, or of thought,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102420">Before your more mysterious purposes? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e102430" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>●f</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e102440">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102450">Then since we are alone, and in a place</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102460">Free from the bold intrusion of an eye,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102470">Feign us the prince to whom we sent you forth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102480">And speak our embassy unto ourself. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e102490" who="A01853-belgiosa">
              <speaker>●el</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e102500">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102510">Great prince, to have the offer of a crown</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102520">Is rare, and your felicity: my lord,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102530">Milan's protector, but your servant, knowing</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102540">The ancient right your predecessors had</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102550">In usurped Naples, by us woos your grace</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102560">(Consider unto what he woos your grace)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102570">Not to maintain his power, but make your own,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102580">To take a kingdom that e'en sighs for you. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102590">So shall the infamy of a lost crown</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102600">Rot in the earth with your dead ancestors,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102610">And the recovery revive their names</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102620">To wait upon your triumph with your foes:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102630">For so much justice needs no other power,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102640">And yet such is your power, that it is able</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102650">To make whatever you should fancy, just:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102660">But that your virtue is above that power. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102670">I will not call you usurer of fame,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102680">By this large act, when the astonished world</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102690">Now fifty ages off from us, shall read</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102700">Not in the boastings of a painted tomb</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102710"><pb facs="12" n="6"/> (The flatteries of great rottenness) but your 〈…〉</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102720">Writ in 〈…〉 s true characters,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102730">For making conquered crowns the rudiments</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102740">Of your victorious infancy in arms,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102750">When France shall know no other Charlemagne. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e102760" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e102770">But should we fail in the attempt? what then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e102780" who="A01853-belgiosa">
              <speaker>Belg.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e102790">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102800">Can heaven fail justice? or those powers commit</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102810">Sins which they punish? O my gracious lord</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102820">Sin not with that weak thought: but if they should</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102830">Sforza will never:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e102840" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e102850">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102860">He is always noble,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102870">But he'll undo us with a benefit,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102880">To give a kingdom is above requital. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e102890" who="A01853-belgiosa">
              <speaker>Belg.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e102900">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102910">His hopes are but the praise of honest deeds,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102920">If in the rearward of your spreading fame,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102930">That fills all mouths, some happy tongue may glance</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102940">At him, as a poor engine of your glory,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102950">That could impart, but not possess a fame. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e102960" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e102970">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102980">Excellent man, if to this welcome speech</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e102990">Thou givest as fair an answer. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e103000" who="A01853-belgiosa">
              <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e103010">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103020">This in brief</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103030">After some scruple, and a little pause</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103040">He whispered he would come. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e103050" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e103060">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103070">Exactly done. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103080">But leave us now, my noble Belgiosa,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103090">Till we may study a reward for thee. <stage xml:id="A01853-e103100">●x. Belg.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103110">The twilight hastens, when Vitellio</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103120">And Malatesta one of an high trust<stage xml:id="A01853-e103130">E 〈…〉 Vitell. and 〈…〉.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103140">With our fond nephew, promised conference. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103150">And here they are. Is it decreed brave friends ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103160">Shall it be swiftly done▪ nay, 'tis no matter,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103170">Your colour says you dare not. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e103180" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e103190">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103200">It lies then:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103210">If that my colour show me disobedient</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103220"><pb facs="12" n="7"/> to my good lord, be I for ever pale:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103230">But when shall Galeazzo's wished-for death</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103240">Show we dare somewhat? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e103250" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>●f</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e103260">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103270">We would gladly have</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103280">A poison teach him linger to his death,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103290">And a month hence we shall expect his knell. <stage xml:id="A01853-e103300">Ex.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103310">Now are we entered, and now to retire</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103320">Were the worse treason: like an enraged fire</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103330">The more we are opposed, the more we'll spread</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103340">And make our foes our fuel: to be head</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103350">We'll cut off any member, and condemn</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103360">Virtue of folly for a diadem,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103370">Banish religion, and make blood as cheap</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103380">As when two armies turned into one heap</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103390">Of carcases, lie groveling , what care we</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103400">For the slight tainture of disloyalty? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103410">None will commend the race till it be run,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103420">And these are deeds not praised till they are done. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e103430">
            <head>Scaena tertia.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e103440">Juliano, Picinino.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e103450" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>●ul</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e103460">My Picinino, holds this sad news true?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e103470" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pici.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e103480">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103490">My Juliano, yes; 'tis in each voice</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103500">That some persuasion flattering Ferdinand,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103510">That the French journey was but a report,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103520">Made him revoke Alphonso, his brave son,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103530">Who with an army had endangered us:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103540">For the wise old man fearing, a deep fear</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103550">Might arm an enemy, else too weak for him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103560">And make us hasten the French war, gave o'er</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103570"><pb facs="13" n="8"/> his war with us: but when he understands</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103580">That all this quiet does not purchase peace,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103590">The cozened prince seeks the sure peace of death,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103600">And leaves his ruin to destroy his son. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e103610" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e103620">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103630">Will the French come? then prithee, death, come too. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103640">Why should our eyes dulled to all other sights</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103650">By age and sorrow, be reserved for sight</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103660">Of war and sorrow? O discourteous heavens! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103670">Why have you dallied with us to white hairs? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103680">Why kept till this time, must we perish now? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103690">O wherefore are we come so near the grave</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103700">And are not in it yet? yet pardon me</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103710">Good heaven, your acts are above question:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103720">Yet I may shed these tears for Italy;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103730">Slave of that world, which once, her valour slaved,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103740">Restoring back her triumphs with her spoil,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103750">Distracted in herself, and only fit</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103760">To make a bankrupt poet heal his credit</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103770">With matter for fresh tragedies. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e103780" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e103790">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103800">Good heaven! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103810">Is this to ease misfortune, or increase it? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103820">If passion could whine out felicity,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103830">Or plenteous tears could drown unhappiness,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103840">I have eyes too, and they contain their showers,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103850">Nor would I ere be niggard of a grief. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103860">But tears being only tears, an easy de●</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103870">Of childish eyes, and all the rest of grief</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103880">Commanding smiles, more than compassion,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103890">I thank my genius I am resolute</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103900">To laugh at fortune when she is most angry ▪</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e103910" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e103920">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103930">Such laughter may have little mirth in it,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103940">And I shall have more comfort in a tear. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e103950" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e103960">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103970">You may, good fountain, y●●, drop on, to so,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103980">If so much moisture will revive thy cheeks</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e103990"><pb facs="13" n="9"/> whilst I'll be young with laughter. I am he</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104000">That fears a sorrow, more than misery. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e104010">
            <head>Scaena quarta.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104020" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vitellio.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104030">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104040">This is the place, and this the time: good heaven! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104050">What an odd place, and what an uncouth time? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104060">Had I been hired to murder Sforza here,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104070">Hell could not prompt more fit occasion. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104080">I like nor it, nor him: but here he comes. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e104090">Ent. Sforza.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104100" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104110">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104120">Welcome Vitellio, thy haste is welcome:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104130">Nay compliment with him, whom thou wouldst kill,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104140">Be free to us as we do know thee true. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104150">Speak, yet I need not bid thee, for thine eye</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104160">Sparkles a joyful answer. It is done. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104170" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104180">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104190">'Tis done my lord, and now my lord, 'tis told</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104200">(That Galeazzo is no more a man)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104210">And with an even scruple, for to me</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104220">The act's as easy as relation. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104230" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104240">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104250">Thou speak'st true manhood: 'tis thy art alone</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104260">That gives us certain honour: there are some</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104270">Strive for eternity with loss of life,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104280">At least with hazard of the loss of it,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104290">And think they are revenged when they are killed? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104300">These are our valiant duelists, and these</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104310">Do bleed whilst we do conquer ▪ heal their wounds,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104320">While we receive none: then, at last, unfold</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104330">(Man of deep art, that canst prevent the fates,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104340">And cut a thread, which they had thought to spun</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104350">Forty years younger) thy wise mysteries. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104360"><pb facs="14" n="10"/>Thy constant, 〈…〉 failing 〈…〉,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104370">Which cause a death, without a fear of death,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104380" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104390">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104400">Here are some drugs, but of these some, not one</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104410">But can command a life where ere it is,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104420">And ruinate the strongest workmanship</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104430">That heaven ere bragged to have composed of earth. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104440">Powders of speedy fate, but above all</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104450">The instruments, which make me near to death</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104460">Of such endeared familiarity,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104470">This glass has nimblest operation:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104480">Whose liquor cast upon the face of man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104490">Straight dulls him to an everlasting sleep. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104500" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104510">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104520">Is this the liquor of eternity? <stage xml:id="A01853-e104530">Vitellio fall as dead ▪</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104540">Then take thy lethe, and go sleep for ever. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104550" who="A01853-malatesta">
              <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104560">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104570">I am deceived, or esse this is the place<stage xml:id="A01853-e104580">Enter Malas.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104590">Which Sforza chooseth when he is alone. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104600">Yes, this is it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104610" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104620">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104630">What Malatesta come? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104640">What devil brought him hither? O cross stars ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104650">Be sudden, Sforza, now, or thou art lost:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104660">He must believe our guilt was accident. <stage xml:id="A01853-e104670">My fa●●● upon Vitellio.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104680">Speak, my Vitellio ▪ oh tune thy lips</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104690">But to one syllable, but to one groan</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104700">And I am satisfied. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104710" who="A01853-malatesta">
              <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104720">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104730">What fight is here? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104740">Vitellio dead, and Sforza turned a mourner? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104750" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104760">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104770">Shouldst thou die thus, how would my name be soiled ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104780">For though I am at guiltless of thy death,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104790">As innocence, or if there be a name</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104800">That hath less being: yet the envious world</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104810">Will quit curst fortune of so great a crime,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104820">And give it me: yet speak. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104830" who="A01853-malatesta">
              <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104840">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104850">I' 〈…〉 my lord,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104860">To ask your 〈…〉 when 〈…〉 chance</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104870"><pb facs="14" n="11"/> first frighted heaven? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104880" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104890">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104900">Now, Malatesta, now ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104910">When could unhappiness reign so, but now? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104920">As if he meant to be before his lord,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104930">He had no sooner told the prince must die,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104940">But he straight died. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e104950" who="A01853-malatesta">
              <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e104960">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104970">Then courage, my good lord. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104980">Since it is thus, make the best use of it:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e104990">For now you need not fear to be revealed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105000">When one mouth's stopped, and th'other is your own:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105010">But since your last retirement, we have been</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105020">Instructed by the speed of frequent posts,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105030">Of the a rival of the King of France. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e105040" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e105050">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105060">With thanks, a while, my Malatesta, leave us. <stage xml:id="A01853-e105070">●x.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105080">Why should we longer think of other powers,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105090">And not bring offerings now to our own brain? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105100">Which gives us agents of all kinds of men,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105110">And Kings as well as poisoners: this w●●e King</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105120">Must trouble Naples, who would trouble us,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105130">Divert invasions which are yet not made,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105140">And thus our ends are cheaply brought about,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105150">We only at the charge of plot: they fight,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105160">And Galiazzo dies, whom either King</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105170">Were they not thus entangled, would preserve:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105180">We shall be conquerors without fighting thus,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105190">And their poor swords shall cut a way for us.<stage xml:id="A01853-e105200">Surgio Vitellio.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105210">I'm for you France. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e105220" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e105230">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105240">And I am for you, Sforza,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105250">Not poisoned yet, unless 'twere by thy tears. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105260">The other liquor had an antidote. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105270">Happy suspect! had I been credulous</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105280">And thought his love as free as it would seem</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105290">I had not been, distrust has ransomed me. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105300">But Malatesta is entrapped, I know</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105310"><pb facs="15" n="22"/> Sforza for nothing did not ask the skill ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105320">My equal villain perishes, and I</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105330">Thus being accessary to his death</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105340">May sin to innocence, by posting off</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105350">The prince's fate to him: whilst a disguise</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105360">Shall keep alive the fame that I am dead. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105370">And thus half truth shall come to light, and I,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105380">Be wisely cleared by double villainy. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e105390">●● ▪</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e105400">
            <head>Scaena quinta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e105410">Caiazzo, Sanseverin, Malvezzo.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e105420" who="A01853-sanseverin">
              <speaker>Sans.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e105430">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105440">As I am noble, 'twas a glorious sight,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105450">To see two princes, in their state at once:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105460">As if two suns had harmlessly conspired</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105470">To beautify, and not to fright the heavens. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105480">Why should the formal nicety of state</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105490">Debar these often interviews? I think</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105500">They would be medicine against tyranny:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105510">For, when a prince sees all things under him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105520">Heads of eternal nakedness, and men</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105530">That make their glory of their servitude ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105540">He thinks he's uncontrollable, that none</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105550">Without a saucy imputation</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105560">Dares warn him to his duty: but suppose</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105570">An equal majesty should once become</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105580">His usual object, one, whose unchecked blood</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105590">Runs full as high as his, than he does learn,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105600">That there's a commonwealth of princes too,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105610">Not one sole monarch ▪</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e105620" who="A01853-caiazzo">
              <speaker>Cai.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e105630">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105640">Yet, Sanseverin,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105650">If you observed some clouds obscured both suns,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105660"><pb facs="15" n="23"/> for, when they smiled most freely, and expressed</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105670">Their nearest friendship by a strict embrace,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105680">They looked so jealously, as if they feared</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105690">A closer stab: and then the King took leave</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105700">With that excess of haste, that one would think</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105710">(After this eager preparation,)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105720">He did intend his journey to leave us,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105730">Not to win Naples. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e105740" who="A01853-malatesta">
              <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e105750">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105760">'Tis a dangerous time,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105770">(And yet I seem to cross the truth I speak</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105780">When I not fear to call't a dangerous time)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105790">Sforza is overwise, and so attempts</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105800">Upon the confidence of his own brain</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105810">(A brain, though wise, yet I may safely say,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105820">Within the possibility of error)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105830">Things, that can only hap by miracle</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105840">To any good. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e105850" who="A01853-sanseverin">
              <speaker>Sans.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e105860">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105870">Why, what can happen ill? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105880">Fear you a war? and what's to be feared there? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105890">Lest that a mortal die, lest that the life</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105900">Due to a knotty gout, or grating stone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105910">Have a more easy period by the sword. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105920">Let them fear war, who fear to see their gold ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105930">Lest that the sun should have a sight with them ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105940">Holding so much of earth, they're turned to it,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105950">Who have no more life than their dirty acres,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105960">Men, I may say, in the worst part of men. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105970">And why like these run we an idle race</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105980">Of threescore years, and then sneak to a death? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e105990">Whilst soldiers master their mortality</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106000">And die by men, if that at all they die. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106010">Malvezzo know, when all things sifted are,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106020">Peace only pleaseth them that never knew war. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A01853-e106030">
          <pb facs="16" n="24"/>
          <head>Actus secundi</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e106040">
            <head>Scaena prima.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e106050">Juliano, Picinino.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106060" who="A01853-julia">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e106070">Herded you the general whispering ▪</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106080" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e106090">No, what i 〈…〉</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106100" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e106110">The Duke is ill. —</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106120" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e106130">And do they whisper that ▪</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106140" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e106150">Yes: and, they say, he has strange fits.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106160" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e106170">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106180">How strange</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106190">Is poison strange in Italy ▪ why, know,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106200">As princes live above the vulgar, so</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106210">Their death has a prerogative: mean men</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106220">May dream away their time to fourscore years,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106230">And when their rotten joints drop to their dust ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106240">Only some trivial infirmity,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106250">A palsy, or an ague bears the blame:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106260">But 'tis not state for princes to be old,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106270">And yet they must not be supposed to die</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106280">By the respectless treason of disease,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106290">But by some strange unheard ▪ of accident</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106300">That fate did never dream of: but no more,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106310">You know Vitellio, and the height of grace</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106320">Sforza has showed him ▪ 'tis suspicious</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106330">When wisdom flatters villainy: then come,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106340">Let us be private, and discourse some treason. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e106350"><pb facs="16" n="25"/>Enter, after solemn music, Sforza, Sanseverin, Caiazzo, and soldiers: when after some private whispering they depart several ways.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106360" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e106370">But stay, my Picinino, who are here?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106380" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e106390">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106400">O the grand favourite, Sanseverin,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106410">A most full bubble, valiant vanity:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106420">That in high terms can swear down fortresses,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106430">Blow away armies with a powerful breath,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106440">And spoil the enemy before he sees him:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106450">But when he comes to action, lie as still,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106460">As in the tale, that lumpish King of frogs,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106470">Which Jove did give them in his merriment. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106480">Were tilting valour, I never knew a man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106490">Of larger worth: could he but break the ranks</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106500">Of enemies as well as he does spears,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106510">Milan never saw a braver general. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106520">But there's his brother too. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106530" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e106540">Ay, that's the man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106550" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e106560">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106570">('tis wonder we can know so much of him)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106580">He that can sound the depth of that sly brain</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106590">Has a large plummet, trust me Julian,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106600">An hundred lawyers make up that one head,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106610">And scarcely too: quick Proteus to him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106620">To this Caiazzo was an idiot,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106630">A plain flat idiot, I tell thee man,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106640">Meander never knew so many windings ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106650">If, as they say, an emulation</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106660">Is bred by likeness, I do wonder much</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106670">How Sforza is induced to employ him. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106680">Who has more devil in him, than himself. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106690" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e106700">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106710">But why is this employment? why these arms? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106720"><pb facs="17" n="16"/>When all but Naples are our friends, and they</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106730">Not able now to show themselves our foes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106740">Engaged, and almost lost in the French war. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106750" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e106760">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106770">Tricks, Juliano, statists call them arts,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106780">Not to be fadomed by a vulgar reach:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106790">But though I want the villainy to know,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106800">Yet I have so much spleen to laugh at them;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106810">And take a comfort in this plainer sense:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106820">No subtlety can cozen providence. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e106830">
            <head>Scaena secunda.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e106840">Ascanio, Galeazzo, Isabella, Julia.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106850" who="A01853-ascanio">
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e106860">How rests the prince?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106870" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Isab.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e106880">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106890">O my good lord, he rests ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106900">But 'tis a quiet, such as the seas have,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106910">When that the winds have spent their violence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106920">And out of impotence bestow a calm:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106930">'Tis more a death, than slumber, you may see</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106940">His senses rather weary, then at rest. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106950" who="A01853-ascanio">
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e106960">Are then his fits so raging?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e106970" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Isab.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e106980">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e106990">Nothing else,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107000">Should he but wake, you'd think two armies met ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107010">And strove together for the loudest shout. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107020">Disease has spread herself o'er all his parts,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107030">And only spared his tongue, as if some star</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107040">Not knowing otherwise to clear itself</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107050">From imputation of tyranny,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107060">For such exact plaguing of innocence</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107070"><pb facs="17" n="17"/> had left him that to curse withal, that so</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107080">To all that heard his fury, he might seem</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107090">To be thus tortured for his blasphemy. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107100" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 all</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e107110">Water, some water.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107120" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 ab.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e107130">Now the fit begins:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107140" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 all</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107150">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107160">Some of my slaves run, and exhaust the ●o,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107170">Charge him no more to vent his idle streams</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107180">Into the glutted main, but rather pour</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107190">All his moist mouths on me: d'ye stare, begone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107200">Use not your eyes at all, unless to weep:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107210">And that, not tears of sorrow; but of help,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107220">Such as may cool me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107230" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 c.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107240">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107250">Patience, sweet prince,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107260">Add not unto the fire of your disease,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107270">The heat of passion. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107280" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 l.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107290">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107300">What red thing is this? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107310">Ha, Isabella, tell me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107320" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107330">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107340">'Tis your uncle. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107350">The noble prince Ascanio. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107360" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 l.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107370">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107380">'Tis false;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107390">He is nor prince, nor noble: hark you friends,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107400">He talks of passion, and of patience,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107410">Let him discourse of Aetna, or Vesuvius,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107420">Or of a greater heat than I do feel,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107430">And I will answer him: patience to me? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107440">Go bid rough seas be patient. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107450" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 c.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107460">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107470">He grows worse,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107480">And opposition does inflame him more:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107490">Methinks I see his eyelids faintly strive,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107500">Against death's closing. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107510" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 l.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107520">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107530">O! my joints are fire,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107540">Why does not heaven shed cataracts, and lower</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107550">Once to my comfort? are they hot as I,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107560">Have they no moisture, for a suppliant? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107570"><pb facs="18" n="18"/>Then, though hot heaven oppose, when once my br 〈…〉</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107580">Hath left this corpse, I'll have a cold by death. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107590" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107600">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107610">Herded you that groan my lord — o he is dead:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107620">Crack then ye tardy heart strings, quickly crack,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107630">And give me leave to overtake the fligh ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107640">Of my dead husband. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107650" who="A01853-ascanio">
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107660">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107670">What is passed our help,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107680">Let it be passed our grief: 'tis fortitude</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107690">To suffer chances counterbuffs as one</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107700">That by his expectation had deceived</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107710">All her faint threatenings: till this sadder time</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107720">Your life has had one constant scene of joy,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107730">Which here is interrupted: you should thank</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107740">The heavens because they were not tedious</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107750">In their delights: for this variety. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107760">As hunger praiseth feasts, so it may be</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107770">You'll love joy better for this misery. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e107780">
            <head>Scaena tertia.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e107790">Sforza, Beatrice.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107800" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107810">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107820">How covetous thou art to learn mishap? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107830">Beatrice the answer kills thee. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107840" who="A01853-bettrice">
              <speaker>Bet.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107850">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107860">Kill me then,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107870">But not deny me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107880" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107890">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107900">Dearest, I am lost,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107910">And in my ruin, thou. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107920" who="A01853-bettrice">
              <speaker>Bet.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107930">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107940">I would be so,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107950">Safety were ruin were it otherwise. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107960">Yet tell me Sforza, how are you so lost? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e107970" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e107980">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e107990">O what a busy torture woman is! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108000">I must say somewhat, but the main is silence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108010">Vitellio's loss, yes, that hath lost me too:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108020"><pb facs="18" n="19"/> no sooner killed than lost, so strangely gone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108030">As if the dead had learned a motion</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108040">So to convey themselves unto the grave. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108050">Will you be still unkind? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e108060" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e108070">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108080">Thou shalt hear all ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108090">The French have conquered Naples, and which draws</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108100">Blood from our soul, without a drop of blood:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108110">When thus we plotted it, that when both Kings</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108120">Had wearied out themselves with equal slaughter,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108130">And here Alphonso tottered, and there Charles;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108140">When loss had seized the conqueror, than we</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108150">Would have amazed the conqueror afresh</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108160">With new alarms: when by the flattery</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108170">Of chance, France gets a kingdom without blood,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108180">And by dry victory has undone a plot</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108190">Worth many kingdoms: I presumed on this,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108200">Naples had soldiers enough to last</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108210">Killing a year, in which space, we resolved</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108220">To arm all Italy against the French,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108230">And cunningly drive out, whom we called in:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108240">Which, ere we could accomplish, is disclosed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108250">And conquering France intends to hinder it,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108260">By our invasion: o my policy! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108270">Must I be wounded with the sword I gave? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108280">And find those enemies, whom only I</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108290">Enabled to my injury? well; heaven,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108300">Your kindness is a miracle sometime,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108310">Beyond all reason, but your curse is wit,<stage xml:id="A01853-e108320">Enter Ascan.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108330">My fault is my fault's punisher. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e108340" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 c.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e108350">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108360">Long life,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108370">And happy to our Duke. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e108380" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e108390">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108400">How my Ascanio? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108410">Recall thyself, good Cardinal, what Duke? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108420">Whilst Galeazzo lives? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e108430" who="A01853-ascanio">
              <pb facs="19" n="20"/>
              <speaker>As●.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e108440">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108450">Most truly Duke,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108460">For Galeazzo's dead. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e108470" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e108480">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108490">Alas, poor child,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108500">I could have wished thee longer life, but since</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108510">Heaven's will is otherwise, 'twere blasphemy</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108520">To storm at that which is the will of heaven. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108530">I hate that impotent rebellion. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e108540">Enter Sanseu.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e108550" who="A01853-sanseverin">
              <speaker>Sans.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e108560">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108570">My lord, so cross was fortune, that you were</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108580">Made almost bankrupt by a too much thrift:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108590">For when you had discharged those numerous troops,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108600">Whose charges lay as hard upon the state</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108610">As an invasion could, than Orleans moved</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108620">And stole Novarra, which disastrous news</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108630">So heated the remainder of your troops</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108640">(As if you had added to their valour more,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108650">When you abated from their multitudes)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108660">That by a nimble victory, they made</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108670">His conquest be his prison. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e108680" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e108690">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108700">Noble friend</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108710">Stand thou, and our state stands: o why do men</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108720">Cry out on age, on eating age? as though</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108730">Our many griefs were from our many years,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108740">And the last times were worst: we rather find</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108750">That nothing is so dangerous to Kings</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108760">As a young principality: for 'tis</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108770">With them almost as with young plants, which yield</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108780">Unto the least entreaty of the wind,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108790">And need no stronger blast, but gaining age</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108800">Scarce stoop to thunder: may we once arise</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108810">Unto this happy firmness of estate,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108820">This blessed maturity of prince, we stand</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108830">Fearless of fall, but if heaven envy us</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108840">And have decreed our ruin with our rising,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108850">Yet such we'll have it void of all base fears</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108860">Our foes shall grieve our ruin was not theirs. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e108870">
            <pb facs="19" n="21"/>
            <head>Scaena quarta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e108880">Caiazzo, Belgiosa, Malvezzo.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e108890" who="A01853-malatesta">
              <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e108900">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108910">My lords, since we are met so happily,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108920">(If you esteem me not too bo●d, to ask</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108930">The story of your high famed actions) ●</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108940">Bless me with the relation. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e108950" who="A01853-caiazzo">
              <speaker>Cai</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e108960">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108970">I much fear</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108980">Mine are not worthy your attention:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e108990">Yet if it please you, noble Belgiosa,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109000">(Because my story will depend on that)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109010">To show the reason why the giddy French,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109020">So strangely left their conquest: such your power,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109030">Such a full conquest have you of your friend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109040">I'll shame myself for your content. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e109050" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 l.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e109060">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109070">Then, thus:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109080">From us France hurried thorough Lombary</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109090">And fled to conquer, who had seen that haste</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109100">Would easily supposed it to have been</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109110">Rather a flight then an invasion. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109120">The Pope quakes at the progress, and admits</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109130">Young Ferd'nand into Rome, that if the French</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109140">Should dare a fight, they might find Naples there. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109150">France slights that fainter opposition,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109160">And speaks his scorn in thunder, Naples flies,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109170">And all his army hath no other use</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109180">Then to become unwilling harbingers</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109190">To show their lodgings to the conquering French ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109200">Who like fierce winds that sweep away their lets,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109210">Or like encroaching tides, take swiftly in</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109220">The offered countries, not defended, now</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109230">Saint german yields, and saucy Capua</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109240"><pb facs="20" n="22"/> that dared a competition once with Rome,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109250">Aversa takes the precedent, and now</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109260">The King of Naples finds home foes, and such</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109270">As durst be valiant against their prince,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109280">And use their fond arms in a mutiny,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109290">Which were not safe enough for a defence. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109300">He taking the advantage of thou crime</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109310">Unconquered by the French, to these he yields,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109320">And chooseth rather to become no prince</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109330">Then keep the crown, which they would take away. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e109340" who="A01853-malatesta">
              <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e109350">What was the issue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e109360" who="A01853-belgiosa">
              <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e109370">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109380">Strangely pitiful:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109390">He that had navies yesterday, has now</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109400">Scarce a bark left him, scarce a plank or two,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109410">To trust him to the mercy of the seas,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109420">The seas more courteous than the multitude:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109430">In which he makes for Ischia, and leaves</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109440">His enemy his successor. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e109450" who="A01853-caiazzo">
              <speaker>Cai.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e109460">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109470">And he</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109480">(As I have seen some wavering amourist)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109490">Neglects his conquest for the laziness,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109500">For when 'twas certain f●r ●●●a●d was fled,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109510">Whilst they might justly yet fear his return,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109520">The French return, as if they meant to try</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109530">Which would be soonest weary of the haste,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109540">Who had the swifter pace to 〈…〉 away:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e109550" who="A01853-belgiosa">
              <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e109560">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109570">That is 〈…〉 act of new governors,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109580">Such storeys are as an 〈…〉 as the world. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109590">Till they do try what they can do, they think</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109600">They may do all things, their first act is ●●●●●</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109610">(As if they meant 〈…〉 to kill then reign)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109620">It matters not upon what ground ▪ there is</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109630">Pretence enough to quit a conqueror</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109640">From the least show of 〈…〉 y: but then</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109650"><pb facs="20" n="23"/> when they have felt the least of wars extremes</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109660">They rave, they faint, they cross what they first did,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109670">And are e'en weary of a victory. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e109680" who="A01853-caiazzo">
              <speaker>Cai.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e109690">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109700">France made this certain truth, who in his brags</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109710">Had sworn the fall of Mahomet: but now</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109720">When he might hear the groans of Graecia</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109730">Delivered by the echoes of their sea,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109740">To make them more, he thinks on a retreat,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109750">And chooseth home before a victory ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109760">It was a valley, where our Taro laves</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109770">The root of Apennine, and a large plain</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109780">Sphered with a row of swelling earth makes war</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109790">A spacious amphitheatre: where we</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109800">Stayed for their coming; when mature advice</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109810">That crowns most actions, strangely injured us,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109820">For rashness would have stolen a victory</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109830">Which tedious consultation gave away. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109840">Success had smiled on our temerity</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109850">Had we assaulted them upon the hills</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109860">And added to the mountains with the French. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109870">But I am tedious: only our van fought,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109880">And 'twas the Frenchmens victory to resist:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109890">Both were o'ercome, both conquerors, for they</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109900">Still kept the field, and we still kept the prey. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e109910" who="A01853-belgiosa">
              <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e109920">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109930">O what is valour joined with modesty! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109940">This conquers both your fortune and your skill. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109950">Should you but write a story; and profess</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109960">That pureness from all passion which you've shown. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109970">You would be credited, though 'twere your own. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109980">But what reward is't to be but believed? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e109990">You shall be ever praised: what you have done</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110000">Fears neither envy, nor oblivion:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110010">And for this act succession shall see</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110020">Caiazzo as long-lived as Italy ▪</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e110030">
            <pb facs="21" n="24"/>
            <head>Scaena quinta.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e110040" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vitellio disguised.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e110050">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110060">I wonder Malatesta still survives:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110070">Sure Sforza has forgotten himself; my death</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110080">Does but half clear him, and if th'other live,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110090">He cannot look for a full innocence. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110100">It is not mercy, certainly: o, no,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110110">Mercy with him is folly: but 'tmay be</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110120">He fears that had he killed us both at once</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110130">Rumor would be too busy, and all mouths</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110140">Would cry, that chance had too much project in't. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110150">This is the place of destiny, 'tis here</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110160">Sforza does actuate his bloody arts,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110170">Mistaking privacy for innocence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110180">And thinks he's good, because he is not seen ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110190">Here must I wait for a discovery. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e110200">Enter Sforza.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e110210" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e110220">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110230">I must once more be cruel, yet not I,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110240">This is the murder of necessity:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110250">But what has he deserved, who has done naught</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110260">But what we charged, and so performed our thought? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110270">Is death due to obedience 〈…〉 can this hand</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110280">Yield to his fate, that sealed to his command? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110290">Yet he, or I must perish: shall I see</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110300">My life, my honour, my eternity ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110310">Lie at his mercy, and be safe, so long</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110320">As he is pleased to temper his rude tongue? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110330">Till he be drunk, or treacherous? I'll first</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110340">Study amongst all actions, which is worst</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110350">And overact it ▪ though our former deed</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110360">Was from ambition, this is yet from need:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110370"><pb facs="21" n="25"/> death is too good reward for such a slave,<stage xml:id="A01853-e110380">Enter Malatesta.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110390">And sure there is no blabbing in the grave. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110400">But here he comes: why are thy looks so grim? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110410">Why, Malatesta, in thy furrowed face</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110420">See I the signs of anger, or of grief? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110430">Command thy face to a more smiling form,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110440">That I may think thee pleased when thou dost tell</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110450">What does displease thee. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e110460" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 all</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e110470">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110480">'Twas a foolish dream,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110490">That stole my colour from my paler cheeks. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110500">Last night I saw Vitellio. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e110510" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈◊〉.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e110520">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110530">And what? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110540">Canst thou fear shadows? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e110550" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 all</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e110560">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110570">Yes if shadows speak,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110580">If that their threatenings be substantial. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110590">From such a paper as your highness holds,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110600">He forced me breath in death. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e110610" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 f.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e110620">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110630">This paper holds</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110640">A strange perfume, of such a cunning virtue,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110650">That at a distance it scarce smells at all. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110660">And at the nose it gives the best of scents. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110670">Make the experiment:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e110680" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 all</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e110690">O! I am slain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e110700" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈◊〉.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e110710">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110720">Heav'ns what a stillness here is? what a death</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110730">Of the whole man at once? the wand'ring eye</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110740">Now finds a station, and the busy pulse</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110750">Is now for ever idle: where's the tongue</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110760">That but e'en now could say as much as this,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110770">When that the soul could prompt it? but e'en now</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110780">Here was a thing could speak, and poison too,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110790">That knew more ways to kill, than ever heaven</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110800">Did to make man: and could his subtlety,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110810">That could give death, not know to keep out death? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110820">Fie, what a bulk it is, what a great lump</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110830"><pb facs="22" n="26"/> of nothing, that shall lose that nothing too? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110840">What a dead toy is man, when his thin breath</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110850">Flies to its kindred air? O why at all</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110860">Did heaven bestow, or why at all bereave</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110870">Man of this vapour of eternity? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110880">And must we one day be a stock like this,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110890">Fit only to enrich the greedy earth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110900">And fill an house of death, perhaps before</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110910">We see the issue of another plot? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110920">Must we lie subject to be trampled on,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110930">By some, perhaps not politicians? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110940">Where's then our wisdom? our deep providence</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110950">Are they dirt too? O heavens! but if they are</l>
              </lg>
              <stage xml:id="A01853-e110960">Enter some negroes to carry away the body</stage>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e110970">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110980">Or dirt ▪ or nothing, I'll enjoy my fame. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e110990">And rottenness shall seize me, not my name. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111000" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e111010">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111020">Are those the instruments? well my black friends,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111030">I eased you of a labour: all succeeds</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111040">According to the flattery of my wish,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111050">And my suspicion turns to prophecy. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111060">But my so bloody, and so wary Sforza,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111070">Your agent's dead, but not your crime: 'twill out,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111080">And by this carcase: I will fly to France,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111090">Divulge loud papers, — they are writ already, —</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111100">And here they are, these I will swear were found</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111110">In the dead poisoner's pockets: by this means</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111120">Sforza's proclaimed a murderer, I'm freed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111130">And make it be his guilt, which was my deed. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e111140">Vitellio going forth meets with Isabella.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e111150">
            <pb facs="22" n="27"/>
            <head>Scaena quinta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e111160">Vitellio, Isabella, Julia.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111170" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e111180">Madam I have some news of that import, that (If you please to command privacy) will both desire, and fright your patience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111190" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e111200">Be brief.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111210" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e111220">First know I am Vitellio. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111230" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e111240">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111250">Thou art a villain, and a poisoner then,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111260">Hast thou a drug for us? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111270" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e111280">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111290">Yes such an one</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111300">Shall make you love a poison: read, and wonder. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111310" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e111320">I do: and more, how thou couldst purchase this without a guilt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111330" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e111340">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111350">I did peruse the spoils</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111360">Of Malatesta's carcase, whom I found</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111370">Most strangely guilty, and as strangely dead,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111380">Whose pockets furnished me with these instructions. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111390" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e111400">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111410">Thus we learn murder from thy felony:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111420">But what should make me trust a confessed rogue? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111430" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e111440">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111450">My villainy: my credit is my crime:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111460">Had not I stole, you had not understood. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111470" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e111480">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111490">I must believe't: but dar'st thou poison well? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111500">Commit a crime, which thou mayst glory of? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111510" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e111520">On whom dear lady?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111530" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e111540">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111550">Nay I care not whom. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111560">But I can give reward to a wise crime. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111570" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e111580">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111590">My quick dispatch shall make you gladly know</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111600">I understand, what you desire, and hide. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e111610">Exit.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111620" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e111630">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111640">Now should he poison Sforza. O fond hope! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111650">That mak'st us think all true that we desire. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111660">Should he betray us now? for what? that we</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111670"><pb facs="23" n="28"/> entreated him to kill, we knew not whom. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111680">By this expression thus much I have won:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111690">I may be made, but cannot be undone. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e111700">
            <head>Scaena sext●.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e111710" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Picinino.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e111720">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111730">Fortune is merry, and the heaven disposed</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111740">To play with me, I am turned favourite. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111750">Methinks my hairs ashamed of their white hue</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111760">Should blush to youth: oh how I could look big,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111770">Take giant strides, dote on my lovely self,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111780">And talk as silly as any lord. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111790">To see the prettiness of action,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111800">Of state-employment: Sforza's to be crowned,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111810">And I must win the popular suffrages. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111820">Good heavens! was ever such a merry load</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111830">Imposed on man: some cry the times are ill,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111840">Others could wish them better, and a third</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111850">Knows how to make all well, but tells not how,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111860">And, cause that he is silent, would be wise. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111870">But in conclusion I do find them ready</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111880">(On supposition of no more expense,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111890">And that their voice is sued for, not their purse)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111900">To give a lusty acclamation. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e111910"><pb facs="23" n="29"/>Sforza, 3 ambassadors, Caiazzo, Sanseverin, Malvezzo, as in procession, they offer up the French banners at the altar, whilst this is sung.</stage>
            <lg type="song" xml:id="A01853-e111920">
              <head>Song.</head>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e111930">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111940">Io, io, gladly sing,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111950">Till the heaven with wonder ring. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111960">He is fled, let Milan say</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111970">Once more, he is fled, the day</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111980">Clears again, and makes us see</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e111990">A braver light of victory. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112000">Io, io, etc. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e112010">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112020">Yet he had before he fought</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112030">(By the speedy war of thought)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112040">Conquered Italy, and so</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112050">Has hastened his own overthrow. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112060">Io, io, etc. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e112070">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112080">Henceforth let them learn to live</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112090">In the peace, that home doth give,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112100">Nor again so fondly rave,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112110">To travel for a foreign grave. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112120">Io, io, etc. </l>
              </lg>
            </lg>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e112130" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e112140">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112150">First we thank heaven, by whose most gracious aid</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112160">We have the means, and reason to thank you. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112170">Now we begin to lift up our faint heads,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112180">And entertain, though scarce believe a peace:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112190">Now Italy at length has lost her yoke,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112200">Which she was wont to give, but never bear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112210">And therefore wondered at the strangeness more</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112220"><pb facs="24" n="30"/> than at the weight of't: in this noble act</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112230">Sforza claims nothing but the happiness,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112240">Which he acknowledges received from you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e112250" who="A01853-ambassador_1">
              <speaker>1 Amb. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e112260">Sforza's deserts exceed the height of praise.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e112270" who="A01853-ambassador_2">
              <speaker>2 Amb. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e112280">He has slaved Italy by freeing it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e112290" who="A01853-ambassador_3">
              <speaker>3 Amb. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e112300">Milan must know him for her Romulus. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e112310" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e112320">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112330">We know ourself so underneath this praise,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112340">That could we but suspect untruth in you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112350">We'd call all this but mockery. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e112360" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e112370">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112380">D'ye doubt? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112390">Make you a question of the name of it? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112400">Why call it as it is, plain flattery. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e112410" who="A01853-caiazzo">
              <speaker>Caiaz.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e112420">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112430">We wondered lately at the prouder French,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112440">And gave too high a value to their acts:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112450">When in a serious estimation,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112460">Their chiefest victory was of the miles,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112470">And more a journey than a war: if they</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112480">Could gain a fame by nimble travelling,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112490">How shall we rear a trophy to his name,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112500">That made them go far faster than they came? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112510">For my part (Though I know his modesty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112520">Which will refuse the honours he deserves)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112530">I'd have him forced unto the government,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112540">To rule that happy land which he hath saved. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e112550">Omnes. A Sforza, a Sforza. Ascanio crowns him. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e112560" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e112570">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112580">Sforza will never gain say the general voice,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112590">Your love I like beyond your gift: kind heavens! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112600">Show by my governments integrity</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112610">You were the people's prompter, and I'll show</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112620">(If you but actuate my just desires)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112630">I only am their Duke in goodness: since</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112640">Milan hath chose, it shall applaud her prince. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A01853-e112650">
          <pb facs="24" n="31"/>
          <head>Actus tertii</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e112660">
            <head>Scaena prima.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e112670" who="A01853-galeazzi">
              <speaker>Vmbra Galeatii.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e112680">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112690">No rest in death? why then I see they err</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112700">That give a quiet to a sepulchre. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112710">'Tis our hard fate, nor can man choose but die,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112720">But where grief is, is immortality. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112730">This draws our juiceless bones to a new day,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112740">From Lethe's banks, where we have learned the way,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112750">(An easy learning) to return our woes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112760">And laugh at our misfortunes in our foes. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112770">We'll draw felicity out of our fall,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112780">And make our ghost revenge our funeral. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112790">That our dim eyes, and with pale death benighted,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112800">May by revenge be cleared, and we be righted</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112810">(If other punishment should come too slow)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112820">By the exacter justice of our foe. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112830">When being betrayed by them he trusted most,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112840">He shall be prisoner in a foreign coast,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112850">When wanting sustenance, his teeth shall chaw</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112860">His arms for food, and their once feeders gnaw. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112870">When hell shall have but part of him, when he</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112880">That now triumphs shall be less ghost than we. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e112890">
            <pb facs="25" n="32"/>
            <head>Scaena secunda.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e112900">Sforza ▪ Ascanio.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e112910" who="A01853-ascanio">
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e112920">Sforza, you are undone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e112930" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e112940">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112950">Why my Ascanio? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112960">Fortune is fearful of so foul a crime. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e112970" who="A01853-ascanio">
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e112980">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e112990">You durst be bad, and yet improvident,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113000">And so it is not fortunes, but your crime. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113010">Which shall I first begin to blame? your fault</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113020">Or (Pardon if I call it) foolishness:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113030">I faint to think that you are passed excuse,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113040">Both with the honest and the politic. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e113050" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e113060">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113070">Come nearer, my dear Cardinal, and tell</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113080">In easier terms what 'tis that troubles you:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113090">Is Galeazzo's death divulged? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e113100" who="A01853-ascanio">
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e113110">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113120">It is:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113130">The time, the manner, and the murderer,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113140">Nor am I free from th'imputation:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e113150" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e113160">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113170">You speak what you suspect, not what is true,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113180">Does speech come from the dead? can their dried nerves</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113190">Borrow a tongue for accusation? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113200">This is no other than the voice of guilt,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113210">The speech of our home-executioner:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113220">And yet I fear — and yet what should I fear? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113230">Blood hath strange organs to discourse withal,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113240">It is a clamorous orator, and then<stage xml:id="A01853-e113250">Enter Sanseverin, halberdeers and Vitel.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113260">Even nature will exceed herself to tell</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113270">A crime so thwarting nature. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e113280" who="A01853-sanseverin">
              <speaker>Sans.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e113290">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113300">My good lord,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113310">Pardon the zeal of my intrusion,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113320">I bring hidden danger with me: 'twas my chance</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113330">As I was passing to the bedchamber,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113340"><pb facs="25" n="33"/> just at the door to find this muffled man,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113350">Waiting some treacherous opportunity. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113360">Each circumstance swelled with suspicion,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113370">The place, the time, the person, all did seem</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113380">To bear a danger worthy of your fear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113390">At least your wiser disquisition. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e113400" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e113410">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113420">Thou art all goodness, and deservest of us</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113430">Beyond the niggardly reward of thanks:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113440">But what are you that thus be cloud your face,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113450">Who, not unlike that over-bashful fowl,<stage xml:id="A01853-e113460">He discourse himself.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113470">Delight in darkness? Ha! Vitellio! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113480">The wonder is resolved by a new wonder. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e113490">Ex. Sans.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e113500" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>Vit.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e113510">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113520">Sforza I live: d'ye stare? I live: these words</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113530">Are not the fond delusions of the air,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113540">As you officiously would gull yourself;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113550">But from a solid substance, had not we<stage xml:id="A01853-e113560">Enter Sans. with two negroes.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113570">Been by your diligent spy too soon surprised,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113580">Before our projects full maturity,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113590">Thy death more fully should have proved my life. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e113600" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e113610">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113620">Fool that I was, who thought to take thy life</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113630">By that which nourished it: there's none so mad</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113640">Would poison serpents, I'll work surely now,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113650">Once more I'll try your immortality. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113660">Strangle the monster. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e113670" who="A01853-vitellio">
              <speaker>〈…〉 it.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e113680">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113690">'Twas a doubtful chance</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113700">Within this hour who first should own those words. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113710">But, tyrant, weary thy invention</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113720">To find variety of punishment,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113730">Yet all that thou canst do, exceeds not this,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113740">A pin could do as much: weak, silly Sforza,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113750">All thou canst do to me exceeds not that</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113760">Which I did on the person of thy prince:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113770">Disease would prove a better murderer. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e113780" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>〈…〉 f.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e113790">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113800">Stop that malignant throat. — oh my Ascanio,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113810"><pb facs="26" n="34"/> thus must they toil which work an height by blood,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113820">How I could wish an innocent descent</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113830">To new subjection? how I hate that wish</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113840">How scorn all thoughts that have not danger in them ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113850">Get us more Remora's, sweet Cardinal,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113860">Or rather than to droop to idleness ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113870">We'll work to be no prince, ourself recalling:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113880">In rising, most, some wit there is in falling. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e113890">
            <head>Scaena tertia.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e113900" who="A01853-caiazzo">
              <speaker>Caiazzo.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e113910">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113920">Assist me, hell, for I intend an act,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113930">Which should your puny fiends but think upon,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113940">Would make their blacker cheeks receive a blush,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113950">Would give a redness which your weaker fire</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113960">Had never that heating power to work in them:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113970">An act, the heavens did only then declare</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113980">They would permit to be performed by man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e113990">When they created night: for were all day,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114000">Could such a crime be as well seen as done,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114010">Their immortality might justly fear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114020">Lest all the guilt should be removed on them,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114030">As idle, or as cruel lookers on,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114040">Whilst heaven, on earth did suffer: this black night</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114050">Must Isabella die, die, by this hand:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114060">This chapel is her ordinary walk,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114070">Discovered to me by her Julia,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114080">Where when she comes to see her husband's tomb,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114090">This hand shall make her fit for such a room. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e114100"><pb facs="26" n="35"/>Enter Isabella and Julia with two torches, she places them at either end of the tome, and exit. Isabella draws towards the tomb, and speaks.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e114110" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e114120">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114130">Prince of shades, (For unto me</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114140">Still thou keepest thy majesty)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114150">If thou art not wholly lost,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114160">And there's something in a ghost:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114170">Hear thy Isabella's vow:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114180">If hereafter I allow</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114190">Of a second match, or know</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114200">Any man, but for a foe,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114210">Saving him that shall engage</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114220">His revenge unto my rage:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114230">(Hear just heavens) may I then be</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114240">Made another ghost like thee,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114250">May I die, and never have</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114260">What I visit now, a grave. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e114270" who="A01853-caiazzo">
              <speaker>Cai.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e114280">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114290">O do not hear her heaven, and kill me straight</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114300">If I dare touch her: he that sees those eyes</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114310">And dares attempt to make those eyes not see,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114320">Has a blind soul: burn clearer, you kind lights ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114330">Oh do not envy me the sight of her:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114340">But what's there in a sight? I must be brief,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114350">If not for love, yet for ambition:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114360">Her marriage makes me greater than her death,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114370">And she has taught me the condition. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114380">Pardon, bright angel, and return the sword,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114390">Which Sforza made me swear to sheath in you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114400">Into my bosom ▪</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e114410" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e114420">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114430">No, obey your prince,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114440"><pb facs="27" n="36"/> if you have goodness in you keep your oath,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114450">Murder is nothing unto perjury. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e114460" who="A01853-caiazzo">
              <speaker>Cai.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e114470">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114480">By this fair hand you injure me, and more</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114490">Than ever Sforza did: can you suppose</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114500">(Though you had heard the vows he forced me to)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114510">I meant what I protested? that this hand</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114520">Which ever yet has used a sword for you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114530">Would use it now for your destruction. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114540">Revoke that thought, dear lady, that harsh thought,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114550">And let not so much sweeter innocence</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114560">Make itself guilty by suspicion,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114570">Suspicion of impossibilities. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114580">Rather command, and you shall quickly see</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114590">That he, who would have armed me against you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114600">Shall find in his own entrails the just steel. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e114610" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is. aside.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e114620">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114630">What traps are these to catch the innocent? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114640">Sforza I smell your project, 'tis too rank. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114650">My lord, no more: your speech is dangerous,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114660">I must not hear it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e114670" who="A01853-caiazzo">
              <speaker>Cai.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e114680">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114690">You shall see it then:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114700">Do not believe me madam till I've done,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114710">Till I do bring my credit in my arms,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114720">The traitor's head, and when you see that time ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114730">Confess you owe your life unto my crime. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e114740">
            <head>Scaena quarta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e114750">Picinino, Juliano.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e114760" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e114770">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114780">What will become of this declining state? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114790">Can we believe that the yet patient heaven</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114800">Will any longer suffer? and not give</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114810">Destruction as notorious as our crimes. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114820">Awake, stern justice, and unsheathe thy sword,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114830"><pb facs="27" n="37"/> the scabbard will not heal us, but the edge,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114840">Nor is't enough to brandish, but to strike:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114850">Let then thy terror give us innocence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114860">That mildness may no longer injure man. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e114870" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>●ic</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e114880">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114890">Why, thou perpetual murmurer, thou sea</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114900">Tossed with eternal tempest, thou dark sky</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114910">With everlasting clouds, thou — any thing,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114920">Whom, being angry I can call no more:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114930">Think better of those acts thou canst not mend. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114940">Will Sforza be less bad, because thou whinest? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114950">Or dost thou think thy pitiful complaints</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114960">Can beg a goodness of Ascanio? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114970">I never knew that mighty use of tears,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114980">That they could wash away another's fault:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e114990">When thou shalt want a tear for a fit grief,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115000">Sanseverin will be a coward still:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115010">And when thy groans are turned to thy last gasp,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115020">Caiazzo will not be less treacherous. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e115030">Enter Sanseverin, with divers suitors following him, some of whose bills he tears, others laughs at, others puts up. Exit.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e115040" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>●●l</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e115050">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115060">Now for thy thunder, heaven, now for a piece</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115070">Of thy most eminent artillery. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115080">Are you still silent? see, he tears their papers,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115090">Papers, perhaps, wherein they worship him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115100">Give him more titles, than they give their god ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115110">And yet he tears them. O vast favourite! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115120">Swelled by the airy favour of thy prince,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115130">Till thou hast dimmed the light that made thee shine,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115140">Till Sforza's less than his Sanseverin. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115150">Tell me, good Picinino, does the sun</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115160">Spend all his rays upon one continent? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115170">Or have you ever seen the partial heavens</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115180">Upon one acre lavish all her showers,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115190"><pb facs="28" n="38"/> while the rest moulder with dry barrenness? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e115200" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e115210">I have not, Juliano, but what then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e115220" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e115230">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115240">Are you to seek for the collection? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115250">Why, has not Sforza made himself our sun? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115260">Are not his favours our refreshing showers? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115270">Why should one suck up what is due to all,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115280">Why is the prince made a monopoly? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e115290" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e115300">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115310">Thou mak'st me laugh at thy fond question:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115320">What? are not princes men ▪ of the same mould,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115330">Of the same passions with inferiors? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115340">Do not they fear, desire, and hate (As we)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115350">And shall we only hinder them from love? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115360">Cobbler's may have their friends, and why not Kings? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115370">Because they're higher than the rest of men,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115380">Shall they be therefore worse? and therefore want</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115390">The benefits, because they have the rule? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115400">O hard condition of majesty! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115410">The former accusation of Kings</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115420">Has been their cruelty, that they did hate</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115430">The people they should govern: oh hard plight! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115440">O strange perverseness! shall their love at length,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115450">Their friendship be imputed as their fault? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115460">Would heaven our Sforza had no worse a crime. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e115470">Enter Sanseverin again with his train of suitors.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e115480" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e115490">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115500">You are a worthy advocate, and here</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115510">Comes your great patron: go and ask your ●ee:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e115520" who="A01853-sanseverin">
              <speaker>Sans.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e115530">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115540">This is a saucy importunity:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115550">You have your answer. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e115560" who="A01853-suitor_1">
              <speaker>1 suitor. </speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e115570">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115580">O my gracious lord,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115590">Look on these scars I gained in the French ●●●●e,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115600">Where I have lost my fortunes. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e115610" who="A01853-suitor_2">
              <speaker>2 Sutor. </speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e115620">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115630">So have I,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115640"><pb facs="28" n="39"/> scarce left alive to tell my misery. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e115650" who="A01853-sanseverin">
              <speaker>●ans's</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e115660">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115670">You have been drunk, and quarrelled — must the state</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115680">Find plasters for your broken heads? — no more —</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115690">Nay, if you'll take no answer, I must call</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115700">Them that will drive you hence. O my tired ears! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115710">Henceforth I vow to stop them at your suits,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115720">And be as deaf, as you are impudent. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e115730">Exit.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e115740" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e115750">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115760">Yes, do good Aeolus — how he blows them hence! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115770">How clears his passage with a lusty frown! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115780">And yet it may be that despised wretch</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115790">Worn out of clothes, and flesh, whom his high scorn</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115800">Would not vouchsafe once more to look upon,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115810">Durst in the field do more, than he durst see,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115820">Than he would there vouchsafe to look upon. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e115830" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e115840">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115850">As if that valour were the only praise,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115860">And none were to be loved, but they that fight:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115870">Where were we then? what would become of us? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115880">Thou thinkst it paradox, but 'tis most true,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115890">A soldier is the greatest enemy,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115900">Of whom the commonwealth can be afraid:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115910">Prefer you which you please; yet unto them</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115920">Which are the sole physicians of state,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115930">Who with the teeming of a pregnant brain,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115940">Search the diseases and the remedies,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115950">Valour is nothing but a desperate vice,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e115960">And there's no safety, but in cowardice. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e115970">
            <head>Scaena quinta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e115980">Sforza, Ascanio, Malvezzo.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e115990" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e116000">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116010">We are not man, for such an empty thing</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116020">Could not have this solidity of joy:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116030"><pb facs="29" n="40"/> say the French King is dead, and say withal</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116040">We are immortal, and ones happy truth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116050">Shall expiate for the others flattery. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116060">But speak the manner too as well, as death ▪</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e116070" who="A01853-ascanio">
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e116080">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116090">When now his gadding thoughts had won the world ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116100">And Italy was to be taken in</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116110">But only as an easy seat, from whence</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116120">He might derive his further victories;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116130">Ottoman quaked, and 'twas in chance, if now</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116140">New Rome, should be new-french, and the proud t 〈…〉</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116150">Be brought to know what their beginnings were ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116160">When fortune had advanced him to that height ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116170">That grown forgetful of a lowly tomb,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116180">He reared huge pyramids, and troubled art</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116190">To match his fancy with magnificence</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116200">Fit for a conquering builder, who had learned</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116210">To ruin first, and then to build a city. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116220">When marbles were to be in rich with wounds ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116230">And cut for their advancement ▪ then, heaven's sport ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116240">He raised competitors to dare the heavens:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116250">Nor dreams his own descent into low earth. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e116260" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e116270">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116280">Ascanio, you make him live too long,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116290">Tell how he died, without more circumstance. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e116300" who="A01853-ascanio">
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e116310">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116320">He went (Such was his use) to see the play</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116330">At tennis ▪ court, when by his trembling Queen</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116340">He sank into half-death: thence he's conveyed </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116350">To the next room, where on a couch of straw,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116360">As if a downbed were too soft for him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116370">Whom rottenness attended, and the grave,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116380">That harder lodging of mortality,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116390">A King, a conquering, youthful King expires. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116400">Thrice from death's slumbers he awaked to speak,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116410">Thrice did he cry to heaven, unto deaf heaven ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116420"><pb facs="29" n="41"/> and after nine hours death he died. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e116430" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e116440">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116450">I find</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116460">A certain grumbling against fortune here:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116470">Which that I may whet to a lively rage,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116480">Repeat Malvezzo her last treachery</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116490">Against the French, and Neopolitan. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e116500" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 all</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e116510">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116520">Naples now won, and the unstable French</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116530">(As if they were afraid of their own luck)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116540">Ridiculously leaving what they'd won ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116550">The deputy was Mompenieer, a man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116560">Of an high birth, but of unequal deeds. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116570">For when young Ferdinand with some few boats</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116580">(Which only fear might make a navy of,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116590">And nothing but the strength of cowardice</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116600">Could possibly judge strong) approached the shore,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116610">As if the poor prince once more had desired</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116620">Only to see his ancient government,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116630">And therefore had adventured to the sea,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116640">The sea was in the city, for never was</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116650">Such a confusion in the vulgar waves:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116660">All cry a Ferdinand, a Ferdinand,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116670">E'en those who lately banished Ferdinand:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116680">Part open the gates to him, and part shut up</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116690">The French into the citadels, where he</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116700">Besiegeth his once conquerors. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e116710" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e116720">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116730">'Tis true</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116740">Not the world only ▪ but a man's a ball,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116750">Will fortune never leave her tossing him ▪</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e116760" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 all</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e116770">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116780">Whether their own neglect forced them to want,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116790">Or want to yield, 'tis doubted: but they yield:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116800">Thus as in trivial sports we oft have seen</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116810">After a tedious inconstancy,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116820">The cork return to him that struck it first,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116830">So in this fatal revolution,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116840"><pb facs="30" n="42"/> fortune gives Naples unto him again ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116850">Whom she first injured in the taking it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e116860" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e116870">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116880">Who hearing this would not erect his soul</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116890">To a contempt ▪ of fortune! that blind wretch</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116900">Whom only sottishness hath deified? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116910">Man hath a nobler godhead in himself,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116920">His virtue and his wisdom, unto these ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116930">Bend all our knees ▪ let us still honour these:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116940">And count it comfort in our lowest state,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e116950">He that is wise, would not be fortunate. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A01853-e116960">
          <head>Actus quarti</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e116970">
            <head>Scaena prima.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e116980">Sforza, Ascanio, Caiazzo, Sanseverin, a boy.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e116990" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e117000">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117010">We leave it to your care, Sanseverin;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117020">But see the night grows old, good rest my lords ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117030">Why stay'st thou ▪ my Aurelio? good boy</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117040">I'll see no bed tonight ; then go, yet stay,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117050">If they have not escaped thy memory</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117060">Sing me those verses which you made of sleep. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <floatingText xml:id="A01853-e117070">
              <body xml:id="A01853-e117080">
                <div type="song" xml:id="A01853-e117090">
                  <head>Song.</head>
                  <lg xml:id="A01853-e117100">
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117110">How I laugh at their fond wish</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117120">Whose desire</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117130">Aims no higher</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117140">Than the baits of Midas dish? </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117150">What is gold but yellow dirt?</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117160">Which th'unkind</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117170">Heaven's refined</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117180"><pb facs="30" n="43"/> when they made us love our hurt. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117190">Would to heaven that I might steep</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117200">My faint eyes</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117210">In the wise,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117220">In the gentle dew of sleep? </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117230">Whose effects do pose us so,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117240">That we deem</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117250">It does seem</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117260">Both death's brother and his foe. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117270">This does always with us keep,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117280">And being dead</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117290">That's not fled:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e117300">Death is but a longer sleep. </l>
                  </lg>
                </div>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e117310" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 f.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e117320">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117330">Pretty philosophy! go boy, go sleep,<stage xml:id="A01853-e117340">●x.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117350">Enjoy the good thou singest — this boy can sleep,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117360">Sleep quietly, and sing himself asleep:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117370">Making that gentle rest unto his song. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117380">But I'll go read: what have we here? A map? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117390">Welcome thou lively picture of the world:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117400">Now I'll peruse my large dominions,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117410">What a vast compass they do fill in thee? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117420">How Po is wearied with his tedious course,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117430">But running only through our continent? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117440">Ha! where is Po? which is our continent? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117450">If that my eyes deceive me not, I see</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117460">My empire is comprised within my nail:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117470">What a poor point I me master of? A blot ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117480">Made by the swiftest tincture of the ink? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117490">But what did this point cost me? this small blot? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117500">My innocence, my conscience, my soul;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117510">I killed a nephew, to obtain this blot. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117520">O horrid purchase! all this toil, this guilt</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117530">For so despised a nothing? let me see,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117540"><pb facs="31" n="44"/> here is no room to sit, to walk, to stand,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117550">In all my land I cannot place myself,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117560">Nor be at all, where I would be the Duke. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117570">But the sad tapers do deny their light,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117580">And stranger fire supplies an horrid day</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117590">Of lightning: help us, heaven, make us confess,<stage xml:id="A01853-e117600">Asc●●● umb. Gal●●</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117610">There is a power in your mercy too. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e117620" who="A01853-umbra">
              <speaker>Vmb.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e117630">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117640">Is then a time, when all our time is spent</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117650">That thou of us shouldst fear a punishment? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117660">O happy purchased privacy! to have</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117670">The free possession of an humble grave. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117680">Wilt poison us from that? why starest thou so? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117690">We do not shun a kinsman, but a foe:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117700">Believe it Sforza, I am a near ghost,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117710">Nor is our kindred by thy murder lost:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117720">Raise thy cheered look, see Galeazzo here:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117730">Traitor, and coward, does thy faint breast fear</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117740">The shadow, which is made? or is a soul</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117750">Unclothed of earth, more abled to control</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117760">Him that unclothed it! Then I see to die</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117770">Is more to right, then suffer injury. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117780">Know I am still thy prince, and if that man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117790">In such a miracle of villain can</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117800">At last be sound, in this thy manhood show</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117810">That thou dar'st hear thy doom of overthrow. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e117820" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e117830">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117840">Villain be dumb: we are too tamely mild</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117850">That deadmen dare affront us, assume flesh,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117860">And we will make a second ghost of thee. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e117870" who="A01853-galeazzi">
              <speaker>Vmb.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e117880">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117890">Thy threats are air, like us: but to go on</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117900">In curse; now that thy wisdom hopes upon</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117910">A joy in unmolested royalty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117920">Now shalt thou have only a certainty</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117930">Of high unhappiness, and be undone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117940">Losing thy rule no better than 'twas woned. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117950"><pb facs="31" n="45"/>Fetters shall bind thy legs, not crowns thy head,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117960">And as a cursed beast is prohibited</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117970">From common show; so thou, of beasts the worst,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117980">Must die imprisoned, and, what's most accursed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e117990">Obey, to death, all comforts ta'en away,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118000">Robbed of the light, and the sweet heaven of day:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118010">Then flatter not thy miseries, to know</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118020">Is not to hinder fate, fall shalt thou low,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118030">Sink to despair, despair to naught, and die,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118040">Than lower fall, and then as low as I. <stage xml:id="A01853-e118050">Descendit umb.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118060">Sink into earth, and do not reach thy hell,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118070">Prophetic bubble: might thy threats prove true,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118080">For we could wish the death that thou foretellest,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118090">That our fierce shadow might pursue thee still,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118100">To fright thy ghost to nothing: oh weak heavens! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118110">Was this a terror for a man? to send</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118120">A bugbear, framed out of the empty air. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118130">This does confirm, not fright us: this might be</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118140">A terror to my picture, not to me. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e118150">
            <head>Scaena secunda.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e118160">Caiazzo.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e118170" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e118180">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118190">It must succeed: fortune may show her spite,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118200">Her power she cannot, in the hour I'm made</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118210">A prince's lord, or murderer: I've placed</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118220">Close at the outward door, Sanseverin,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118230">That if success do crown my hopes, his cares</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118240">May give me safety, with my happiness,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118250">That I be not surprised: but if I fail</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118260">I have in joined him on the noise he hears,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118270">Straight to go call the Duke, and enter hither. <stage xml:id="A01853-e118280">Ent ▪ isob.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118290">Madam, 'tis done: and now the guilty head</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118300"><pb facs="32" n="46"/> (Which whilst it stood, made all to fear their head,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118310">Who durst affirm it did usurp a crown,)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118320">Most humbly bends, and offers it to you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e118330" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e118340">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118350">Which I accept: but for no other end</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118360">Then to revenge his death, base wretch, on thee:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118370">If that head be not planted there, 't shall off:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118380">You shall enjoy your master's death. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e118390" who="A01853-caiazzo">
              <speaker>Cai.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e118400">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118410">How's this? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118420">Is this a love-trick, lady? I had thought</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118430">After your thanks parted twixt heaven and me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118440">You would with greediness have given yourself</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118450">To him that gave you your desires:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e118460" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e118470">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118480">Fond thought! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118490">Dost think I'd love a man that kills a man? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118500">Make him my prince, who hath dispatched his own</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118510">Was treason ever preface unto love? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118520">Hadst thou monopolised perfection,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118530">And shared a thousand Cupids in each eye:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118540">I would contemn the proudest of their shafts,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118550">And give thee only what is due, disdain. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e118560" who="A01853-caiazzo">
              <speaker>Cai.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e118570">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118580">You'll urge me to just vengeance? do you hear</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118590">Madam ingratitude, quickly profess</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118600">That this harsh language was but a wise bait</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118610">To make him faster, who was sure before,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118620">Or I profess I'll join your death with his</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118630">With thy loathed Sforza. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e118640" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e118650">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118660">I believe thee now,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118670">And trust me, so believe, that I could thank thee,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118680">I love thy cruelty, though not thy person. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e118690" who="A01853-caiazzo">
              <speaker>Cai.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e118700">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118710">Hath death so little horror? well I'll do</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118720">What shall enforce you to desire a death. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118730">This poniards point shall nail thee to the ●●●t●</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118740">Struck through thy arms: where do not hope up</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118750">A noble ravisher, my swarthy slaves,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118760"><pb facs="32" n="47"/> slaves hated of their fellow black a Moors,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118770">Shall on thy honour's ruin tire then lust,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118780">And kill thee in thy loathful suffering. <stage xml:id="A01853-e118790">Ent. Sforza, Sanseverin ▪ Belgiosa.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118800">What dare you struggle? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118810">A rape, a rape. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118820">O my good lord you come in such a time</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118830">As I could wish for, for this hour or more</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118840">This wicked woman hath been wooing me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118850">To murder your most sacred majesty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118860">And for reward hath promised me herself,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118870">Together with the duchy: my good lord,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118880">In detestation of such treachery,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118890">I gave her some harsh answers, with which moved,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118900">She used a woman's craft, and cried a rape. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118910">Is this truth, Isabella; see, she's dumb:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118920">Have I then lived to have you seek my death? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118930">A cousin-traitor? yet you shall not die,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118940">Nor know another prison than my court,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118950">I love to see my murderer: oh heavens! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118960">Why, should I fear to kill her? yet 'tis reason:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e118970">Who is no true prince, can ne'er punish treason. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e118980" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e118990">And I shall take you at your word, dear Sforza. </p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e119000">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e119010">
            <head>Scaena tertia.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e119020">Juliano, Picinino.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e119030" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e119040">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119050">It cannot be, good Julian, no more:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119060">I do not love these over-earnest dreams. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119070">The French invade us? when their jolly King</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119080">With limber slaves does only mock a war,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119090">Which like so many reeds against a stone</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119100"><pb facs="33" n="48"/> punish their own attempt with their own r 〈…〉 ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119110">Breaking themselves, no● armours: when we 〈…〉</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119120">The court is lost in masks, reality</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119130">Is so far fled since the last victory,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119140">That we may think the court itself a mask ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119150">Eternal music, revels without end</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119160">Tire the too-much delighted soldier,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119170">Whose arms have now forgotten their ancient use,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119180">His spirits only active in his heels,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119190">And canst thou think they'll dance to Italy? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e119200" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e119210">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119220">I've heard some tell that a great city once</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119230">Was built by music: would we might not find</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119240">Our country to be ruined by a dance:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119250">Oh fear the toying of an enemy. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e119260" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e119270">What cannot be believed, cannot be feared.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e119280" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e119290">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119300">You'll not believe, not you, till the French swords</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119310">Dive to the bottom of your doubting heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119320">Till that th'unkinder news is brought so near,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119330">You cannot have the power to believe it:<stage xml:id="A01853-e119340">Ent. Sa 〈…〉 with s 〈…〉</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119350">Can you believe this is a drum that beats? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119360">That this is the courageous general? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119370">Can you believe, that he believes 'tis true? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e119380" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e119390">But who assists us in this dreadful time?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e119400" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e119410">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119420">As many as we have deserved: not one:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119430">Sforza has too much wisdom to have friends. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e119440" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e119450">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119460">And we have too much — I said nothing, did I? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119470">I did not speak against the state ▪ I hope? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119480">Nor said that we had too much patience? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e119490" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e119500">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119510">Is Picinino then o'ercome at last,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119520">Now I could change my sorrow for a smile. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e119530" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e119540">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119550">I must confess an anger though not grief:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119560">Oh how I love to fit me to mischance</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119570">And when that has no reason, then I'm ●ad. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119580">Why should our Milan blood stain the French swords</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119590"><pb facs="33" n="49"/> unto a glory? Sforza does offend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119600">Denies the heavenly powers, or names them then,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119610">When he does dare them with bold perjury,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119620">Loads his black soul with murder of a man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119630">That could have made his execution, justice. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119640">This Sforza does, but what is this to me? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119650">Why shall this throat be cut for his? why thine? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119660">Why shall our countries ruin fill his penance? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119670">The heavens do know no mean but either waste</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119680">Their benefits on dull ingratitude</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119690">Or throw away their thunder, so it hit</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119700">So it not fail, they care not whom it strike,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119710">Whether the guilty, or the innocent. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e119720" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e119730">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119740">This is a grief of higher fault than mine,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119750">You make a war with them you should appease,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119760">And urge the heavens to our calamities. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119770">First we were punished with, and now for Sforza,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119780">Could any justice have more method in't. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e119790" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e119800">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119810">Well Julian, I me sorry for my grief,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119820">And so persuade thee to that holy truth. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119830">I now could rave against myself, not heaven,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119840">But 'tis as fruitless, as to wish good luck:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119850">Then let the French press upon victory,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119860">Let them amaze the air with stranger fire,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119870">Raised by our cities flaming funerals. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119880">Swell they the Po with blood, act o'er, whate'er </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119890">Has been the brag of royal murderers,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119900">Yet our defence is here: fortune may fail</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119910">But our true souls shall never, we may lose</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119920">An aged life, but not eternity:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119930">And with this strength the field must needs be ours:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119940">Who do not fear, do beat the conquerors. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e119950">
            <pb facs="34" n="50"/>
            <head>Scaena quarta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e119960">Sforza. Ascanio. A guard. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e119970" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e119980">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e119990">What noise is this that from a foreign foe</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120000">Recalls our anger? yet our purer hands</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120010">Know not the die of blood: we should be loath</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120020">To learn a valour on our subjects first. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e120030" who="A01853-nuncio_1">
              <speaker>1 nunc. </speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e120040">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120050">The people now have raved to quietness:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120060">But till that Landriano, whom you used</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120070">About the last taxation, was become</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120080">Their rages sacrifice, I durst have sworn</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120090">The French were in the city. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e120100" who="A01853-nuncio_3">
              <speaker>2 nun.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e120110">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120120">This sad hour</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120130">(I'm sorry that you hear this truth from me)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120140">Your Duchess is departed. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e120150" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e120160">Whither villain?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e120170">(Fren●●</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e120180" who="A01853-nuncio_2">
              <speaker>2 nun.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e120190">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120200">To that free crown, where she shall fear no</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120210">To heaven. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e120220" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e120230">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120240">O envious heaven! why do you give</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120250">Men such hard precepts of mortality,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120260">And take them hence before that they can learn? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120270">Must not she live, because she lived too well? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120280">Alas my wife! </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e120290" who="A01853-ascanio">
              <speaker>Asc.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e120300">Alas my sister, ●!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e120310" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e120320">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120330">Who dared that groan? good Cardinal, no more,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120340">I know not what I could deny to thee:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120350">Take to thee all for what the French so toil,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120360">But kindly leave my grief unto myself. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e120370" who="A01853-nuncio_3">
              <speaker>3 Nun.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e120380">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120390">Pardon, my lord, ill fortune's eloquence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120400">Unless you hear you cannot cure your harms;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120410">The French, now entered Lombardy, sat down</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120420">Before Valenza: where the mouth of death,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120430"><pb facs="34" n="51"/> the thundering cannon being scarcely brought,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120440">But just presented to the yet sound wall,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120450">Discovered there was somewhat more unsound:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120460">For Rattagnino, the false governor</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120470">Entreats a parley, gives away the strength,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120480">Swears the town French, and gives the key to them,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120490">With which they open Lombardy. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e120500" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e120510">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120520">My fact;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120530">None can be guilty of this crime, but I:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120540">That after treason durst again trust treason. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120550">This very man, whose easy heart relents</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120560">At a French death, and wisely is afraid</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120570">His manners might be called in question,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120580">If he should put them off to sue again,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120590">To ask the second time, for what he held:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120600">Out of his zeal to virtue, and good luck,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120610">Did the like act for us, and gave a strength<stage xml:id="A01853-e120620">Ent. Mal. wounded</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120630">Which all our duchy never could have forced. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120640">What more revolting yet? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e120650" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>●al</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e120660">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120670">O my good lord! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120680">I fear this is beyond addition. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120690">O my blood fails me, but my tongue does more,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120700">Fearing the story that it must relate. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120710">Your army being parted, and this half</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120720">Caiazzo leading, that Sanseverin,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120730">My troops did fall among the French men's scouts. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120740">From whom we learned their numbers, and intent,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120750">To march with speed for Milan: this sad news</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120760">We sent to count Caiazzo, with advice,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120770">That he would instantly rejoin with us,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120780">To stop their further entrance: he pretends</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120790">That the Venetians hemming in his camp</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120800">Have made his danger greater: yet he moves,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120810">Makes to the river, and when now our thoughts</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120820"><pb facs="35" n="52"/> had left their wavering, and did seem assured</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120830">His actions would be better than his words,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120840">I saw, oh misery that ere I saw! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120850">That crossing o'er the Po he did embrace</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120860">Those men which he in duty should have killed:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120870">(Oh 'tis this kills me, not my want of blood)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120880">I in just anger set upon the rear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120890">And after many vain attempts, have brought</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120900">My carcase, to entreat for my revenge. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e120910" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e120920">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120930">This is conspiracy: Caiazzo false? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120940">Tell me that contradictions then are true,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120950">Tell me the heavens no more do travel now</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120960">Being grown inconstant to their motion:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120970">Or that the earth pursy with too long ease</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120980">Would with a walk at length refresh herself:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e120990">Tell me that princes may be fortunate,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121000">Those that like me are credulous: or if</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121010">You'd speak of things more hard to be believed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121020">Tell me, there are, that birth of fear, called gods,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121030">And if they be, that they do think of man:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121040">Tell me, oh prithee tell me somewhat else,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121050">Or I shall think thee false, and not Caiazzo,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121060">But I do know thee true, know thy wounds true,<stage xml:id="A01853-e121070">E 〈…〉 sansen 〈…〉</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121080">And must conclude Caiazzo is most false. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e121090" who="A01853-sanseverin">
              <speaker>Sans.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e121100">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121110">To be o'ercome, my lord, is wretched chance,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121120">But not to fight at all will be thought crime,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121130">I never durst think so to survive ill luck</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121140">As to become the fatal messenger? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121150">But I must say, I durst not fight, and more,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121160">I must entreat your cowardice, your foes</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121170">Are strengthened with your army (O pardon me</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121180">Let me not tell you, how) and all our troops,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121190">Have no power left us but for a safe flight. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e121200" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e121210">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121220">I did expect this: was not man at first</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121230"><pb facs="35" n="53"/> placed on this curious theater, to see</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121240">How he could act all parts: do we not know</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121250">What we can fear is nothing? providence</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121260">Long since hath spent our fear; for a wise man,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121270">When he does found his happiness, forecasts</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121280">Mischiefs, that fate had never practised yet,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121290">Which if they happen, if they prove too true,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121300">They meet, not overtake him, and so find</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121310">A scorn, because a preparation. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121320">I knew it might be thus, though I not feared,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121330">And know it may be better, though not hope:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121340">Yet let us never despair, nor by low thoughts</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121350">Excuse fate for her present injury. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121360">And when once more her favours we shall feel,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121370">Then say, that fortune has no standing wheel. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e121380">
            <head>Scaena quinta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e121390">〈…〉 ter at one door, Triulcio, Aubeny, Caiazzo: at the other some senators of Millan, who deliver the keys of the city.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e121400" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e121410">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121420">We here present you with our keys great lords,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121430">Yet do not think us cowards, who do part</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121440">So easily with that, which if we pleased</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121450">We might, in spite of force, as easily keep:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121460">We know your right, justice does open these gates,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121470">And not your swords, nor our disloyalty;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121480">We leave a traitor that hath first left us,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121490">And now are glad to entertain our prince. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e121500" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 iu</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e121510">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121520">Is he fled then? O our unhappy sloth! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121530">Why ran we not as well as we did fight? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121540">Are cowards swifter than their conquerors. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e121550"><pb facs="36" n="54"/>Above as in the citadel appear Isobella, and Julia.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e121560" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e121570">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121580">Do not dissuade me, Julia, 'tis true</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121590">I may escape, but whither? all is lost,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121600">In Naples we find France, as well as here. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121610">O who'd endure the tyranny of hope,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121620">That could so quickly gain a liberty? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121630">If I but fall I'm free; o Julia,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121640">The greatest distance twixt my bliss, and me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121650">Reacheth no farther than to the next earth. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121660">Can I behold in a perplexed flight</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121670">(Of which I know no comfort, and no end)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121680">This my sweet infant crying for the food,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121690">Which I'm uncertain where to beg for him? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121700">No, I'll descend, and if the greedy French</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121710">Will have our blood with our dominions,<stage xml:id="A01853-e121720">She comes down with some soldiers ▪</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121730">Yet I shall joy to have a speedy end</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121740">And call a nimble enemy, a friend. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e121750" who="A01853-triulcio">
              <speaker>Tri.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e121760">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121770">What answer from the citadel? once more</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121780">Give them a summons, if they yield not then<stage xml:id="A01853-e121790">Enter Isabella</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121800">Give an assault. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e121810" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e121820">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121830">You shall not need my lords,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121840">What you could wish you have, most cheaply have,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121850">The conquest of a woman, and a child. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121860">I'm Isabella, (Let not that sad name</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121870">Be ominous to conquerors,) and this</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121880">This pretty infant, is my luckless child,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121890">Born prince of that, which you have made your prey. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121900">Why do you one consult another's face,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121910">As you would see, who could be cruel first? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121920">Be not at all, or if at all, to me. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121930">O do not war with infants! can these hands</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121940">Deserve your fear or anger? these weak hands</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121950">That cannot reach themselves unto their teat? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121960"><pb facs="36" n="55"/>Who have so much of young infirmity,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121970">They cannot lift themselves to ask your mercy? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121980">O let them have, because they cannot ask. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e121990">How many dismal accidents may chance</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122000">To take him hence, before he grow to man,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122010">And so excuse, and yet fulfil your purpose? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122020">O let disease be cruel, and not you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e122030" who="A01853-triulcio">
              <speaker>Tri.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e122040">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122050">Madam, you shall be honourably used,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122060">You, and your fair son: take your liberty</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122070">To choose your own free course: for this young lord,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122080">He must to France with us, where he shall learn</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122090">The good of royal education:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122100">Where he shall know the happy difference</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122110">Between a petty, and a kingly court. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122120">Some wait upon the Princess. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e122130" who="A01853-isabella">
              <speaker>Is.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e122140">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122150">O my stars! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122160">What have I done? ay me? I have betrayed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122170">What tyranny had left me, my sweet boy:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122180">For whom I never knew a grief; till now</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122190">I brought him forth with pleasure, when I think</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122200">Upon this pain of parting: my dear child,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122210">Oh too too like thy mother; if thou chance</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122220">To draw thy life unto that hated length,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122230">That thou arrive to the discretion</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122240">To know, what by my folly, thou hast lost,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122250">Call it no more, o do not call it crime,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122260">No mother willingly would lose a son:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122270">While in some darker cell I will in tomb</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122280">Thy ruins cause, where whatsoever tear</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122290">Sorrow did once force, no devotion shall:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122300">That my new name unto the heavens may reach</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122310">Whom misery the way to bliss did teach. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e122320">Exit.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e122330" who="A01853-triulcio">
              <speaker>Tri.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e122340">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122350">Never till now had we the victory,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122360">And now no single one, this happy hour</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122370"><pb facs="37" n="56"/> has gained a a conquest for posterity. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122380">They may be idle now, now the French youth</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122390">May grow up without wounds, and at their homes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122400">Steal to a private grave, no more being forced</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122410">To death, though by a glory; nay this land</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122420">May thank us, for our thrift of victory,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122430">For lighting on this blessed occasion,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122440">Which makes us need no more to conquer them:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122450">If heaven continue us this kindness still,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122460">We'll measure out our conquests by our will. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A01853-e122470">
          <head>Actus quinti</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e122480">
            <head>Scaena prima.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e122490">Sforza, Ascanio, Sanseverin.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e122500" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e122510">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122520">O what is man? and all that happiness</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122530">That puffs him to security? today</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122540">One acts a prince, and swelled with majesty</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122550">Fills a proud throne, from whence the multitude</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122560">Thinks he rules fortune too, as well as them,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122570">Whilst she in just esteem of her own name,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122580">Makes him forgotten, or odious, that none</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122590">Can be so miserably fooled, to wish</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122600">His well-appareled misery: thus we</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122610">That did enjoy beyond a crown, a brain</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122620">Able to meet, or challenge the worst chance:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122630">Yet in the space of a few days, a space</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122640">Of too short lasting to expel a man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122650">(By the most subtle fetches of the law)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122660">Out of a false inheritance: we lost,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122670">We were expelled out of a monarchy;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122680">But does fate make a stand at this? O no,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122690">She is not constant, no not in her curse,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122700">But giving most again, which once was mine</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122710"><pb facs="37" n="57"/> she gives me too the capability</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122720">Of a new curse. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e122730" who="A01853-ascanio">
              <speaker>〈…〉 Sc.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e122740">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122750">Of a new joy: for shame</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122760">Give thanks at least for your felicity:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122770">Can you repine being crammed, and so deserve</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122780">A bountiful unhappiness? I've known</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122790">Some that have long endured a tedious siege,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122800">Or a more tedious sickness, who have been</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122810">Forced to a lasting Lent, when they have come</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122820">Or to their health, or to their liberty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122830">Not dare to take the nourishment they might,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122840">Making themselves their sickness, and their foe:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122850">Is not my Sforza one of these? you grieve</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122860">Because you have no longer cause to grieve. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e122870" who="A01853-sanseverin">
              <speaker>〈…〉 ans.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e122880">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122890">O I do fear your grief, that it does glance</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122900">With a most undeserved disgrace at me;</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122910">As if I were akin unto the fault</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122920">Of my false brother: oh repeat that thought,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122930">It is no great thing I request you to,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122940">But trust unto the faith that you have found. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122950">Would I betray, and follow you? d'ye think,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122960">I'd be so mad to buy my banishment? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122970">No man would be unprofitably false,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122980">Nor I for any profit: speak yourself</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e122990">If I have left you, when your fortune did? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123000">Nay, than my love was greatest, when you least,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123010">I was your subject, when you were no prince. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e123020" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>〈…〉 f.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e123030">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123040">Sanseverin, thy fear is too too fond,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123050">And like the people, the authority,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123060">Who make an impious confusion</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123070">Of an high birth, and of an higher crime:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123080">Who in a saucy thwarting to their prince,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123090">Count him still worst, whom he has made the best,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123100">As if we gave him, with his honours, crimes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123110"><pb facs="38" n="58"/> and made him vicious, when fortunate. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123120">No, let them spend their breath in idle talk,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123130">Count thee or treacherous, or cowardly? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123140">Whilst to thy Sforza thou art still the same,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123150">Most valiant, and with thy valour, wise,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123160">That by thy abstinence a while from war,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123170">Hast saved us forces for a victory. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e123180" who="A01853-sanseverin">
              <speaker>Sans.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e123190">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123200">The subjects' life lies in the prince's voice:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123210">Now you have cleared me I dare hasten war,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123220">And wish more enemies, than cowards fear:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123230">That you may see, by my neglect of blood,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123240">(Which I shall only love when shed for you)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123250">How slander was my most feared enemy. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e123260" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e123270">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123280">No more, my dearest friend: we lose all time</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123290">Which we do save from fight, still there does flock</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123300">New forces to our army, and the French</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123310">Are now as much amazed, as proud before:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123320">We lately took the Swissers into pay,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123330">Those that dare sell their lives to any cause,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123340">Whom gold hath armed for me: if they proceed</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123350">In their first heat, we win: but if they fail</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123360">We cannot be more wretched than we were:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123370">The vilest chance of luck can make us know</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123380">But an addition to an overthrow. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e123390">
            <head>Scaena secunda.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e123400">The captain of the swizzers, with a soldier, as a fugiti 〈…〉 from the French.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e123410" who="A01853-soldier">
              <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e123420">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123430">Now w' are alone I dare reveal myself,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123440">I am not what I seem, a fugitive,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123450">But one that from Triulcio do bring</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123460"><pb facs="38" n="59"/> letters that much concern you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e123470" who="A01853-captain">
              <speaker>Captain</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e123480">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123490">What? to me? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123500">Letters unto his enemy? let's see:<stage xml:id="A01853-e123510">Ex. soul.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123520">Expect an answer in my tent. — what's here? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <floatingText xml:id="A01853-e123530">
              <body xml:id="A01853-e123540">
                <div type="letter" xml:id="A01853-e123550">
                  <head>Letter.</head>
                  <lg xml:id="A01853-e123560">
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123570">Thou man of action, whom th' Italians</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123580">Feel their Achilles, both to wound, and heal:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123590">Triulcio salutes thee: what is past,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123600">As past recall he will not mention,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123610">But for the future this; you aid a man,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123620">From whom you cannot any way expect</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123630">Reward, or honour, such his poverty</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123640">Both in desert, and means? but against whom? </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123650">I will not urge they are your countrymen,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123660">Partakers of the same sweet soil with you,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123670">Who only differ in their better choice:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123680">Yet so far do I prize your worth, to think,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123690">You have not put off nature, nor have changed</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123700">With your home air, your home-affections. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123710">That you are still a Swisser: think of this,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123720">And that at other times 'twere shame to fly,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01853-e123730">Now only flight shows magnanimity. </l>
                  </lg>
                </div>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e123740" who="A01853-triulcio">
              <speaker>Triulcio.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e123750">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123760">What shall I do? O I am lost in doubt,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123770">Nor know, what to refuse, or what to grant. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123780">Shall then the Swissers to their valour add</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123790">A tainture of disloyalty? to whom? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123800">Who can accuse us for our treachery? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123810">One that has patronised it by his act:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123820">That hath betrayed his nephew: shall a man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123830">Be counted treacherous, that betrays vice? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123840">It was a crime to aid him, can it be</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123850">A crime to leave him too? O paradox! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123860"><pb facs="39" n="60"/>Resolve me goodness what 'tis best to do:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123870">And that does whisper a dislike: for what,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123880">What goodness can there be in civil war? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123890">When we shall kill them that were born with us,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123900">When we shall make the father die his sword</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123910">In the son's blood, and strangely give a death</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123920">To him, to whom he kindly gave a life,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123930">When the mixed blood of the same family</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123940">Shall make a cruel incest: this we do</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123950">If we are honest: I'll learn treason first,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123960">And the most accurate sin. Triulcio,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123970">Our country calls us, and not thou, to be</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e123980">Dishonest than is the best honesty. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e123990">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e124000">
            <head>Scaena tertia.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e124010">Picinino in his study, with a deaths-head and a watch.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e124020" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e124030">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124040">This is the sum, I can but be like this. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124050">After the prouder threatening of the French,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124060">After the sure impression of diseases</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124070">I can but be like this: then let me think</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124080">What loss I have when I am made like this:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124090">This fears no French: a peace of ordinance</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124100">Can break, but not astonish this, no force</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124110">Can draw a tear, no not a sigh from hence:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124120">And can it be a loss to be like this? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124130">O death! why art thou feared? why do we think</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124140">'Tis such a horrid terror ▪ not to be? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124150">Why, not to be, is, not to be a wretch,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124160">Why, not to be, is, to be like the heavens,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124170">Not to be subject to the power of fate:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124180">Oh there's no happiness but not to be.<stage xml:id="A01853-e124190">To the watch.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124200"><pb facs="39" n="61"/>But thou discloser of the stealth of time,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124210">Let me inquire how much is worn away</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124220">Of this sad hour: the half? O speedy time! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124230">That mak'st us feel, ere we can think of age,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124240">Ere we can take an order for the grave. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e124250">Enter Jul.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e124260" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e124270">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124280">What? deep in meditation, noble friend? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124290">So studious of your watch? alas good man,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124300">Thou needst not this faint help to guess at fate,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124310">These silver hairs are watch enough for thee. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e124320" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e124330">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124340">I only look how many minutes hence</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124350">Midan expires. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e124360" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e124370">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124380">O swift arithmetic,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124390">To sum by minutes our sad duchies age. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e124400" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e124410">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124420">This watch doth teach real philosophy,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124430">There is no tutor to this active brass:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124440">What is a kingdom, but a larger watch? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124450">Wound up by fate unto some scores of years,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124460">And then it falls: good Juliano list,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124470">Hark how it beats, how strongly, and how fast,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124480">Beyond the motion of a nimble pulse:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124490">Who would not think this were a lasting noise? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124500">And yet it ends: after some date of hours</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124510">The watch will be as silent as the head. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124520">O 'tis our folly, folly, my dear friend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124530">Because we see th'activity of states,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124540">To flatter them with false eternity:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124550">Why longer than the dweller lasts the house? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124560">Why should the world be always, and not man? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124570">Sure kingdoms are as mortal as their Kings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124580">And stay but longer for their period. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e124590" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e124600">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124610">I fear our climacterical is now:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124620">When all professions turn to soldier,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124630">To that curst art that thrives by destiny. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124640">The scythes are straighted into swords, and th'earth</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124650"><pb facs="40" n="62"/> being not wounded is undone, where once</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124660">Stood buildings, which an humble poetry</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124670">Without too bold a swelling might give Kings:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124680">Whole mines undone to beautify one roof,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124690">Now only desolation dwells: weak grief,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124700">To say corn grows, where once a city stood,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124710">That sustenance is there where no men are,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124720">This is a trifling, and halfe-misery:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124730">Our lands now only furnish us with graves,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124740">Can hide us, but not feed us; we would think</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124750">Our cities standing, though the buildings fell,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124760">If we had no grief, but fertility. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e124770" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e124780">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124790">But on what strength does Sforza still subsist</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124800">Against so powerful foes? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e124810" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e124820">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124830">The emperor</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124840">Has sold him some few Almains, but his hopes</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124850">Chiefly depend upon the valiant Swizze,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124860">Who were the chief in his depression. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e124870" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e124880">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124890">Has his gross brain not learned the danger yet</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124900">Of bringing strangers into Italy? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124910">He called the French to Naples, who have now</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124920">Found Milan too: oh what's the difference</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124930">Betwixt a mercenary and a foe? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124940">But that we kill one for his outrages,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124950">And hire the other? Juliano, I</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e124960">May feel misfortune, but will never buy. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e124970">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e124980">
            <head>Scaena quarta.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e124990">Sforza, Sanseverin.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e125000" who="A01853-sanseverin">
              <speaker>Sans.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e125010">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125020">The French are mighty, and portentously</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125030">Rise by their fall: strong shame begets a rage,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125040">And a disdain, that you whom they expelled</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125050"><pb facs="40" n="63"/> should hazard their expulsion, makes them hazard,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125060">Whate'er being ventured, adds a fame to man,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125070">And gives a glory to his misery. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125080">They are so far from the base fear of death,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125090">That they embraced, and like those fiercer curs,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125100">That spend their anger on the senseless stone</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125110">Not daring to attempt on him that threw,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125120">They with a senseless anger break the darts</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125130">That nail them to the earth, as if they scorned</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125140">Their killer should survive them: other lets,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125150">As heat, or hunger, are their exercise:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125160">That one would think they'd lost all part of man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125170">When they did mean to show the best: my lord,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125180">I wish a swift, but love a certain conquest:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125190">I think 'twere wisdom to protract the fight. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e125200" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>●f</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e125210">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125220">I know thou speakst what thou thinkst best: but know,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125230">'Tis wisdom to delay on equal fame:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125240">But when a foe has won opinion,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125250">Which draws all eyes, and hearts to him, oh then</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125260">A valiant desperation fits a man:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125270">For victory is not impossible,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125280">And honour necessary: my best friend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125290">Call forth our Swissers, and if happy swords</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125300">Though few, may cut a way to glory, come:<stage xml:id="A01853-e125310">Enter Capt with Swiz:</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125320">The purchase is above the pains: but here</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125330">Come they that shall fill histories: brave friends</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125340">Now is the time we shall employ your swords,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125350">And teach the world your valour. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e125360" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>Capt</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e125370">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125380">You may fail:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125390">'Tis better to be wise: Sforza, I'm come</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125400">To take my leave of you, nor shall much breath</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125410">Be spent in ceremonial compliment,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125420">I am the French King's soldier. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e125430" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e125440">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125450">Speak low,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125460"><pb facs="41" n="64"/> let not the air feel such a treason, know</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125470">There is a power above us, and that power</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125480">Thunders sometimes, I know, thou dar'st not stand</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125490">In contestation with the power of heaven:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125500">Revoke thy words. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e125510" who="A01853-captain">
              <speaker>Captain</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e125520">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125530">I'll do no miracles:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125540">My voice and faith are passed. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e125550" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e125560">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125570">Yes they are past:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125580">Thou art made up all of disloyalty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125590">Reason hath nothing of thee: yet relate</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125600">(If thou hast any relics left of sense,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125610">I'll not conjure thee by strange honesty)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125620">Why dost thou leave the heavens, and us, and so</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125630">For nothing dost commit a double treason? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e125640" who="A01853-captain">
              <speaker>Captain</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e125650">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125660">I'll satisfy you thus, you see I do't:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125670">Strike up a march. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e125680" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e125690">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125700">Yet stay: what is the price</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125710">That makes thee treacherous, I'll turn prodigal</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125720">To buy thee to a virtue: stay: be rich,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125730">Without a curse, without a fault. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e125740" who="A01853-captain">
              <speaker>Captain</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e125750">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125760">'Tis vain,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125770">I'm deaf to rhetoric: yet say thou'st met</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125780">With a good perjurer, my word is past,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125790">And to be twice a traitor, is a fault</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125800">No sorrow can atone for: yet thus far</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125810">I'll strain myself to please thee, 'tis well known,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125820">Unless you get unto Ascanio,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125830">Your hopes are at the last, but between you</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125840">And him, the French have interposed themselves,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125850">Nothing remains but that you trust to me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125860">And in a Swissers coat disguise yourself,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125870">That you may pass their army. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e125880" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e125890">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125900">O hard strait,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125910">Must Sforza impotently hide himself? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125920"><pb facs="41" n="65"/>Or can a prince be hid? I have oft heard</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125930">Sparks of divinity adorn his face,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125940">To clear him from the multitude: why then,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125950">The being a prince will make us be no prince,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125960">We being betrayed by our own majesty. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125970">Yet off ye envied robes, fall to the earth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125980">Oh fall so low, that henceforth man may scorn</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e125990">The labour of descent to take you up:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126000">On, on, ye happy robes, that like good clouds</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126010">Do not obscure, but for a time defend</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126020">The threatened sun, that he may after shine</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126030">With higher vigour: I have heard of some,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126040">That wear their flesh with haircloth for their crimes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126050">As thinking to be good if they were rough,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126060">By such a wild repentance: be it so<stage xml:id="A01853-e126070">Enter Triulcio with the French.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126080">These robes offended, than there is an hope</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126090">These rags may expiate heaven</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e126100" who="A01853-triulcio">
              <speaker>Tri.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e126110">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126120">Brave soldiers,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126130">How we rejoice we may embrace at last,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126140">Not with armed hands, without the guilt and shame</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126150">Of civil murder ▪ but are these the troops</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126160">That now must learn to use their valour well? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126170">To give a death without a prodigy? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126180">A conquering cheerfulness adorns their face ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126190">These are not common soldiers: look you pale,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126200">Than I must know the mystery. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e126210" who="A01853-captain">
              <speaker>Captain</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e126220">I'm betrayed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e126230" who="A01853-triulcio">
              <speaker>Tri.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e126240">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126250">Yea I know all, but yet from thy forced tongue</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126260">Will I extract confession; fetch a rack,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126270">To make him howl the truth, he will not speak. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e126280" who="A01853-captain">
              <speaker>Captain</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e126290">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126300">I can dare torments for wise honesty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126310">But when you know as much as I can tell,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126320">Should I conceal't, all policy would judge,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126330">I did deserve the worst that I endured:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126340"><pb facs="42" n="66"/> who told you this was Sforza? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e126350" who="A01853-sforza">
              <speaker>Sf.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e126360">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126370">O my brain! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126380">Must subtlety perish by subtlety? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126390">And our high wisdom find a conqueror? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126400">Make an end nature, the great work is done,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126410">Sforza is overreached — weak, childish rage:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126420">Is this to lessen, or make misery? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126430">Can passion lose us, or a courteous tear</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126440">Wash off our fetters? if it can, pour eyes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126450">Pour out wet comfort; if it can, refuse</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126460">The curse of slumber, but it cannot, then</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126470">Covet a slumber everlastingly,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126480">And be like 〈…〉, imprisoned in your lids. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126490">Convey us quickly hence, kind friends, you know</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126500">Sforza can never be a prisoner here. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126510">Convey us thither where we are no prince. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126520">And must we woo our ruin? never man</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126530">Is a true wretch, but when he loseth all,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126540">And wants the sad election of his fall ▪</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A01853-e126550">
            <head>Scaena ultima.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A01853-e126560">Juliano, Picinino</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e126570" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e126580">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126590">I'm lost in this confusion: one reports ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126600">We have lost all; another instantly</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126610">Kil● all the French at once: thus every street ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126620">Is filled with wandring people; some cry ▪ arm,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126630">Others run crying, to persuade a slight:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126640">All have an earnest business in the stir,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126650">But in the help not any. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e126660" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e126670">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126680">These are they ▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126690">That if a● happy messenger should come</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126700"><pb facs="42" n="67"/> with Sforza's victory, would pretend at least</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126710">To be o'ercome with joy: the gorgeous walls</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126720">Should shine with painted triumphs, and the French</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126730">Should be again vanquished in pageant. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126740">But if his fortune yield to the French force,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126750">What obloquy's will be enough for him? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126760">Disgrace will then be wit, and any brain</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126770">Will venture on a libel. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e126780" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 l.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e126790">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126800">'Tis the use,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126810">The popular folly to admire events,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126820">And those low souls think that the sword is just,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126830">Proportioning the reason by the end</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126840">Of the chief acts, of the best enterprise,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126850">And so by folly run into a crime. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e126860" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 Ic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e126870">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126880">No matter for their wisdom, were they good:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126890">Oh why are such termed innocents? but friend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126900">What is our aim? A flight our age denies,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126910">And whither should we fly, but to the grave? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126920">O I have so much people in me too,<stage xml:id="A01853-e126930">Enter Malvezzo.</stage></l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126940">That I could wish thy company. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e126950" who="A01853-malatesta">
              <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e126960">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126970">Good heavens! </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126980">Am I escaped? may I stay safely here? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e126990">My fear has left such near impressions,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127000">I scarce dare think that this is liberty. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e127010" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 Ic.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A01853-e127020">Noble Malvezzo, is there any hope?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e127030" who="A01853-malatesta">
              <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e127040">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127050">As much as in despair: we are betrayed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127060">Sforza is made a prisoner, all's lost,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127070">And Milan, without blows, is once more French. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e127080" who="A01853-unassigned">
              <speaker>〈…〉 Ic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e127090">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127100">Now I remember what I dreamt last night,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127110">(If it be safe to call a vision, dream,)</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127120">I saw our Sforza in so pale a shape,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127130">That envy never was described more wan,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127140">Who frighted me with this relation. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <quote xml:id="A01853-e127150">
              <pb facs="43" n="68"/>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e127160">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127170">Start not astonished mortal: let no fear</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127180">Chill thee to my pale image, but fix here:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127190">Let thy once prince be thy now spectacle,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127200">Whilst I the direst tragedy shall tell</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127210">That ever challenged wonder: briefly then,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127220">I was betrayed, betrayed, and by those men</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127230">By whom I conquered:] 'tis an happy end</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127240">To perish for, but never by a friend. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127250">This our first death: but then — oh could cursed time</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127260">Dare ever such a minute, such a crime? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127270">Then was I pinioned, than these royal hands</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127280">Were forced obedient to the base commands</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127290">Of an insulting conqueror, and knit</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127300">Unto a hated union; 'twere fit</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127310">If ever heaven shed tears, than to distil</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127320">Mournings elixir, though th'expense should kill</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127330">The hopes of after ages: but heaven smiled</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127340">Nor any courteous cloud ▪ were wisely piled</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127350">Over the sun's sharp beames, but they gazed on</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127360">With the same visage of compassion</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127370">As did my torturers, [by whom I'm brought</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127380">Unto a place the which some shallower thought</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127390">Has faintly termed a prison, but to tell</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127400">The truth of horror, was on earth, an hell:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127410">Darkness so dwell there, that I might be won</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127420">To wish the cruel comfort of the sun,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127430">Which erst I raved at: 'twas a narrow cave,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127440">Formed to the model of a lesser grave,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127450">Or straightened coffin, all was length, for they</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127460">Left not the height that I might kneel to pray. </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127470">Was ever such a bed? could ever yet</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127480">Cruelty boast of such a subtle wit</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127490">To bury so! some that have entered earth</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127500">Alive, like me, yet by the usual mirth</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127510"><pb facs="43" n="69"/> of justice had their burial with meat,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127520">As if't should be their punishment to eat,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127530">From which I me barred, I had no food, but me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127540">And yet a guest of famine; courtesy</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127550">At last seized heaven, I died, and so though late,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127560">I both appeased and triumphed over fate. </l>
              </lg>
            </quote>
            <l xml:id="A01853-e127570">But where am I? what ecstasy was this? </l>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e127580" who="A01853-juliano">
              <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e127590">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127600">How quickly we learn misery? no ghost</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127610">Would have so courteously relinquished hell</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127620">To teach us happiness: if a kind star</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127630">Had cast a fortune on us beyond wish,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127640">We might expect the story from the star</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127650">As soon as the dear benefit: but when grief</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127660">That against which we would seal up our ears,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127670">When that is meant us, we shall surely hear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127680">Though heaven do strain for a new miracle,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127690">So to amaze us to a certainty:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127700">Though rotten carcases regain a voice,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127710">And hell is bounteous of intelligence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127720">To give us tears. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A01853-e127730" who="A01853-picinino">
              <speaker>Pic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A01853-e127740">
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127750">Why, than an end to tears,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127760">Let's scorn the sorrow, which we owe to hell:</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127770">Now learn we the prodigious effects</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127780">Of wise ambition: for 'twere easy justice</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127790">To ruin foolish usurpation,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127800">Heaven needs not stickle in't: but when those men</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127810">Who are as accurate, as bad, who can</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127820">So shape their vice into a virtuous mould,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127830">That we repine at the accusers more,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127840">Than at the guilty: when that these men fall,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127850">Who then will call that wise, which he sees bad? </l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127860">Such wisdom made, and ruined him: than ye</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127870">That dazzle with your majesty, and sit</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127880">Too near to thunder, and not fear it, know</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127890"><pb facs="44" n="70"/> Sforza, and learn a wise contempt of wisdom,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127900">Frailty attends your best, and strongest trick,</l>
                <l xml:id="A01853-e127910">And there's no fool unto the politic. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="A01853-e127920">
        <head>The epilogue.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A01853-e127930">
          <l xml:id="A01853-e127940">Somewhat beyond an end? and can there be</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e127950">Tediousness counted an apology? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e127960">It was prolixity of speech offended,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e127970">And can that error by more speech be mended? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e127980">Your patience stints the wonder: that is it</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e127990">Hath dared us to be public, and to fit</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128000">These times of tempest, with a blustering scene. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128010">If ought do please, if we have hit the mean,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128020">That neither cloys the auditor, nor starves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128030">Felicity hath crowned us, if ought swerves</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128040">From plausible invention, know 'twas it</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128050">Which we intend, which is in stead of wit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128060">Tears grace a tragedy, and we are glad</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128070">To have the happy power to make you sad. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128080">Continue it, and our applause is high,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128090">Not from your hand so much, as from your eye. </l>
        </lg>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A01853-e128100">
      <div type="poem" xml:id="A01853-e128110">
        <head>To the ambitious.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A01853-e128120">
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128130">Tell me, mortals, if there be</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128140">Ought beside stupidity</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128150">Hidden in you at the least,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128160">If you are not all one beast</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128170"><pb facs="44"/> wherefore do you cloud your face</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128180">If you want the chiefest place? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128190">Why do you respect? O why? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128200">Not how good 'tis, but how high? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128210">Would you all be Kings? O vain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128220">This is but to entertain</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128230">Such desires, that you may fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128240">Lest the heaven should lend an ear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128250">Lest you have what you desired,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128260">And in your own bogs be mired. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128270">Height is baseness, if it be</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128280">Levelled by equality,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128290">And the earth were a plain still. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128300">If it were but one great hill. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128310">Would you all be Kings? as though</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128320">Standing pools should wish to flow. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128330">Or a river make his plea</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128340">To exceed into a sea:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128350">As if of the stars not one,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128360">But should strive to be the sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128370">Or the lark would partner be</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128380">In the eagle's sovereignty. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128390">Would you not be mad to see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128400">If a beast, a stone, a tree</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128410">To the heavenly powers ran</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128420">Angry that they were not man? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128430">Nay in us consider well</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128440">To what monsters we should swell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128450">If but any part should be</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128460">Of the man's infirmity. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128470">What should lead, or what be led,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128480">If the foet were made the head? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128490">What should speak, or what should see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128500">If this itch of majesty</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128510"><pb facs="45"/> made the mouth, for being nigh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128520">Beg advancement to the eye. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128530">Would you all be Kings, poor men! </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128540">Wish, what you would wish again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128550">Which within your thoughts dares bide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128560">And's not fearful to be tried. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128570">What's a King, consider well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128580">But the public sentinel? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128590">But a beacon, which we find</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128600">Highly subject to the wind? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128610">And can any still desire</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128620">To be worse, so he be higher? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128630">Are you weary of your sleep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128640">Can you count it bliss, to creep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128650">To take pains unto that height,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128660">Whence your fall may gain a weight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128670">Would you all be Kings? you may,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128680">Every man hath regal sway,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128690">And 'tis this the fault does bear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128700">Not that he commands, but where</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128710">Do thy thoughts rebel? would pride</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128720">Have thy worst acts magnified? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128730">Does ambition make thee flee</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128740">To forbidden sovereignty. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128750">Know it is a braver way</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128760">To forbid, than to obey:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128770">Know it is a nobler deed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128780">To give over, than to speed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128790">Were this all? would every one</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128800">But command himself alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128810">But command his own desire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128820">From the thought of rising higher:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128830">It would not be a grief to see</l>
          <l xml:id="A01853-e128840">An universal monarchy. </l>
        </lg>
        <trailer xml:id="A01853-e128850">Finis.</trailer>
        <pb facs="45"/>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A01853"><item xml:id="A01853-sforza" n="49">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-sforza</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">49</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-unassigned" n="40">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">40</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-picinino" n="27">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-picinino</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">27</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-juliano" n="24">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-juliano</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">24</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-isabella" n="24">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-isabella</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">24</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-vitellio" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-vitellio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-caiazzo" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-caiazzo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-ascanio" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-ascanio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-sanseverin" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-sanseverin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-malatesta" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-malatesta</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-belgiosa" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-belgiosa</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-captain" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-captain</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-triulcio" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-triulcio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-galeazzo" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-galeazzo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-galeazzi" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-galeazzi</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-nuncio_3" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-nuncio_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-bettrice" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-bettrice</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-ambassador_2" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-ambassador_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-ambassador_1" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-ambassador_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-suitor_1" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-suitor_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-nuncio_1" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-nuncio_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-soldier" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-soldier</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-umbra" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-umbra</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-nuncio_2" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-nuncio_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-ambassador_3" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-ambassador_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-julia" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-julia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01853-suitor_2" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01853-suitor_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

