<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A01506">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Entertainment at Norwich <date type="creation_date">1578</date></title>
        <author>B. G. (?)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A01506.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The ioyfull receyuing of the Queenes most excellent Maiestie into hir Highnesse citie of Norvvich the things done in the time of hir abode there: and the dolor of the citie at hir departure. Wherein are set downe diuers orations in Latine, pronounced to hir Highnesse by Sir Robert Wood Knight, now Maior of the same citie, and others: and certaine also deliuered to hir Maiestie in vvriting: euery of the[m] turned into English.</title>
            <author>B. G. Bernard Garter.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>28 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2004 November (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99841430</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 11627.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 75.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">6011</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01506</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The ioyfull receyuing of the Queenes most excellent Maiestie into hir Highnesse citie of Norvvich the things done in the time of hir abode there: and the dolor of the citie at hir departure. Wherein are set downe diuers orations in Latine, pronounced to hir Highnesse by Sir Robert Wood Knight, now Maior of the same citie, and others: and certaine also deliuered to hir Maiestie in vvriting: euery of the[m] turned into English.</title>
            <title type="alt">Joyfull receyving of the Queenes most excellent Majestie into hir Highnesse citie of Norwich</title>
            <title type="alt">Joyfull receyving of the Queenes most excellent Majestie into hir Highnesse citie of Norwich.</title>
            <title type="alt">Entertainment at Norwich.</title>
            <title type="alt">Receiuing of the Q. Maiestie into hir citie of Norwich.</title>
            <title type="alt">Receiving of the Q. Majestie into hir citie of Norwich.</title>
            <author>B. G. Bernard Garter.</author>
            <author>Wood, Robert, fl. 1578.</author>
            <author>Googe, Barnabe, 1540-1594,</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[56] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Imprinted by Henrie Bynneman,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
            <date>[1578]</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Heading of dedication signed: Ber. Gar., i.e. Gernard Garter.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Sometimes attributed to Barnabe Googe.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Partly in verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Publication date from STC; Elizabeth's visitation lasted from 16 to 22 Aug. 1578.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-G4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: The receiuing of the Q. Maiestie into hir citie of Norwich.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Another edition has "Henry Bynneman" in imprint.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Elizabeth, -- I, -- Queen of England, -- 1533-1603 -- Poetry.</term>
          <term>Norwich (England) -- History -- Early works to 1800.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A01506-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A01506-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A01506-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e100040">The joyful receiving of the Queen's most excellent majesty into her highness city of Norwich: the thing done in the time of her abode there: and the ●●lor of the city at her departure.</p>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e100050">Wherein are set down divers orations in Latin, pronounced to her highness by sir Robert wood knight, now mayor of the same city, and others: and certain also delivered to her majesty in writing: ●arry of them turned into English.</p>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e100060">
          <figure xml:id="A01506-e100070"/>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e100080">At London, imprinted by Henry Bynneman.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A01506-e100090">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>¶ To the right worshipful sir Owen Hopton knight, the Queen's majesty's lieutenant of her highness tower of London, Ber. Gar. citizen of London wisheth health and increase of worship.</head>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e100100">Sithence at my return from Norwich (Right worshipful) you vouchsafed to impart unto me your earnest desire to understand the order and manner how her majesty was received into that worthy city: I am bold likewise to decipher unto your worship what occasion offered themselves to me upon the same your request. First appeared to me the majesty of my prince, which beautifieth her kingdom, as the bright shining beams of beautiful Phoebus decketh forth the earth: which gladded the hearts of the people there, as they no less laboured to travail forth to view the excellency of their sovereign, than the true labouring bee enforceth herself in the spring time (When dame Flora first decketh the soil) to seek their delights, and our profit, amongst the sweet smelling flowers. Then the abundant clemency of her highness, receiving the loyal hearts of her loving people in part, as good as their meaning deserved, so inflamed their former desires, as every spark kindled a bonfire. The nobility delighting this harmony, so endeavoured to hold in tune every string of this heavenly music, as there seemed but one heart in Queen, counsel, and commonalty. The mayor, magistrates, and good citizens employed their study and substance<pb facs="3"/> to hold on this happy beginning, the prince had her pleasure, the nobility their desire, the whole train such entertainment: as for the time of her continuance there, Norwich seemed (If any such there be) a terrestrial paradise. But when the frowning Friday followed, which called her majesty thence, I leave (Because I am loath to tell) the dolour that was, to the report of them that did see it. These all, right worshipful, upon your demand, presented themselves unto me to be uttered, and these (I think) are the things which you desired to hear. And because I doubt not but that there are a great number of your virtuous mind herein: to satisfy both them and you, I have here set forth what my final capacity could collect (Touching the premises) during the whole time of her abode there. Accept my rude and rash dealing in this my doing, I beseech you, for that your worshipful request carrieth me to my uttermost limit: wherein, though the sudden chop of an unskilful carpenter perhaps disquareth the strong timber of this beautiful 〈◊〉 yet let the skilful eye of your worship and other learned readers (To whom I submit me) place the same to the best purpose, and hold my good will as recompense of my fault, and bind me to them, and you for ever. Vale. </p>
        <closer xml:id="A01506-e100110">
          <signed xml:id="A01506-e100120">Your worships to command. B. G.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A01506-e100130">
      <div type="account" xml:id="A01506-e100140">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>¶ The receiving of the Queen's majesty into her highness' city of Norwich.</head>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e100150">On Saturday being the xvi. of August. 1578. and in the twentieth year of the reign of our most gracious sovereign lady Elizabeth by the grace of God Queen of England, France, and Ireland, defendor of the faith. Etc. the same our most dread and sovereign lady (Continuing her progress in Norfolk) immediately after dinner set forward from Brakenashe, where she had dined with the lady style, being five miles distant from Norwich, towards the same her most dutiful city: sir Robert wood, than esquire, and now knight, mayor of the same city, at one of the clock the same happy day, set forward to meet with her majesty in this order: first there road before him well and seemly mounted, threescore of the most comely young men of the city as bachelors, apparelled all in black Satin doublets, black hose, black taffeta hats and yellow bands, and their universal livery was a mandylion of purple taffeta, laid about with silver lace: and so apparelled, marched forwards two and two in a rank. Then one which represented King Gurgunt, sometime King of England, which builded the castle of Norwich, called Blanch flower, and laid the foundation of the city. He was mounted upon a brave courser, and was thus furnished: his body armed:<pb facs="4"/> his bases of green and white silk: on his head a black velvet hat, with a plume of white feathers. There attended upon him thrée henchmen in white and green: one of them did bear his helmet, the second his tergat, the third his staff. After him a noble company of gentlemen, and wealthy citizens in velvet coats, and other costly furniture, bravely mounted. Then followed the officers of the city every one in his place. Then master sword bearer, with the sword and hat of maintenance. Then master maior, and four and twenty aldermen, and master recorder, all in scarlet gowns, whereof, so many as had been majors of the city, and were justices, did wear their scarlet cloaks. Then followed so many as had been sheriffs, and were no aldermen, in violet gowns, and satin tippets. Then followed divers other, to keep the people from disturbing the array aforesaid. This every thing in due and comely order, they all (Except Gurgunt which stayed her majesties coming within a flight shot or two of the city, where the castle of Blanch flower was in most beautiful prospect) marched forwards to a bridge, called Hartford bridge, the uttermost lymit that way, distant from the city two miles or thereabouts, to meet with her majesty: who, within one hour or little more after their attendance, came in such gracious and princely wife, as ravished the hearts of all her loving subjects, and might have terrified the stoutest heart of any enemy to behold. Whether the majesty of the prince, which is incomparable, or joy of her subjects, which exceeded measure, were the greater, I think would have appalled the judgement of Apollo to define. The acclamations and cries of the people to the almighty god for the preservation of her majesty, rattled so loud, as hardly for a great time could any thing be heard: but at last, as every thing hath an end, the noise appeased: and master maior saluted her highness with the oration following, and yielded to her majesty there with the sword of the city, and a fair standing cup of silver and guilt, with a cover, and in the cup one hundreth pounds in gold. The oration was in these words:</p>
        <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e100160">
          <body xml:id="A01506-e100170">
            <div type="oration" xml:lang="lat" xml:id="A01506-e100180">
              <pb facs="4"/>
              <head>The mayor's oration.</head>
              <p xml:id="A01506-e100190">Si nobis ab optimo maximo concederetur optio quid rerum humanarum nunc potissimum vellemus: nihil duceremus antiquius (Augustissima princeps) quàm ut tuus ille, qui ita nos recreate, castissimi ocelliradius posset in abditissimos cordium nostrorum angulos se confer. Cerneres profecto quanta sint hilaritate perfusa, quàm in ipsis arterijs et venulis spiritus et sanguis gestiant: dum intuemur te huius regni lumen (Ut David olim fuit israelitici) in hijs tandem finibus post longam spem, et ardentissima vota exoriri. Equidem ut pro me, qui tua ex autoritate et clementia (Quod humillimis gratijs profiteor) celeberrimae huic civitati praesum, et pro hijs meis fratribus, atque omni hoc populo quem tuis auspicijs regimus, ex illorum sensu loquar, quod et ipse<pb facs="5"/> sentio: sic nos demum supplicibus votis exposcimus, ut maiestatem tuam benevolam nobis, et propitiam experiamur: ut nunquam cviquam populo aduenisti gratior quàm nobis. In illius rei luculentissimum indicium, insignia haec honoris, et officij nostri, quae nobis clementissimus princeps henricus quartus quinto svi regni anno cum praetore, senatoribus, et vicecomitibus concessit: (Cùm antea Ballivis (Ut vocant) ultra annalium nostrorum memoriam regeremur) perpetuis deinde regum privilegijs, et corroborata nobis, et aucta magnificè, maiestati tuae omnia exhibemus, quae per tuam unius clementiam (Quam cum immortalibus gratijs praedicare nunquam cessabimus) vicesimo iam anno tenuimus. Atque unâ cum illis, hunc thesaurum, quasi pignus nostrarum et voluntatum, et facultatum, quas omnes, quantae, quantulaeve sint, ad tuum arbitrium devovimvs: ut si<pb facs="5"/> quid omni hoc foelicissimi tui temporis decursu admisimus, quod amantissimos, obsequentissimos, amplitudinis tuae saluti, coronae, emolumento devotissimos non deceat: statuas de nobis, et nostris omnibus, pro tua clementissima voluntate. Sin ita clawm huius civitatis (Deo duce) reximus: ut eam in portu salvam maiestati tuae conservaverimvs, et populum primum gloriae dei, et verae religionis, deinde salutis, honoris, et voluntatis tuae studiosissimum, quantum in nobis est, effecerimus: tum non libet nobis id à te petere, quod insita tibi singularis clementia facillimè à te ipsa impetrabit. Tantum obsecramus, ut amplitudinem tuam deus omnibus et animi, et corporis bonis cumulatissimè bear velit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A01506-e100200">
              <pb facs="6"/>
              <head>The mayor's oration englished.</head>
              <p xml:id="A01506-e100210">If our wish should be granted unto us by the almighty, what human thing we would chiefly desire: we would account nothing more precious (Most royal prince) than that the bright beam of your most chaste eye, which doth so cheer us, might penetrate the secret straight corners of our hearts: then surely should you see how great joys are despised there, and how the spirit and lively blood tickle in our arteries and small veins, in beholding thee the light of this realm (As David was of Israel) now at length, after long hope and earnest petitions, to appear in these coasts. Truly on mine own part, which by your highness' authority and clemency (With humble thanks be it spoken) do govern this famous city, and on the part of these my brothers and all these people which by your authority we rule (Speaking as they mean, and as I myself do think) this only with all our hearts and humble prayers we desire, that we may so find your majesty gracious and favourable unto us, as you for your part never came to any subjects better welcome than to us your poor subjects here. For most manifest token whereof, we present unto your majesty here, these signs<pb facs="6"/> of honour and office, which we received of the most mighty prince Henry the fourth, in the fifth year of his reign, then to us granted in the name of mayor, aldermen, and sheriffs, where as before time out of mind or mention, we were governed by bailiffs (As they term them) which ever since have been both established and increased with continual privileges of Kings: and which by your only clemency (Which with immortal thanks we shall never cease to declare) we have now these. xx. years enjoyed: and together with those signs, this treasure is a pledge of our good wills and hability: which all how great or little soever they be, we pour down at your pleasure, that if we have neglected any thing in all this course of your most happy reign, which becometh most loving, obedient, and well willing subjects to perform, for the preservation of your crown, and advancement of your highness, you may then determine of us and all ours, at your most gracious pleasure. But if we have (God being our guide) so ordered the governance of this city, that we have kept the same in safety to your majesty's use, and made the people therein (As much as in us lieth) first, most studious of God's glory and true religion, and next of your majesty's health, honour, and pleasure, then ask we<pb facs="7"/> nothing of you, for that the singular clemency ingraffed in your highness, will easily of itself grant that which is requisite for us to obtain. We only therefore desire, that God would abundantly bless your highness with all good gifts of mind and body.</p>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e100220">Which oration ended, her majesty accepting in good part every thing delivered by the mayor, did thankfully answer him in these words, or very like in effect. We heartily thank you, master maior, and all the rest, for these tokens of goodwill, nevertheless princes have no need of money: God hath endowed us abundantly, we come not therefore, but for that which in right is our own, the hearts and true allegiance of our subjects, which are the greatest riches of a kingdom: whereof as we assure ourselves in you, so do you assure yourselves in us of a loving and gracious sovereign: wherewith was delivered to master maior, a mace or sceptre, which he carried before her to her lodging, which was in the Bishop of Norwich his palace, two miles distant from that place. The cup and money was delivered to a gentleman, one of her majesty's footmen to carry: master maior said to her, sunt hic centum librae puri auri, the cover of the cup lifted up, her majesty said to the footman, look to it, there is a hundreth pound. With that her highness, with the whole company, marched towards Norwich, till they came to a place called the town close, distant from the city a good flightshot, where the party, which represented Gurgunt, came forth, as in manner is expressed, and was ready to have declared to her majesty this speech following: but by reason of a shower of rain which came, her majesty hasted away, the speech not uttered: but thus it was. </p>
        <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e100230">
          <body xml:id="A01506-e100240">
            <div type="speech" xml:id="A01506-e100250">
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100260">Leave of to muse most gracious prince of English soil,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100270">What sudden wight in martial wise approacheth near:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100280"><pb facs="7"/> King Gurgunt I am hight, King Belin's eldest son,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100290">Whose sire Dunwallo first, the British crown did wear. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100300">Whom truthless Gutlack forced to pass the surging seas,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100310">His falsehood to revenge, and Denmark land to spoil. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100320">And finding in return, this place a gallant vent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100330">This castle fair I built, a fort from foreign soil:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100340">To win a conquest, gets renown and glorious name,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100350">To keep and use it well, deserves eternal fame. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100360">When brute through cities, towns, the woods and dales did sound</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100370">Elizabeth this country peerless Queen drew near:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100380">I was found out, myself in person noble Queen</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100390">Did haste, before thy face in presence to appear. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100400">Two thousand years well-nigh in silence lurking still:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100410">Hear, why to thee alone this service I do yield. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100420">Besides that, at my city's suit, their founder first</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100430">Should gratulate most this joyful sight in open field. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100440">Four special points and rare concurring in us both</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100450">This special service have reserved to thee alone:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100460">The glory though of each in thee doth far surmount,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100470">Yet great with small compared, will like appear anon. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100480">When doubtful wars the British princes long had wrong,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100490">My grandsire first uniting all did wear the crown. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100500">Of York and Lancaster, who did conclude the broils? </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100510">Thy grandsire Henry seventh, a King of great renown. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100520">Mine uncle Brennus eke, my father joining hands,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100530">Old Rome did raze, and sack, and half consume with fire:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100540">Thy puissant father so, new Rome that purple whore</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100550">Did sack, and spoil her near of all her glittering tire. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100560">Lo Cambridge schools by mine assignment founded first,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100570">By thee my Cambridge schools are famous through the world,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100580">I thirty wand'ring ships of banished men relieved. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100590">The throngs of banished souls that in this city dwell,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100600">Do weep for joy, and pray for thee with tears untold. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100610">In all these things thou noble Queen dost far excel. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100620">But lo to thee I yield as duty doth me bind</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100630">In open field myself, my city, castle, key,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100640"><pb facs="8"/> most happy father's Kings in such a daughter Queen,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100650">Most happy England were, if thou shouldst never die. </l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100660">Go on most noble prince, for I must haste away,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100670">My city gates do long, their sovereign to receive:</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100680">More true thou never couldst, nor loyal subjects find,</l>
              <l xml:id="A01506-e100690">Whose hearts full fast with perfect love to thee do cleave. </l>
            </div>
          </body>
        </floatingText>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e100700">Then her majesty, drew near the gates of the city called saint Stephen's gates, which with the walls there were both gallantly and strongly repaired. The gate itself was thus enriched and beautified. First theportcullis was new made both timber and iron, than the outward side of the gate was thus beautified: the Queen's arms were most richly and beautifully set forth in the chief front of the gate, on the oneside thereof, but somewhat lower, was placed the scutcheon of s. George, or saint George his cross: on the other side, the arms of the city: and directly under the Queen's majesty's arms was placed thefalcon, her highness' badge in due form, and under the same were written these words, God and the Queen we serve. The inner side of the gate was thus beautified: on the right side was gorgeously set forth the red rose, signifying the house of York, on theleft the side white rose, representing the house of Lancaster: in the midst was the white and red rose united, expressing the union, under thewhich was placed by descent the arms of the Queen, and under that were written these two verses:<quote xml:id="A01506-e100710"><l xml:id="A01506-e100720">Division kindled strife,</l><l xml:id="A01506-e100730">Blessed union quenched the flame:</l><l xml:id="A01506-e100740">Thence sprang our noble phoenix dear, the peerless prince of fame. </l></quote></p>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e100750">And besides that, at this gate, the waits of the city were placed with loud music, who cheerfully and melodiously welcomed her majesty into the city: and then passed she forward, through saint Stephen's street, where the first pageant was placed in form following.</p>
        <div type="pageant" xml:id="A01506-e100760">
          <pb facs="8"/>
          <head>¶ The first pageant was in saint Stephen's parish in this manner. </head>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e100770">It was builded somewhat like the manner of a stage, of xl. foot long, and in breadth eight foot. From the standing place upward, was a bank framed in the manner of a free stone wall, in very decent and beautiful sort: and in the height thereof were written these sentences. Viz. </p>
          <quote xml:id="A01506-e100780">
            <list xml:id="A01506-e100790">
              <item xml:id="A01506-e100800">The causes of this common wealth are,</item>
              <item xml:id="A01506-e100810">God truly preached. <list xml:id="A01506-e100820"><item xml:id="A01506-e100830">Justice duly executed. </item><item xml:id="A01506-e100840">Idleness expelled. </item><item xml:id="A01506-e100850">The people obedient. </item><item xml:id="A01506-e100860">Labour cherished. </item></list></item>
              <item xml:id="A01506-e100870">Universal concord preserved.</item>
            </list>
          </quote>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e100880">From the standing place downward, it was beautified with painters work artificially, expressing to sight the portraiture of these several looms, and the weavers in them (As it were working) and over every loom the name thereof, viz. Over the first loom was written the weaving of worsted: over the second, the weaving of Russels: over the third, the weaving of darnix: over the fourth, the weaving of tuft mockado: the fifth the weaving of lace: the sixth the weaving of Caffa: the seventh the weaving of fringen1. And then was there the portraiture of a matron, and two or thrée children, and over her head was written these words, good nurture changeth qualities. Upon the stage there stood knitting at the one end eight small women children spinning worsted yarn, and at the other end as many knitting of worsted yarn hose: and in the midst of the said stage stood a pretty boy richly apparelled, which represented the common wealth of the city. And all the rest of the stage was furnished with men, which made the said several works, and before every man the work in deed: and every thing thus in readiness, stayed her majesty's coming and when she did come, the child which represented, common wealth, did speak to her highness these words. Viz. </p>
          <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e100890">
            <body xml:id="A01506-e100900">
              <div type="speech" xml:id="A01506-e100910">
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e100920">
                  <pb facs="9"/>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e100930">Most gracious prince, undoubted sovereign Queen,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e100940">Our only joy next god, and chief defence:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e100950">In this small show, our whole estate is seen. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e100960">The wealth we have, we find proceed from thence,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e100970">The idle hand hath here no place to feed,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e100980">The painful wight hath still to serve his need. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e100990">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101000">Again, our seat denies our traffic here,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101010">The sea too near decides us from the rest,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101020">So weak we were within this dozen year,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101030">As care did quench the courage of the best:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101040">But good advice, hath taught these little hands</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101050">To rend in twain the force of pining bands. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e101060">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101070"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A01506-e101080"><p n="1" xml:id="A01506-e101090">1. Pointing to the spinners.</p><p n="2" xml:id="A01506-e101100">2. Pointing to the looms</p><p n="3" xml:id="A01506-e101110">3. Pointing to the works.</p></note>from combed wool we draw this slender thread,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101120">From thence the looms have dealing with the same,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101130">And thence again in order do proceed,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101140">These several works, which skilful art doth frame:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101150">And all to drive dame need into her cave,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101160">Our heads and hands together laboured have. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e101170">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101180">We bought before the things that now we sell,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101190">These slender imps, their works do pass the waves,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101200">God's peace and thine we hold and prosper well,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101210">Of every mouth the hands the charges saves. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101220">Thus through thy help and aid of power divine,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101230">Doth Norwich live, whose hearts and goods are thine. </l>
                </lg>
                <closer xml:id="A01506-e101240">
                  <signed xml:id="A01506-e101250">B. G.</signed>
                </closer>
                <trailer xml:id="A01506-e101260">Finis.</trailer>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e101270">This show pleased her majesty so greatly, as she particularly viewed the knitting and spinning of the children, perused the looms, and noted the several works and commodities which were made by these means: and then after great thanks by her given to the people, marched towards the market place, where was made a second device as followeth.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="pageant" xml:id="A01506-e101280">
          <pb facs="9"/>
          <head>The second pageant.</head>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e101290">The second pageant thwarted the street at the entrance of the market, between master Skinner and master Quash, being in breadth two and fifty foot of assize, and was divided into thrée gates, viz. in the midst a main gate, and on either side a postern: the main gate in breadth fourteen foot, each postern eight foot, their heights equal to their proportion: over each postern was as it were a chamber, which chambers were replenished with music. And over all the gates, passed a stage of eight foot broad, made in the manner of a pageant, both curious, rich, and delightful, the whole work from the pageant downward, seemed to be Jasper and marble. In the forefront towards her majesty, was the arms of England on the one side the gate, and on the other side the falcon with crown and sceptre, which is her own badge. The other side was beautified with the arms of England on the one side the gate, and with the crest of England on the other side. The stage or pageant was replenished with five personages apparelled like women. The first was, the city of Norwich: the second Debora: the third Judith: the fourth Esther: the fifthe Martia, sometime Queen of England. At the first sight of the prince, and till her majesty's coming to the pageant, the musicians, which were close in the chambers of the said pageant, used their loud music, and then ceased: wherewith her highness stayed, to whom the personage representing the city of Norwich, did speak in these words. viz. </p>
          <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e101300">
            <body xml:id="A01506-e101310">
              <div type="speeches" xml:id="A01506-e101320">
                <div type="speech" xml:id="A01506-e101330">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101340">Whom fame resounds with thundering trump, which rends the rattling skies,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101350">And pierceth to the haughty heavens, and thence descending flies</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101360">Through flickering air: and so conjoins the sea and shore together,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101370">In admiration of thy grace, good Queen thou'rt welcome hither,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101380">More welcome than Terpsichore, was to the town of Troy. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101390">Seafaring men by gemini conceive not half my joy:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101400">Strong Hercules to Theseus was never such delight</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101410">Nor Nisus to Euryalus as I have in this sight,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101420">Penelope did never thirst Ulysses more to see</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101430">Than I poor Norwich hungered have to gain the sight of thee. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101440"><pb facs="10"/>And now that these my happy eyes behold thy heavenly face,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101450">The lord of lords I humbly pray, to bliss thy noble grace</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101460">With Nestor's life, with Sibyl's health, with Croesus' stock and store,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101470">With all good gifts of Salomon, and twice as many more. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101480">What should I say? thou art my joy next god, I have none other,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101490">My Princess and my peerless Queen, my loving nurse and mother. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101500">My goods and lands, my hands and heart, my limbs and life are thine,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101510">What is mine own in right or thought, to thee I do resign. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101520">Grant then (O gracious sovereign Queen) this only my request,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101530">That that which shall be done in me, be construed to the best. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101540">And take in part my slender shows, wherein my whole pretence</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101550">Is for to please you majesty, and end without offence. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101560">So shall I clap my hands for joy, and hold myself as rich</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101570">As if I had the gold of Jude, and double twice as much. </l>
                  <closer xml:id="A01506-e101580">
                    <signed xml:id="A01506-e101590">B. G.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer xml:id="A01506-e101600">Finis.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="speech" xml:id="A01506-e101610">
                  <head>Then spoke Debora</head>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101620">Where princes sitting in their thrones set god before their sight</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101630">And live according to his law, and guide their people right,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101640">There doth his blessed gifts abound, there kingdoms firmly stand</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101650">There force of foes cannot prevail, nor fury fret the land. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101660">Myself (O peerless prince) do speak by proof of matter past,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101670">Which proof by practice I performed, and foiled his foes at last. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101680">For Jabin King of Canaan, poor Israel did spite,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101690">And meant by force of furious rage to overrun us quite. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101700">Nine hundred iron chariots, he brought into the field. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101710">With cruel captain Sisera by force to make us yield. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101720">His force was great, his fraud was more, he fought, we did defend,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101730">And twenty winters long did last this war without an end. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101740">But he that neither sleeps nor slacks such furies to correct,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101750">Appointed me Debora for the judge of his elect:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101760">And did deliver Sisera into a woman's hand. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101770">I slew them all, and so in rest his people held the land. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101780">So mighty prince, that puissant lord, hath placed thee here to be,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101790">The rule of this triumphant realm alone belongeth to thee. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101800"><pb facs="10"/>Continue as thou hast begun, weed out the wicked rout,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101810">Uphold the simple, meek and good, pull down the proud and stout. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101820">Thus shalt thou live and reign in rest, and mighty God shalt please. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101830">Thy state be sure, thy subjects safe, thy common wealth at ease. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101840">Thy god shall grant thee length of life, to glorify his name,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e101850">Thy deeds shall be recorded, in the book of lasting fame. </l>
                  <closer xml:id="A01506-e101860">
                    <signed xml:id="A01506-e101870">B. G.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer xml:id="A01506-e101880">Finis.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="speech" xml:id="A01506-e101890">
                  <head>Then spoke Judith. </head>
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e101900">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e101910">O flower of grace, o prime of gods elect,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e101920">O mighty Queen and finger of the lord,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e101930">Did God sometime by me poor wight correct. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e101940">The champion stout that him and his abhorred? </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e101950">Then be thou sure thou art his mighty hand,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e101960">To conquer those which him and thee withstand. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e101970">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e101980">The rage of foes Betbulia did besiege,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e101990">The people faint were ready for to yield:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102000">God aided me poor widow ne'ertheless,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102010">To enter into Holofernes field,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102020">And with this sword by his directing hand,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102030">To slay his foe, and quiet so the land. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e102040">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102050">If this his grace were given to me poor wight,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102060">If widows hand could vanquish such a foe:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102070">Then to a prince of thy surpassing might. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102080">What tyrant lives but thou mayest overthrow. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102090">Persever then his servant as thou art,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102100">And hold for aye a noble victor's part. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer xml:id="A01506-e102110">
                    <signed xml:id="A01506-e102120">B. G.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer xml:id="A01506-e102130">Finis.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="speech" xml:id="A01506-e102140">
                  <head>Then Hester spoke.</head>
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e102150">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102160">The fretting heads of furious foes have skill,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102170">As well by fraud as force to find their prey:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102180">In smiling looks doth lurk a lot as ill,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102190">As where both stern and sturdy streams do sway,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102200">Thyself o Queen, a proof hath seen of this,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102210">So well as I poor Esther have iwis. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e102220">
                    <pb facs="11"/>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102230">As Jabin's force did Israel perplex,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102240">And Holofernes fierce Betbuliel besiege,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102250">So Hamon's slights sought me and mine to vex,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102260">Yet showed a face a subject to his liege. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102270">But force nor fraud, nor tyrant strong can trap,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102280">Those which the lord in his defence doth wrap. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e102290">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102300">The proofs I speak by us have erst been seen,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102310">The proofs I speak, to thee are not unknown. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102320">Thy god thou knowest most dread and sovereign Queen,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102330">A world of foes of thine hath overthrown,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102340">And hither now triumphantly doth call</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102350">Thy noble grace, the comfort of us all. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e102360">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102370">Dost thou not see the joy of all this flock? </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102380">Vouchsafe to view their passing gladsome cheer,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102390">Be still (Good Queen) their refuge and their rock,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102400">As they are thine to serve in love and fear:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102410">So fraud, nor force, nor foreign foe may stand</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e102420">Against the strength of thy most puissant hand. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer xml:id="A01506-e102430">
                    <signed xml:id="A01506-e102440">B. G.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer xml:id="A01506-e102450">Finis.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="speech" xml:id="A01506-e102460">
                  <head>Then spoke Martia. </head>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102470">With long discourse (O puissant prince) some tract of time we spend,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102480">Vouchsafe yet now a little more, and then we make an end. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102490">The thundering blast of fame, whereof dame Norwich first did speak,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102500">Not only shook the air and skies, but all the earth did break,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102510">It rend up graves, and bodies raised, each spirit took his place,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102520">And this alonely word was heard: here cometh the pearl of grace,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102530">Here comes the jewel of the world, her peoples whole delight,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102540">The paragon of present time, and prince of earthly might. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102550">The voice was strange, the wonder more: for when we viewed the earth</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102560">Each prince that erst had reigned here, received again his breath,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102570">And with his breath, a liberty to hold again his place,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102580">If any one amongst us all exceed your noble grace. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102590">Some comfort every one conceived to catch again his own,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102600">His utmost skill was trimly used, to have his virtues known. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102610">The plays surpass my skill to tell, but when each one had said,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102620"><pb facs="11"/> Apollo did himself appear and made us all dismayed. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102630">Will you contend with her (Quoth he,) within whose sacred breast</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102640">Dame Pallas and myself have framed our sovereign seat of rest? </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102650">Whose skill directs the muses nine, whose grace doth Venus stain:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102660">Her eloquence like Mercury: like Juno in her train? </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102670">Whose god is that eternal love which holds us all in awe? </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102680">Believe me, you exceed the bounds of equity and law. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102690">Therewith they shrunk themselves aside, not one I could espy,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102700">They couched them in their caves again and there full quiet lie,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102710">Yet I that Martia hight, which sometime ruled this land,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102720">As Queen for thirty three years space, gate licence at his hand,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102730">And so Gurguntius did, my husband's father dear,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102740">Which built this town and castle both, to make our homage here,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102750">Which homage mighty Queen accept: the realm and right is thine:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102760">The crown, the sceptre, and the sword to thee we do resign. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102770">And wish to God, that thou mayst reign, twice Nestor's years in peace,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102780">Triumphing over all thy foes, to all our joys increase. Amen. </l>
                  <closer xml:id="A01506-e102790">
                    <signed xml:id="A01506-e102800">B. G.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer xml:id="A01506-e102810">Finis.</trailer>
                </div>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e102820">Herewith she passed under the gate, with such thanks, as plainly expressed her noble nature: and the musicians within the gate upon their soft instruments used broken music, and one of them did sing this ditty.</p>
          <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e102830">
            <body xml:id="A01506-e102840">
              <div type="song" xml:id="A01506-e102850">
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e102860">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102870">From slumber soft I fell asleep ,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102880">From sleep to dream, from dream to deep delight,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102890">Each gem the gods had given the world to keep</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102900">In princely wise came present to my sight:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102910">Such solace then did sink into my mind,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102920">As mortal man on mould could never find. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e102930">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102940">The gods did strive, and yet their strives were sweet,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102950">Each one would have a virtue of her own,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102960">Dame Juno thought the highest place most meet</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102970">For her, because of riches was her throne. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102980">Dame Venus thought by reason of her love</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e102990">That she might claim the highest place above. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e103000">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103010"><pb facs="12"/>The virgin's state Diana still did praise,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103020">And Ceres praised the fruit of fertile soil:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103030">And prudence did dame Pallas chiefly raise. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103040">Minerva all for eloquence did strive,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103050">They smiled to see their quarelling estate ▪</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103060">And Jove himself decided their debate. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e103070">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103080">My sweets (Quod he) leave of your sugared strife,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103090">In equal place I have assigned you all:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103100">A sovereign wight there is that heareth life,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103110">In whose sweet heart I have enclosed you all. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103120">Of England soil she is the sovereign Queen,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103130">Your vigours there do flourish fresh and green. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e103140">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103150">They skipped for joy and gave their frank consent,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103160">The noise resounded to the haughty sky:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103170">With one loud voice they cried all, content,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103180">They clapped their hands, and therewith waked I.</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103190">The world and they concluded with a breath,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e103200">And wished long reign to Queen Elizabeth. </l>
                </lg>
                <closer xml:id="A01506-e103210">
                  <signed xml:id="A01506-e103220">B. G.</signed>
                </closer>
                <trailer xml:id="A01506-e103230">Finis</trailer>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103240">Herewith she passed through the market place, which was goodly garnished, and thence through the other streets which were trimly decked, directly to the cathedral church, where te deum was song, and after service she went to the Bishop's palace, where her majesty kept thetime she continued in Norwich. All this was upon Saturday the xvi. of August. 1578. </p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103250">Upon the Monday following, m. churchyard brought Mercury in a gallant coach strangely apparelled, into the green yard under the privy or bedchamber window, out of the which, the Queen's majesty looked: which Mercury, in verse made for thepurpose, uttered to her highness, that if it were her pleasure at any time to take the air abroad, there were devises to be seen to pleasure her majesty, and according to that promise, on Tewsday following (For before that day by means of the weather she went not abroad) he performed a very pretty pleasant show before her highness without s. Benel's gates as she went towards<pb facs="12"/> Cossie park to hunt. In which day the minister of the Dutch church pronouncing to her majesty the oration following, presented the cup therein mentioned, which I esteem to be worth fifty pounds, very curiously wrought.</p>
          <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e103260">
            <body xml:id="A01506-e103270">
              <div type="oration" xml:lang="lat" xml:id="A01506-e103280">
                <head>Oratio ad serenissimam angliae reginam habita. 19. Augusti. 1578. à ministro ecclesiae belgogermanicae nordovici in loco publico.</head>
                <p xml:id="A01506-e103290">Magna oratoribus qui percelebrat●rum aetate vixerunt fuit laus, serenissima regina, quod judicum animos partim svaviloquentia, partim posita rei personaeque ante ipsorum oculos calamitate, in quemcunque vellent animi habitum transformarent: prius membrum non vulgarem nobis ob oculos ponit hominum facilitatem, quod adeo sequaces dictoque audientes fuerint, ut se linguis duci paterentur: posterius magnam ubique apud gentes, quarum respublica optabili ordine fuit constituta obtinuit gratiam: long autem maiorem apud cos qui christo nomen dederunt: omnium verò maximam apud te o serenissima regina, ecclesiae christi matrix, cuius animum verbo dei obsequentem instruxit, non fucatus hic sermo, sed christi spiritus, pietatisque zelus: ipsissima piorum calamitas afflictorumque lachrymae, lachrymae inquam christifidelium te commoverunt, misera dispersaque christi membra quibusuis iniurijs obiecta, mille iam mortibus territa, in tutelam salutemque animi iuxta ac corporis recipere atque protegere: ob haec singularia tua in nos pietatis beneficia, et quod tutore optimo magistratus in hac tua nordovicensi urbe (Quam maiestas tua nobis ob christi religionem exulantibus domicilij loco clemeter concessit) vivimus, add quod populi in nos animum favorabilem experimur, inprimis deo patri, et domino unico servatori nostro jesu christo, deinde et tibi serenissimae reginae immortales non quas debemus sed quas possimus agimus gratias: porrò humile quidem et unicum tamen nostrum est votum, animi nostri gratitudinem maiestati tuae ostendere: ecce igitur nullum munus, sed animum nostrum: nullum regium splendorem, sed pietatis posteritatisque monumentum serenissimae tuae maiestati consecratum, hoc autem co gratius maiestati tua<pb facs="13"/> ●ore confidimus, quod inculpati pijssimique josephi historia dei erga maiestatem tuam bonitas, ad vinum sit delineata, quem nulla astutia, nullum robur, nulla denique regnandi libido, sed fides constans, Christiani pectoris pietas, coelestisque virtus, singulari dei favore ex sanguinaria fratrum conspiration, mortisque metu, ad summam dignitatem, regnique decus evexerunt: in huius fratres non ●liena videtur proverbialis illa apud habraeos sententia, invidia malarum rerum Appetitus, et studium variae gloriae hominibus saepissime occasio sunt svi interitus, tamen quod josephi animum attinet, ea fuit praeditus et temperantia, et fortitudine, ut nimis iniquus simul et pranus censeri posset, qui eum vel minimo vindicandi affectu accusare velit, adco dei providentiae et se, et omne vitae svae studium, vitae inquam in alieno regno discrimen commisit, ut non aliunde quàm à solo dei nutu pendere visus sit: sed quorsum ista? In te ne haec ipsa aliaque consimilia o serenissima regina, et regni tui ratione omnium oculis conspicua sunt? Haec inquam esse ecclesiae christi foelicissimum gaudium, spiritual diadema, et summum decus, huius vero regni verè regium splendorem, atque perennem gloriam, quis nisi mente captus inficias ire potest? Pijssime tu quidem singulari dei bonitate animum josephi tum in regni tui conservation, tum in regno christi amplificando imitata es o nutrix ecclesiae dei fidelissima, solius enim dei est nunc per res (Prout hominum ●culis sunt subiectae) secundasdisperdere, illum autem per quaevis tentationum genera rerumque discrimina extollere: quos ut vasa svae misericordiae agnoscit, ita etiam et bonitate et spiritus svi tum consolation, tum fortitudine ad aeterna vitae foelicitatem prosequitur: quod nostrum votum ratum esse, maiestatem tuam regnique ordinem spirituali prudentia ac sapientia stabilire, camque in longam aetatem servare, tuae item maiestatis subditos vera svi cognition magis ac magis imbuere, dignetur bonus ille and clemens deus, per merita filij svi domini nostri jesu christi. Amen.</p>
              </div>
              <div type="account" xml:lang="lat" xml:id="A01506-e103300">
                <pb facs="13"/>
                <p xml:id="A01506-e103310">Regiae maiestati post orationem oblation est monumentum aliquod, in cuius superficie artificiose sculpta erat historia josephi; e● genesi.</p>
                <p xml:id="A01506-e103320">In circumferentia vero hoc carmen.</p>
                <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e103330">
                  <body xml:id="A01506-e103340">
                    <div type="inscription" xml:id="A01506-e103350">
                      <l xml:id="A01506-e103360">Innocuum pietas ad regia sceptra josephum,</l>
                      <l xml:id="A01506-e103370">Ex manibus fratrum, carnificisque, rapit:</l>
                      <l xml:id="A01506-e103380">Carcere et insidijs sic te regina tuorum</l>
                      <l xml:id="A01506-e103390">Ereptam duxit culmina ad ista deus. </l>
                    </div>
                  </body>
                </floatingText>
                <p xml:id="A01506-e103400">Inscriptio eras in ipsius capacitate scripta in orbem, hoc modo. </p>
                <p xml:id="A01506-e103410">Serenissimae angliae reginae elizabethae, ecclesiae belgicae nordovici ob religionem exulantes, hoc monumentum et pietatis et posteritatis ergô consecrabant. 1578.</p>
                <p xml:id="A01506-e103420">In interiore ipsus parte erat insigne serpentis in gyrum conuo●●ti, cvi media insidebat columba, cum hoc christi elogio: prudens ut serpens, simplex ut columba. </p>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e103430">
            <body xml:id="A01506-e103440">
              <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A01506-e103450">
                <head>¶ The minister of the Dutch church his oration in English.</head>
                <p xml:id="A01506-e103460">The orators (Most gracious Queen) which lived in the age of them that won greatest renown; were highly commended, for that they could transform the judge's minds partly, by eloquence, and partly by setting down before their eyes the calamity of the thing and person they spoke of, into what disposition them listed: the first part declareth unto us no common facility of men, in that they were so willing in following, and attentive in hearing, as they would suffer themselves to be led by eloquence: the last, obtained great favour amongst all nations, whose common weal was governed in good order, and far greater amongst the Christians: but greatest of all with thee oh most excellent Queen, the nurse of Christ his church, whose mind obedient to god's word, the spirit of Christ, and zeal of godliness, and not this profane kind of speech hath instructed: the very calamity of godly men, and tears of the afflicted, the tears, I say, of faithful Christians have thoroughly moved thee to defend and protect the miserable and dispersed members of Christ object to every kind of injury, before beaten in pieces by<pb facs="14"/> a thousand deaths with the safety and preservation as well of mind as body: for these thy singular benefits of godliness towards us, and that we live under so good a tutor being magistrate in this the city of Norwich, which thy majesty hath of clemency granted unto us for a mansion place, which were banished for Christ his religion, and moreover that we find the minds of the people favourable towards us, first we give immortal thanks, not such as we ought, but such as we are able unto God the father, and the lord our only saviour Jesus Christ, and then unto thee most merciful Queen. Moreover it is our humble and yet our only petition to show unto your majesty the thankfulness of our mind: behold therefore dedicated to your most excellent majesty not any gift but our mind, no princely jewel but a monument of godliness and posterity, the which we hope will be so much the more acceptable to your majesty, for because the goodness of God towards your majesty is lively drawn out of the history of the innocent and most godly Josephus, whom neither policy, strength nor desire of bearing rule, but constant faith, godliness of a Christian heart, and heavenly virtue by God's singular mercy, delivered from the bloody conspiracy of his brothers and fear of death, and brought unto high dignity and royal kingdom: to whose brothers that proverbial sentence of the Hebrews is very fitly alluded. Envy being the desire of evil things, and covetousness of transitory renown, is often times the occasion of man's destruction: but touching the mind of Josephus, the same was endued with such temperance and fortitude, that he might be thought no less unjust than wicked, that would accuse him so much as with the least affection of revengement: so wholly did he commit himself and all the government of his life, his life, I say, put in hazard in a strange kingdom unto the providence of God, that he seemed to hang of no other thing than the only will of God. But to what end speak I this? Are not these self same things, and others there like (O most excellent Queen) by the eyes of all men clearly beholden in thee, and the order of thy kingdom? What man (I say) having his wits, can deny these things to be the most happy joy, spiritual crown, and chiefest ornament of Christ's church, and truly of this kingdom the princely beauty and perpetual renown? Thou surely dost follow most holily, the mind of Josephus, by the singular goodness of God, as well in preserving thy kingdom, as in amplifying the kingdom of Christ (O thou most faithful nurse of the church of God:) for it is in God only to destroy this man by prosperity (As it seemeth unto man) and advance another by all kinds of adversity and human danger: whom he acknowledgeth as the vessels of his mercy: and so by his goodness, together with the consolation and strength of his spirit, doth bring them to the happiness of eternal life, which our petition<pb facs="14"/> that good and merciful God grant may be ratified in establishing your majesty and governance of your kingdom with spiritual wisdom and understanding, in preserving the same for many years, and in induing your majesty's subjects more and more with true knowledge of him, for his son's sake our lord Jesus Christ. Amen.</p>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103470">The oration ended, there was a certain monument presented to her princely majesty, in the upper part whereof, was artificially graven the history of Josephus out of genesis. </p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103480">In the compass thereof was this verse. </p>
          <quote xml:id="A01506-e103490">
            <l xml:id="A01506-e103500">To royal sceptres, godliness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A01506-e103510">Josephus innocent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A01506-e103520">Doth take, from brother's bloody hands, and murderer's intent. </l>
            <l xml:id="A01506-e103530">So thee, oh Queen, the lord hath led from prison and deceit</l>
            <l xml:id="A01506-e103540">Of thine, unto these highest tops of your princely estate. </l>
          </quote>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103550">In the inner part of the same, there was the figure of a serpent, interfolding itself: in the midst whereof did sit a dove with this sentence of Christ, mat. 10.16. Wise as the serpent, and meek as the dove. </p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103560">The Wednesday towards evening, master Church-yard was likewise ready upon the water with another device, when her majesty was without the gates towards mount Surrey, but weather hindered it so, as nothing was then done by him. But as she returned homeward, within Bishop's gate at the hospital door, master Stephan Limbert, master of the grammar school in Norwich stood ready to render her an oration: her majesty drew near unto him, and thinking him fearful, said graciously unto him: be not afeard. He answered her again in English: I thank your majesty, for your good encouragement: and then with good courage entered into this oration.</p>
          <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e103570">
            <body xml:id="A01506-e103580">
              <div type="oration" xml:lang="lat" xml:id="A01506-e103590">
                <pb facs="15"/>
                <head>¶ Ad illustrissimam principem elizabetham angliae, franciae, et hiberniae reginam etc. ante fores<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e103600"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg> nordouicensis, oratio stephani limberti ludimagistri publici.</head>
                <p xml:id="A01506-e103610">Aegyptum fama est inundante nilo (Serenissima regina,) et aureo pactoli flumine quotannis lidiam irrigari, quaeres in ijs agris maxima faecunditatis causa putatur: in nos autem atque adeo universam angliam, qua late patet, non è tmolo aut alijs nescio quibus montibus, sed ex illo perenni et uberrimo fonte bonitatis tuae, multi maximique pietatis, iusliciae, mansuetudinis, aliorumque innumerabilium bonorum, prae quibus iam viluit aurum et obsolevit, coptos●ssimi rivi profluxerunt. Atque ut ex infinitis vel unum leutter attingam, propterca quòd de pluribus dicere nec est huius loci et temporis, nec facultatis meae. Insignem illam misericordiam celsitudinis tuae, nobilissima regina, et ad levandum pauperrimorum hominum inopiam incredibilem propensionem (Qua de plurimis virtutibus nulla deo gratior,<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e103620"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg> ut canit homerus,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A01506-e103630"><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e103640">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg></note> in summa principe nulla mortalibus admitabilior esse potest) quibus tandem laudibus efferemus? quàm honorificis verbis prosequemur? <seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e103650">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>, hoc est, hospitium pauperum celeberrimum est apud omnes posteros regiae virtutis atque beneficentiae monumentum futurum, institutum quidem ab illustrissimo Henrico, patre celsitudinis tuae, a nobilissimo edouardo fratre maximis tabulis consignatum, à tua verò maiestate, quod non minorem laudem meretur, cringlefordiensibus fundis et possessionibus egregiè nuper auctum atque amplificatum, ut non tam alients iam ornamentis quàm proprijs virtutibus meritò laetari possis. Recordata quip es pro tua singulari prudentia atque erudition, divinam illam sapientissimi platonis legem, quam unde cimo de legibus libro scriptam reliquit,<pb facs="15"/><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e103660"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>. tantamigitur benignitatem, tam eximiam, et incredibilem misericordiam tuam, (Illustrissima princeps) quibus complectemur studijs? quibus officijs, aut qua voce grati animi voluntatem testificabimur? Cùm enim omnes referendae gratiae study and labour, vel accuratissimas rationes exquisiverimus, ne uni us quidem huius beneficij, quo nos augustissimae maiestati tuae obstrictos esse et devinctos agnoscimus, magnitudinem assequi poterimus. Superabimur vel ab hoc uno et singulari merito, nedum sperandum est, ut immenso reliquorum meritorum pelago, quod tum in omnes tibi subditos publicè, et generatim, tum in hanc civitatem proprie ac particulatim exundavit, pares esse queamus. Verè nos iam<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e103670"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg> incolimus, and in beatis illis insulis de quibus meminit Hesiodus<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e103680"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg> aetatem agimus, qui non modo frugibus, lana, pecore, alijsque subsidijs humanae vitae, sed multo magis verae religionis verbique divini, in quibus animi solis acquiescunt preciosissimis opibus abundamus. Sunt qui britanniam alterum orbem appellaverunt, quod hac aetate nostra dici rectissime posse arbitror, cùm enivi omnes undique terrae gravissimis bellis affligantur, et discordiarum iactentur fluctibus, soli nos, celsitudine tua clanum moderante, in pacatissimo portu navigamus, et ab orbe malorum disiuncti, in caelum quodammodo foelicitatis sublati videmur. Quod est ergo officij nostri, primum deo opt. Max. gratias agimus, cuius unius bonitati omnem hanc, quantacunque est, be atitudinem acceptam referimus, precamurque ut cam nobis propriam et perpetuam esse velit: deinde celsitudini tuae, serenissima regina, cuius opera, cura, solicitudine, et partam hanc nobis foelicitatem et tot annos conservatam agnoscimus. Laetamur hoc aspectu tuo, et gratulamur incredibili study, quod tum ex meo ipsius sensu loquor, tum omnes qui iam undique confluxerunt nordovicenses tui à me dici postulant. Atque utinam in haec pectora possess oculos inserere, et occultos animorum nostrorum sinus perlustrare, videres profectò inclusam intus, quae tantis angustijs erumpere non potest, infinitam molem voluntatis. Fidem omnem, studium, observantiam, quae tantae principi debentur, ut hactenus promptissimè detulimus, ita studiosissimè semper deferemus, et si quando<pb facs="16"/> casus aliquis inciderit (Quod deus omen avertat) ut sacrosanctae maiestatis tuae, aut istius florentissimi regni vel salus in discrimen veniat, vel dignitas periclitetur, non solum bonorum omnium ac facultatum effusionem, sed laterum nostrorum oppositus et corporum pollicemur. Rogamus deinde et obsecramus excellentiam tuam, illustrissima regina, ut et hoc nostrum qualecunque officium a summa benevolentia animoque quàm gratissimo profectum boni consulas, et de nobis nordovicensibus sic existimes, ad lautiores te fortasse subditos venisse saepe, ad laetiores nunquam.</p>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e103690">
            <body xml:id="A01506-e103700">
              <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A01506-e103710">
                <head>The oration of Stephan Limbert, public schoolmaster, to the most magnificent prince, Elizabeth of England, France, and Ireland Queen, etc. before the gates of the hospital of Norwiche.</head>
                <p xml:id="A01506-e103720">It is reported (Most gracious Queen,) that Egypt is watered with the yearly overflowing of Nilus, and Lidia with the golden stream of Pactolus, which thing is thought to be the cause of the great fertility of these countries: but upon us, and farther, over all England, even in the uttermost borders many and main rivers of godliness, justice, humility, and other innumerable good things, in comparison of the which, gold is vile and naught worth, do most plentifully gush out, and those not from Tmolus, or other hills I know not which, but from that continual and most abundant wellspring of your goodness. And that of those infinite goodnesses I may lightly touch one, for that neither place, time, nor my faculty doth permit to speak of many: with what praises shall we extol: with what magnificent words shall we express that<pb facs="16"/> notable mercy of your highness, most renowned Queen, and uncredible readiness to relieve the need of poor men, than the which of many virtues none can be more acceptable unto God, as Homer writeth, neither any virtue in a mighty prince more wondered at amongst men. This hospital of poor men is most famous, which will be a monument of princely virtue and beneficence amongst all posterity, instituted by the most mighty King Henry your highness' father, confirmed with the great seal, by the most noble King Edward your brother, but by your majesty which deserveth no less praise, of late notably increased and amplified by the lands and possessions of Cringleford, that you may not now worthily rejoice so much in others ornaments, as your own virtues. For you are said for your singular wisdom and learning, to have studied that divine law of the most wise Plato, which he left written in the eleventh book of laws. Such your great bounty therefore, so exceeding, and incredible mercy (Oh most virtuous prince) in what books shall we comprehend? with what duties, or with what voice shall we testify the good will of a thankful mind? For when we diligently seek all the most exquisite and curious means of thanksgiving: we cannot so much as attain unto the greatness of this one benefit, by the which we acknowledge ourselves bound and straight holden to your most royal majesty. We shall be overcome, even with this one and singular benefit, so much the less hope have we then in any point to countervail the huge sea of the rest of thy benefits which overfloweth on every side as well publicly and generally over all thy subjects, as properly and particularly upon this city. We certainly now inhabit, and lead our lives in those most happy lands of the which Hesiodus maketh mention, which not only abound with all manner of grain, will, cattle, and other aids of man's life, but much more with the most precious treasure of true religion and the word of God, in the which only the minds of men have rest and peace. There be that call England another world, which I think may be most true in this our age: for whereas all lands on every side of us are afflicted with most grievous wars, and tossed with the floods of dissension, we only, your highness governing our stern, do sail in a most peaceable haven, and severed from the world of mischiefs, do seem after a sort to be taken up into a heaven of happiness. We therefore, according to our bounden duty, first give thanks unto God almighty, unto whose goodness only with thanks we refer all this our happiness, how great soever it be, and pray that he would vouchsafe to make the same proper and perpetual unto us. And afterwards, unto your highness, (Oh most gracious Queen) by whose study, care and diligence we confess this blessedness to be gotten, and so many years preserved unto us.</p>
                <p xml:id="A01506-e103730"><pb facs="17"/>We are glad in this beholding you, and we rejoice with desire more than may be believed, which as I speak of mine own thought, so also all these subjects of Norwich desire me to say the same in their behalf. And I would to God you could pierce these our breasts with your eyes, and thoroughly view the hidden and covered creeks of our minds: then undoubtedly should you behold an infinite heap of good will closely shut up within, which cannot break out of so narrow straits. All the faith, study, and obedience, which are due to so great a prince, as hitherto we have most willingly employed, so will we always most diligently perform the same: and if at any time any chance shall happen (Which fortune God turn from us) that the state of thy blessed majesty or of this florishing realm should come in danger, or the worthiness thereof be in hazard, we do not only protest the effusion of all our goods and substance, but also the putting forth and brunt of our strengths and bodies therein. Finally we desire and beseech thy excellency (Most renowned Queen) well to accept of this our duty, howsoever it be, proceeding from a singular good will, and a most thankful mind, and so to think of us citizens of Norwich, that perhaps you have many times come to people more wealthy, but to more joyful never.</p>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103740"><gap extent="1" unit="pages" xml:id="A01506-e103750" n="17-a-2700"/><pb facs="17"/>Immediately after the beginning of the oration, her majesty called to her the French ambassadors, whereof there were iij. and divers English lords, and willed them to hearken, and she herself was very attentive, even until the end thereof. And the oration ended, after she had given great thanks therefore to master Limbert, she said to him: it is the best that ever I heard, you shall have my hand, and pulled off her glove, and gave him her hand to kiss, which before kneeling on his knee, he arose and kissed, and then she departed to the court, without any other show that night, but that she sent back to know his name.</p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103760">The next night being Thursday, there was an excellent princely mask brought before her after supper, by master Goldingham in the privy chamber, it was of gods and goddesses, both strangely and richly apparelled.</p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103770">The first that entered was Mercury. </p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103780">Then entered two torch-bearers in purple taffeta mandelions laid with silver lace, as all other the torchberers were.</p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103790">Then entered a consort of music, viz six musicians, all in long vestures of white sarsenet girded about them, and garlands on their heads playing very cunningly.</p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103800">Then two torch-bearers more.</p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103810">The Jupiter and Juno. </p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103820">Then two torch bearers more.</p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103830">Then Mars and Venus. </p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103840">Then two torch bearers more.</p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103850">Then Apollo and Pallas. </p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103860">Then two torch-bearers.</p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e103870">Then Neptune and Diana: and last cometh Cupido and concludeth thematter. Thus when they had once marched about the chamber, Mercury dischargeth his message in these words to the Queen.</p>
          <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e103880">
            <body xml:id="A01506-e103890">
              <div type="masque" xml:id="A01506-e103900">
                <sp xml:id="A01506-e103910" who="A01506-mayor">
                  <p xml:id="A01506-e103920">The good meaning mayor, and all his brothers, with the rest, have not rested from praying unto the gods to prosper thy coming hither, and the gods themselves moved by their unfeigned prayers, are ready in person to bid thee worthily welcome, and I Mercury the god of merchants and merchandise, and therefore a favourer of these citizens, being thought meetest and chosen fittest to signify the same. <pb facs="18"/>Gods there be also which cannot come, being tied by the time of the year, as Ceres in harvest, Bacchus in wines, Pomena in orchards. Only Himineus denyeth his good will, either in presence, or in person: notwithstanding, Diana hath so counterchecked him therefore, as he shall ever hereafter be at your commandment. For my part, as I am a rejoicer at your coming, so am I a furtherer of your welcome hither, and for this time I bid you farewell.</p>
                </sp>
                <stage xml:id="A01506-e103930">Then marched they about again, and that done, Jupiter spoke to the Queen in this sort, and then gave her a ryding wand of whales ●n curiously wrought.</stage>
                <sp xml:id="A01506-e103940" who="A01506-jupiter">
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e103950">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e103960">Fear not o Queen, thou art beloved so,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e103970">As subjects true, will truly thee defend:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e103980">Fear not my power to overthrow thy woe,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e103990">I am the God that can each miss amend. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104000">Thou dost know, great Jupiter am I,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104010">That gave thee first thy happy sovereignty. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e104020">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104030">I give thee still, as ever thou haste had,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104040">A peerless power, unto thy dying day:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104050">I give thee rule to overcome the bad,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104060">And love, to love thy loving subjects aye. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104070">I give thee here this small and slender wand,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104080">To show, thou shalt in quiet rule the land. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <stage xml:id="A01506-e104090">Then Juno spoke, whose gift was a purse curiously wrought.</stage>
                <sp xml:id="A01506-e104100" who="A01506-juno">
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e104110">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104120">Is Juno rich? no sure she is not so</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104130">She wants that wealth, that is not wanting here,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104140">Thy good gets thee friends, my wealth wins many a foe,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104150">My riches rusts, thine shine passing clear. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104160">Thou art beloved of subjects far and nigh,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104170">Which is such wealth as money cannot buy. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e104180">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104190">Farewell fair Queen, I cannot give thee aught,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104200">Nor take away thy good that is so bound:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104210">Thou canst not give, that I so long have sought,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104220">Ne can I hold the riches thou hast found. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104230"><pb facs="18"/>Yet take this gift, though poor I seem to be,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104240">That thou thyself shalt never poorer be. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <stage xml:id="A01506-e104250">Then after they had marched again about, Mars gave his gift, which was a fair pair of knives, and said.</stage>
                <sp xml:id="A01506-e104260" who="A01506-mars">
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e104270">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104280">Where force doth fiercely seek to foster wrong,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104290">There Mars doth make him make a quick recoil,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104300">Nor can endure that he should harbour long,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104310">Where naughty wights manure in goodly soil,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104320">This is the use that aids the force of war,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104330">That Mars doth mend, that force doth seek to mar. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e104340">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104350">And though o Queen thou beest a prince of peace,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104360">Yet shalt thou have me fastly sure at need:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104370">The storms of strife, and blustering broils to cease,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104380">Which foreign foes, or faithless friends may breed. </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104390">To conquer, kill, to vanquish and subdue,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104400">Such feigned folk, as loves to live untrue. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <p xml:id="A01506-e104410">These words were graven on those knives.</p>
                <quote xml:id="A01506-e104420">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104430">To hurt your foe, and help your friend,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104440">These knives are made unto that end. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104450">Both blunt and sharp you shall us find,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104460">As pleaseth best your princely mind. </l>
                </quote>
                <stage xml:id="A01506-e104470">Then spoke Venus, whose gift was a white dove.</stage>
                <sp xml:id="A01506-e104480" who="A01506-venus">
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e104490">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104500">In vain (Fair Queen) from heaven my coming was,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104510">To seek t'amend that is no way amiss:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104520">For now I see thy favour so doth pass,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104530">That none but thou, thou only she it is,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104540">Whose beauty bids each wight to look on thee,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104550">By view they may another Venus see. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e104560">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104570">Where beauty boasts, and favour doth not fail,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104580">What may I give to thee oh worthy wight? </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104590">This is my gift, there shall no woe prevail,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104600">That seeks thy will, against thy will's delight,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104610"><pb facs="19"/> not where they will, but where it likes thy mind,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104620">Accept that friend, if loyal thou him find. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <stage xml:id="A01506-e104630">
                  <p xml:id="A01506-e104640">The dove being cast off, ran directly to the Queen, and being taken up and set upon the table before her majesty, fate so quietly, as if it had been tied.</p>
                  <p xml:id="A01506-e104650">Then after they had marched again about Apollo presented his gift, which was, an instrument called a bandonet, and did sing to the said instrument this ditty, as he played.</p>
                </stage>
                <sp xml:id="A01506-e104660" who="A01506-apollo">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104670">It seemeth strange to see such strangers here,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104680">Yet not so strange, but strangers knows you well:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104690">Your virtuous thoughts to gods do plain appear,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104700">Your acts on earth bewrays how you excel:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104710">You cannot die, love here hath made your lease,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104720">Which gods have sent, and God sayeth shall not cease. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104730">Virtuous desire desired me to sing,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104740">No subject's suit, though suitors they were all,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104750">Apollo's gifts are subjects to no King,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104760">Rare are thy gifts, that did Apollo call,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104770">Then still rejoice, sithence God and man say so,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104780">This is my gift, thou never shalt have woe. </l>
                </sp>
                <stage xml:id="A01506-e104790">Pallas then speaketh, and presenteth her gift, which was a book of wisdom.</stage>
                <sp xml:id="A01506-e104800" who="A01506-pallas">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104810">Most worthy wight, what wouldst thou have of me? </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104820">Thou haste so much, thou canst enjoy no more:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104830">I cannot give, that once I gave to thee,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104840">Nor take away thy good I gave before. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104850">I robbed was by nature's good consent</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104860">Against my will, and yet I was content. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104870">A Pallas thou, a Princess I will be:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104880">I Queen of loss, thou goddess which haste got:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104890">I sometime was, thou only now art she,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104900">I take, thou gavest that luck that was my lot,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104910"><pb facs="19"/> I give not thee this book to learn thee aught,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e104920">For that I know already thou art taught. </l>
                </sp>
                <stage xml:id="A01506-e104930">Then after they had marched again about, Neptune did speak: his gift was, a great artificial fish, and in the belly thereof a noble pike, which he threw out before her majesty.</stage>
                <sp xml:id="A01506-e104940" who="A01506-neptune">
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e104950">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104960">What art thou (Queen) that gods do love thee so? </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104970">Who won their wills to be so at thy will? </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104980">How can the world become thy cruel foe? </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e104990">How can disdain or malice seek to kill? </l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e105000">Can sea or earth devise to hurt thy hap,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e105010">Since thou by gods dost sit in fortune's lap. </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg xml:id="A01506-e105020">
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e105030">As heaven and earth have vowed to be thine,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e105040">So Neptunes seas have sworn to drench thy foes,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e105050">As I am God, and all the waters mine,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e105060">Still shalt thou get, but never shalt thou lose:</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e105070">And since on earth my wealth is naught at all,</l>
                    <l xml:id="A01506-e105080">Accept good will, the gift is very small. </l>
                  </lg>
                </sp>
                <stage xml:id="A01506-e105090">Diana presented a bow and arrows nocked and headed with silver. Her speech was this.</stage>
                <sp xml:id="A01506-e105100" who="A01506-diana">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105110">Whoever found on earth a constant friend,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105120">That may compare with this my virgin Queen? </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105130">Whoever found a body and a mind</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105140">So free from stain, so perfect to be seen,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105150">O heavenly hue, that aptest is to soil,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105160">And yet dost live from blot of any foil</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105170">Rare is thy gift ▪ and given to few or none,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105180">Maliced therefore of some that dare not say,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105190">More shines thy light, for that I know but one,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105200">That any such show, to follow on their way. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105210">Thou thou art she, take thou the only praise,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105220">For chastest dame in these our happy days:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105230">Accept my bow, since best thou dost deserve,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105240">Though well I know thy mind can thee preserve. </l>
                </sp>
                <stage xml:id="A01506-e105250"><pb facs="20"/>Cupido his speech, his gift an arrow of gold.</stage>
                <sp xml:id="A01506-e105260" who="A01506-cupid">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105270">Ah ha, I see my mother out of sight,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105280">Then let the boy now play the wag a while,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105290">I seem but weak, yet weak is not my might,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105300">My boyish wit can oldest folk beguile. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105310">Who so doth think, I speak this but in jest,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105320">Let me but shoot, and I shall quench his rest,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105330">Mark here my shafts: this all is made of wood,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105340">Which is but soft, and breeds but soft goodwill. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105350">Now this is guilt, yet seems it gold full good,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105360">And doth deceive blind loving people still. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105370">But here is one is seldom felt or seen:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105380">This is of gold, meet for the noblest Queen. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105390">Wherefore dame fair, take thou this gift of me,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105400">Though some deserve, yet none deserve like you,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105410">Shoot but this shaft at King or Caesar: he,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105420">And he is thine, and if thou wilt allow. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105430">It is a gift, that many here would crave,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105440">Yet none, but thou, this golden shaft may have. </l>
                </sp>
                <p xml:id="A01506-e105450">There was written upon the shaft.</p>
                <quote xml:id="A01506-e105460">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105470">My colour joy, my substance pure,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105480">My virtue such as shall endure. </l>
                </quote>
                <closer xml:id="A01506-e105490">
                  <signed xml:id="A01506-e105500">Goldingham.</signed>
                </closer>
                <trailer xml:id="A01506-e105510">Finis.</trailer>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e105520">Sir majesty received these gifts very thankfully, the gods and goddesses with the rest of the mask marched about the chamber again, and then departed in like manner as they came in. Then the Queen called to her master Robert wood, the mayor of Norwich, whom first the heartily thanked: and took by the hand, and used secret conference, but what, I know not. And thus this delightful night passed, to the joy of all which saw her grace in so pleasant plight.</p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e105530">The next day being Friday in which day the course removed, the streets towards saint Benet's gates, were hanged,<pb facs="20"/> from the one side to the other, with cords made of herbs and flowers, with garlands, coronets, pictures, rich clothes, and a thousand devices. At the gates themselves, there was a stage made, very richly apparelled with cloth of gold, and crimson velvet, whereupon in a close place made thereon for the purpose, was placed very sweet music: and one ready to tender her this speech following. The doleful hour of her departure came, she passed from the court, to those gates, with such countenances, both of her majesty's part, and her subjects, now dolorous, now cheerful, as plainly showed the loving hearts of both sides: when she came there, the speech was thus uttered unto her.</p>
          <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e105540">
            <body xml:id="A01506-e105550">
              <div type="speech" xml:id="A01506-e105560">
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e105570">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105580">Terrestrial joys are tied with slender ●ile,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105590">Each happy hap full hastily doth slide,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105600">As summer season lasteth but a while,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105610">So winter storms do longer time abide:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105620">Alas what bliss can any time endure? </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105630">Our sunshine day is dashed with sudden shower. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e105640">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105650">Could tongue express our secret joys of heart,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105660">(O mighty prince) when thou didst come in place? </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105670">No no God wot, nor can express the smart</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105680">Thy subjects feel in this departing case. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105690">But gracious Queen, let here thy grace remain</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105700">In gracious wise, till thy return again. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e105710">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105720">In lieu whereof, receive thy subjects' hearts,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105730">In fixed faith continually thine own:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105740">Who ready rest to lose their vital parts</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105750">In thy defence, when any blast is blown. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105760">Thou art our Queen, our rock and only stay,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105770">We are thine own to serve by night and day. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e105780">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105790">Farewell o Queen, farewell o mother dear,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105800">Let Jacob's god thy sacred body guard:</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105810">All is thine own that is possessed here,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105820">And all in all is but a small reward</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105830"><pb facs="21"/> for thy great grace, God length thy life like no,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105840">To govern us, and eke thy realm in joy. Amen. </l>
                </lg>
                <closer xml:id="A01506-e105850"><signed xml:id="A01506-e105860">B. G.</signed>and spoken by himself, to whom her majesty said: we thank you heartily.</closer>
                <trailer xml:id="A01506-e105870">Finis.</trailer>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e105880">Then with the music in the same place was song this short ditty following, in a very sweet voice.</p>
          <floatingText xml:id="A01506-e105890">
            <body xml:id="A01506-e105900">
              <div type="song" xml:id="A01506-e105910">
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e105920">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105930">What 'vaileth life, where sorrow soaks the heart? </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105940">Who feareth death that is in deep distress? </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105950">Release of life doth best abate the smart</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105960">Of him, whose woes are quite without redress. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105970">Lend me your tears, resign your sighs to me,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e105980">Help all to wail the dolour which you see. </l>
                </lg>
                <lg xml:id="A01506-e105990">
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e106000">What have we done, she will no longer stay? </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e106010">What may we do to hold her with us still? </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e106020">She is our Queen, we subjects must obey. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e106030">Grant, though with grief to her departing will. </l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e106040">Conclude we then, and sing with sobbing breath,</l>
                  <l xml:id="A01506-e106050">God length thy life, (O Queen Elizabeth.) </l>
                </lg>
                <closer xml:id="A01506-e106060">
                  <signed xml:id="A01506-e106070">B. G.</signed>
                </closer>
                <trailer xml:id="A01506-e106080">Finis.</trailer>
              </div>
            </body>
          </floatingText>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e106090">Then departed her majesty out of the gates, within a flight shot or little more whereof, master Churchyard had another show, which I leave to himself to utter: because my hope is, he will manifest that amongst the rest shortly.</p>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e106100">This finished, her majesty in princely manner marched towards the confines of the liberties of the city of Norwich, which I suppose almost two miles: before she came there, master maior broke to my lord chamberlain, that he was to utter to her majesty another oration, whereof my lord seemed to have good liking: but before they came to the said confines,<pb facs="21"/> master maior was willed to forbear the utterance of the same his oration, because it was about vii. of the clock, and her majesty had then five miles to ride. Nevertheless he gave to her majesty both his orations in writing, which she thanked him for. She also thanked the mayor, every alderman, and the commoners, not only for the great cheer they had made her, but also for the open households they kept to her highness' servants, and all other. Then she called master maior and made him knight: and so departing, said: I have laid up in my breast such good will, as I shall never forget Norwich, and proceeding onward did shake her riding rod and said: farewell Norwich, with the water standing in her eyes: in which great good will towards us all, I beseech God to continue her majesty with long and triumphant reign over us all. Amen. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="oration" xml:lang="lat" xml:id="A01506-e106110">
        <head>The mayor's oration at her departure, delivered in writing.</head>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e106120">Qvae venientia lata sunt, ea cum recedunt solent esse tristiora. Quid enim (Sum deus) potuit hic sol usquàm conspicere beatius, quam nos videbamur nobis, vel cum hic primum (Serenissima princeps) maiestatis tuae splendour illuxerit: vel reliquo hoc perexiguo sanè tempore quo in tua praesentia, tanquam in omnium rerum falicissima ubertat● conqutevimus: sed vae illi rerum humanarum vicissitudini, quae nihil illibatum, nihil aeternum patitur: ita voluptas tristitiam trahit, et letitiam nostram dolour non excipit solum: sed acerbissime intercipit: ita ut, qui nuper accidentem te lautitijs omnibus excepimus: abeuntem nunc, si id pateretur amplitudinis tuae et tanti comitaetus celebritas, pullatis vestibus prosequeremur. Tanti d●loris causam si postules, nescio quid svae maiestatis personae tuae deus indidit, quod summam tui Reverentian aamirabilis cvi●sdam amoris plenam e●citat, quo fit ut agre pattamur nos à te devils. Accedit quòd utcunque amplitudini tuae visi sum●● (Quae tua est clementiae) omne gratitudinis officio satisfecisse: nobis tamen ipsis nondum satisfecimus, nec unquam sanè satisfacturi sum●s. Longioris tamen temperis usuram optaremus, si id commodum esset, ut si nō maius, at certe diuturnius specimen vel obedienciae, velamoris nostri exhiberemus. Sed et voluntati tuae et utilitati public● cedendum est: quam te et velle semper, and in omnibus spectare satis nobis magno cum emclumento nostro est compertum. I nunc igitur, i pede farsto, quo tua te virtus vocat. Nes autem vel hoc ipsum abunde consolabitur, (Qu●d et immortales gratias, et perpetuam rei memoriam meretur) te principem post omnium memoriam praestantissimam dignatam nostres lares tam humaniter invisisse. Postremum hoc eri●, nos hic coram te, quam dominus unxie, atque omni hac celebritate deum nunc intuentem testari in a●imas nostra●, nos fidem et obedientiam in illo, nostram tibi uns inperpetuum reseruaturos. Tu religionis nutrix, reipublicae mater, principum decu●, subditorum solacium, falicissimè (Nellem dicere) vale.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A01506-e106130">
        <pb facs="22"/>
        <head>The mayors last oration englished.</head>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e106140">Those things which at their coming are joyful, when they depart are the more sorrowful. For what (O mighty God) could this sun at any time behold more happy, than we did seem to ourselves, either when first (O most merciful prince) the brightness of thy majesty did here shine out, or else in all the time we rested in your presence, as in a paradise or most happy abundance of all things. But woe to that changeable course of human things, which suffreth nothing uncorrupt, nor any thing eternal ▪ so pleasure bringeth after it sadness, and grief doth not only sòdainly take away our delights, but most bitterly cut of the same. So that we that lately received thee approaching with all joys: should follow thee departing (If the renown of your highness and train would suffer it) with mourning garments. If you demand the cause of so great sorrow, I know not what part of his majesty God hath endued your person withal, which doth stir up great reverence of thee, but full of a certain wonderful love, whereby it comes to pass that we hardly suffer ourselves to be severed from your presence. Add moreover, that we seem after a sort unto your highness (Such is your clemency) to have satisfied every point of gratefulness: yet have we not, nor ever shall we satisfy ourselves in that behalf. We would wish a longer use of time (If it were profitable) that we might express, if not a greater, yet a more continual show of our love and obedience. But we must both yield to your pleasure, and to the common wealth, for that we know assuredly to our great and singular advancement, you never cease to seek out and afford the same to all your subjects. Go now therefore, go with lucky step thither, whether thy virtue calleth thee. And for us, this shall comfort us abundantly (Which deserveth both immortal thanks and perpetual memory) that thou so renowned a prince, hast vouchsafed so courteously to visit our dwellings. And finally, we here before thee, whom God hath anointed, and before all this famous assembly, take God (Which now beholdeth us) to our witness, that we will keep our faith and obedience in him to thee only for ever. Thou nurse of religion, mother of the common wealth, beauty of princes, solace of thy subjects, most happily (O how I rue to speak it) farewell.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="oration" xml:lang="lat" xml:id="A01506-e106150">
        <pb facs="22"/>
        <head>Oratio st. limberti quae discessura principe recitata fuisset, nisi quod sero iter ingressa est.</head>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e106160">Scribit Gellius in noctibus atticis, eminentissima princeps, phavorinum philosophum dixisse, nunc matrem esse diem, nunc esse never cam, et hunc versum longo hominum aevo probatum sermonibus suis usurpasse,<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e106170"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>. Quem ipse Gellius ita interpretatur, dolorum ac voluptatum esse vicissitudines, non omni dic bene esse posse, sed isto bene, atque alio malè. Nihil autem nec venustius unquam nec verius dictum fuisse, tum perpetua rerum humanarum volubilit as, et crebrae mutationes indicant, tum hodiernus dies fidem f●cit amplissimam. Non enim tam recreavit nos è diuturno me roar atque desyderio laetissimus ille aduentus celsitudinis tuae, quàm isto quem undiqueiam parari videmus discessu exanimamur, utque ●mnium aetatum atque ordinum infiniti plausus et gratulationes venientem exceperunt: ita nemo est qui non discedentem etiam luctu et ●achrymis prosequatur. Equidem ut de me ipso loquar, quoniam meus mihi notissimus est animus, nunquam me duriorem provinciam sustinuisse profiteor, quàm est haec imposita mihi hoc tempore, non solum ut affarar cruditissimam principem, quod tamen per se arduum est et difficile, sed multo magis ut hoc tristi et acerbo valedicendi munere defungerer. Quis enim non vehementer indolueris brevissimo tempore ac veluti<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e106180"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg> vidisse se quod maxim concupierat, ereptum ante quam eo penitus perfrui liceret? Quam luctuosum est, lactentes infantulos ab uberibus matrum et charissimis amplexibus divelli? A patribus filios quibus unicè diliguntur gravio●i aliquo casu separari? Nullis tamen mortalibus arbitror naturam tantos amores tantam benevolentiam, aut in cos quos procrearunt ingenerasse, aut a quibus sunt procreati, quanta est ea qua nos omnes celsitudinem tuam communem, videlicet parentem patriae, suspicimus, colimus, veneramur. Magna vis est amicitiae et necessitudinis, quae saepe facit, ut qui vel societate aliqua, vitaeque consuetudine aliquandiu coniuncti fuerint, ita cohaereant animis et quasi coalescant: ut a se invicem distrahi atque disiungi molestissime serant. Hinc theseasides omnium ore ac literis celebrata, aliorumque innumerabilium arctissima necessitudo, quos nulla peris cula, nulli terra marique labores, ab eorum quibus convixissent svavissim●<pb facs="23"/> comitatu depellere potuerunt. Quae autem tanta studia, tanti ardores animo●um usquam reperti sunt, qui nostris erga te praestantissima princeps synceris minimeque fucatis voluntatibus conferantur? Non satis ostendunt ista fidem et benevolentiam nostram, maior est quàm vel cviusquam eruditissimi copia, nedum huius ingenij mei mediocritate possit illustrari. Nullas unquam res arctiori nexu et maiori concordia, quàm animum et corpus natura colligavit, quod et in vita declarat incredibilis illorum conspiratio, sibique mutu● subueniendi cura, and in morte gravissima distractio. Nos autem qui christianam religionem ac pietate profitemur, multo magis quàm illi Decij, scaevolae, curtij, qui se pro repub romana denovisse dicuntur, et patriam, et cam qua patriae salus continetur etiam vita nostra chariorem habere didicimus. Quis enim est qui pro ea dubitet mortem oppetere, quae si non esset, graviorem morte seruitutem perpeti cogeretur? Neque vero est haec pietas tuorum animis leviter infixa, et quasi summo fundata solo, illustrissima regina, sed altis nixa radicibus qua nullis fortunae procellis ac tempestatibus concuti, nullis subuerti machinis, nullo impetu expugnari potest. Quantum enim facit ad amoris et fidei stabilitatem, quod sciamus celsitudinem tuam non arbitrio vacillantis fortunae, sediure haereditario, hoc est<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e106190"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg> dominationem et imperium obtinuisse, nec homericum tibi jovem<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e106200"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>, sed verum illum rerum omnium opificem et fabricatorem in manu● tradidisse? ac propterea summam esse nobis parendi necessitatem etiam divinitus impositam, ne gyganteo more<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e106210"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>, ut est in fabulis, ipsique deo sceleratissimè bellum indicere videamur. Quid cùm perspiciamus quantis quamque divinis rempub meritis aff●cerit celsitudo tua utiam ex innumerabilibus terris ac gentibus quae soli subiectae sunt, nulla, non dicam, anteferrinobis, sed ●e comparari quidem possit. Non ad illam parend●legem et necessitatem summam etiam oporter voluntatem accedere? Quid enim referam vigintiiam totos annos in tanta nos pace, tanta tranquillirate vixisse, quantam non solum haec aetas nunquam vidit, sed ne omnium quidem seculorum ac gentium annals vetustatisque monumenta memoriae prodiderunt? Quid commemorem long velut è specula prospectas tempestates, praevisa simul et anticipata censilio gravissima pericula, clandestinas insidias non tam vi quàm arte obrutas, omnes denique nefari●s conatus maximo cum applausis extinctos, nullo aut sane perexiguo mo●um populari? Facerent ista quidem ut qualiscunque<pb facs="23"/> esses, omnem tamen fidem et benevolentiam maiestati tuae libentissimis animis praestaremus. I am vero cùm mitissimam te et clementissimam principem habeamus, quae in summa potestate constitut● ne tantillum quidem ab aequitate modoque recedis, quis est tam ferus ac ferreus, quem non ad omnem observantiam tantae virtutis invitarent? Quare si firmissima sit custodia principum fides, subditorum, quemadmodum prudentissimos sensisse viros accepimus, quid potest tutius esse et securius excellentia tua, quàm tanta tuorum studia muniverunt? Extraxi longius orationem meam, nobilissima regina, ut paulo diutius frueremur usurae incundissimi conspectus tui, quem non fine maxima molestia gravissimoque dolore amissuri sumus. Said quia ferenda sors est quae vitari non potest, ne profectionem tuam plus aequo remorari videar dum obsequi studeo cupiditati nostrae, finem dicendifaciā. Tuam vero maiestatem quam ex oculis nostris hodiernus dies eripiet animis tamen et voluntatibus prosequemur, absentem semper intuebimur, legibus et mandatis studiosissime obtemperabimus, salutem denique et incolumitatem tuam quae nostra etiam salus continetur, deo opt. Max. assiduis precibus quàm diutissimè tuendam et conservandam commendabimus.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A01506-e106220">
        <pb facs="24"/>
        <head>Mr. Limbert's oration, which had been rehearsed at her graces departing, but that she set late forward in her progress.</head>
        <p xml:id="A01506-e106230">Gellius in his noctibus atticis (Most excellent Princess) doth write, that it was the saying of Phaevorinus the philosopher, that the day was one while a mother, another while a stepdame: and that he used this verse, long time allowed, among men, in his accustomed communication,<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e106240"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>. Which verse Gellius in this manner expoundeth: that of sorrows and pleasures there be changes, that it cannot be well every day with us, but this day well, and that day ill. And surely, that nothing hath been at any time more gallantly or truly spoken, both the continual course of man's uncertain estate, and the often alterations whereto he is subject, manifestly declare, beside that, this present day giveth evident proof thereof. For, the most joyful coming of your highness, did not so much recreate and comfort us in our daily desire and longing, as we are discouraged by this your departing, whereto we see preparation made on all hands. And as all ages and degrees received your majesty, with joy and gladness at your coming: so there is not one but lamenteth and mourneth at your graces going. And doubtless for my part, because mine own heart is best known to myself, I protest that I never took upon me a greater charge, then that, wherewith at this present I am burdened: not only to speak face to face with a most learned lady and Princess, which notwithstanding is, of itself, a hard and a busy matter: but, which is much more, that to me is befallen the sad and sorrowful office of leave taking. For, who would not be exceedingly grieved, to see the thing which he principally desired, in a very short time, and as it were<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e106250"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>, at an instant taken away, before he might have thereof full fruition? How lamentable a thing is it, to pull away sucking babes from the breasts and bosoms of their most loving<pb facs="24"/> mothers? That sons and fathers, through some miserable misfortune, should be sundered? Yet I notwithstanding am of opinion, that nature hath not engendered in any man, such large love, and so great good will, no not toward them whom they have begotten, or of whom they themselves have been begotten, as is the love and good will wherewith we advance, obey, and reverence your majesty, being the mother and nurse of this whole common wealth, and country. Great is the force of friendship and familiarity, which oftentimes bringeth to pass, that they, which either by some kind of fellowship, or by an accustomed condition of life, in tract of time have been closely knit, and so become both of one mind, and as it were grown together, that hard and scant they may be separated, and set in sunder. Hereof sprang the faithfulness of Theseus, commended by the mouth and monuments of all men: and the entire friendship of innumerable more, whom no dangers, nor labours, either by sea or land, could sequester from their sweet society and comfortable company, with whom they long had lived. And what desires, or what delights have anywhere been found, that may be compared with the sincere affection, and unfeigned good will, which we bear to your highness, most excellent Princess? These are not sufficient shows of our faith and benevolence, which is much greater, than that the eloquence of any learned man, or that the slenderness of my wit and capacity may make it manifest. Nature at no time tied any thing with a straighter knot, or set several things at greater agreement, than the soul and the body: a declaration whereof is, the incredible consent and concord of them both, the mutual care and regard of succouring each other resting in them both: and the grievous departing, at the hour of death, the one from the other remaining in them both. But we which profess Christian religion and godliness, have learned this lesson, not only to love our country, but also her highness, in whom the health and safety of our country consisteth, far above the valiant Decij, the scaevolae the Curtii, which ventured their lives for the common wealth of Rome: yea, to love her grace much<pb facs="25"/> better than our own lives. For, what is he that would doubt to die for her sake, who if she were not, he should be constrained to abide a bondage much more bitter than death? Neither is this faithful love of us your subjects (Most excellent Queen) lightly laid up in our hearts, and scarcely covered as it were in the ground, but deeply rooted, so that by no storms nor tempests of fortune it can be shaken, by no engines overthrown, by no force or violence undertrodden. For how much maketh it for the establishment of faith and love, in that we know your majesty hath obtained regiment and rule, not at the pleasure and appointment of wavering fortune, but by right of inheritance, that is to say,<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e106260"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>: nor that the homerical Jupiter<seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e106270"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>, but that the maker and creator of all things delivered it into your highness' hands? And therefore a singular necessity of obedience is laid upon us, even by God himself, least in giant guise as it is feigned, we set shoulder against God, and being at defiance with him most wickedly, bid him battle. When we behold those excellent and divine benefits, which your grace hath bestowed upon the common wealth, in so much that among many, yea innumerable countries', and nations under the sun, none (I will not say may be preferred before us) but not so much as one may be compared with us. Ought not then a singular love and good will to be linked with that law, and necessity of obedience? For what should I make rehearsal of full twenty years, wherein we have lived in such peace and tranquillity, as not only this our age hath never seen the like, but as in old records and ancient chronicles of all ages and people, is nowhere mentioned? What should I call to memory hurly-burlies foreseen afar off, as from an espial: exceeding great dangers, not only perceived by wisdom, but also prevented by counsel: secret snares, and privy practises disappointed, not to much by violence, as by policy: finally, all treacherous attempts, and rebellious enterprises, with great gladness and rejoicing extinguished, without any tumult at all, or very little (Doubtless) ensuing among<pb facs="25"/> the people? These things might make us (Although your grace were otherwise than you are) perform all duty of faith and love, with most willing minds to your majesty. Now, for so much as we have your highness, our merciful and bountiful sovereign, who possessing principality and royal regiment, dost not swerve an hair's breadth from justice and equity, what is he for a man so savage and obstinate, whom these so singular and rare virtues may not allure to all love and allegiance? Wherefore, if the surest safety of princes is the faith of their subjects (As we have heard very wise men hold opinion) what can be more safe, what can be more sure, than your excellency, which the studies and endeavours of your people, being so great, have fenced and fortified? I have made mine oration the longer (Most noble Queen) to the intent we might the longer enjoy your comfortable presence, from the which, to our great grief and sorrow, we shall depart. But because luck must be born, which can not be avoided, lest I might seem more than is meet to delay your grace's progress, whiles I am in hand to please mine own humour, I will make an end. Concerning your majesty, whose presence this day will shut from our sight, we will notwithstanding in your absence behold and reverence, we will love your highness with all our hearts, minds, and endeavours: we will most dutifully obey your grace's laws and commandments. Finally, your majesty's good estate (Whereupon likewise our safety dependeth) we will commend to almighty God in our daily prayers, that the same a long time may be continued, and also preserved. Amen.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="poem" xml:lang="lat" xml:id="A01506-e106280">
        <pb facs="26"/>
        <head>¶ Ad solemn nubibus obductum die lunae. 18. Augusti. 1578.</head>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106290">Splendide phoebe redi, cur te sub nube recondis? </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106300">Innuba pallas adest, splendide phoebe redi. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106310">Hasta minax procul est, non gorgonis or a videbis,</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106320">Pallas inermis adest, splendide phoebe redi. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106330">Scilicet à tanto metuis tibi lumine forsan:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106340">Ne superet radios foemina phoebe tuos. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106350">Pulcher Apollo tibi ne sit regina rulori:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106360">Ipse decore tuo vincis, et illa svo. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106370">Euge redux reducem quia pulsa nocte reducis</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106380">Phoebe diem: toto est gratius orbe nihil. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106390">Haec pepulit tetri tenebras noctemque papismi,</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106400">Et liquidum retulit relligione diem. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106410">Euge nigras nebulas radijs quia saepe repellis</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106420">Phoebe tuis: paene est gratius orbe nihil. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106430">Texuerant remoras discrimina mille papistae:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106440">Ne ceptum princeps continuaret iter:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106450">Nec tamen hunc nebulae potuerunt condere solemn:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106460">Quamvis tu nebulis cedis Apollo tuis. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106470">Ergo iubar nostrum repulisse obstacula cernis:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106480">Sic age, sol nebulas lumine pelle tuo. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106490">Splendide phoebe redi, cur te sub nube recondis? </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106500">Innuba pallas adest, splendide phoebe redi. </l>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A01506-e106510">
          <head>Eiusdem.</head>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106520">Svstinet, ornat, habet, regnum, literaria, formam,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106530">Provida, docta, decens, Juno, Minerva, venus. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106540">Singula dona trium simul Elizabetha dearum</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106550">Provida, docta, decens, sustinet, ornat, habet. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106560">Esse deas lusi: divinam dicimus istam:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106570">Quamuis nec liceat nec libet esse deam. </l>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A01506-e106580">
        <pb facs="26"/>
        <head>¶ To the sun covered with clouds, upon Monday, being the 18. of August. 1578.</head>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106590">In shadowing clouds why art thou closed? Ò Phoebus bright retire:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106600">Unspoused Pallas present is, o Phoebus bright retire. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106610">The threatening spear is flung far off, doubt not grim Gorgon's ire:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106620">Unarmed Pallas present is, o Phoebus bright retire. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106630">Perhaps thou art afraid: and why? at this so large a light:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106640">Lest that a woman should excel, thy beams (O Phoebus) bright. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106650">Let not a Queen, a virgin pure, which is, and ever was,</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106660">Oh fair Apollo, make thee blush: you both in beauty pass. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106670">O Phoebus safe and sound return, which, banishing the night,</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106680">Bringst back the day: in all the world nothing of like delight. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106690">She, only she, the darkness drave of poprye quite away:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106700">And, by religion, hath restored the bright and lightsome day. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106710">O Phoebus, with thy beams, which foil'st the clouds both blind and black,</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106720">The world, in manner all, a thing of like delight doth lack. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106730">A thousand dangers and delays, the Papists had devised,</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106740">To th'end our Princess should abridge, her progress enterprised:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106750">Yet this our bright and shining sun, cast light through every cloud:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106760">Although in clouds thou art content, Apollo, oft to shroud. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106770">Thou seest our sun in comely course, cuts off each stop and stay:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106780">Do thou the like, and by thy light drive every cloud away. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106790">In shadowing clouds why art thou closed? O Phoebus bright retire:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e106800">Unspoused Pallas present is: o Phoebus bright retire. </l>
        <div type="part" xml:id="A01506-e106810">
          <head>By the same.</head>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106820">Her kingdom all by providence, Queen Juno doth uphold:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106830">And of Minerva lady learned, is learned lore extolled:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106840">And Venus fair of countenance, hath beauty uncontrolled. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106850">These sundry gifts of goddesses three, Elizabeth possesseth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106860">By providence her people's peace, and comfort she increaseth:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106870">Her learning, learning amplifies: her beauty never ceaseth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106880">I did but jest, of goddesses to give them three the name:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106890">This lady mayst thou goddess call, for she deserves the same:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106900">Although she will not undertake, a title of such fame. </l>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="dialogue" xml:lang="lat" xml:id="A01506-e106910">
        <pb facs="27"/>
        <head>Gloria civilis an bellica maior. Dialogus.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A01506-e106920"><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e106930">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e106940" who="A01506-polemos">
          <speaker>Po●e. </speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106950">Graecia alexandrum, praeclaros roma triumphos</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106960">Caesatis eximij, fortem britannia Brennum</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106970">Arthurumque canit, permul●os anglia reges</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e106980">Edidit invictos summo quos aequat olympo. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e106990" who="A01506-politicus">
          <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107000">Ergò nihil maius? superant haec omnia laude●</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107010">Virgineae, semper mirabitur anglia nomen</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107020">Elizabetha tuum, famamque ad sydera tollet</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107030">Donec brumali concrescet frigore tellus. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107040">Donec et aestivis candescet solibus aether</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107050">Tempora nulla tuae capient oblivia laudis. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e107060" who="A01506-polemos">
          <speaker>Pole.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107070">Innumeras Macedo gentes sua sub iuga misit</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107080">Et totum quà terra patet fortissimus orbem</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107090">Imperio parere svo, virtute subegit</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107100">Et doluit quod non alius superesset et orbis</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107110">Quem bello peteret, rigidis et sterneret armis. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107120">Quis referat, tua quanta fuit celeberrime Caesar</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107130">Gloria, cuitoties devictis hostibus urbem</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107140">Ingresso, proceres clar●s statuere triumphos? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107150">Aurato quoties, curru devectus in arcem</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107160">Romanae genti spectacula laeta dedisti? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107170">Roma recens Brenni funestis ignibus arsit</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107180">Nobilis Arthurus pictos dare terga coegit</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107190">Saxoneasque manus, f●cit iam regia virtus</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107200">Anglorum nomen quàm formidabile gallis? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107210">O memoranda mihi bello quae fama paratur. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e107220" who="A01506-politicus">
          <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107230">Vera quidem narras, nec enim mihi carpere laudes</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107240">Tantorum procerum magno discrimine partas</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107250">Nec vafrè tenebras inducere fortibus ausis</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107260">Est animus, per me constet sua fama cvique. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107270">Said qui iustitia firmant et legibus aequis</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107280">Imperium, spaertamque svam conamine toto</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107290">Exornare student tutis et finibus uti</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107300">Quantò maiores illi meruêre triumphos? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107310">Jura celebrantur plusquam Minonia bell●</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107320"><pb facs="27"/> quis non praeponet Solomonia regna paternis? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107330">Praetulit ipse deus, qui non sua templa davidem</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107340">Belligerum volvit manibus fabricare cruentis. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107350">Pacificus sacras extruxit filius aedes</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107360">Qui iusto sanctoque svi moderamine regni</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107370">Clarus, in aeternum memori celebrabitur aeu●. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107380">Quis non ante numae foelicia tempora ponet</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107390">Romuleis bello rigidis? Quae denique possunt</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107400">Singula si lustres conferri secula nostris? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107410">O memoranda mihi quae gloria pace paratur. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e107420" who="A01506-polemos">
          <speaker>Pole.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e107430">Said me laurea delectat.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e107440" who="A01506-politicus">
          <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e107450">Me mitis oliva,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e107460" who="A01506-polemos">
          <speaker>Pole.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A01506-e107470">At pulchrum multis dominari gentibus.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e107480" who="A01506-politicus">
          <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107490">Esto</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107500"><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e107510"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e107520" who="A01506-polemos">
          <speaker>Pole.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107530">Fortis memorabile nomen</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107540">Magnanimique ducis toto clarescit in orbe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e107550" who="A01506-politicus">
          <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107560">Exiguas quantum stellas radiantia phoebi</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107570">Lumina, sublustres tenebras lux alma diei:</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107580">Civilis tantum superat prudentia martem. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e107590" who="A01506-polemos">
          <speaker>Pole.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107600">Vis dirimat nostram critici sententia litem? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107610">Non etenim lingua tecum contendere pergam</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107620">Cui pugnae est assueta manus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e107630" who="A01506-politicus">
          <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107640">Placet, ergo loquatur</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107650">Et statuat finem Criticus certaminis huius</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107660">Ambiguas doctè novit componere lights. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A01506-e107670" who="A01506-criti">
          <speaker>Criti.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107680">Quisque svo trahitur study, non omnibus idem</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107690">Est animus, iwat hunc tranquillae pacis, at illum</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107700">Martis et horrifici delectat gloria belli,</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107710">Said mea iam breviter quae sit sententia dicam. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107720">Foelix quilongo cruciatus membra dolore</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107730">Post multos noctu gemitus, suspicia luce</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107740">Amissas tandem vires animumque recepit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107750">Said tamen hic quanto foelicior esset habendus</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107760">Languida si nunquam sensissent corpora morbum? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107770">Cur geritur bellum laetae nisi pacis amore? </l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107780">Quaesi consilio poterit, fatisque benignis</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107790"><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e107800"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg> servari, bella facessant</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107810">Perpetuae maior pacis quàm gloria Martis</l>
          <l xml:id="A01506-e107820">Si modo labe caret maculis nec spargitur ullis. </l>
        </sp>
        <closer xml:id="A01506-e107830">
          <signed xml:id="A01506-e107840">Stephani limberti carmen.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="poem" xml:lang="grc" xml:id="A01506-e107850">
        <pb facs="28"/>
        <head><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e107860">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>.</head>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e107870"><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e107880">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>,</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e107890">
          <seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e107900"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>
        </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e107910">
          <seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e107920"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>
        </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e107930">
          <seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e107940"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>
        </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e107950">
          <seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e107960"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>
        </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e107970">
          <seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e107980"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>
        </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e107990">
          <seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e108000"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>
        </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108010"><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e108020"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108030">
          <seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e108040">〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>
        </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108050"><seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A01506-e108060"> 〈◊〉 〈◊〉 〈◊〉</seg>. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A01506-e108070">
          <signed xml:id="A01506-e108080">W. G.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="poem" xml:lang="lat" xml:id="A01506-e108090">
        <pb facs="28"/>
        <head>¶ Ad civitatem norwicensem de aduentu serenissimae reginae elizabethae.</head>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108100">Ergo tibi antiquae laudes, et avita resurget</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108110">Gloria norwice, et veteris spe● reddita famae est:</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108120">Namque tuos regina lares faelicibus intrat</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108130">Auspicijs, clarumque tuae jubar intulit urbi. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108140">Magnum numen habes, quo nil augustius usquam</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108150">Sol videt, aut ingens maius complectitur orbis. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108160">Illa suis magnum verae pietatis amorem. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108170">Restituit, sanctamque fidem sine fraud dolosa</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108180">Reddidit aeternis è fontibus: illa tumentem</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108190">Aequantemque deo semet regumque tyrannum</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108200">Fregit, et inferno damnatum carcere mersit. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108210">Perge pijs animis dignasque evolvito grates,</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108220">Aduentumque sacrum divinae principis altis</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108230">●udibus illustra, vocesque in sidera mitte. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108240">Nempe facis: video motus vultusque tuorum</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108250">Feruoresque avidos, plaususque et anhela flagrantum</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108260">Pectora, sincerasque praeces, atque undique vulgi</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108270">Laetitiam ingentem: neque enim haec sacra frequentant</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108280">Soli primates urbis, lectusque Senatus,</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108290">Quin etiam populus, pueri, innuptaeque pvellae</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108300">Exultant animis: adeo vox omnibus una est</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108310">Aduentasse decus reg●i, atque hac urbe coruscum</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108320">Illuxisse jubar, magnamque in secula famam</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108330">Norwico partam, nullus quam carpere livor</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108340">Aut violare potest, nostris non eximet aetas</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108350">Mentibus, aut nigra condet sub nube vetustas. </l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108360">Macte animis, n●tat ista deus, meritumque laborem</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108370">Laudat, et obsequijs vestris studioque fideli</l>
        <l xml:id="A01506-e108380">Attribuet longos, optatae principis annos. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A01506-e108390">
          <signed xml:id="A01506-e108400">Gul. Goldingham, Madgemag. .</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A01506"><item xml:id="A01506-polemos" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-polemos</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01506-politicus" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-politicus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01506-criti" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-criti</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01506-mars" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-mars</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01506-apollo" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-apollo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01506-venus" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-venus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01506-juno" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-juno</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01506-mayor" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-mayor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01506-pallas" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-pallas</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01506-cupid" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-cupid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01506-neptune" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-neptune</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01506-jupiter" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-jupiter</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A01506-diana" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A01506-diana</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
</list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

