<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A11265">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Thomas Lord Cromwell <date type="creation_date">1602</date></title>
        <author>S., W. </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Madeline Burg</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A11265.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The true chronicle historie of the whole life and death of Thomas Lord Cromwell. As it hath beene sundrie times publikely acted by the right honorable the Lord Chamberlaine his seruants. Written by W.S.</title>
            <author>W. S.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>26 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2005 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99840295</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 21532.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">4782</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11265</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The true chronicle historie of the whole life and death of Thomas Lord Cromwell. As it hath beene sundrie times publikely acted by the right honorable the Lord Chamberlaine his seruants. Written by W.S.</title>
            <author>W. S.</author>
            <author>Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616,</author>
            <author>Smith, Wentworth, fl. 1601-1623,</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[52||] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>[By R. Read] for William Iones, and are to be solde at his house neere Holburne conduict, at the signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1602.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Attributed to Wentworth Smith and (on slight grounds) to William Shakespeare.--Folger Shakespeare Library Catalogue.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-F4 G1||.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Imperfect; Slight print show-through; all after G1 lacking.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>Cromwell, Thomas, -- Earl of Essex, -- 1485?-1540 -- Early works to 1800.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A11265-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A11265-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A11265-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A11265-e100040">The true chronicle history of the whole life and death of Thomas lord Cromwell. </p>
        <p xml:id="A11265-e100050">As it hath been sundry times publicly acted by the right honourable the lord chamberlain his servants. </p>
        <p xml:id="A11265-e100060">Written by W. S.</p>
        <p xml:id="A11265-e100070">
          <figure xml:id="A11265-e100080"/>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="A11265-e100090">Imprinted at London for William Jones, and are to be sold at his house near Holborn conduct, at the sign of the gunne..</p>
        <p xml:id="A11265-e100100">1602.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A11265-e100110">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A11265-e100120">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>The life and death of the lord Cromwell. </head>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e100130">Enter three smithes, Hodge and two other, old Cromwell's men.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100140" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodge.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e100150">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100160">Come masters, I think it be passed five o'clock ,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100170">Is it not time we were at work:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100180">My old master he'll be stirring anon. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100190" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e100200">I cannot tell whether my old master will be stirring or no: but I am sure I can hardly take my afternoons nap, for my young master Thomas,</p>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e100210">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100220">He keeps such a quill in his study,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100230">With the sun, and the moon, and the seven stars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100240">That I do verily think he'll read out his wits. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100250" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodge.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e100260">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100270">He skill of the stars, there's goodman car of Fulhum,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100280">He that carried us to the strong ale, where goody Trundell</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100290">Had her maid got with child: oh he knows the stars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100300">He'll tickle you Charles wain in nine degrees,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100310">That same man will tell you goody Trundell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100320">When her ale shall miscarry, only by the stars. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100330" who="A11265-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e100340">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100350">I that's a great virtue, indeed I think Thomas</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100360">Be nobody in comparison to him. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100370" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e100380">Well masters come, shall we to our hammers?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100390" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodge.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e100400">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100410">I content, first let's take our morning's draught,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100420">And then to work roundly. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100430" who="A11265-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e100440">I agreed, go in Hodge. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e100450">Exit omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e100460">Enter young Cromwell. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100470" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e100480">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100490">Good morrow morn, I do salute thy brightness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100500">The night seems tedious to my troubled soul:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100510">Whose black obscurity binds in my mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100520">A thousand sundry cogitations:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100530">And now Aurora with a lively dye,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100540">Adds comfort to my spirit that mounts on high. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100550"><pb facs="3"/>Too high indeed, my state being so mean,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100560">My study like a mineral of gold:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100570">Makes my heart proud wherein my hopes enrolled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100580">My books is all the wealth I do possess,<stage xml:id="A11265-e100590">Here within they must beat with their hammers.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100600">And unto them I have engaged my heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100610">Oh learning how divine thou seems to me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100620">Within whose arms is all felicity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100630">Peace with your hammers leave your knocking there,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100640">You do disturb my study and my rest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100650">Leave off I say, you mad me with the noise. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e100660">Enter Hodge and the two men.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100670" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodge.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e100680">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100690">Why how now master Thomas how now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100700">Will you not let us work for you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100710" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e100720">You fret my heart, with making of this noise.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100730" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e100740">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100750">How fret your heart, I but Thomas, you'll</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100760">Fret your father's purse if you let us from working. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100770" who="A11265-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e100780">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100790">I this 'tis for him to make him a gentleman,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100800">Shall we leave work for your musing, that's well i'faith,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100810">But here comes my old master now. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e100820">Enter old Cromwell. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100830" who="A11265-old_cromwell">
          <speaker>Old. Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e100840">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100850">You idle knaves, what are you loitering now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100860">No hammers walking and my work to do:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100870">What not a heat among your work today. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100880" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e100890">Marry sir your son Thomas will not let us work at all,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100900" who="A11265-old_cromwell">
          <speaker>Old. Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e100910">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100920">Why knave I say, have I thus carked and cared</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100930">And all to keep thee like a gentleman,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100940">And dost thou let my servants at their work:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e100950">That sweat for thee knave, labour thus for thee,</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100960" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e100970">Father their hammers do offend my study.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e100980" who="A11265-old_cromwell">
          <speaker>Old. Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e100990">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101000">Out of my doors knave if thou likest it not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101010">I cry you mercy is your ears so fine:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101020">I tell thee knave these get when I do sleep,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101030">I will not have my anvil stand for thee. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101040" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e101050">There's money father I will pay your men.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e101060">He throws money among them.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101070" who="A11265-old_cromwell">
          <speaker>Old. Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e101080">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101090">Have I thus brought thee up unto my cost,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101100">In hope that one day thou wouldst relieve my age,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101110"><pb facs="3"/> and art thee now so lavish of thy coin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101120">To scatter it among these idle knaves. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101130" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e101140">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101150">Father be patient, and content yourself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101160">The time will come I shall hold gold as trash:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101170">And here I speak with a presaging soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101180">To build a palace where now this cottage stands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101190">As fine as is King Henry's house at sheen. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101200" who="A11265-old_cromwell">
          <speaker>Old Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e101210">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101220">You build a house, you knave you'll be a beggar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101230">Now afore God all is but cast away,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101240">That is bestowed upon this thriftless lad,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101250">Well had I bound him to some honest trade:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101260">This had not been, but it was his mother's doing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101270">To send him to the university,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101280">How build a house where now this cottage stands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101290">As fair as that at sheen, he shall not hear me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101300">A good boy Tom, I con thee thank Tom,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101310">Well said Tom, gramarcies Tom,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101320">Into your work knaves, hence you saucy boy. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e101330">Exit all but young Cromwell. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101340" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e101350">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101360">Why should my birth keep down my mounting spirit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101370">Are not all creatures subject unto time:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101380">To time, who doth abuse the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101390">And fills it full of hodgepodge bastardy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101400">There's legions now of beggars on the earth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101410">That their original did spring from Kings:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101420">And many monarchs now whose fathers were,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101430">The riff-raff of their age: for time and fortune</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101440">Wears out a noble train to beggary,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101450">And from the dunghill minions do advance</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101460">To state: and mark in this admiring world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101470">This is but course, which in the name of fate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101480">Is seen as often as it whirls about:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101490">The river Thames that by our door doth pass,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101500">His first beginning is but small and shallow:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101510">Yet keeping on his course, grows to a sea. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101520">And likewise Wolsey, the wonder of our age,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101530">His birth as mean as mine, a butcher's son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101540"><pb facs="4"/> now who within this land a greater man. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101550">Then Cromwell cheer thee up, and tell thy soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101560">That thou mayst live to flourish and control. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e101570">Enter old Cromwell. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101580" who="A11265-old_cromwell">
          <speaker>Old Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e101590">Tom Cromwell, what Tom I say?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101600" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e101610">Do you call sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101620" who="A11265-old_cromwell">
          <speaker>Old Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e101630">Here is master Bowser come to know, if you have dispatched his petition, for the lords of the counsel or no.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101640" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e101650">Father I have, please you to call him in.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101660" who="A11265-old_cromwell">
          <speaker>Old Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e101670">That's well said Tom, a good lad Tom. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e101680">Enter master Bowser. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101690" who="A11265-bowser">
          <speaker>Bow.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e101700">Now master Cromwell, have you dispatched this petition?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101710" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e101720">I have sir, here it is, please you peruse it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101730" who="A11265-bowser">
          <speaker>Bow.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e101740">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101750">It shall not need, we'll read it as we go by water:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101760">And master Cromwell, I have made a motion</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101770">May do you good, and if you like of it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101780">Our secretary at Antwerp, sir is dead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101790">And the merchants there hath sent to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101800">For to provide a man fit for the place:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101810">Now I do know none fitter than yourself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101820">If with your liking it stand master Cromwell. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101830" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e101840">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101850">With all my heart sir, and I much am bound,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101860">In love and duty for your kindness shown. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101870" who="A11265-old_cromwell">
          <speaker>Old Cro</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e101880">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101890">Body of me Tom make haste, lest somebody </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101900">Get between thee and home Tom. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101910">I thank you good master Bowser, I thank you for my boy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101920">I thank you always, I thank you most heartily sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e101930">Ho a cup of beer there for master Bowser. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101940" who="A11265-bowser">
          <speaker>Bow.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e101950">It shall not need sir, master Cromwell will you go.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101960" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e101970">I will attend you sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e101980" who="A11265-old_cromwell">
          <speaker>Old Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e101990">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102000">Farewell Tom, God bless thee Tom,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102010">God speed thee good Tom. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e102020">Exit omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e102030">Enter Bagot a broker, solus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102040" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102050">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102060">I hope this day is fatal unto some,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102070"><pb facs="4"/> and by their loss must Bagot seek to gain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102080">This is the lodging of master Fryskiball,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102090">A liberal merchant, and a Florentine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102100">To whom Banister owes a thousand pound,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102110">A merchant bankrupt, whose father was my master,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102120">What do I care, for pity or regard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102130">He once was wealthy, but he now is fallen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102140">And this morning have I got him arrested,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102150">At the suit of master Friskiball,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102160">And by this means shall I be sure of coin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102170">For doing this same good to him unknown:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102180">And in good time, see where the merchant comes. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e102190">Enter Fryskiball. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102200" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e102210">Good morrow to kind master Friskiball. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102220" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102230">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102240">Good morrow to yourself good master Bagot,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102250">And what's the news you are so early stirring:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102260">It is for gain, I make no doubt of that. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102270" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102280">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102290">It is for the love sir that I bear to you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102300">When did you see your debtor Banister? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102310" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102320">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102330">I promise you, I have not seen the man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102340">This two months day, his poverty is such,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102350">As I do think he shames to see his friends. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102360" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102370">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102380">Why then assure yourself to see him straight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102390">For at your suit I have arrested him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102400">And here they will be with him presently. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102410" who="A11265-friar">
          <speaker>Fry.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102420">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102430">Arrest him at my suit, you were to blame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102440">I know the man's misfortunes to be such,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102450">As he's not able for to pay the debt,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102460">And were it known to some he were undone. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102470" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102480">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102490">This is your pitiful heart to think it so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102500">But you are much deceived in Banister,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102510">Why such as he will break for fashion's sake,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102520">And unto those they owe a thousand pound,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102530">Pay scarce a hundred, oh sir beware of him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102540">The man is lewdly given, to dice and drabs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102550">Spends all he hath in harlots companies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102560"><pb facs="5"/> it is no mercy for to pity him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102570">I speak the truth of him, for nothing else,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102580">But for the kindness that I bear to you,</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102590" who="A11265-friar">
          <speaker>Fry.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102600">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102610">If it be so, he hath deceived me much,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102620">And to deal strictly with such a one as he,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102630">Better severe than too much lenity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102640">But here is master Banister himself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102650">And with him as I take the officers. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e102660">Enter Banister his wife and two officers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102670" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ban.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102680">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102690">O master Friskiball you have undone me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102700">My state was well nigh overthrown before,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102710">Now altogether downcast by your means. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102720" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Mistress Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102730">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102740">O master Friskiball, pity my husband's case,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102750">He is a man hath lived as well as any,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102760">Till envious fortune and the ravenous sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102770">Did rob, disrobe, and spoil us of our own. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102780" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102790">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102800">Mistress Banister, I envy not your husband,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102810">Nor willingly would I have used him thus:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102820">But that I hear he is so lewdly given,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102830">Haunts wicked company, and hath enough,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102840">To pay his debts, yet will not be known thereof. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102850" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ban.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102860">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102870">This is that damned broker, that same Bagot,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102880">Whom I have often from my trencher fed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102890">Ingrateful villain for to use me thus:</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102900" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e102910">What I have said to him is naught but truth.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e102920" who="A11265-mrs_banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ban.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e102930">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102940">What thou hast said, springs from an envious heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102950">A cannibal that doth eat men alive,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102960">But here upon my knee believe me sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102970">And what I speak, so help me God is true,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102980">We scarce have meat to feed our little babes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e102990">Most of our plate is in that broker's hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103000">Which had we money to defray our debt,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103010">Oh think we would not bide that penury:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103020">Be merciful, kind master Friskiball,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103030">My husband, children, and myself will eat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103040">But one meal a day, the other will we keep and sell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103050"><pb facs="5"/> as part to pay the debt we owe to you:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103060">If ever tears did pierce a tender mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103070">Be pitiful, let me some favour find. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e103080" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e103090">Be not you so mad sir, to believe her tears,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e103100" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e103110">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103120">Go to, I see thou art an envious man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103130">Good ministers Banister kneel not to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103140">I pray rise up, you shall have your desire. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103150">Hold officers be gone, there's for your pains,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103160">You know you owe to me a thousand pound,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103170">Here take my hand, if ear God make you able,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103180">And place you in your former state again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103190">Pay me: but if still your fortune frown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103200">Upon my faith I'll never ask you crown:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103210">I never yet did wrong to men in thrall. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103220">For God doth know what to myself may fall. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e103230" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ban.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e103240">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103250">This unexpected favour undeserved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103260">Doth make my heart bleed inwardly with joy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103270">Ne'er may ought prosper with me is my own,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103280">If I forget this kindness you have shown. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e103290" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e103300">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103310">My children in their prayers both night and day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103320">For your good fortune and success shall pray. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e103330" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e103340">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103350">I thank you both, I pray go dine with me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103360">Within these three days, if God give me leave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103370">I will to Florence to my native home,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103380">Bagot hold, there's a portague to drink,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103390">Although you ill deserved it by your merit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103400">Give not such cruel scope unto your heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103410">Be sure the ill you do will be requited,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103420">Remember what I say, Bagot farewell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103430">Come master Banister, you shall with me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103440">My fare is but simple, but welcome heartily. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e103450">Exit all but Bagot. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e103460" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e103470">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103480">A plague go with you, would you had eat your last,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103490">Is this the thanks I have for all my pains,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103500">Confusion light upon you all for me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103510">Where he had wont to give a score of crowns,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103520">Doth he now foist me with a portague:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103530">Well I will be revenged upon this Banister. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103540"><pb facs="6"/>I'll to his creditors, buy all the debt he owes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103550">As seeming that I do it for good will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103560">I am sure to have them at an easy rate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103570">And when 'tis done, in Christendom he stays not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103580">But I'll make his heart to ache with sorrow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103590">And if that Banister become my debtor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103600">By heaven and earth I'll make his plague the greater. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e103610">Exit Bagot. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e103620">Enter chorus. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e103630" who="A11265-chorus">
          <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e103640">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103650">Now gentlemen imagine, that young Cromwell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103660">In Antwerp Ledger for the English merchants:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103670">And Banister to shun this Bagot's hate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103680">Hearing that he hath got some of his debts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103690">Is fled to Antwerp, with his wife and children,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103700">Which Bagot hearing is gone after them:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103710">And thither sends his bills of debt before,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103720">To be revenged on wretched Banister,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103730">What doth fall out, with patience sit and see,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103740">A just requital of false treachery. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e103750">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e103760">Cromwell in his study with bags of money before him casting of account.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e103770" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e103780">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103790">Thus far my reckoning doth go straight and even,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103800">But Cromwell this same ployding fits not thee:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103810">Thy mind is altogether set on travel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103820">And not to live thus cloistered like a nun,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103830">It is not this same trash that I regard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103840">Experience is the jewel of my heart. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e103850">Enter a post.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e103860" who="A11265-post">
          <speaker>Post.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e103870">I pray sir are you ready to dispatch me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e103880" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e103890">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103900">Yes here's those sums of money you must carry,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103910">You go so far as Frankford do you not. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e103920" who="A11265-post">
          <speaker>Post.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e103930">I do sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e103940" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e103950">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103960">Well prithee make all the haste thou canst,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103970">For there be certain English gentlemen:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103980">Are bound for Venice, and may happily want,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e103990">And if that you should linger by the way:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104000">But in hope that you'll make good speed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104010"><pb facs="6"/> there's two angels to buy you spurs and wands. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104020" who="A11265-post">
          <speaker>Po.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e104030">I thank you sir this will add wings indeed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104040" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e104050">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104060">Gold is of power would make an eagle's speed. <stage xml:id="A11265-e104070">Enter mistress Banister. </stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104080">What gentlewoman is this that grieves so much,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104090">It seems she doth address herself to me. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104100" who="A11265-mrs_banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e104110">God save you sir, pray is your name master Cromwell. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104120" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e104130">My name is Thomas Cromwell gentlewoman.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104140" who="A11265-mrs_banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e104150">Know you not one Bagot sir, that's come to Antwerp. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104160" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e104170">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104180">No trust me, I never saw the man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104190">But here are bills of debt I have received,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104200">Against one Banister a merchant fallen into decay. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104210" who="A11265-mrs_banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e104220">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104230">Into decay indeed, long of that wretch,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104240">I am the wife to woeful Banister:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104250">And by that bloody villain am pursued,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104260">From London here to Antwerp,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104270">My husband he is in the governor's hands:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104280">And God of heaven knows how he'll deal with him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104290">Now sir your heart is framed of milder temper,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104300">Be merciful to a distressed soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104310">And God no doubt will treble bless your gain. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104320" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e104330">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104340">Good mistress Banister, what I can, I will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104350">In any thing that lies within my power. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104360" who="A11265-mrs_banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e104370">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104380">O speak to Bagot that same wicked wretch,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104390">An angel's voice may move a damned devil. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104400" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e104410">Why is he come to Antwerp as you here?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104420" who="A11265-mrs_banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e104430">I hard he landed some two hours since.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104440" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e104450">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104460">Well mistress Banister assure yourself. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104470">I'll speak to Bagot in your own behalf:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104480">And win him to all the pity that I can,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104490">Mean time, to comfort you in your distress,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104500">Receive these angels to relieve your need,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104510">And be assured that what I can effect:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104520">To do you good, no way I will neglect. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104530" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e104540">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104550">That mighty God that knows each mortals heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104560">Keep you from trouble sorrow grief and smart. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e104570">Exit mistress Banister.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104580" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker><pb facs="7"/>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e104590">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104600">Thanks courteous woman,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104610">For thy hearty prayer:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104620">It grieves my soul to see her misery,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104630">But we that live under the work of fate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104640">May hope the best, yet knows not to what state</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104650">Our stars and destinies hath us asigned,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104660">Fickle is fortune and her face is blind. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e104670">Enter Bagot solus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104680" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e104690">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104700">So all goes well, it is as I would have it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104710">Banister he is with the governor:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104720">And shortly shall have gyves upon his heels,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104730">It glads my heart to think upon the slave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104740">I hope to have his body rot in prison:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104750">And after here, his wife to hang herself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104760">And all his children die for want of food,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104770">The jewels that I have brought to Antwerp,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104780">Are reckoned to be worth five thousand pound,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104790">Which scarcely stood me in three hundreth pound,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104800">I bought them at an easy kind of rate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104810">I care not which way they came by them</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104820">That should them me, it comes not near my heart:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104830">And lest they should be stolen as sure they are,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104840">I thought it meet to sell them here in Antwerp,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104850">And so have left them in the governor's hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104860">Who offers me within two hundreth pound</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104870">Of all my price: but now no more of that,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104880">I must go see and if my bills be safe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104890">The which I sent to master Cromwell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104900">That if the wind should keep me on the sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104910">He might arrest him here before I came:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104920">And in good time, see where he is: God save you sir. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104930" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e104940">And you, pray pardon me, I know you not.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104950" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e104960">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104970">It may be so sir, but my name is Bagot,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e104980">The man that sent to you the bills of debt. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e104990" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e105000">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105010">O the man that pursues Banister,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105020">Here are the bills of debt you sent to me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105030">As for the man you know best where he is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105040"><pb facs="7"/> it is reported you have a flinty heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105050">A mind that will not stoop to any pity;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105060">An eye that knows not how to shed a tear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105070">A hand that's always open for reward,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105080">But master Bagot would you be ruled by me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105090">You should turn all these to the contrary,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105100">Your heart should still have feeling of remorse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105110">Your mind according to your state be liberal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105120">To those that stand in need and in distress;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105130">Your hand to help them that do stand in want,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105140">Rather than with your poise to hold them down,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105150">For every ill turn show yourself more kind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105160">Thus should I do, pardon I speak my mind. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105170" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e105180">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105190">Ay sir, you speak to hear what I would say,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105200">But you must live I know, as well as I:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105210">I know this place to be extortion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105220">And 'tis not for a man to keep him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105230">But he must lie, cog, with his dearest friend;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105240">And as for pity, scorn it, hate all conscience,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105250">But yet I do commend your wit in this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105260">To make a show, of what I hope you are not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105270">But I commend you and 'tis well done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105280">This is the only way to bring your gain. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105290" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e105300">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105310">My gain: I had rather chain me to an oar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105320">And like a slave there toil out all my life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105330">Before I'd live so base a slave as thou:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105340">I like an hypocrite to make a show,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105350">Of seeming virtue and a devil within,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105360">No Bagot, would thy conscience were as clear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105370">Poor Banister ne'er had been troubled here. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105380" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e105390">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105400">Nay good master Cromwell be not angry sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105410">I know full well you are no such man;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105420">But if your conscience were as white as snow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105430">It will be thought that you are other wise. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105440" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e105450">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105460">Will it be thought that I am other wise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105470">Let them that think so know they are deceived;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105480">Shall Cromwell live to have his faith misconstered,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105490"><pb facs="8"/> Antwerp for all the wealth within thy town,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105500">I will not stay here not two hours longer:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105510">As good luck serves my accounts are all made even,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105520">Therefore I'll straight unto the treasurer,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105530">Bagot I know you'll to the governor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105540">Commend me to him, say I am bound to travail,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105550">To see the fruitful parts of Italy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105560">And as you ever bore a Christian mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105570">Let Banister some favour of you find. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105580" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e105590">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105600">For your sake sir I'll help him all I can,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105610">To starve his heart out ere he gets a groat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105620">So master Cromwell do I take my leave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105630">For I must straight unto the governor. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e105640">Exit Bagot. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105650" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e105660">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105670">Farewell sir, pray you remember what I said,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105680">No Cromwell, no, thy heart was ne'er so base:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105690">To live by falsehood or by brokery,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105700">But falls out well, I little it repent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105710">Hereafter, time in travel shall be spent. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e105720">Enter Hodge his father's man.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105730" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e105740">Your son Thomas, quoth you, I have been thomased, I had thought it had been no such matter to a gone by water: for at Putney I'll go you to parish-garden for two pence, sit as still as may be, without any wagging or jolting in my guts, in a little boat too: here 'We were scarce four mile in the great green water, but I thinking to go to my afternoons unchines, as 'twas my manner at home, but I felt a kind of rising in my guts: at last one a the sailors spying of me, be a good cheer says he, set down thy victuals, and up with it, thou hast nothing but an eel in thy belly: well toot went I, to my victtualles went the sailors, and thinking i to be a man of better experience than any in the ship, asked me what wood the ship was made of: they all swore I told them as right as if I had been acquainted with the carpenter that made it, at last we grew near land,<pb facs="8"/> and I grew villainous hungry, went to my bag, the devil a bit there was, the sailors had tickled me, yet I cannot blame them, it was a part of kindness, for I in kindness told them what wood the ship was made of, and they in kindness eat up my victuals, as indeed one good turn asketh another: well would I, could I, find my master Thomas in this Dutch town, he might put some English bear into my belly.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105750" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e105760">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105770">What Hodge my father's man, by my hand welcome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105780">How doth my father? what's the news at home? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105790" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e105800">Master Thomas, oh God master Thomas, your hand, glove and all, this is to give you to understanding that your father is in health, and Alice Downing here hath sent you a nutmeg, and Bess make water a race of ginger, my fellow will and Tom hath between them sent you a dozen of points, and good man Tolle of the goat a pair of mittons, myself came in person, and this is all the news.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105810" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e105820">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105830">Gramercy good Hodge, and thou art welcome to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105840">But in as ill a time thou comest as may be:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105850">For I am travelling into Italy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105860">What sayest thou Hodge wilt thou bear me company. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105870" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodge.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e105880">Will I bear thee company Tom, what tellest me of Italy, were it to the furthest part of Flanders, I would go with thee Tom, I am thine in all weal and woe, thy own to command, what Tom, I have passed the rigorous waves of Neptune's blasts, I tell you Thomas I have been in the danger of the floods, and when I have seen Boreas begin to play the ruffian with us, then would I down of my knees and call upon Vulcan. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105890" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e105900">And why upon him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105910" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e105920">Because as this same fellow Neptune is God of the seas, so Vulcan is lord over the smiths, and therefore I being a smith, thought his godhead would have some care yet of me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105930" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e105940">A good conceit, but tell hast thou dined yet?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105950" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e105960">Thomas to speak the truth, not a bit yet I.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e105970" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e105980">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e105990">Come go with me, thou shalt have cheer good store. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106000">And farewell Antwerp if I come no more. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106010" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker><pb facs="9"/>Hodg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e106020">I follow thee sweet Tom, I follow thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e106030">Exit omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e106040">Enter the governor of the English house, Bagot, Banister, his wife, and two officers.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106050" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106060">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106070">Is Cromwell gone then, say you master Bagot,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106080">What dislike I pray, what was the cause? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106090" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106100">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106110">To tell you true, a wild brain of his own,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106120">Such youth as they cannot see when they are well:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106130">He is all bent to travail, that's his reason,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106140">And doth not love to eat his bread at home. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106150" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106160">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106170">Well, good fortune with him, if the man be gone. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106180">We hardly shall find such a one as he,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106190">To fit our turns, his dealings were so honest:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106200">But now sir, for your jewels that I have,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106210">What do you say, will you take my prize. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106220" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e106230">O sir, you offer too much underfoot.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106240" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106250">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106260">'Tis but two hundred pound between us man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106270">What's that in payment of five thousand pound. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106280" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106290">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106300">Two hundred pound, byr lady sir 'tis great,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106310">Before I got so much, it made me sweat. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106320" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106330">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106340">Well master Bagot, I'll proffer you fairly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106350">You see this merchant master Banister,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106360">Is going now to prison at your suit. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106370">His substance all is gone, what would you have,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106380">Yet in regard I knew the man of wealth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106390">Never dishonest dealing, but such mishaps,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106400">Hath fallen on him, may light on me, or you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106410">There is two hundred pound between us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106420">We will divide the same, I'll give you one,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106430">On that condition you will set him free:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106440">His state is nothing, that you see yourself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106450">And where naught is, the King must lose his right. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106460" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106470">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106480">Sir, sir, you speak out of your love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106490">'Tis foolish love sir sure to pity him:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106500">Therefore content yourself, this is my mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106510">To do him good I will not bate a penny,</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106520" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ban.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106530">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106540">This is my comfort though thou dost no good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106550"><pb facs="9"/> a mighty ebb follows a mighty flood. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106560" who="A11265-mrs_banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106570">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106580">O thou base wretch whom we have fostered,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106590">Even as a serpent for to poison us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106600">If God did ever right a woman's wrong:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106610">To that same God I bend and bow my heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106620">To let his heavy wrath fall on thy head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106630">By whom my hopes and joys are, butchered. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106640" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106650">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106660">Alas fond woman, I pray thee pray thy worst,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106670">The fox fares better still when he is cursed. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e106680">Enter master Bowser a merchant.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106690" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106700">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106710">Master Bowser your welcome sir from England,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106720">What's the best news? how doth all our friends? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106730" who="A11265-bowser">
          <speaker>Bow.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106740">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106750">They are all well and do commend them to you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106760">There's letters from your brother and your son:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106770">So fair you well sir, I must take my leave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106780">My haste and business doth require such. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106790" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e106800">Before you dine sir, what go you out of town.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106810" who="A11265-bowser">
          <speaker>Bow.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106820">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106830">I'faith unless I hear some news in town,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106840">I must away there is no remedy. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106850" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106860">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106870">Master Bowser what is your business, may I know it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106880">You may sir and so shall all the city. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e106890" who="A11265-bowser">
          <speaker>Bow.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e106900">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106910">The King of late hath had his treasury robbed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106920">And of the choicest jewels that he had:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106930">The value of them was some seven thousand pound,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106940">The fellow that did steal the solewels, he is hanged,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106950">And did confess that for three hundred pound,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106960">He should them to one Bagot dwelling in London:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106970">Now bagot's fled, and as we here to Antwerp,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106980">And hither am I come to seek him our,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e106990">And they that first can tell me of his news,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107000">Shall have a hundred pound for their reward. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107010" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e107020">How just is God to right the innocent.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107030" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107040">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107050">Master Bowser you come in happy time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107060">Here is the villain Bagot that you seek,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107070">And all those jewels have I in my hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107080">Officers look to him, hold him fast. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107090" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e107100">The devil ought me a shame, and now hath paid it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107110" who="A11265-bowser">
          <speaker><pb facs="10"/>Bow.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107120">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107130">Is this that Bagot? fellows bear him hence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107140">We will not now stand for his reply;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107150">Lade him with irons, we will have him tried</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107160">In England where his villainies are known. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107170" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker>Bag.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107180">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107190">Mischief, confusion, light upon you all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107200">Oh hang me, drown me, let me kill myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107210">Let go my arms let me run quick to hell. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107220" who="A11265-bowser">
          <speaker>Bow.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e107230">Away, bear him away, stop the slave's mouth.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e107240">They carry him away.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107250" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e107260">Thy works are infinite, great God of heaven.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107270" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e107280">I hard this Bagot was a wealthy fellow.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107290" who="A11265-bowser">
          <speaker>Bow.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107300">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107310">He was indeed, for when his goods were zeased,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107320">Of jewels, coin, and plate within his house,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107330">Was found the value of five thousand pound,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107340">His furniture fully worth half so much,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107350">Which being all strained for, for the King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107360">He frankly gave it to the Antwerp merchants,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107370">And they again, out of their bounteous mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107380">Hath to a brother of their company,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107390">A man decayed by fortune of the seas,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107400">Given Bagot's wealth, to set him up again:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107410">And keep it for him, his name is Banister. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107420" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107430">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107440">Master Bowser, with this happy news,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107450">You have revived two from the gates of death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107460">This is that Banister, and this his wife. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107470" who="A11265-bowser">
          <speaker>Bow.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107480">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107490">Sir I am glad my fortune is so good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107500">To bring such tidings as may comfort you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107510" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ban.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107520">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107530">You have given life unto a man deemed dead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107540">For by these news, my life is newly bred. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107550" who="A11265-mrs_banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107560">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107570">Thanks to my God, next to my sovereign King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107580">And last to you that these good hopes doth bring. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107590" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107600">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107610">The hundred pound I must receive as due</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107620">For finding Bagot, I freely give to you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107630" who="A11265-bowser">
          <speaker>Bow.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107640">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107650">And master Banister, if so you please,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107660">I'll bear you company, when you cross the seas. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107670" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ban.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107680">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107690">If it please you sir, my company is but mean,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107700">Stands with your liking, I'll wait on you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107710" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker><pb facs="10"/>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107720">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107730">I am glad that all things do accord so well </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107740">Come master Bowser, let us in to dinner:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107750">And mistress Banister, be merry woman,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107760">Come after sorrow now, let's cheer your spirit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107770">Knaves have their due, and you but what you merit. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e107780">Exit omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e107790">Enter Cromwell and Hodge in their shirts, and without hats.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107800" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107810">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107820">Call ye this seeing of fashions? </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107830">Marry would I had stayed at Putney still,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107840">Oh master Thomas, we are spoilt we are gone. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107850" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e107860">Content thee man, this is but fortune.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107870" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e107880">Fortune, a plague of this fortune makes me go wetshod, the rogues would not leave me a shoe to my feet, for my hose they scorned them with their heels, but for my doublet and hat, oh lord they embraced me, and unlaced me, and took away my clothes, and so disgraced me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107890" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e107900">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107910">Well Hodge, what remedy? </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e107920">What shift shall we make now? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107930" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodge.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e107940">Nay I know not, for begging I am naught, for stealing worse: by my troth I must even fall to my old trade, to the hammer and the horse heels again: but now the worst is, I am not acquainted with the humour of the horses in this country, whether they are not coultish, given much to kicking, or no, for when I have one leg in my hand, if he should up and lay tother of my chops, I were gone, there lay I, there lay Hodge. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107950" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e107960">Hodge I believe thou must  for us both.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107970" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodge.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e107980">O master Thomas, have not I told you of this, have not I many a time and often, said Tom, or master Thomas, learn to make a horse-shoe, it will be your own another day: this was not regarded. Hark you Thomas, what do you call the fellows that robbed us.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e107990" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e108000">The bandetto.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108010" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e108020">The bandetto do you call them, I know not what they are called here, but I am sure we call them plain thieves in<pb facs="11"/> England, oh Thomas that we were now at Putnay, at the ale there.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108030" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e108040">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108050">Content thee man, here set up these two bills,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108060">And let us keep our standing on the bridge:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108070">The fashion of this country is such,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108080">If any stranger be oppressed with want,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108090">To write the manner of his misery,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108100">And such as are disposed to succour him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108110">Will do it, what hast thou set them up? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108120" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e108130">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108140">I their up, God send some to read them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108150">And not only to read them, but also to look on us:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108160">And not altogether to look on us,<stage xml:id="A11265-e108170">One  stands at one end, and one at tother.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108180">But to relieve us, oh cold, cold cold. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e108190">Enter Friskiball the merchant and reads the bills.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108200" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fris.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e108210">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108220">What's here? two Englishmen robbed by the bandetto,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108230">One of them seems to be a gentleman:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108240">'Tis pity that his fortune was so hard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108250">To fall into the desperate hands of thieves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108260">I'll question him of what estate he is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108270">God save you sir, are you an Englishman? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108280" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e108290">I am sir a distressed Englishman.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108300" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e108310">And what are you my friend.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108320" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e108330">Who I sir, by my troth I do not know myself what I am now, but sir, I was a smith sir, a poor farrier of Putnay, that's my master sir yonder, I was robbed for his sake sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108340" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e108350">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108360">I see you have been met by the bandetto,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108370">And therefore need not ask how you came thus </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108380">But Friskiball why dost thou question them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108390">Of their estate and not relieve their need,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108400">Sir the coin I have about about me is not much:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108410">There's sixteen ducats, for to clothe yourselves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108420">There's sixteen more to buy your diet with,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108430">And there's sixteen to pay for your horse hire:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108440">'Tis all the wealth you see my purse possesses,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108450">But if you please for to inquire me out,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108460">You shall not want for ought that I can do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108470">My name is Friskiball a Florence merchant,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108480"><pb facs="11"/> a man that always loved your nation. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108490" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e108500">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108510">This unexpected favour at your hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108520">Which God doth know, if ever I shall requite it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108530">Necessity makes me to take your bounty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108540">And for your gold can yield you naught but thanks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108550">Your charity hath helped me from despair. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108560">Your name shall still be in my hearty prayer. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108570" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e108580">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108590">It is not worth such thanks; come to my house,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108600">Your want shall better be relieved then thus. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108610" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e108620">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108630">I pray excuse me, this shall well suffice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108640">To bear my charges to Bononia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108650">Whereas a noble Earl is much distressed:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108660">An Englishman, Russell the Earl of Bedford,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108670">Is by the French King, sold unto his death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108680">It may fall out, that I may do him good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108690">To save his life, I'll hazard my heart blood:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108700">Therefore kind sir, thanks for your liberal gift,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108710">I must be gone to aid him there's no shift. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108720" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e108730">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108740">I'll be no hinderer to so good an act,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108750">Heaven prosper you, in that you go about;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108760">If fortune bring you this way back again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108770">Pray let me see you: so I take my leave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108780">All good a man can wish, I do bequeath. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e108790">Exit Friskiball. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108800" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e108810">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108820">All good that God doth send, light on your head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108830">There's few such men within our climate bred. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108840">How say you now Hodge, is not this good fortune. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108850" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e108860">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108870">How say you, I'll tell you what master Thomas</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108880">If all men be of this gentleman's mind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108890">Let's keep our standings upon this bridge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108900">We shall get more here with begging in one day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108910">Than I shall with making horshoes in a whole year. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108920" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e108930">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108940">No Hodge, we must begone unto Bononia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108950">There to relieve the noble Earl of Bedford:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108960">Where if I fail not in my policy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e108970">I shall deceive their subtle treachery. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e108980" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodge.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e108990">Nay I'll follow you, God bless us from the thieving bandettoes again.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e109000">Exit omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e109010"><pb facs="12"/>Enter Bedforde and his host.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109020" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e109030">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109040">Am I betrayed, was bedford born to die,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109050">By such base slaves in such a place as this:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109060">Have I escaped so many times in France,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109070">So many battles have I over passed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109080">And made the French stir when they heard my name;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109090">And am I now betrayed unto my death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109100">Some of their heart's blood first shall pay for it. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109110" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hoa.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e109120">They do desire my lord to speak with you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109130" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e109140">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109150">The traitors do desire to have my blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109160">But by my birth, my honour, and my name:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109170">By all my hopes, my life shall cost them dear. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109180">Open the door, I'll venture out upon them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109190">And if I must die, then I'll die with honour. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109200" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hoa.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e109210">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109220">Alas my lord that is a desperate course,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109230">They have begirt you round about the house:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109240">Their meaning is to take you prisoner,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109250">And so to send your body unto France. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109260" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e109270">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109280">First shall the ocean be as dry as sand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109290">Before alive they send me unto France:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109300">I'll have my body first bored like a sieve,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109310">And die as Hector, 'gainst the Myrmidons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109320">Ear France shall boast Bedofrds their prisoner,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109330">Treacherous France that 'gainst the law of arms:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109340">Hath here betrayed thy enemy to death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109350">But be assured my blood shall be revenged,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109360">Upon the best lives that remains in France,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109370">Stand back, or else thou runnest upon thy death. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e109380">Enter a servant.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109390" who="A11265-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e109400">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109410">Pardon my lord, I come to tell your honour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109420">That they have hired a neopolitan:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109430">Who by his oratory hath promised them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109440">Without the shedding of one drop of blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109450">Into their hands safe to deliver you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109460">And therefore craves none but himself may enter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109470">And a poor swain that attends on him. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e109480">Exit servant.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109490" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker><pb facs="12"/>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e109500">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109510">A Neopolitan bid him come in,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109520">Were he as cunning in his eloquence:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109530">As Cicero the famous man of Rome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109540">His words would be as chaff against the wind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109550">Sweet-tongued Ulysses that made Ajax mad;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109560">Were he and his tongue in this speakers head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109570">Alive he wins me not, then 'tis no conquest dead. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e109580">Enter Cromwell like a Neopolitan, and Hodge with him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109590" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e109600">Sir are you the master of the house,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109610" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hoa.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e109620">I am sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109630" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e109640">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109650">By this same token you must leave this place,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109660">And leave none but the Earl and I together,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109670">And this my peasant here to tend on us. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109680" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hoa.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e109690">With all my heart, God grant, you do some good.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e109700">Exit host. Cromwell shuts the door.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109710" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e109720">Now sir, what's your will with me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109730" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e109740">Intends your honour, not to yield yourself:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109750" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e109760">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109770">No good man goose, not while my sword doth last,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109780">Is this your eloquence for to persuade me. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109790" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e109800">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109810">My lord my eloquence is for to save you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109820">I am not as you judge a neopolitan:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109830">But Cromwell your servant, and an Englishman. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109840" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e109850">How Cromwell, not my farrier's son.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109860" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e109870">The same sir, and am come to succour you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109880" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e109890">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109900">Yes faith sir, and I am Hodge, your poor smith,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109910">Many a time and oft, have I shooed your Dapper grey. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109920" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e109930">And what avails it me that thou art here.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e109940" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e109950">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109960">It may avail if you'll be ruled by me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109970">My lord you know the men of Mantua;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109980">And these Bononians are at deadly strife,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e109990">And they my lord, both love and honour you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110000">Could you but get out of the Mantua port,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110010">Then were you safe despite of all their force. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110020" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e110030">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110040">Tut man thou talkest of things impossible,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110050">Dost thou not see that we are round beset:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110060">How then is it possible, we should escape. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110070" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker><pb facs="13"/>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e110080">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110090">By force we cannot, but by policy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110100">Put on the apparel here that Hodge doth wear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110110">And give him yours: the states they know you not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110120">For as I think they never saw your face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110130">And at a watchword must I call them in,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110140">And will desire, that we safe may pass</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110150">To Mantua, where I'll say my business lies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110160">How doth your honour like of this device? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110170" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e110180">O wondrous good: but wilt thou venture Hodge? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110190" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e110200">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110210">Will I oh noble lord, I do accord, in any thing I can,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110220">And do agree, to set thee free, do fortune what she can. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110230" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e110240">Come then let's change our apparel straight.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110250" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e110260">Go Hodge make haste, lest they chance to call.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110270" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e110280">I warrant you I'll fit him with a suit. Exit Earl and Hodge.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110290" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e110300">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110310">Heavens grant this policy doth take success,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110320">And that the Earl may safely scape away. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110330">And yet it grieves me for this simple wretch,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110340">For fear they should offer him violence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110350">But of two evils, 'tis best to shun the greatest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110360">And better is it that he lives in thrall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110370">Than such a noble Earl as he should fall. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110380">Their stubborn hearts, it may be will relent:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110390">Since he is gone, to whom their hate is bent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110400">My lord have you dispatched. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e110410">Enter Bedford like the clown, and Hodge in his cloak and his hat.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110420" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e110430">How dost thou like us Cromwell, is it well?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110440" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e110450">O my lord excellent, Hodge how dost feel thyself?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110460" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e110470">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110480">How do I feel myself, why as a noble man should do</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110490">O how I feel honour come creeping on,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110500">My nobility is wonderful melancholy:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110510">Is it not most gentleman like to be melancholy,</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110520" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e110530">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110540">Yes Hodge, now go sit down in his study. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110550">And take state upon thee. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110560" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodge.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e110570">I warrant you my lord, let me alone to take state upon<pb facs="13"/> me: but hark you my lord, do you feel nothing bite about you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110580" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e110590">No trust me Hodge. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110600" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e110610">I they know they want their pasture; it's a strange thing of this vermin, they dare not meddle with nobility.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110620" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e110630">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110640">Go take thy place Hodge, I'll call them in. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110650">All is done, enter and if you please. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e110660">Hodge sits in the study, and Cromwell calls in the states.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e110670">Enter the states and officers, with halberts.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110680" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e110690">What have you won him? will he yield himself?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110700" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e110710">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110720">I have an't please you, and the quiet Earl,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110730">Doth yield himself to be disposed by you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110740" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e110750">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110760">Give him the money that we promised him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110770">So let him go, whether it please himself. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110780" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e110790">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110800">My business sir lies unto Mantua,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110810">Please you to give me safe conduct thither. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110820" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e110830">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110840">Go and conduct him to the Mantua port,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110850">And see him safe delivered presently. <stage xml:id="A11265-e110860">Exit Cromwell and Bedford. </stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110870">Go draw the curtains, let us see the Earl,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110880">Oh he is writing, stand apart a while. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110890" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodge.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e110900">Fellow William, I am not as I have been, I went from you a smith, I write to you as a lord: I am at this present writing, among the Polonian Casiges. I do commend my lordship to Raphe and to Roger, to Bridget and to Doritie, and so to all the youth of Putnay. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e110910" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e110920">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110930">Sure these are the names of English noblemen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110940">Some of his special friends, to whom he writes:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110950">But stay he doth address himself to sing. <stage xml:id="A11265-e110960">Here he sings a song.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110970">My lord I am glad you are so frolic and so blithe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110980">Believe me noble lord if you know all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e110990">You'd change your merry vain to sudden sorrow. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111000" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hodg.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e111010">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111020">I change my merry vain, no thou bononian, no,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111030">I am a lord and therefore let me go,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111040">And do defy thee and thy sasigis,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111050">Therefore stand off, and come not near my honour. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111060" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e111070">My lord this jesting cannot serve your turn.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111080" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e111090">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111100">Dost think thou black Bononian beast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111110">That I do flout, do gibe or jest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111120">No, no, thou bear pot, know that I, a noble Earl a lord perdie. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111130" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker><pb facs="14"/>Governor</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e111140">What means this trumpets sound.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e111150">A trumpet sounds. Enter a messenger. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111160" who="A11265-citizen">
          <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e111170">One come from the states of Mantua. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111180" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e111190">What would you with us speak, thou man of Mantua? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111200" who="A11265-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e111210">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111220">Men of Bononia: this my message is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111230">To let you know the noble Earl of Bedford:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111240">Is safe within the town of Mantua,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111250">And wills you send the peasant that you have,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111260">Who hath deceived your expectation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111270">Or else the states of Mantua have vowed:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111280">They will recall the truce that they have made,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111290">And not a man shall stir, from forth your town,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111300">That shall return unless you send him back. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111310" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e111320">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111330">O this misfortune how it mads my heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111340">The Neopolitan hath beguiled us all;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111350">Hence with this fool: what shall we do with him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111360">The Earl being gone a plague upon it all. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111370" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e111380">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111390">No I'll assure you I am no Earl, but a smith sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111400">One Hodge, a smith at Putnay sir:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111410">One that hath gulled you, that hath bored you sir. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111420" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e111430">Away with him, take hence the fool you came for.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111440" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e111450">Ay sir: and I'll leave the greater fool with you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111460" who="A11265-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e111470">Farewell Bononians, come friend a long with me,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111480" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e111490">My friend afore, my lordship will follow thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e111500">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111510" who="A11265-governor">
          <speaker>Governor</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e111520">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111530">Well Mantua, since by thee the Earl is lost,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111540">Within few days I hope to see thee crossed. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e111550">Exit omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e111560">Enter chorus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111570" who="A11265-chorus">
          <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e111580">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111590">Thus far you see how Cromwell's fortune passed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111600">The Earl of Bedford being safe in  </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111610">Desires Cromwell's company into France,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111620">To make requital for his ,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111630">But Cromwell doth deny the Earl his suit:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111640">And tells him that those parts he meant to see,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111650">He had not yet set footing on the land,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111660">And so directly takes his way to Spain:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111670">The Earl to France, and so they both do part,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111680">Now let your thoughts as swift as is the wind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111690"><pb facs="14"/> skip some few years, that Cromwell spent in travel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111700">And now imagine him to be in England:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111710">Servant unto the master of the rolls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111720">Wherein short time where he began to flourish,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111730">An hour shall show you what few years did cherish. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e111740">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e111750">The music plays, they bring out the banquet. Enter sir Christopher hales, and Cromwell, and two servants.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111760" who="A11265-hales">
          <speaker>Hales.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e111770">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111780">Come sirs, be careful of your master's credit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111790">And as our bounty now exceeds the figure</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111800">Of common entertainment: so do you</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111810">With looks as free, as is your master's soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111820">Give former welcome to the thronged tables,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111830">That shall receive the Cardinal's followers. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111840">And the attendants of the lord chancellor. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111850">But all my care Cromwell depends on thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111860">Thou art a man, differing from vulgar form,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111870">And by how much thy spirit is ranked 'bove these,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111880">In rules of art, by so much it shines brighter by travel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111890">Whose observance pleads his merit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111900">In a most learned, yet unaffecting spirit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111910">Good Cromwell cast an eye of fair regard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111920">Bout all my house, and what this ruder flesh,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111930">Through ignorance, or wine, do miscreate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111940">Salve thou with courtesy: if welcome want,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111950">Full bowls, and ample banquets will seem scant. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e111960" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e111970">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111980">Sir, whatsoever lies in me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e111990">Assure I will show my utmost duty. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e112000">Exit Crom.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112010" who="A11265-hales">
          <speaker>Hales.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112020">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112030">About it then, the lords will straight be here,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112040">Cromwell, thou hast those parts would rather suit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112050">The service of the state, then of my house,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112060">I look upon thee with a loving eye,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112070">That one day will prefer thy destiny. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e112080">Enter messenger. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112090" who="A11265-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e112100">Sir the lords be at hand,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112110" who="A11265-hales">
          <speaker>Hales.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112120">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112130">They are welcome, bid Cromwell straight attend us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112140">And look you all things be in perfect readiness. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e112150"><pb facs="15"/>The music plays. Enter Cardinal Wolsay, sir Thomas Moor and Gardiner. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112160" who="A11265-wolsey">
          <speaker>Wol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e112170">O sir Christopher you are too liberal, what a banquet to?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112180" who="A11265-halberdier">
          <speaker>Hal.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112190">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112200">My lords if words could show, the ample welcome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112210">That my free heart affords you, I could then become a prater:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112220">But I now must deal like a feast politician,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112230">With your lordships, defer your welcome till the banquet end,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112240">That it may then salve our defect of fair:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112250">Yet welcome now and all that tend on you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112260" who="A11265-wolsey">
          <speaker>Wol.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112270">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112280">Thanks to the kind master of the rolls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112290">Come and sit down, sit down sir Thomas More:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112300">'Tis strange, how that we and the Spaniard differ,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112310">Their dinner, is our banquet after dinner,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112320">And they are men of active disposition,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112330">This I gather, that by their sparing meat:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112340">Their body is more fitter for the wars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112350">And if that famine chance to pinch their maws,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112360">Being used to fast it breeds less pain. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112370" who="A11265-halberdier">
          <speaker>Hal.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112380">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112390">Fill me some wine: I'll answer Cardinal Wolsay:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112400">My lord we Spaniards are of more freer souls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112410">Then hunger-starved, and ill complexioned Spaniards,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112420">They that are rich in Spain, spare belly food;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112430">To deck their backs with an Italian hood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112440">And silks of civil: and the poorest snake,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112450">That feeds on lemons, pilchers, and ne'er heated</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112460">His pallet with sweet flesh, will bear a case,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112470">More fat and gallant, than his starved face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112480">Pride, the inquisition, and this belly evil,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112490">Are in my judgement, Spain's three headed devil. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112500" who="A11265-more">
          <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112510">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112520">Indeed it is a plague unto their nation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112530">And stager after in blind imitation. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112540" who="A11265-halberdier">
          <speaker>Hal.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112550">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112560">My lords with welcome, I present your lordships</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112570">A solemn health. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112580" who="A11265-more">
          <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112590">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112600">I love health well, but when healths do bring,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112610">Pain to the head, and bodies surfeiting:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112620">Then cease I healths: nay spill not friend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112630"><pb facs="15"/> for though the drops be small,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112640">Yet have they force, to force men to the wall. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112650" who="A11265-wolsey">
          <speaker>Wol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e112660">Sir Christopher is that your man.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112670" who="A11265-halberdier">
          <speaker>Hal.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112680">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112690">And like your grace he is a scholar and a lingest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112700">One that hath travelled many parts of Christendom my lord. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112710" who="A11265-wolsey">
          <speaker>Wol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e112720">My friend come nearer, have you been a traveller.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112730" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112740">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112750">My lord I have added to my knowledge, the lo countries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112760">France, Spain, Germany, and Italy:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112770">And though small gain, of profit I did find,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112780">Yet did it please my eye, content my mind. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112790" who="A11265-wolsey">
          <speaker>Wol.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112800">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112810">What do you think of the several states,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112820">And princes courts as you have travelled. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112830" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112840">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112850">My lord no court with England may compare,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112860">Neither for state nor civil government:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112870">Lust dwells in France, in Italy, and Spain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112880">From the poor peasant to the prince's train,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112890">In Germany, and holland riot serves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112900">And he that most can drink, most he deserves:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112910">England I praise not: for I here was born,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112920">But that she laugheth the others unto scorn. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112930" who="A11265-wolsey">
          <speaker>Wol.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112940">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112950">My lord there dwells within that spirit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112960">More than can be discerned by outward eye,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e112970">Sir Christopher will you part with your man. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e112980" who="A11265-halberdier">
          <speaker>Hal.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e112990">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113000">I have sought to proffer him to your lordship,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113010">And now I see he hath preferred himself. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113020" who="A11265-wolsey">
          <speaker>Wol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e113030">What is thy name.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113040" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e113050">Cromwell my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113060" who="A11265-wolsey">
          <speaker>Wol.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e113070">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113080">Then Cromwell here we make thee solicitor of our causes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113090">And nearest next ourself:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113100">Gardener give you kind welcome to the man. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e113110">Gardiner embraces him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113120" who="A11265-more">
          <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e113130">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113140">My lord you are a royal winer,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113150">Hath got a man besides your bounteous dinner,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113160">Well knight, pray we come no more:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113170">If we come often, or shut up thy door. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113180" who="A11265-wolsey">
          <speaker>Wol.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e113190">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113200">Sir Christopher hadst hadst thou given me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113210">Half thy lands: thou couldst not have pleased me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113220"><pb facs="16"/> so much as with this man of thine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113230">My infant thoughts do spell:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113240">Shortly his fortune shall be lifted higher,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113250">True industry doth kindle honour's fire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113260">And so kind master of the rolls farewell. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113270" who="A11265-halberdier">
          <speaker>Hal.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e113280">Cromwell farewell.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113290" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e113300">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113310">Cromwell takes his leave of you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113320">That near will leave to love and honour you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e113330">Exit omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e113340">Enter chorus. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113350" who="A11265-chorus">
          <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e113360">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113370">Now Cromwell's highest fortunes doth begin,<stage xml:id="A11265-e113380">The music plays, as they go in.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113390">Wolsay that loved him as he did his life:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113400">Committed all his treasure to his hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113410">Wolsay is dead, and Gardiner his man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113420">Is now created Bishop of Winchester:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113430">Pardon if we omit all Wolsey's life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113440">Because our play depends on Cromwell's death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113450">Now sit and see his highest state of all;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113460">His height of rising: and his sudden fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113470">Pardon the errors is all ready past,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113480">And live in hope the best doth come at last:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113490">My hope upon your favour doth depend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113500">And look to have your liking ere the end. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e113510">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e113520">Enter Gardiner Bishop of Winchester, the Dukes of Norfolk, and of Suffolk, sir Thomas More, sir Christopher Halles, and Cromwell. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113530" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Nor.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e113540">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113550">Master Cromwell since Cardinal Wolsey's death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113560">His majesty is given to understand:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113570">There's certain bills and writings in your hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113580">That much concerns the state of England,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113590">My lord of Winchester is it not so. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113600" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e113610">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113620">My lord of Norfolk, we two wear whilom fellows,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113630">And master Cromwell, though our master's love:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113640"><pb facs="16"/> did bind us, while his love was to the King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113650">It is no boot now to deny these things,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113660">Which may be prejudicial to the state:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113670">And though that God hath raised my fortune higher,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113680">Than any way I looked for, or deserved. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113690">Yet my life no longer with me dwell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113700">Than I prove true unto my sovereign:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113710">What say you master Cromwell? have you those writings, ay, or no? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113720" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e113730">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113740">Here are the writings, and upon my knees,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113750">I give them up, unto the worthy Dukes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113760">Of Suffolk, and of Norfolk: he was my master,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113770">And each virtuous part,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113780">That lived in him, I tendered with my heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113790">But what his head complotted 'gainst the state. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113800">My country's love commands me that to hate:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113810">His sudden death I grieve for, not his fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113820">Because he sought to work my country's thrall. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113830" who="A11265-suffolk">
          <speaker>Suff.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e113840">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113850">Cromwell, the King shall here of this thy duty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113860">Whom I assure myself will well reward thee:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113870">My lord let's go unto his majesty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113880">And show these writings which he longs to see. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e113890">Exit Norfolk and Suffolk. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e113900">Enter Bedford hastily.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113910" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e113920">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113930">How now, who's this Cromwell? </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113940">By by soul, welcome to England:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113950">Thou once didst save my life, didst not Cromwell? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e113960" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e113970">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113980">If I did so, 'tis greater glory for me, that you remember it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e113990">Then of myself vainly to report it. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114000" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114010">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114020">Well Cromwell, now is the time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114030">I shall commend thee to my sovereign:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114040">Cheer up thyself, for I will raise thy state,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114050">A Russell yet was never found ingrate </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e114060">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114070" who="A11265-hales">
          <speaker>Hales.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114080">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114090">O how uncertain is the wheel of state,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114100">Who lately greater than the Cardinal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114110">For fear, and love: and now who lower lies? </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114120"><pb facs="17"/>Gay honours are but fortune's flatteries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114130">And whom this day, pride and promotion swells,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114140">Tomorrow, envy and ambition quells. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114150" who="A11265-more">
          <speaker>More.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114160">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114170">Who sees the cobweb entangle the poor fly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114180">May boldly say the wretch's death is nigh. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114190" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114200">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114210">I know his state and proud ambition,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114220">Was too too violent to last overlong. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114230" who="A11265-hales">
          <speaker>Hales.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114240">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114250">Who soars too near the sun with golden wings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114260">Melts them, to ruin his own fortune brings. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e114270">Enter the Duke of Suffolk. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114280" who="A11265-suffolk">
          <speaker>Suf.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114290">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114300">Cromwell kneel down in King Henry's name,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114310">Arise sir Thomas Cromwell, thus begins thy fame. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e114320">Enter the Duke of Norfolk. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114330" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Norf.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114340">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114350">Cromwell the majesty of England,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114360">For the good liking he conceives of thee:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114370">Makes thee master of the jewel house,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114380">Chief secretary to himself, and with all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114390">Creates thee one of his highness privy counsel. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e114400">Enter the Earl of Bedforde. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114410" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e114420">Where is sir Thomas Cromwell is he knighted,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114430" who="A11265-suffolk">
          <speaker>Suf.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e114440">He is my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114450" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114460">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114470">Then to add honour to his name,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114480">The King creates him lord keeper of his privy seal:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114490">And master of the rolls,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114500">Which you sir Christopher do now enjoy;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114510">The King determines higher place for you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114520" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e114530">My lords, these honours are too high for my desert,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114540" who="A11265-more">
          <speaker>More.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114550">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114560">O content thee man, who would not choose it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114570">Yet thou art wise in seeming to refuse it. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114580" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114590">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114600">Here's honours, titles, and  ,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114610">I fear this climbing, will have   </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114620" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker><pb facs="17"/>Norff.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114630">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114640">Then come my lords, let's altogether bring,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114650">This new made counsellor to England's King. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e114660">Exit all but gardener. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114670" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114680">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114690">But Gardiner means his glory shall be dimmed:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114700">Shall Cromwell live a greater man than I,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114710">My envy with his honour now is bred,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114720">I hope to shorten Cromwell by the head. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e114730">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e114740">Enter Friskiball very poor.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114750" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fris.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e114760">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114770">O Friskiball, what shall become of thee? </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114780">Where shalt thou go, or which way shalt thou turn,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114790">Fortune that turns her too unconstant wheel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114800">Hath turned thy wealth and riches in the sea,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114810">All parts abroad wherever I have been,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114820">Grows weary of me, and denies me succour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114830">My debtors they, that should relieve my want,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114840">Forswears my money, says they owe me none:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114850">They know my state too mean, to bear out law,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114860">And here in London, where I oft have been,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114870">And have done good to many a wretched man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114880">Am now most wretched here, despised myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114890">In vain it is, more of their hearts to try,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e114900">Be patient therefore, say thee down and die. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e114910">He lies down.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e114920">Enter good man Seely, and his wife Joane. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114930" who="A11265-seely">
          <speaker>Seely.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e114940">Come Joan, come, let's see what he'll do for us now? Iwis we have done for him, when many a time and often he might have gone a hungry to bed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114950" who="A11265-wife">
          <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e114960">Alas man, now he is made a lord, he'll never look upon us, he'll fulfil the old proverb: set beggars a horseback, and they'll ride: a welladay for my cow, such as he, hath made us come behind hand, we had never pawned our cow else to pay our rent.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114970" who="A11265-seely">
          <speaker><pb facs="18"/>Seely.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e114980">Well Joan he'll come this way: and by God's dickers I'll tell him roundly of it, and if he were ten lords: 'a shall know that I had not my cheese and my bacon for nothing.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e114990" who="A11265-wife">
          <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e115000">Do you remember husband how he would mouch up my cheese cakes, he hath forgotten this now, but we'll remember him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115010" who="A11265-seely">
          <speaker>Seelie.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e115020">I we shall have now three flaps with a fox tail: but i'faith I'll gibber a joint, but I'll tell him his own: stay who comes here, oh stand up here he comes, stand up.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e115030">Enter Hodge very fine with a tipstafe, Cromwell, the mace carried before him: Norfolk, and Suffolk, and attendants.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115040" who="A11265-hodge">
          <speaker>Hod.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115050">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115060">Come away with these beggars here, rise up sirrah,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115070">Come out the good people: run afore there ho. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e115080">Friskiball riseth, and stands afar off.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115090" who="A11265-seely">
          <speaker>Seelie.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e115100">I we are kicked away now, we come for our own, the time hath been he would a looked more friendly upon us: and you Hodge, we know you well enough though you are so fine.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115110" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115120">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115130">Come hither sirrah, stay what men are these,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115140">My honest host of Hounslow, and his wife:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115150">I owe thee money father, do I not. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115160" who="A11265-seely">
          <speaker>Seelie.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e115170">I by the body of me dost thou, would thou wouldst pay me, good four pound it is, I have a the post at home.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115180" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115190">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115200">I know 'tis true, sirrah give him ten angels,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115210">And look your wife, and you do stay to dinner:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115220">And while you live: I freely give to you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115230">Four pound a year, for the four pound I ought you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115240" who="A11265-seely">
          <speaker>Seelie.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115250">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115260">Art not changed, art old Tom still,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115270">Now God bless the good lord Tom:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115280"><pb facs="18"/> home Joan home, I'll dine with my lord Tom today,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115290">And thou shalt come next week,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115300">Fetch my cow, home Joan, home. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115310" who="A11265-wife">
          <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115320">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115330">Now God bless thee, my good lord Tom,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115340">I'll fetch my cow presently. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e115350">Exit wife.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e115360">Enter Gardiner. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115370" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115380">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115390">Sirrah, go to yond stranger, tell him I desire him</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115400">Stay at dinner, I must speak with him;</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115410" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115420">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115430">My lord of Norfolk: see you this same bubble,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115440">That same puff, but mark the end, my lord mark the end. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115450" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Nor.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115460">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115470">I promise you, I like not something he hath done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115480">But let that pass, the King doth love him well. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115490" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115500">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115510">Good morrow to my lord of Winchester,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115520">I know you bear me hard, about the abbey lands. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115530" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115540">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115550">Have I not reason, when religion is wronged,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115560">You had no colour for what you have done. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115570" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115580">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115590">Yes the abolishing of Antichrist,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115600">And of this popish order from our realm:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115610">I am no enemy to religion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115620">But what is done, it is for England's good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115630">What did they serve for but to feed a sort:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115640">Of lazy abbotes, and of full fed friars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115650">They neither plow, nor sow, and yet they reap,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115660">The fat of all the land, and suck the poor:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115670">Look what was theirs, is in King Henry's hands,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115680">His wealth before lay in the abbey lands. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115690" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115700">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115710">Indeed these things you have alleged my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115720">When God doth know the infant yet unborn:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115730">Will curse the time, the abbeys were pulled down,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115740">I pray now where is hospitality,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115750">Where now may poor distressed people go:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115760">For to relieve their need, or rest their bones,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115770">When weary travel doth oppress their limbs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115780">And where religious men should take them in,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115790"><pb facs="19"/> shall now be kept back with a mastiff dog,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115800">And thousand thousand. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115810" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Nor.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115820">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115830">O my lord no more: things passed redress,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115840">'Tis bootless to complain. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115850" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e115860">What shall we to the convocation house.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115870" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Nor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e115880">We'll fellow you my lord, pray lead the way.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e115890">Enter old Cromwell like a farmer.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115900" who="A11265-old_cromwell">
          <speaker>Old. Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115910">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115920">How, one Cromwell made lord keeper since I left Putnay</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115930">And dwelled in Yorkshire, I never heard better news:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115940">I'll see that Cromwell, or it shall go hard. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e115950" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e115960">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115970">My aged father: state set aside,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115980">Father on my knee I crave your blessing:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e115990">One of my servants go and have him in,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116000">At better leisure will we talk with him. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116010" who="A11265-old_cromwell">
          <speaker>Old. Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116020">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116030">Now if I die, how happy were the day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116040">To see this comfort rains forth showers of joy. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e116050">Exit old Cromwell.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116060" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Nor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e116070">This duty in him shows a kind of grace,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116080" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e116090">Go on before for time draws on apace.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e116100">Exit all but Friskiball. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116110" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fris.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116120">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116130">I wonder what this lord would have with me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116140">His man so strictly gave me charge to stay:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116150">I never did offend him to my knowledge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116160">Well, good or bad, I mean to bide it all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116170">Worse than I am, now never can befall. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e116180">Enter Banister and his wife.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116190" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116200">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116210">Come wife I take it be almost dinner time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116220">For master Newton, and master Crosbie sent to me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116230">Last night, they would come dine with me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116240">And take their bond in: I pray thee hie thee home,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116250">And see that all things be in readiness. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116260" who="A11265-mrs_banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116270">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116280">They shall be welcome, husband I'll go before,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116290">But is not that man master Friskiball:</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e116300">She runs and embraces him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116310" who="A11265-bagot">
          <speaker><pb facs="19"/>Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116320">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116330">O heavens it is kind master Friskiball,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116340">Say sir, what hap hath brought you to this pass. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116350" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fris.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e116360">The same that brought you to your misery.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116370" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116380">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116390">Why would you not acquaint me with your state,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116400">Is Banister your poor friend quite forgotten:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116410">Whose goods, whose love, whose life and all is yours. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116420" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116430">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116440">I thought your usage would be as the rest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116450">That had more kindness at my hands than you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116460">Yet looked askance, whenas they saw me poor:</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116470" who="A11265-mrs_banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116480">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116490">If Banister should bear so base a heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116500">I never would look my husband in the face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116510">But hate him as I would a cockatrice. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116520" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116530">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116540">And well thou mightest, should Banister deal so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116550">Since that I saw you sir, my state is mended:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116560">And for the thousand pound I owe to you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116570">I have it ready, for you sir at home,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116580">And though I grieve your fortune is so bad:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116590">Yet that my haps to help you, makes me glad,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116600">And now sir will it please you walk with me. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116610" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fris.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116620">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116630">Not yet I cannot, for the lord chancellor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116640">Hath here commanded me to weight on him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116650">For what I know not: pray God 'tis for my good. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116660" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116670">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116680">Never make doubt, of that I'll warrant you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116690">He is as kind a noble gentleman:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116700">As ever did possess the place he hath. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116710" who="A11265-mrs_banister">
          <speaker>Mi Ba.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116720">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116730">Sir my brother is his steward if you please,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116740">Weal go along, and bear you company:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116750">I know we shall not want for welcome there. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116760" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fris.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e116770">Withal my heart: but what's become of Bagot. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116780" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e116790">He is hanged, for buying jewels of the Kings.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116800" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fris.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116810">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116820">A just reward for one so impious,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116830">The time draws on, sir will you go along. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116840" who="A11265-banister">
          <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e116850">I'll follow you kind master Friskiball. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e116860">Exit omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e116870"><pb facs="20"/>Enter two merchants.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116880" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116890">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116900">Now master Crosbie, I see you have a care,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116910">To keep your word, in payment of your money. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116920" who="A11265-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116930">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116940">By my faith I have reason upon a bond,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116950">Three thousand pound is too much to forfeit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116960">Yet I doubt not master Banister. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e116970" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e116980">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e116990">By my faith your sum is more than mine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117000">And yet I am not much behind you too,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117010">Considering that today I paid at court. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117020" who="A11265-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e117030">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117040">Mass and well remembered:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117050">What's the reason the lord Cromwell's men,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117060">We are such long skirts upon their coats,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117070">They reach almost down to their very ham. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117080" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e117090">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117100">I will resolve you sir, and thus it is;</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117110">The Bishop of Winchester, that loves not Cromwell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117120">As great men are envied, as well as less. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117130">A while ago there was a jar between them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117140">And it was brought to my lord Cromwell's ear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117150">That Bishop Gardiner would sit on his skirt,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117160">Upon which word, he made his men long blew coats,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117170">And in the court wore one of them himself:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117180">And meeting with the Bishop, quoth he, my lord</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117190">Here's skirt enough now for your grace to sit on,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117200">Which vexed the Bishop to the very heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117210">This is the reason why they wear long coats. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117220" who="A11265-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e117230">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117240">'Tis always seen, and mark it for a rule,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117250">That one great man will envy still another:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117260">But 'tis a thing that nothing concerns me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117270">What shall we now to master banisters? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117280" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e117290">I come, we'll pay him royally for our dinner.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e117300">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e117310">Enter the usher and the shower, the meat goes over the stage.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117320" who="A11265-usher">
          <speaker>Vsher.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e117330">Uncover there gentlemen.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e117340"><pb facs="20"/>Enter Cromwell, Bedford, Suffolk, old Cromwell, Friskiball, goodman Seelie, and attendants.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117350" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e117360">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117370">My noble lords of Suffolk and of Bedford,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117380">Your honour's welcome to poor Cromwell's house:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117390">Where is my father? nay be covered father,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117400">Although that duty to these noble men, doth challenge it</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117410">Yet I'll make bold with them. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117420">Your head doth bear the calendar of care:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117430">What Cromwell covered, and his father bore,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117440">It must not be. Now sir to you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117450">Is not your name Friskiball and a Florentine. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117460" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fris.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e117470">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117480">My name was Friskiball, till cruel fate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117490">Did rob me of my name and of my state. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117500" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e117510">What fortune brought you to this country now?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117520" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e117530">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117540">All other parts hath left me succourless,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117550">Save only this, because of debts I have,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117560">I hope to gain for to relieve my want. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117570" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e117580">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117590">Did you not once upon your Florence bridge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117600">Help two distressed men, robbed by the Bandetro,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117610">His name was Cromwell? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117620" who="A11265-friskiball">
          <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e117630">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117640">I never made my brain a calendar of any good I did,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117650">I always loved this nation with my heart. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117660" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e117670">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117680">I am that Cromwell that you there relieved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117690">Sixteen ducats you gave me for to clothe me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117700">Sixteen to bear my charges by the way,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117710">And sixteen more I had for my horse hire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117720">There be those several sums justly returned,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117730">Yet with injustice, serving at my need,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117740">And to repay them without interest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117750">Therefore receive of me these four several bags,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117760">In each of them there is four hundred mark,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117770">And bring me the names of all your debtors,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117780">And if they will not see you paid, I will:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117790"><pb facs="21"/> oh God forbid, that I should see him fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117800">That helped me in my greatest need of all:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117810">Here stands my father that first gave me life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117820">Alas what duty is too much for him:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117830">This man in time of need did save my life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117840">And therefore cannot do too much for him. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117850">By this old man I often times was fed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117860">Else might I have gone supperless to bed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117870">Such kindness have I had of these three men,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117880">That Cromwell no way can repay again:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117890">Now in to dinner, for we stay too long,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117900">And to good stomachs is no greater wrong. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e117910">Exit omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e117920">Enter gardener in his study, and his man.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117930" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e117940">Sirrah, where be those men I caused to stay?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117950" who="A11265-sergeant">
          <speaker>Sergeant</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e117960">They do attend your pleasure sir within.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e117970" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e117980">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e117990">Bid them come hither, and stay you without,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118000">For by those men, the fox of this same land,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118010">That makes a goose of better than himself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118020">We'll worry him unto his latest home,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118030">Or gardener will fail in his intent. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118040">As for the Dukes of Suffolk and of Norfolk,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118050">Whom I have sent for to come speak with me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118060">Howsoever outwardly they shadow it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118070">Yet in their hearts I know they love him not:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118080">As for the Earl of Bedford he is but one,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118090">And dares not gainsay what we do set down:<stage xml:id="A11265-e118100">Enter the two witnesses.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118110">Now my friends, you know I saved your lives,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118120">When by the law you had deserved death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118130">And than you promised me upon your oaths,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118140">To venture both your lives to do me good. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118150" who="A11265-both_witnesses">
          <speaker>Both witness</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e118160">We swore no more, than that we will perform.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118170" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e118180">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118190">I take your words, and that which you must do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118200"><pb facs="21"/> is service for you God, and for your King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118210">To root a rebel from this flourishing land,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118220">One that's an enemy unto the church:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118230">And therefore must you take your solemn oaths,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118240">That you heard Cromwell the lord chancellor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118250">Did wish a dagger at King Henry's heart:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118260">Fear not to swear it, for I heard him speak it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118270">Therefore we'll shield you from ensuing harms. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118280" who="A11265-2_witness">
          <speaker>2. wit</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e118290">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118300">If you will warrant us the deed is good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118310">We'll undertake it. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118320" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e118330">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118340">Kneel down, and I will here absolve you both,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118350">This crucifix I lay upon your head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118360">And sprinkle holy-water on your brows,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118370">The deed is meritorious that you do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118380">And by it shall you purchase grace from heaven. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118390" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e118400">Now sir we'll undertake it by our souls.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118410" who="A11265-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e118420">For Cromwell never loved none of our sort.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118430" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e118440">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118450">I know he doth not, and for both of you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118460">I will prefer you to some place of worth:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118470">Now get you in, until I call for you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118480">For presently the Duke's means to be here. <stage xml:id="A11265-e118490">Exit wit.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118500">Cromwell sit fast, thy time's not long to reign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118510">The abbeys that were pulled down by thy means,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118520">Is now a mean for me to pull thee down:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118530">Thy pride upon thy own head lights upon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118540">For thou art he hath changed religion:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118550">But now no more, for here the Dukes are come. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e118560">Enter Suffolk, Norfolk, and the Earl of Bedford. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118570" who="A11265-suffolk">
          <speaker>Suff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e118580">God-den to my lord Bishop.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118590" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Nor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e118600">How fares my lord? what are you all alone?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118610" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e118620">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118630">No not alone my lords, my mind is troubled:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118640">I know your honours muse wherefore I sent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118650">And in such haste: what came you from the King? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118660" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Norff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e118670">We did, and left none but lord Cromwell with him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118680" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker><pb facs="22"/>Gard.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e118690">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118700">O what a dangerous time is this we live in,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118710">There's Thomas Wolsay, he's already gone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118720">And Thomas More, he followed after him:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118730">Another Thomas yet there doth remain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118740">That is far worse than either of those twain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118750">And if with speed my lords we not pursue it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118760">I fear the King and all the land will rue it. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118770" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e118780">Another Thomas, pray God it be not Cromwell. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118790" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e118800">My lord of Bedford, it is that traitor Cromwell. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118810" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e118820">Is Cromwell false, my heart will never think it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118830" who="A11265-suffolk">
          <speaker>Suff.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e118840">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118850">My lord of Winchester, what likelihood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118860">Or proof have you of this his treachery. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118870" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e118880">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118890">My lord too much, call in the men within,<stage xml:id="A11265-e118900">Enter witnesses.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118910">These men my lord upon their oaths affirm,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118920">That they did here lord Cromwell in his garden,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118930">Wished a dagger sticking at the heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e118940">Of our King Henry, what is this but treason? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118950" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e118960">If it be so, my heart doth bleed with sorrow.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118970" who="A11265-suffolk">
          <speaker>Suff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e118980">How say you friends, what did you here these words?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e118990" who="A11265-1_witness">
          <speaker>1. witness</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e119000">We did and like your grace.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119010" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Norff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e119020">In what place was lord Cromwell when he spoke them?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119030" who="A11265-2_witness">
          <speaker>2. witness</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119040">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119050">In his garden, where we did attend a suit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119060">Which we had waited for two year and more. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119070" who="A11265-suffolk">
          <speaker>Suff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e119080">How long is't since you heard him speak these words?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119090" who="A11265-2_witness">
          <speaker>2. witness</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e119100">Some half year since </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119110" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e119120">How chance that you concealed it all this time?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119130" who="A11265-1_witness">
          <speaker>1. witness</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e119140">His greatness made us fear, that was the cause,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119150" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119160">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119170">Ay, ay, his greatness that's the cause indeed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119180">And to make his treason here more manifest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119190">He calls his servants to him round about,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119200">Tells them of Wolsey's life, and of his fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119210">Says that himself hath many enemies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119220">And gives to some of them a park or manor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119230">To others leases, lands to other some:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119240">What need he do thus in his prime of life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119250">And if he were not fearful of his death. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119260" who="A11265-suffolk">
          <speaker><pb facs="22"/>Suff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e119270">My lord these likelihoods are very great.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119280" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119290">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119300">Pardon me lords, for I must needs depart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119310">Their proofs are great, but greater is my heart. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e119320">Exit Bedford. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119330" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Norff.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119340">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119350">My friends take heed of that which you have said,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119360">Your souls must answer what your tongues reports:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119370">Therefore take heed, be wary what you do. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119380" who="A11265-2_witness">
          <speaker>2. witness</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e119390">My lord we speak no more but truth.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119400" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Norff.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119410">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119420">Let them depart my lord of Winchester,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119430">Let these men be close kept,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119440">Until the day of trial. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119450" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119460">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119470">They shall my lord  ho take in these two men,<stage xml:id="A11265-e119480">Exit witnesses.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119490">My lords, if Cromwell have a public trial,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119500">That which we do, is void by his denial:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119510">You know the King will credit none but him. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119520" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Nor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e119530">'Tis true, he rules the King even as he pleases.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119540" who="A11265-suffolk">
          <speaker>Suff.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e119550">How shall we do for to attach him then.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119560" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119570">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119580">Marry my lords thus, by an act he made himself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119590">With an intent to entrap some of our lives,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119600">And this it is: if any councillor</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119610">Be convicted of high treason,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119620">He shall be executed without a public trial,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119630">This act my lords he caused the King to make. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119640" who="A11265-suffolk">
          <speaker>Suff.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119650">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119660">'A did indeed, and I remember it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119670">And now it is like to fall upon himself. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119680" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Nor.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119690">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119700">Let us not slack it, 'tis for England's good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119710">We must be wary, else he'll go beyond us. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119720" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119730">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119740">Well hath your grace said my lord of Norfolk</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119750">Therefore let us presently to Lambeth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119760">Thither comes Cromwell from the court tonight ,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119770">Let us arrest him, send him to the tower,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119780">And in the morning, cut off the traitor's head. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119790" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Norf.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119800">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119810">Come then about it, let us guard the town,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119820">This is the day that Cromwell must go down. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119830" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119840">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119850">Along my lords, well Cromwell is half dead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119860"><pb facs="23"/> he shaked my heart, but I will shave his head. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e119870">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e119880">Enter Bedford solus.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119890" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119900">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119910">My soul is like a water troubled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119920">And gardener is the man that makes it so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119930">Oh Cromwell I do fear thy end is near:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119940">Yet I'll prevent their malice if I can,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119950">And in good time, see where the man doth come,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e119960">Who little knows how nears his day of dome. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e119970">Enter Cromwell with his train, Bedford makes as though he would speak to him: he goes on.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e119980" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e119990">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120000">Your well encountered my good lord of Bedford,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120010">I see your honour is addressed to talk,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120020">Pray pardon me, I am sent for to the King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120030">And do not know the business yet myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120040">So fare you well, for I must needs be gone. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e120050">Exit all the train.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120060" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120070">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120080">You must, well what remedy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120090">I fear too soon you must be gone indeed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120100">The King hath business, but little dost thou know,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120110">Whose busy for thy life: thou thinks not so. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e120120">Enter Cromwell and  again</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120130" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120140">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120150">The second time well met my lord of Bedford,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120160">I am very sorry that my haste is such,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120170">Lord Marquess Dorset being  to death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120180">I must receive of  the  seal</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120190">At Lambeth, soon my lord we'll talk our fill,</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e120200">Exit the train.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120210" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e120220">How smooth and easy is the way to death.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e120230">Enter a servant.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120240" who="A11265-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120250">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120260">My lord the Dukes of Norfolk and of Suffolk,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120270"><pb facs="23"/> accompanied with the Bishop of Winchester,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120280">Entreats you to come presently to Lambeth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120290">On earnest matters that concerns the state. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120300" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120310">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120320">To Lambeth, so: go fetch me pen and ink,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120330">I and lord Cromwell there shall talk enough,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120340">I and our last I fear and if he come,<stage xml:id="A11265-e120350">He writes a letter.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120360">Hear take this letter, and bear it to lord Cromwell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120370">Bid him read it, say it concerns him near,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120380">Away begone, make all the haste you can,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120390">To Lambeth do I go a woeful man. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e120400">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e120410">Enter Cromwell and his train.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120420" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120430">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120440">Is the barge ready I will straight to Lambeth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120450">And if this one day's business once were past,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120460">I'd take my ease tomorrow after trouble,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120470">How now my friend wouldst thou speak with me. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e120480">The messenger brings him the letter, he puts it in his pocket.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120490" who="A11265-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e120500">Sir hears a letter from my lord of Bedford. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120510" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120520">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120530">O good my friend commend me to thy lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120540">Hold take those angels, drink them for thy pains. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120550" who="A11265-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120560">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120570">He doth desire your grace to read it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120580">Because he says it doth concern you near. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120590" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120600">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120610">Bid him assure himself of that, farewell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120620">Tomorrow tell him shall he hear from me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120630">Set on before there, and away to Lambeth. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e120640">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e120650">Enter Winchester, Suffolk, Norfolk, Bedford, sergeant at arms, the harauld, and halberts.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120660" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120670">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120680">Halberts stand close unto the water side,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120690">Sergeant at arms be bold in your office,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120700">Herald deliver your proclamation. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120710" who="A11265-halberdier">
          <speaker>Ha.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120720">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120730">This is to give notice to all the King's subjects</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120740"><pb facs="24"/> the late lord Cromwell lord chancellor of England,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120750">Vicar general over the realm,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120760">Him to hold and esteem as a traitor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120770">Against the crown and dignity of England,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120780">So God save the King. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120790" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e120800">Amen.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120810" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120820">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120830">Amen, and root thee from the land,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120840">For whilst thou livest truth cannot stand. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120850" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Nor.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120860">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120870">Make a lane there, the traitors at hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120880">Keep back Cromwell's men,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120890">Drown them if they come on, sergeant your office. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e120900">Enter Cromwell, they make a lane with their halberds.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120910" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120920">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120930">What means my lord of Norfolk by these words,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120940">Sirs come along. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120950" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e120960">Kill them if they come on.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e120970" who="A11265-sergeant">
          <speaker>Sar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e120980">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e120990">Lord Cromwell in King Henry's name,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121000">I do arrest your honour of high treason. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121010" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e121020">Sergeant me of treason.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e121030">Cromwel's men offer to draw.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121040" who="A11265-suffolk">
          <speaker>Suf.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e121050">Kill them if they draw a sword.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121060" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121070">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121080">Hold I charge you, as you love me draw not a sword,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121090">Who dares accuse Cromwell of treason now. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121100" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121110">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121120">This is no place to reckon up your crime,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121130">Your dovelike looks were viewed with serpent's eyes,</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121140" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121150">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121160">With serpent's eyes indeed, by thine they were,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121170">But gardener do thy worst, I fear thee not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121180">My faith compared with thine as much shall pass,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121190">As doth the diamond excel the glass:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121200">Attached of treason, no accusers by,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121210">Indeed what tongue dares speak so soul a lie. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121220" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Nor.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121230">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121240">My lord, my lord, matters are too well known,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121250">And it is time the King had note thereof. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121260" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121270">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121280">The King, let me go to him face to face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121290">No better trial I desire then that,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121300"><pb facs="24"/> let him but say that Cromwell's faith was feigned,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121310">Then let my honour, and my name be stained:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121320">If ever my heart against my King was set,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121330">Oh let my soul in judgement answer it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121340">Then if my faiths confirmed with his reason,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121350">'Gainst whom hath Cromwell then committed treason,</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121360" who="A11265-suffolk">
          <speaker>Suf.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121370">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121380">My lord your matter shall be tried,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121390">Mean time, with patience content yourself. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121400" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121410">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121420">Perforce I must with patience be content,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121430">Oh dear friend Bedford dost thou stand so near,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121440">Cromwell rejoiceth one friend sheds a tear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121450">And whither is't, which way must Cromwell now? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121460" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121470">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121480">My lord you must unto the tower,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121490">Lieutenant take him to your charge. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121500" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121510">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121520">Well where you please, yet before I part,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121530">Let me confer a little with my men. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121540" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e121550">As you go by water so you shall.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121560" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e121570">I have some business present to impart.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121580" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Nor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e121590">You may not stay lieutenant take your charge.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121600" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121610">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121620">Well, well my lord, you second Gardiner's text,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121630">Norfolk farewell, thy turn will be the next. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e121640">Exit Cromwell and the lieutenant.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121650" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e121660">His guilty conscience makes him rave my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121670" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Nor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e121680">I let him talk his time is short enough.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121690" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121700">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121710">My lord of Bedford, come you weep for him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121720">That would not shed half a tear for you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121730" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e121740">It grieves me for to see his sudden fall.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121750" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e121760">Such success wish I to traitors still.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e121770">Exeunt.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e121780">Enter two citizens.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121790" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121800">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121810">Why? can this news be true is't possible,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121820">The great lord Cromwell arrested upon treason,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121830">I hardly will believe it can be so,</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121840" who="A11265-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121850">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121860">It is too true sir, would it were otherwise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121870">Condition I spent half the wealth I had,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121880"><pb facs="25"/> I was at Lambeth, saw him there arrested,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121890">And afterwards committed to the tower. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121900" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e121910">What wast for treason that he was committed?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121920" who="A11265-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121930">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121940">Kind noble gentleman, I may rue the time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121950">All that I have, I did enjoy by him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121960">And if he die, than all my state is gone. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e121970" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e121980">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e121990">It may be doubted that he shall not die,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122000">Because the King did favour him so much. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122010" who="A11265-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e122020">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122030">O sir, you are deceived in thinking so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122040">The grace and favour he had with the King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122050">Hath caused him have so many enemies:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122060">He that in court secure will keep himself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122070">Must not be great, for then he is envied at. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122080">The shrub is safe, whenas the cedar shakes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122090">For where the King doth love above compare,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122100">Of others they as much more envied are. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122110" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e122120">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122130">'Tis pity that this noble man should fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122140">He did so many charitable deeds. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122150" who="A11265-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e122160">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122170">'Tis true, and yet you see in each estate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122180">There's none so good, but some one doth him hate. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122190">And they before would smile him in the face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122200">Will be the foremost to do him disgrace:</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122210">What will you go along unto the court? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122220" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e122230">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122240">I care not if I do, and here the news. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122250">How men will judge what shall become of him. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122260" who="A11265-xxxx_2">
          <speaker>2.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e122270">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122280">Some will speak hardly, some will speak in pity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122290">Go you to the court, I'll unto the city,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122300">There I am sure to hear more news than you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122310" who="A11265-xxxx_1">
          <speaker>1.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e122320">Why then soon will we meet again.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e122330">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e122340">Enter Cromwell in the tower.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122350" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e122360">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122370">Now Cromwell hast thou time to meditate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122380">And think upon thy state, and of the time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122390">Thy honours came unsought, I and unlooked for,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122400">Thy fall as sudden, and unlooked for to,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122410"><pb facs="25"/> what glory was in England that I had not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122420">Who in this land commanded more than Cromwell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122430">Except the King who greater than myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122440">But now I see, what after ages shall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122450">The greater man, more sudden is their fall. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122460">And now I do remember the Earl of Bedford</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122470">Was very desirous for to speak to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122480">And afterwards sent to me a letter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122490">The which I think I have still in my pocket,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122500">Now may I read it, for I now have leisure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122510">And this I take it is. </l>
          </lg>
          <stage xml:id="A11265-e122520">He reads the letter.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A11265-e122530">
            <lg xml:id="A11265-e122540">
              <l xml:id="A11265-e122550">My lord come not this night to Lambeth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A11265-e122560">For if you do, your state is overthrown. </l>
              <l xml:id="A11265-e122570">And much I doubt your life, and if you come:</l>
              <l xml:id="A11265-e122580">Then if you love yourself, stay where you are. </l>
            </lg>
          </stage>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e122590">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122600">O God had I but read this letter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122610">Then had I been free from the lions paw,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122620">Deferring this, to read until tomorrow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122630">I spurned at joy, and did embrace my sorrow. <stage xml:id="A11265-e122640">Enter the lieutenant of the tower and officers.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122650">Now master lieutenant, when's this day of death. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122660" who="A11265-lieutenant">
          <speaker>Lieutenant</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e122670">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122680">Alas my lord would I might never see it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122690">Here are the Dukes of Suffolk and of Norfolk,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122700">Winchester, Bedford, and sir Richard Ratcliffe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122710">With others, but why they come I know not. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122720" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e122730">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122740">No matter wherefore, Cromwell is prepared,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122750">For Gardiner has my state and life ensnared,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122760">Bid them come in, or you shall do them wrong,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122770">For here stands he, whom some thinks lives too long,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122780">Learning kills learning, and instead of ink</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122790">To dip his pen, Cromwel's heart blood doth drink. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A11265-e122800"><pb facs="26"/>Enter all the nobles.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122810" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Norf.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e122820">Good morrow Cromwell, what alone so sad.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122830" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e122840">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122850">One good among you, none of you are bad,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122860">For my part, it best fits me be alone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122870">Sadness with me, not I with any one. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122880">What is the King acquainted with my cause? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122890" who="A11265-norfolk">
          <speaker>Norf.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e122900">We have, and he hath answered us my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122910" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e122920">How, shall I come to speak with him myself?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122930" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e122940">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122950">The King is so advertised of your guilt. </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122960">He will by no means admit you to his presence. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e122970" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Cro.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e122980">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e122990">No way admit me, am I so soon forgotten,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123000">Did he but yesterday embrace my neck,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123010">And said that Cromwell was even half himself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123020">And is his princely ears so much bewitched</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123030">With scandalous ignomy, and slanderous speeches,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123040">That now he doth deny to look on me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123050">Well my lord of Winchester, no doubt but you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123060">Are much in favour with his majesty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123070">Will you bear a letter from me to his grace? </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e123080" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e123090">Pardon me, I'll bear no traitors letters.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e123100" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e123110">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123120">Ha, will you do this kindness then? </l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123130">Tell him by word of mouth, what I shall say to you. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e123140" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e123150">That will I.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e123160" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e123170">But on your honour will you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e123180" who="A11265-gardiner">
          <speaker>Gard.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e123190">I on my honour.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e123200" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e123210">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123220">Bear witness lords,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123230">Tell him when he hath known you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123240">And tried your faith but half so much as mine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123250">He'll find you to be the falsest hearted man</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123260">In England: pray tell him this. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e123270" who="A11265-bedford">
          <speaker>Bed.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A11265-e123280">Be patient good my lord in these extremes.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A11265-e123290" who="A11265-cromwell">
          <speaker>Crom.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A11265-e123300">
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123310">My kind and honourable lord of Bedford,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123320">I know your honour always loved me well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A11265-e123330">But pardon me, this still shall be my theme,</l>
          </lg>
          <gap extent="4" unit="pages" xml:id="A11265-e123340" n="26-a-3350"/>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="26"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A11265"><item xml:id="A11265-cromwell" n="98">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-cromwell</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">98</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-hodge" n="38">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-hodge</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">38</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-gardiner" n="34">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-gardiner</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">34</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-bedford" n="29">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-bedford</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">29</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-bagot" n="23">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-bagot</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">23</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-governor" n="22">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-governor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">22</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-norfolk" n="21">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-norfolk</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">21</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-friskiball" n="20">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-friskiball</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">20</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-banister" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-banister</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-xxxx_1" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-xxxx_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-old_cromwell" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-old_cromwell</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-xxxx_2" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-xxxx_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-suffolk" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-suffolk</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-mrs_banister" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-mrs_banister</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-bowser" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-bowser</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-wolsey" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-wolsey</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A11265-halberdier" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-halberdier</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-messenger" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-seely" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-seely</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-more" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-more</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-hales" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-hales</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-2_witness" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-2_witness</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-chorus" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-chorus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-post" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-post</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-wife" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-wife</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-1_witness" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-1_witness</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-sergeant" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-sergeant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-friar" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-friar</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-citizen" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-citizen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-usher" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-usher</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-lieutenant" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-lieutenant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A11265-both_witnesses" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A11265-both_witnesses</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

