<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Philotas<date type="creation_date">1605</date></title>
        <author>Daniel, Samuel</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Madeline Burg</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A19812_03.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Certaine small poems lately printed with the tragedie of Philotas. Written by Samuel Daniel.</title>
            <author>Daniel, Samuel, 1562-1619.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>110 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99844921</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 6239.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, III, p. 1052.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">9777</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19812</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Certaine small poems lately printed with the tragedie of Philotas. Written by Samuel Daniel.</title>
            <title type="alt">Selections</title>
            <title type="alt">Tragedie of Philotas.</title>
            <author>Daniel, Samuel, 1562-1619.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[224] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by G. Eld for Simon Waterson [and Edward Blount],</publisher>
            <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1605.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-H; A-F.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>H8 and the last two leaves are blank; 1A1,2 are blank except for signature-marks.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>"The tragedie of Philotas" has separate register and title page with imprint: At London printed by G.E. for Simon Waterson and Edward Blount. 1605.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A19812_03-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A19812_03-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A19812_03-e100030">
        <pb facs="66"/>
        <pb facs="66"/>
        <p xml:id="A19812_03-e100040">The tragedy of Philotas.</p>
        <p xml:id="A19812_03-e100050">By Sam: Daniel.</p>
        <p xml:id="A19812_03-e100060">At London printed by G.e. for Simon Waterson and Edward Blount., 1605.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A19812_03-e100070">
        <pb facs="67"/>
        <pb facs="67"/>
        <head>To the prince.</head>
        <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e100080">
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100090">To you most hopeful prince, not as you are</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100100">But as you may be, do I give these lines:</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100110">That when your judgement shall arrive so far,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100120">As t'overlook th'intricate designs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100130">Of uncontented man: you may behold</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100140">With what encounters greatest fortune's close,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100150">What dangers, what attempts, what manifold</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100160">Encumbrances, ambition undergoes:</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100170">How hardly men digest felicity;</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100180">How to th'intemperate, to the prodigal,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100190">To wantonness, and unto luxury</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100200">Many things want, but to ambition all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100210">And you shall find the greatest enemy</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100220">That man can have, is his prosperity. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e100230">
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100240">Here shall you see how men disguise their ends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100250">And plait bad courses under pleasing shows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100260">How well presumption broken ways defends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100270">Which clear-eyed judgement gráuely doth disclose. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100280">Here shall you see how th'easy multitude</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100290">Transported, take the party of distress;</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100300">And only out of passion do conclude,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100310">Not out of judgement; of men's practises. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e100320">
          <pb facs="68"/>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100330">How powers are thought to wrong, that wrongs debar,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100340">And Kings not held in danger, though they are. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100350">These ancient representments of times passed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100360">Tell us that men have, do, and always run</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100370">The self same line of action, and do cast</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100380">Their course alike, and nothing can be done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100390">(Whilst they, their ends, and nature are the same●</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100400">But will be wrought upon the selfsame frame. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e100410">
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100420">This benefit, most noble prince, doth yield</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100430">The sure records of books, in which we find</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100440">The tenure of our state, how it was held</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100450">By all our ancestors, and in what kind</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100460">We hold the same, and likewise how in the end</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100470">This frail possession of felicity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100480">Shall to our late posterity descend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100490">By the same patent of like destiny. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100500">In them we find that nothing can accrue</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100510">To man, and his condition that is new. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e100520">
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100530">And though you have a swannet of your own,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100540">Which on the banks of Douen meditates</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100550">Sweet notes for you, and unto your renown</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100560">The glory of his music dedicates;</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100570">And in a lofty tune is set to sound</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100580">The deep reports of sullen tragedies. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100590">Yet may this last of me be likewise found,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100600">Amongst the vows that others sacrifice</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100610">Unto the hope of you, that you one day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100620">May grace this now neglected harmony:</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100630">Which set unto your glorious actions may</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100640">Record the same to all posterity. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e100650">
          <pb facs="68"/>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100660">Though I the remnant of another time. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100670">Am never like to see that happiness:</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100680">Yet for the zeal that I have born to rhyme,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100690">And to the muses wish that good success</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100700">To others travail, that in better place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100710">And better comfort, they may be encheered</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100720">Who shall deserve, and who shall have the grace</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100730">To have a muse held worthy to be heard. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100740">And know, sweet prince, when you shall come to know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100750">That 'tis not in the power of Kings to raise</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100760">A spirit for verse that is not born thereto:</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100770">Nor are they born in every prince's days. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100780">For late Eliza's reign, gave birth to more</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100790">Than all the Kings of England did before. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e100800">
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100810">And it may be, the genius of that time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100820">Would leave to her the glory in that kind;</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100830">And that the utmost powers of English rhyme,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100840">Should be within her peaceful reign confined. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100850">For since that time, our songs could never thrive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100860">But lain as if for : though in the prime</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100870">Of this new rising season, we did strive</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100880">To bring the best we could unto the time. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e100890">
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100900">And I although among the latter train,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100910">And least of those that sung unto this land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100920">Have born my part, though in an humble strain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100930">And pleased the gentler that did understand:</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100940">And never had my harmless pen at all</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100950">Distained with any loose immodesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100960">Nor ever noted to be touched with gall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100970">To aggravate the worst man's infamy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100980"><pb facs="69"/>But still have done the fairest offices</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e100990">To virtue and the time, yet naught prevails,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101000">And all our labours are without success,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101010">For either favour or our virtue fails. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101020">And therefore since I have out lived the date</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101030">Of former grace, acceptance, and delight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101040">I would my lines late-borne beyond the fate</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101050">Of her spent line, had never come to light. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101060">So had I not been taxed for wishing well</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101070">Nor now mistaken by the censuring stage</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101080">Nor, in my fame and reputation fell. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101090">Which I esteem more than what all the age</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101100">Or th'earth can give. But years hath done this wrong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101110">To make me write too much, and live too long. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e101120">
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101130">And yet I grieve for that unfinished frame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101140">Which thou dear muse didst vow to sacrifice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101150">Unto the bed of peace, and in the same,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101160">Design our happiness to memorize,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101170">Must, as it is remain, though as it is:</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101180">It shall to after times relate my zeal</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101190">To Kings, and unto right, to quietness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101200">And to the union of the commonweal. </l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101210">But this may now, seem a superfluous vow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101220">We have this peace; and thou hast sung enough</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101230">And more than will be heard, and then as good</l>
          <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101240">As not to write, as not be understood. </l>
        </lg>
        <signed xml:id="A19812_03-e101250">Sam: Dan.</signed>
      </div>
      <div type="argument" xml:id="A19812_03-e101260">
        <pb facs="69"/>
        <head>The argument.</head>
        <p xml:id="A19812_03-e101270">Philotas the son of Parmenio,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A19812_03-e101280">Plutarch in the life of alex.</note> was a man of great estimation among the Macedonians, and next unto Alexander held to be the most valiant of the Greeks: patient of travail, exceeding bountiful, and one that loved his men and friends better than any nobleman of the camp: but otherwise noted of vainglory and prodigality, in so much as his father having notice of his carriage, warned him to make himself less than he was, to avoid the envy of the camp, and the dislike of the King, who grew suspicious of him in respect of the greatness of his father,<pb facs="70"/> and his own popularity, and by having intelligence of certain vaunts of his used to Antigona a fair courtesan born in the city of Pidna, with whom being in love, he let fall many brave words, and boasts of a soldier, to advance his own actions and his fathers, terming Alexander at every word the young man. Which speeches Antigona revealing to a companion of hers, were at length brought to Craterus, who with the woman carried them to Alexander, whereby Philotas lay open to all the advantages that might work his overthrow. <note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A19812_03-e101290">Q. Curtius lib. 6.</note>and in the end concealing a conspiracy (Which was revealed unto him) intended against the King, was thereby suspected to have been a party in the plot: but brought before Alexander, he so defended himself, that he obtained his pardon for that time, supped with the King that night, and yet the next day notwithstanding, was arraigned for the same fact, which he stoutly denying, was afterwards put to torture, and then confessed his treason. And indeed Alexander's drawing a pedigree from heaven<pb facs="70"/> with assuming the Persian magnificence; was the cause that withdrew many the hearts of the nobility and people from him, and by the confession of Philotas was that, which gave a purpose to him and his father to have subverted the King as soon as he had established Asia, and freed them from other fears, which being by Ephestion and Craterus, two the most especial councillors of Alexander gravely and providently discerned, was prosecuted in that manner as became their nearness, and dearness with their lord and master, and fitting to the safety of the state, in the case of so great an aspirer: who no doubt, had he not been prevented, (Howsoever popularly in the army it might be otherwise deemed) he had turned the course of 〈…〉 meant upon his father and himself, or else by his embroilments made it a monster of many heads, as it afterwards proved upon the death of Alexander. The chorus consisting of three Grecians, (As of three estates of a kingdom) and one Persian, representing the multitude and body of a people, who vulgarly<pb facs="71"/> according to their affections carried rather with compassion on great men's misfortunes, then with the consideration of the cause, frame their imaginations by that square, and censure what is done.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A19812_03-e101300">
        <pb facs="71"/>
        <head>The names of the actors.</head>
        <list xml:id="A19812_03-e101310">
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101320">Philotas.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101330">Cebalinus.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101340">Chalisthenes.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101350">Polidamas.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101360">Alexander.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101370">Nichomachus.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101380">Ephestion.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101390">Metron.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101400">Craterus.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101410">Thais a courtesan.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101420">Antigone sometimes one of the concubines of Darius. </item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101430">Attarras.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101440">Clitus.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101450">Sostratus.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101460">Perdiccas.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101470">Chorus.</item>
          <item xml:id="A19812_03-e101480">3. Grecians and a Persian.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A19812_03-e101490">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A19812_03-e101500">
        <pb facs="72"/>
        <pb facs="72"/>
        <head>The tragedy of Philotas.</head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A19812_03-e101510">
          <head>Actus i.</head>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="A19812_03-e101520">
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e101530" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e101540">Philotas. Chalisthenes.</stage>
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e101550">Philotas reading his father's letter.</stage>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e101560">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101570">Make thyself less Philotas than thou art? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101580">What means my father thus to write to me? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101590">Less than I am: in what? how can that be? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101600">Must I be then set underneath my heart? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101610">Shall I let go the hold I have of grace</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101620">Gained with so hard adventures of my blood,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101630">And suffer others mount into my place,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101640">And from below, look up to where I stood? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101650">Shall I degrade th'opinion of my worth? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101660">By putting off employment; as undone</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101670">In spirit or grace: whilst other men set forth</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101680">To get that start of action I have won? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101690">As if such men as I, had any place,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101700">To stay betwixt their ruin, and their grace. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101710">Can any go beyond me, but they will</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101720">Go over me, and trample on my state,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101730">And make their fortune good upon my ill,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101740">Whilst fear hath power to wound me worse than hate? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e101750" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <pb facs="73"/>
              <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e101760">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101770">Philotas, you deceive yourself in this,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101780">Your father means not you should yield in place,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101790">But in your popular dependences:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101800">Your entertainments, guifes, and public grace,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101810">That doth in jealous Kings, distaste the peers,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101820">And makes you not the greater but in fears. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e101830" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e101840">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101850">Alas what popular dependences</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101860">Do I retain? can I shake off the zeal</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101870">Of such as do out of their kindnesses</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101880">Follow my fortunes in the commonweal. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e101890" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e101900">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101910">Indeed Philotas therein you say true:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101920">They follow do, your fortunes, and not you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e101930" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101940">Yea but I find their love to me sincere. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e101950" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101960">Even such as to the wolf the fox doth bear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101970">That visits him but to partake his prey,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e101980">And seeing his hopes deceived turns to betray. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e101990" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102000">I know they would if I in danger stood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102010">Run unto me, with hazard of their blood. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102020" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102030">Yea like as men to burning houses run,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102040">Not to lend aid, but to be lookers on. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102050" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102060">But I with bounty, and with gifts have tied</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102070">Their hearts so sure, I know, they will not slide. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102080" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102090">Bounty and gifts lose more than they do find,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102100">Where many look for good, few have their mind:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102110">Each thinks he merits more than than he hath,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102120">And so gifts laid for love do catch men wrath. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102130" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102140">But many merely out of love attend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102150" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102160">Yea, those that love and have no other end:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102170">Think you that men can love you when they know,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102180">You have them not for friendship, but for show. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102190"><pb facs="73"/>And as you are engaged in your affairs,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102200">And have your ends, think, likewise they have theirs. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102210" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102220">But I do truly from my heart affect</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102230">Virtue and worth, where I do find it set:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102240">Besides my foes do force me in effect,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102250">To make my party of opinion great,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102260">And I must arm me thus against their scorns,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102270">Men must be shod, that go among the thorns. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102280" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102290">Ah good Philotas you yourself be guile,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102300">'Tis not the way to quench the fire with oil. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102310">The meek and humble lamb with small ado,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102320">Sucks his own dam, we see, and others too. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102330">In courts men longest live and keep their ranks,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102340">By taking injuries, and giving thanks. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102350" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102360">And is it so? then never are these hairs,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102370">Like to attain that sober hue of grey,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102380">I cannot plaster and disguise m'affaires,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102390">In other colours then my heart doth lay. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102400">Nor can I patiently endure this fond</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102410">And strange proceeding of authority,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102420">That hath engrossed up all into their hand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102430">By idolizing feeble majesty. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102440">And impiously do labour all they can,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102450">To make the King forget he is a man. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102460">Whilst they divide the spoils, and pray of power,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102470">And none at all respect the public good. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102480">Those hands that guard and get us what is our,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102490">The soldiery, engaged to vent their blood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102500">In worse case seem then Pallas old-grown moil,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102510">Th' Athenians fostered at their public cost;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102520"><pb facs="74"/> for these poor souls consumed with tedious toil</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102530">Remain neglected, having done their most. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102540">And nothing shall bring home of all these wars</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102550">But empty age and bodies charged with scars. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102560" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102570">Philotas, all this public care I fear</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102580">Is but some private touch of your dislike. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102590">Who seeing your own designs not stand to square</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102600">With your desires, no others courses like. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102610">The grief you take things are not ordered well,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102620">Is that you feel yourself I fear not well. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102630">But when your fortunes shall stand parallel</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102640">With those you envy now: all will be well. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102650">For you great men, I see are never more</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102660">Your ends attained the same you were before. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102670">You with a finger can point out the stains</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102680">Of others errors now, and now condemn</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102690">The train of state, whilst your desire remains</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102700">Without. But once got in you jump with them,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102710">And interleague ye with iniquity,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102720">And with a like neglect do temporize</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102730">And only serve your own commodity:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102740">Your fortune then views things with other eyes. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102750">For either greatness doth transform the heart. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102760">Int' other shapes of thoughts or certainly</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102770">This vulgar honesty doth dwell apart</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102780">From power, and is some private quality,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102790">Or rather those fair parts which we esteem</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102800">In such as you, are not the same they seem,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102810">You double with yourselves or else with us.</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102820">And therefore now Philotas even as good. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102830"><pb facs="74"/>T'embrace the times, as swell, and do no good. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102840" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102850">Alas Chalisthenes you have not laid</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102860">True level to my nature, but are wide</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102870">From what I am within; all you have said</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102880">Shall never make me of another side</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102890">Then that I am, and I do scorn to climb</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102900">By shaking hands with this unworthy time. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102910" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102920">The time, Philotas then will break thy neck. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102930" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102940">They dare nor, friend, my faith will keep my neck,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102950">My service to the state hath cautioned</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102960">So surely for mine honour, as it shall</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102970">Make good the place my deeds have purchased</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e102980">With danger, in the love, and hearts of all,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e102990" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103000">Those services, will serve as weights to charge</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103010">And press you unto death, if your foot fail</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103020">Never so little underneath your charge</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103030">And will be deemed, donne, for your own avail. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103040">And who have spirits to do the greatest good,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103050">May do most hurt if they remain not good. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e103060" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103070">Tush. They cannot want my service in the state. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e103080" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Ch</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103090">These times want not men to supply the state. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e103100" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103110">I fear not whilst Parmenio's forces stand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e103120" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103130">Water far off quenches not fire near hand. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103140">You may be fair dispatched, ere he can hear</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103150">Or if he heard, before he could be here. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103160">And therefore do not build upon such sand</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103170">It will deceive your hopes, when all is done</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103180">For though you were the minion of the land</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103190">If you break out, be sure you are undone. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103200">When running with the current of the state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103210"><pb facs="75"/> were you the weakest man of men alive</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103220">And in conventions, and in counsel sat</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103230">And did but sleep or nod, yet should you thrive</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103240">These motive spirits are never fit to rise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103250">And 'tis a danger to be held so wise. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e103260" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103270">What call you running with the slate; shall I</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103280">Combine with those that do abuse the slate? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103290">Whose want of judgement, wit and honesty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103300">I am ashamed to see, and seeing hate. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e103310" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103320">Tush, tush, my lord think not of what were fit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103330">The world is governed more by form, than wit. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103340">He that will fret at lords, and at the rain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103350">Is but a fool, and grieves himself in vain. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103360">Cannot you great men suffer others to</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103370">Have part in rule, but must have all to do. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103380">Now good my lord conform you to the rest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103390">Let not your wings be greater than your nest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e103400" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103410">Solus. See how these vain discursive bookmen talk,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103420">Out of those shadows of their airy powers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103430">And do not see how much they must defalk</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103440">Of their accompts, to make them 'gree with ours. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103450">They little know to what necessities,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103460">Our courses stand allied, or how we are,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103470">Engaged in reputation otherwise</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103480">To be ourselves in our particular. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103490">They think we can command our hearts to lie,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103500">Out of their place: and still they preach to us.</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103510">Pack-bearing patience that base property,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103520">And silly guilt of th'all enduring ass.</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103530">But let them talk their fill, it is but wind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103540"><pb facs="75"/> I must sail by the compass of my mind,</l>
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e103550">Enters a messenger.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103560">My lord, the King calls for you come my lord away,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e103570" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103580">Well then I know there's some new stratagem</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103590">In hand, to be consulted on today. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103600">That I am sent for with such speed, to him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103610">Whose youth and fortune cannot brook delay. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103620">But here's a suitor stands t'impeach my haste,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103630">I would I had gone up the privy way:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103640">Whereby we escape th'attending multitude,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103650">Though I confess, that in humanity</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103660">'Tis better to deny, than to delude. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e103670">Enters Cebalinus.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103680">My lord Philotas I am come with news,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103690">Of great importance that concerns us all,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103700">And well hath my good fortune met with you:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103710">Who best can hear, and best discharge my care. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e103720" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103730">Say what it is and praythee friend be brief. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e103740" who="A19812_03-cebalinus">
              <speaker>Ceb.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103750">The case requires your patience good my lord,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103760">And therefore I must crave your ear a while,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e103770" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103780">I cannot now be long from Alexander. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e103790" who="A19812_03-cebalinus">
              <speaker>Ceb.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103800">Nor Alexander will be long with us,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103810">Unless you hear, and therefore know, the news</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103820">I bring, concerns his life; and this it is,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103830">There is one Dymnus here within the camp:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103840">Whose low estate, and high affections</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103850">Seem to have thrust him int' outrageous ways. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103860">This man affecting one Nichomacus</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103870">A youth, my brother, whom one day h'allures</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103880">Int'a temple where being both alone,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103890"><pb facs="76"/> he breaks out in this sort: Nichomacus</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103900">Sweet lovely youth, ah should I not impart</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103910">To thee the deepest secrets of my heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103920">My heart that hath no lock shut against thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103930">Would let it out sometimes unwares of me. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103940">But as it issues from my faithful love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103950">So close it up in thine, and keep it fast:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103960">Swear to be secret dear Nichomacus. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103970">Swear by the sacred godhead of this place</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103980">To keep my council, and I will reveal</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e103990">A matter of the greatest consequence</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104000">That ever man imparted to his friend. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104010">Youth and desire drawn with a love to know,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104020">Swore to be secret, and to keep it close</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104030">When Dymnus tells him, that within three days</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104040">There should b'effected a conspiracy</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104050">On Alexander's person, by his means</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104060">And divers more of the nobility. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104070">To free their labours and redeem them home,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104080">Which when Nichomacus my brother heard:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104090">Is this your tale saith he? O God forbid</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104100">Mine oath should tie my tongue to keep in this. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104110">This ugly sin of treason, which to tell</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104120">Mine oath compels me, faith against my faith</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104130">Must not be kept. My falsehood here is truth</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104140">And I must tell friend or friend not, I'll tell. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104150">Dymnus amazed hearing beyond conceit</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104160">The self-willed youth vow to reveal their plot:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104170">Stands staring on him, drawing back his breath,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104180">Or else his breath confounded with his thoughts</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104190"><pb facs="76"/> busied with death and horror, could not work,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104200">Not having leisure now, to think what was</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104210">But what would be, his fears were run before,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104220">And at misfortune ere she came to him. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104230">At length yet, when his reason had reduced</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104240">His flying thoughts back to some certain stand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104250">Perceiving yet some distance was betwixt</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104260">Death and his fears which gave him time to work,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104270">With his returning spirits he drew his sword,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104280">Puts it t'his own then to my brother's throat,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104290">Then lays it down, then wrings his hands, then kneels. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104300">Then steadfast looks, then takes him in his arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104310">Weeps on his neck, no word, but oh wilt thou? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104320">Wilt thou, be the destruction of us all? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104330">And finding no relenting in the youth. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104340">His misery grew furious and again</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104350">He takes his sword, and swears to sacrifice</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104360">To silence and their cause, his dearest blood. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104370">The boy amazed, seeing no other way,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104380">Was fain to vow, and promise secrecy;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104390">And as if won t'allow and take that part,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104400">Prays him to tell, who were his complices. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104410">Which, though perplexed with grief for what was done,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104420">Yet thinking now t'have gained him to his side,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104430">Dymnus replies: no worse than Loceus,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104440">Demetrius of the privy chamber, and</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104450">Nicanor, Amyntas, and Archelopis,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104460">Drocenus, aphebetus, Luculaus,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104470">Shall be th'associates of Nichomacus. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104480">This when my brother once had understood,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104490"><pb facs="77"/> and after much ado had got away</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104500">He comes and tells me all the whole discourse:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104510">Which here I have related unto you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104520">And here will I attend t'avouch the same,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104530">Or bring my brother to confirm as much. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104540">Whom now I left behind, lest the conspirators</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104550">Seeing him here unusing to this place,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104560">Suspecting t'b' appeached, might shifts away. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e104570" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104580">Well fellow, I have heard thy strange report,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104590">And will find time t'acquaint the King therewith,</l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19812_03-e104600">
            <head>Scaena secunda.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e104610" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e104620">Antigona and Thais.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104630">What can a free estate afford me more</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104640">Than my incaptived fortune doth allow? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104650">Was I beloved, enriched, and graced before? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104660">Am I not loved, enriched, and graced now? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e104670" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104680">Yea, but before thou wert a King's delight. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e104690" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104700">I might be his although he was not mine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e104710" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104720">His greatness made thee greater in men's sight. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e104730" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104740">More great perhaps without, but not within:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104750">My love was then above me, I am now</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104760">Above my love. Darius then had thousands more</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104770">Philotas hath but me as I do know. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104780">Nor none else will he have, and so he swore. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e104790" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104800">Nay then you may believe him, if he swore. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104810">Alas poor soul, she never came to know</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104820">Her liberty, nor lovers perjuries. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e104830" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104840">Stand I not better with a meaner love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104850"><pb facs="77"/> that is alone to me, then with these powers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104860">Who out of all proportion must b'above</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104870">And have us theirs, but they will not be ours. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104880">And Thais although thou be a Grecian,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104890">And I a Persian, do not envy me. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104900">That I embrace the only gallant man</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104910">Persia, or Greece or all the world can see. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104920">Thou, who art entertained and graced by all</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104930">The flower of honour else, do not despise. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104940">That unto me poor captive should befall</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104950">So great a grace in such a worthies eyes. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e104960" who="A19812_03-unassigned">
              <speaker>Tha, Antigona,</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104970">I envy not thy love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104980">But thinks thee blessed t'enjoy him in that sort. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e104990">But tell me truly didst thou ever prove</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105000">Whether he loved in earnest or in sport</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e105010" who="A19812_03-unassigned">
              <speaker>Ant. Thais;</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105020">Let m'a little glory in my grace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105030">Out of the passion of the joy I feel</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105040">And tell thee a secret, but in any case,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105050">As you're a woman do not it reveal. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105060">One day as I was fitting all alone,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105070">In comes Philotas from a victory</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105080">All blood and dust, yet jolly having won</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105090">The glory of the day most gallantly. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105100">And warmed with honour of his good success. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105110">Relates to me the dangers he was in:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105120">Whereat I wondering, blamed his forwardness. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105130">Faith wench, says he, thus must we fight, toil, win. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105140">To make that young man proud, thus is he born:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105150">Upon the wings of our desserts, our blood</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105160">Sets him above himself and makes him scorn,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105170"><pb facs="78"/> his own, his country, and the authors of his good. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105180">My father was the first that out from Greece</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105190">Showed him the way of Asia, set him on</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105200">And by his project raised the greatest piece</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105210">Of this proud work which now he treads upon. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105220">Parmenio without Alexander much hath wrought,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105230">Without Parmenio, Alexander hath done naught. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105240">But let him use his fortune whilst he may,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105250">Times have their change, we must not still be led. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105260">And sweet Antigona thou mayst one day</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105270">Yet, bless the hour t'have known Philotas' bed. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105280">Wherewith he sweetly kissed me, and now deem,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105290">If that so great, so wise, so rare a man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105300">Would if he held me not in dear esteem</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105310">Have uttered this t'a captive Persian. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105320">But Thais I may no longer stay, for fear</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105330">My lord return, and find me not within,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105340">Whose eyes yet never saw me anywhere </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105350">But in his chamber where I should have been. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105360">And therefore Thais farewell. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e105370" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Th.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105380">Fare well Antigona. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105390">Now have I that which I desired long</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105400">Laid in my lap by this fond woman here,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105410">And means t'avenge me of a secret wrong</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105420">That doth concern my reputation near. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105430">This gallant man, whom this fool in this wise</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105440">Vaunts to be hers, I must confess t'have loved</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105450">And used all th'engines of these conquering eyes</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105460">Affections in his high-built heart t'have moved</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105470">Yet never could: for what my labour seeks</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105480"><pb facs="78"/> I see is lost upon vain ignorance. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105490">Whilst he that is the glory of the Greeks</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105500">Virtues upholder, honour's countenance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105510">Out of this garnish of his worthy parts</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105520">Is fallen upon this foolish Persian,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105530">To whom his secrets gravely he imparts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105540">Which she as wisely keep and govern can:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105550">'Tis strange to see the humour of these men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105560">These great aspiring spirits that should be wise</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105570">We women shall know all; for now and then</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105580">Out of the humour of their jollities</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105590">The smoke of their ambition must have vent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105600">And out it comes what racks should not reveal,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105610">For this her humour hath so much of wind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105620">That it will burst itself if too close pent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105630">And none more fit than us their wisdoms find,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105640">Who will for love or want of wit conceal. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105650">For being the nature of great spirits, to love</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105660">To be, where they may be most eminent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105670">And rating of themselves so far above</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105680">Us in conceit with whom they do frequent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105690">Imagine how we wonder and esteem</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105700">All that they do or say, which makes them strive</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105710">To make our admiration more extreme:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105720">Which they suppose they cannot, less they give</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105730">Notice of their extreme and highest thoughts. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105740">And then th'opinion that we love them too,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105750">Beggars a confidence of secrecy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105760">Whereby whatever they intend to do,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105770">We shall be sure to know it presently. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105780"><pb facs="79"/>But faith, I scorn that such a one as she,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105790">A silly witted wench, should have this grace</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105800">To be preferred and honoured before me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105810">Having but only beauty, and a face. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105820">I that was ever courted by the great</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105830">And gallantest peers and princes of the East,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105840">Whom Alexander in the greatest state</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105850">The earth did ever see him, made his guest. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105860">There where this tongue obtained for her merit</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105870">Eternity of fame: there where these hands</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105880">Did write in fire the glory of my spirit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105890">And set a trophy that for ever stands. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105900">Thais' action with the Grecian acts shall be</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105910">Enregistered alike. Thaeis she that fired</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105920">The stateliest palace th'earth did ever see,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105930">Darius' house that to the clouds aspired,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105940">She is put back behind Antigona,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105950">But soon Philotas shall his error see,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105960">Who thinks that beauty best, men's passions fits,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105970">For that they use our bodies, not our wits:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105980">And unto Craterus will I presently,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e105990">And him acquaint with all this whose discourse,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106000">Who I am sure will take it well of us,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106010">For these great minions, who with envious eye</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106020">Look on each others greatness, will be glad,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106030">In such a case of this importancy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106040">To have th'advantage that may here be had. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e106050" who="A19812_03-chorus">
              <pb facs="79"/>
              <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106060">We as the chorus of the vulgar stand</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106070">Spectators here, to see these great men play</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106080">Their parts both of obedience and command,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106090">And censure all they do, and all they say. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106100">For though we be esteemed but ignorant,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106110">Yet are we capable of truth, and know</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106120">Where they do well, and where their actions want</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106130">The grace that makes them prove the best in show. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106140">And though we know not, what they do within,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106150">Where they attire, their mysteries of state:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106160">Yet know we by th'events, what plots have been,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106170">And how they all without do personate. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106180">We see who well a meaner part became,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106190">Fail in a greater and disgrace the same. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106200">We see some worthy of advancement deemed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106210">Save when they have it: some again have got</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106220">Good reputation, and been well esteemed</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106230">In place of greatness, which before were not. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106240">We see affliction act a better scene,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106250">Then prosperous fortune which hath marred it clean. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106260">We see that all which we have praised in some,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106270">Have only been their fortune, not desert:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106280">Some war have graced, whom peace doth ill become:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106290">And lustful ease hath blemished all their part. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106300">We see Philotas acts his goodness ill,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106310">And makes his passions to report of him</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106320"><pb facs="80"/> worse than he is: and we do fear he will</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106330">Bring his free nature to b'entrapped by them. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106340">For sure there is some engine closely laid</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106350">Against his grace and greatness with the King:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106360">And that unless his humours prove more stayed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106370">We soon shall see his utter ruining. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106380">And his affliction, our compassion draws,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106390">Which still looks on men's fortunes, not the cause,</l>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A19812_03-e106400">
          <head>Actus 2.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A19812_03-e106410">
            <head>Scaena 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e106420">Alexander, Ephestion, Craterus.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e106430" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Alexander.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106440">Ephestion, thou dost Alexander love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106450">Craterus thou the King: yet both you meet</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106460">In one self point of loyalty and love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106470">And both I find like careful, like discreet. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106480">Therefore my faithfulst counsellors to you</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106490">I must a weighty accident impart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106500">Which lies so heavy, as I tell you true</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106510">I find the burden much t'oppress my heart. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106520">Ingratitude and stubborn carriage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106530">In one of whom my love deserved respect,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106540">Is that which moves my passion into rage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106550">And is a thing, I ought not to neglect. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106560">You see how I Philotas raised have</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106570">Above his rank, his peers, beyond his term:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106580">You see the place, the offices I gave,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106590"><pb facs="80"/> as th'earnest of my love to bind his firm. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106600">But all, he deeming rather his deserts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106610">Than the effects of my grace any way,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106620">Begins to play most peremptory parts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106630">As fitter to control then to obey. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106640">And I have been informed, he fosters too,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106650">The faction of that home-bent cowardice,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106660">That would run back from glory, and undo</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106670">All the whole wonder of our enterprise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106680">And one day to ourself presumes to write,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106690">(Seeming our stile and title to upbraid,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106700">Which th'oracles themselves held requisite</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106710">And which not I, but men on me have laid)</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106720">And said he pitied those who under him should live. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106730">Who held himself the son of Jupiter. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106740">Alas good man, as though what breath could give,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106750">Could make mine own thoughts other than they are. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106760">I that am arbiter betwixt my heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106770">And their opinion, know how it stands within,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106780">And find that my infirmities take part,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106790">Of that same frailty, other men live in. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106800">And yet what if I were disposed to wink,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106810">At th'entertained opinion spread so far. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106820">And rather was content the world should think. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106830">Us other than we are, then what we are. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106840">In doing which, I know I am not gone</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106850">Beyond example, seeing that majesty</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106860">Needs all the props of admiration</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106870">That may be got to bear it up on high. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106880">And much more mine, which but e'en now begun</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106890"><pb facs="81"/> by miracles of fortune, and our worth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106900">Needs all the compliments to rest upon:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106910">That reverence and opinion can bring forth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106920">Which this wise man conceives not, and yet takes:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106930">Upon him to instruct us what to do. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106940">But these are but the flourishes he makes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106950">Of greater malice he is bent unto:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106960">For sure methinks I view within his face,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106970">The map of change and innovation:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106980">I see his pride contented with no place,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e106990">Unless it be the throne I sit upon. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e107000" who="A19812_03-ephestion">
              <speaker>Eph</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107010">Had I not heard this from your sacred tongue,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107020">Dear sovereign, I would never have believed</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107030">Philotas folly would have done that wrong</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107040">T'his own worth, and th'honours he received,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107050">And yet methought of late his carriage. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107060">In such exceeding pomp and gallantry,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107070">And such a world of followers; did presage</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107080">That he affected popularity. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107090">Especially since for his service done. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107100">He was adjudged to have the second place</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107110">In honour with Antigonus, which won,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107120">To some th'opinion to be high in grace. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107130">Then this last action leading the right wing,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107140">And th'overthrow he gave, might hap enlarge</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107150">Th'opinion of himself considering,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107160">Th'especial grace and honour of his charge. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107170">Whereby perhaps in rating his own worth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107180">His pride might undervalue that great grace:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107190">From whence it grew, and that which put him forth. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107200"><pb facs="81"/>And made his fortune suiting to the place. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107210">But yet I think he is not so unwise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107220">Although his fortune, youth and jollity. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107230">Makes him thus mad, as he will enterprise</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107240">Ought against course, his faith, and loyalty. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107250">And therefore if your grace did but withdraw,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107260">Those beams of favour which do daze his wants:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107270">He would be soon reduced t'his rank of awe. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107280">And know himself, and bear him as befits. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e107290" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107300">Withdraw our grace, and how can that be done. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107310">Without some sollevation to ensue. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107320">Can he be safe brought in being so far gone,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107330">I hold it not. Say Craterus what think you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e107340" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107350">Sovereign. I know the man, I find his spirit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107360">And malice shall not make me I protest. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107370">Speak other than I know his pride doth merit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107380">And what I speak is for your interest. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107390">Which long ere this I would have uttered,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107400">But that I feared your majesty would take,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107410">That from some private grudge it rather bred,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107420">Then out of care for your dear sister's sake. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107430">Or rather that I sought to cross your grace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107440">Or to confine your favour within bounds,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107450">And finding him to hold so high a place:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107460">In that divine conceit which ours confounds,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107470">I thought the safest way to let it rest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107480">In hope that time some passage open would:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107490">To let in those clear looks into that breast</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107500">That doth but malice and confusion hold. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107510">And now I see you have discerned the man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107520"><pb facs="82"/> whom I protest I hold most dangerous. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107530">And that you ought with all the speed you can</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107540">Work to repress a spirit so mutinous:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107550">For e'en already he is swollen so high,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107560">That his affections overflow the brim</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107570">Of his own powers, not able to deny</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107580">Passage unto the thoughts that govern him. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107590">For but even now I heard a strange report</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107600">Of speeches he should use t'his courtesan:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107610">Vaunting what he had done, and in what sort,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107620">He laboured to advance that proud young man. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107630">(So terming of your sacred majesty)</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107640">With other such extravagant discourse:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107650">Whereof we shall attain more certainty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107660">I doubt not shortly and descry his course,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107670">Meanwhile about your person I advise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107680">Your grace should● all ● more sufficient guard:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107690">And on his actions set such wary eyes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107700">As may thereof take special good regard. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107710">And note what persons chiefly he frequents:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107720">And who to him have the most free access,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107730">How he bestows his time, where he presents,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107740">The large revenue of his bounteousness. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107750">And for his wench that lies betwixt his arms. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107760">And knows his hare I will about with her,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107770">She shall be wrought t'apply her usual charms:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107780">And I will make her my discoverer. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107790">Alex. This counsel Craterus we do well allow,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107800">And give thee many thanks for thy great care. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107810">But yet we must bear fair, lest he should know,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107820"><pb facs="82"/> that we suspect what his affections are,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107830">For that you see he holds aside of power:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107840">Which might perhaps call up some mutiny. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107850">His father old Parmenio at this hour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107860">Rules Medea with no lesser powers than I. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107870">Himself you see gallantly followed:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107880">Holds next to us a special government:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107890">Canus that with his sister married,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107900">Hath under him again commandment:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107910">Amintas and Symanus his dear friends</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107920">With both their honourable offices. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107930">And then the private train that on them tends,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107940">With all particular dependences. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107950">Are motives to advice us how to deal. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107960">Crat. Your grace says true, but yet these clouds of smoke</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107970">Vanish before the sun of that respect</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107980">Whereon men's long-inured affections look</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e107990">With such a native zeal, and so affect:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108000">As that the vain and shallow practises,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108010">Of no such giddy traitor (If the thing,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108020">Be taken in time with due advisedness:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108030">Shall the least show of any feeling bring. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108040">Alex, well then to thee dear Craterus I refer,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108050">Th'especial care of this great business. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19812_03-e108060">
            <pb facs="83"/>
            <head>Scaena 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e108070">Philotas, Ceballinus, Servius.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e108080" who="A19812_03-cebalinus">
              <speaker>Ceb.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108090">My lord. I here have long attendance made</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108100">Expecting to be called t'avouch my news</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e108110" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108120">In troth my friend I have not found the Kings</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108130">At any leisure yet to hear the same. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e108140" who="A19812_03-cebalinus">
              <speaker>Ceb.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108150">No not at leisure to prevent his death? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108160">And is the matter of no more import? </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108170">I'll try another. Yet methinks such men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108180">As are the eyes and ears of princes, should,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108190">Not weigh so light such an intelligence</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e108200" who="A19812_03-servant">
              <speaker>Servant</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108210">My lord the sum you willed me to give,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108220">The captain that did visit you today:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108230">To tell you plain your coffers yield it not,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e108240" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108250">How, if they yield it not, have I not then,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108260">Apparel, plate jewels; why sell them:<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A19812_03-e108270">Plutarch in the life of Alexander.</note></l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108280">And go your way dispatch and give it him. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108290">Methinks I find the King much changed of late,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108300">And unto me his graces not so great. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108310">Although they seem in show all of one rate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108320">Yet by the touch I find them counterfeit</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108330">For when I speak, although I have his ear</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108340">Yet do I see his mind is other where. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108350">And when he speaks to me I see he strives,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108360">To give a colour unto what is not,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108370">For he must think that we whose states, whose lives. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108380">Depend upon his grace learn not by rote,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108390"><pb facs="83"/> t'observe his actions, and to know his trim,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108400">And though indeed princes be manifold,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108410">Yet have they still such eyes to wait on them. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108420">As are to piercing that they can behold. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108430">And penetrate the innards of the heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108440">That no device can set so close a door,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108450">Betwixt their shows and thoughts, but that their art:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108460">Of shadowing it, makes it appear the more. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108470">But many malicing my state of grace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108480">I know do work, with all the powers they have</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108490">Upon that easy nature, to displace</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108500">My fortunes, and my actions to deprave:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108510">And though I know they seek t'enclose him in,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108520">And fain would lock him up and chamber him:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108530">Yet will I never stoop and seek to win</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108540">My way by them, that came not in by them. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108550">And scorn to stand on any other feet</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108560">Then these of mine own worth; and what my plain</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108570">And open actions cannot fairly get</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108580">Baseness and soothing them shall never gain. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108590">And yet, I know my presence and access,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108600">Clears all these mists which they have raised before:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108610">Though with my back straight turns that happiness. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108620">And they again blow up as much or more;</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108630">Thus do we role the stone of our own toil,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108640">And men suppose our hell, a heaven the while. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A19812_03-e108650">
            <pb facs="84"/>
            <head>Scaena 3.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e108660" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e108670">Craterus. Antigona.</stage>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e108680">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108690">Antigona, there is no remedy,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108700">You needs must justify the speech you held,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108710">With Thais, who will your conference verify,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108720">And therefore now it cannot be concealed. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e108730" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Anti.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e108740">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108750">O my good lord I pray you urge me not,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108760">Thais only of a cunning envious wit,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108770">Scorning a stranger should have such allot,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108780">Hath out of her invention forged it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e108790" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e108800">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108810">Why then shall racks and tortures force thee show,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108820">Both this and other matters which we know. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108830">Think therefore if 'twere not a wiser part,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108840">T'accept of rest, rewards, preferment, grace,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108850">And being perhaps so beauteous as thou art,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108860">Of fair election for a nearer place,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108870">To tell the truth, than to be obstinate,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108880">And fall with the misfortune of a man●</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108890">Who in his dangerous and concussed state,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108900">No good to thee but ruin render can●</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108910">Resolve thee of this choice, and let me know</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108920">Thy mind at full, at my returning back. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e108930" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e108940">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108950">What shall I do, shall I betray my love,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108960">Or die disgraced? what do I make a doubt</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108970">Betray my love? O heavenly powers above</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108980">Forbid that such a thought should issue out</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e108990">Of this confused breast: nay rather first</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109000">Let tortures, death, and horror do their worst. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109010"><pb facs="84"/>But out alas this inconsiderate tongue,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109020">Without my hart● consent and privity,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109030">Hath done already this unwilling wrong,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109040">And now it is no wisdom to deny. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109050">No wisdom to deny? yes, yes, that tongue</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109060">That thus hath been the traitor to my heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109070">Shall either powerfully redeem that wrong,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109080">Or never more shall words of breath impart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109090">Yet what can my denial profit him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109100">Whom they perhaps whether I tell or not,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109110">Are purposed upon matters known to them,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109120">To ruinate on some discovered plot. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109130">Let them do what they will. Let not thy heart</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109140">Seem to be accessary in a thought,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109150">To give the left advantage of thy part,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109160">To have a part of shame in what is wrought. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109170">O this were well, if that my dangers could</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109180">Redeem his peril, and his grace restore,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109190">For which, I vow, my life I render would,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109200">If this poor life could satisfy therefore. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109210">But 'tis not for thy honour to forsake</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109220">Thy love for death, that loved thee in this sort,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109230">Alas what notice will the world take</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109240">Of such respects in women of my sort. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109250">This act may yet put on so fair a coat</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109260">Upon my foul profession, as it may</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109270">Not blush t'appear with those of cleanest note,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109280">And have as high a place with fame as they. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109290">What do I talk of fame? do I not see</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109300">This faction of my flesh, my fears, my youth</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109310"><pb facs="85"/> already entered and have bent at me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109320">The joys of life to batter down my truth. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109330">O my subdued thoughts what have you done. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109340">To let in fear and falsehood, to my heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109350">Whom though they have surprised they have not won,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109360">For still my love shall hold the dearest part. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e109370" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Crat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109380">Antigona what are you yet resolved. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e109390" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109400">Resolved my lord t'indure all misery. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e109410" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Crat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109420">And so be sure you shall if that b'your choice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e109430" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109440">What will you have me do my lord, I am</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109450">Content to say what you will have me say. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e109460" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Crat.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109470">Then come go with me to Alexander. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e109480" who="A19812_03-chorus">
              <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e109490">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109500">How dost thou wear, and weary out thy days,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109510">Restless ambition never at an end:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109520">Whose travails no Herculean pillar stays</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109530">But still beyond thy rest thy labours tend. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109540">Above good fortune, thou thy hopes dost raise. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109550">Still climbing and yet never canst ascend:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109560">For when thou hast attained unto the top,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109570">Of thy desires thou hast not yet got up. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109580">That heigh of fortune either is controlled. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109590">By some more powerful overlooking eye:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109600">(That doth the fullness of thy grace withhold)</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109610">Or counterchecked with some concurrency:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109620">That it doth cost far more ado to hold,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109630"><pb facs="85"/> the high attained, then was to get so high. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109640">Where stand thou canst not, but with careful toil,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109650">Nor lose thy hold without thy utter spoil. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109660">There dost thou struggle with thine own distrust,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109670">And others jealousies, their counterplot:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109680">Against some underworking pride that must,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109690">Supplanted be, or else thou standest not:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109700">There wrong is paid with wrong, and he that thrust:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109710">Down others, comes himself to have that lot. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109720">The same concussion doth afflict his breast. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109730">That others shook, oppression is oppressed</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109740">That either happiness dwells not so high,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109750">Or else above. whereto pride cannot rise:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109760">And that the highest of man's felicity,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109770">But in the region of affliction lies:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109780">And that we climb but up to misery,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109790">High fortunes are but high calamities,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109800">It is not in that sphere, where peace doth move,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109810">Rest dwells below it, happiness above. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109820">For in this height of fortune are imbred,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109830">Those thundering fragors that affright the earth. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109840">From thence have all distemperatures their head:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109850">That brings forth desolation, famine, dearth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109860">There certain order is disordered:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109870">And there it is confusion hath her birth. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109880">It is that high of fortune doth undo,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109890">Both her own quietness and others too. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A19812_03-e109900">
          <pb facs="86"/>
          <head>Actus tertius.</head>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="A19812_03-e109910">
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e109920" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e109930">Alex. Metron. Ceballinus. Craterus Perdiccas, Ephest,</stage>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e109940">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109950">Come, Metron say of whom hast thou received,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109960">Th'intelligence of this conspiracy:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109970">Contrived against our person, as thou sayest,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109980">By Dymnus and some other of the camp,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e109990">Is't not some vain report born without cause,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110000">That envy or imagination draws</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110010">From private ends to breed a public fear. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110020">T'amuse the world with things that never were,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110030" who="A19812_03-metron">
              <speaker>Met.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110040">Here may it please your highness is the man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110050">One Ceballinus that brought me the news. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110060" who="A19812_03-cebalinus">
              <speaker>Ceb.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110070">O Alexander I have saved thy life. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110080">I am the man that hath revealed their plot. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110090" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110100">And how cam'st thou to be informed thereof,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110110" who="A19812_03-cebalinus">
              <speaker>Ceb.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110120">By mine own brother, one Nichomacus,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110130">Whom Dymnus chief of the conspirators,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110140">Acquainted with the whole of their intents,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110150" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110160">How long since is it, this was told to thee? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110170" who="A19812_03-cebalinus">
              <speaker>Ceb.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110180">About some three days, my sovereign lord. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110190" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110200">What three days since? and hast thou so long kept</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110210">The thing concealed from us being of that weight. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110220">Guard, take and lay him presently in hold:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110230" who="A19812_03-cebalinus">
              <speaker>Ceb.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e110240">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110250">O may it please your grace I did not keep,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110260">The thing concealed one hour, but presently,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110270">Ran to acquaint Philotas therewithal,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110280"><pb facs="86"/> supposing him a man so near in place,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110290">Would best respect a case that touched so near</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110300">And on him have I waited these two days. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110310">Expecting t'have been brought unto your grace,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110320">And seeing him weigh it light, pretending that</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110330">Your grace's leisure served not fit to hear. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110340">Ay, to the master of your armoury,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110350">Addressed myself forthwith, to Metron here,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110360">Who without making any more delay,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110370">Pressed in unto your grace being in your bath,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110380">Locking me up the while in th'armory,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110390">And all what I could show revealed hath. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110400" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e110410">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110420">If this be so then, fellow I confess,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110430">Thy loyal care of us was more than theirs,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110440">Who had more reason theirs should have been more,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110450">Cause Dymnus to be presently brought forth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110460">And call Philotas straight, who now I see</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110470">Hath not deceived me, in deceiving me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110480">Who would have thought one whom I held so near. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110490">Would from my safety have been so far off,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110500">When most it should and ought import his care,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110510">And wherein his allegiance might make proof</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110520">Of those effects my favours had deserved,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110530">And ought t'have claimed more duly at his hands</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110540">Then any of the rest. But thus we're served. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110550">When private grace out of proportion stands</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110560">And that we call up men from of below:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110570">From th'element of baser property,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110580">And set them where they may behold and know</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110590">The way of might and work of majesty. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110600"><pb facs="87"/>Where seeing those rays, which being sent far off,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110610">Reflect a heat of wonder and respect,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110620">To fail near hand and not to show that proof,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110630">(The object only working that effect,)</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110640">Think seeing themselves (Though by our favour) set. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110650">Within the self same orb of rule with us,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110660">Their light would shine alone if ours were set,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110670">And so presume t'obscure or shadow us.</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110680">But he shall know although his nearness hath,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110690">Not felt our heat that we can burn him too. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110700">And grace that shines can kindle unto wrath:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110710">And Alexander and the King are two. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110720">But here they bring us Dymnus in whose face,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110730">I see is gilt, despair, horror and death. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110740" who="A19812_03-guard">
              <speaker>Guard</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e110750">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110760">Yea death indeed, for ere he could b'attached. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110770">He stabbed himself so deadly to the heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110780">As 'tis impossible that he should live. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110790" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Al.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e110800">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110810">Say Dymnus what have I deserved of thee:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110820">That thou shouldst think worthier to be thy King,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110830">Philotas then ourself. Hold hold he sinks:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110840">Guard keep him up get him to answer us. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110850" who="A19812_03-guard">
              <speaker>Guard</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110860">H'hath spoken his last he'll never answer more▪</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e110870" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Al.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e110880">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110890">Sorry I am for that, for now hath death,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110900">Shut us clean out from knowing him within:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110910">And locked up in his breast all th'other's harts,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110920">But yet this deed argues the truth in gross,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110930">Though we be barred it in particular. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110940">Philotas? are you come look here this man,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110950">This Ceballinus should have suffered death:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110960">Could it but have been proved he had concealed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110970"><pb facs="87"/> th'intended treason from us these two days,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110980">Wherewith he says he straight acquainted thee:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e110990">Think the more near thou art about ourself,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111000">The greater is the shame of thine offence. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111010">And which had been less foul in him then thee. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e111020" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e111030">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111040">Renowned prince, for that my heart is clear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111050">Amazement cannot overcast my face,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111060">And I must boldly with th'assured cheer,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111070">Of my unguilty conscience tell your grace:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111080">That this offence (Thus happening) was not made,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111090">By any the least thought of ill in me:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111100">And that the keeping of it unbewrayed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111110">Was that I held the rumor vain to be. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111120">Considering some who were accused were known,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111130">Your ancient and most loyal servitors:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111140">And such as rather would let out their own:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111150">Heart blood I know then once endanger yours,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111160">And for me then upon no certain note,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111170">But on the brabble, of two wanton youths,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111180">T'have told an idle tale, that would have wrought,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111190">In your distrust, and wrong to others' truths,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111200">And to no end but only to have made,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111210">Myself a scorn and odious unto all. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111220">(For which I rather took the bait was laid:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111230">Then else for any treachery at all.) </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111240">I must confess I thought the safest way,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111250">To smother it a while, to th' end I might:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111260">If such a thing could be, some proofs bewray,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111270">That might yield probability of right. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111280">Protesting that mine own unspotted thought. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111290"><pb facs="88"/>A like belief of others truth did breed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111300">Judging no impious wretch could have been wrought</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111310">T'imagine such a detestable deed. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e111320">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111330">And therefore oh dread sovereign do not way</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111340">Philotas faith by this his oversight. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111350">But by his actions past, and only lay</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111360">Error t'his charge, not malice not despite. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e111370" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Al.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e111380">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111390">Well, lo thou hast a favourable judge,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111400">When though thou hast not power to clear thy blame,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111410">Yet hath he power to pardon thee the same,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111420">Which take not as thy right but as his grace,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111430">Since here the person alters not the case. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111440">And here Philotas, I forgive th'offence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111450">And to confirm the same, lo here's my hand. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e111460" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111470">O sacred hand the witness of my life,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111480">By thee I hold my safety as secure,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111490">As is my conscience free from treachery. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e111500" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111510">Well gotten your charge, and look to our affairs,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111520">For we tomorrow purpose to remove. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e111530">Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e111540" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e111550">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111560">In troth I know not what to judge herein,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111570">Methinks the man seems surely clear in this,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111580">However otherwise his hopes have been,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111590">Transported by his unadvisedness:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111600">It cannot be, a guilty conscience should</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111610">Put on so sure a brow, or else by art</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111620">His looks stand neutral, seeming not to hold</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111630">Respondency of interest with his heart. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111640">Sure for my part, he hath dissolved the knot</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111650">Of my suspicion, with so clear a hand,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111660">As that I think in this ( whatever plot</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111670"><pb facs="88"/> of mischief it may be) he hath no hand</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e111680" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Crat.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e111690">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111700">My lord, the greater confidence he shows,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111710">Who is suspected should be feared the more:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111720">For danger from weak natures never grows,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111730">Who must disturb the world are built therefore. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111740">He more is to be feared that nothing fears,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111750">And malice most effects, that least appears. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111760">Presumption of men's powers as well may breed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111770">Assuredness, as innocency may:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111780">And mischief seldom but by trust doth speed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111790">Who Kings betray, first their belief betray. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111800">I would your grace had first conferred with us</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111810">Since you would needs such clemency have shown. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111820">That we might yet but have advised you thus,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111830">That he his danger never might have known. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111840">In faults wherein an after shame will live. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111850">'Tis better to conceal then to forgive. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111860">For who are brought unto the block of death,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111870">Think rather on the peril they have passed:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111880">Then on that grace which hath preserved their breath,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111890">And more their sufferings then their mercy taste,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111900">He now to plot your danger still may live. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111910">But you his guilt not always to forgive. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e111920">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111930">Know that a man so swollen with discontent,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111940">No grace can cure nor pardon can restore:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111950">He knows how those who once have mercy spent,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111960">Can never hope to have it any more. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e111970">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111980">But say that through remorse he calmer prove,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e111990">Will great Parmenio so attended on,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112000">With that brave army fostered in his love:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112010"><pb facs="89"/> be thankful for this grace you do his son▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112020">Some benefits are odious, so is this:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112030">Where men are still ashamed to confess,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112040">To have so done as to deserve to die:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112050">And ever do desire that men should guess,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112060">They rather had received an injury,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112070">Than life, since life they know in such a case,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112080">May be restored to all but not to grace. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e112090" who="A19812_03-perdicas">
              <speaker>Perd.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e112100">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112110">And for my part my liege I hold this mind</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112120">That sure he would not have so much suppressed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112130">The notice of a treason in that kind,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112140">Unless he were a party with the rest:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112150">Can it be thought that great Parmenios' son,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112160">The general commander of the horse:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112170">The minion of the camp the only one,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112180">Of secret counsel, and of free recourse</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112190">Should not in three days' space have found the King,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112200">At leisure t'hear three words of that import:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112210">Whilst he himself in idle lavishing,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112220">Did thousands spend t'advance his own report? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e112230" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e112240">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112250">And if he gave no credit to the youth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112260">Why did he two days space delay him then? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112270">As if he had believed it for a truth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112280">To hinder his address to other men:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112290">If he had held it but a vain conceit,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112300">I pray why had he not dismissed him straight? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112310">Men in their private dangers may be stout:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112320">But in th'occasions and the fears of Kings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112330">We ought not to be credulous, but doubt,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112340">The intimation of the vainest things. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e112350" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <pb facs="89"/>
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e112360">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112370">Well howsoever, we will yet this night,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112380">Disport and banquet in unusual wise. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112390">That it may seem we weigh this practice light,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112400">However heavy, here within it lies. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112410">King's may not know distrust, and though they fear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112420">They must not take acquaintance of their fear. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19812_03-e112430">
            <head>Scaena 2.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e112440" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e112450">Antigona. Thais.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112460">O you're a secret council-keeper Thais,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112470">In troth I little thought you such a one:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e112480" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112490">And why Antigona what have I done. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e112500" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112510">You know ful well your conscience you bewrays,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e112520" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e112530">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112540">Alas good soul would you have me conceal:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112550">That which yourself could not but needs reveal? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112560">Think you another can be more to you,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112570">In what concerns them not, than you can be,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112580">Whom it imports? Will others hold them true:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112590">When you prove false to your own secrecy? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112600">But yet this is no wonder for we see,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112610">Wiser than we do lay their heads to gauge:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112620">For riotous expenses of their tongues</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112630">Although it be a property belongs,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112640">Especially to us and every age,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112650">Can show strange presidents what we have been,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112660">In cases of the greatest plots of men. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112670">And 'tis the scene on this world's stage we play,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112680"><pb facs="90"/> whose revolution, we with men convert,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112690">And are to act our part as well as they:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112700">Though commonly the weakest, yet apart. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e112710">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112720">For this great motion of a state we see,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112730">Doth turn on many wheels and some though small</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112740">Do yet the greater move, who in degree. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112750">Stir those who likewise turn the greatest of all. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112760">For though we are not wise, we see the wise</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112770">By us are made or make us parties still,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112780">In actions of the greatest qualities</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112790">That they can manage, be they good or ill. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e112800" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e112810">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112820">I cannot tell; but you have made me do,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112830">That which must ever more afflict my heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112840">And if this be my woeful part t'undo,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112850">My dearest love, would I had had no part. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112860">How have I seely woman sifted been</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112870">Examined, tried, flattered, terrified,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112880">By Craterus the cunningest of men,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112890">That never left me till I had descried</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112900">Whatever of Philotas I had known. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e112910" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Tha.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112920">What is that all? perhaps I have thereby</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112930">Done thee more good than thou canst apprehend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e112940" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112950">Such good I rather you should get than I. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112960">If that can be a good t'accuse my friend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e112970" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Th.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112980">Alas thy accusation did but quote</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e112990">The margin of some text of greater note. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113000" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113010">But that is more than thou or I can tell. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113020" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Th.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e113030">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113040">Yes yes Antigona I know it well. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113050">For be thou sure that always those who seek</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113060">T'attack the lion, so provide that still,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113070"><pb facs="90"/> their toils be such as that he shall not scape. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113080">To turn his rage on those that wrought his ill. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113090">Philotas neither was so strong nor high</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113100">But malice overlooked him, and descried,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113110">Where he lay weak, where was his vanity,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113120">And built her countermounts upon that side,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113130">In such sort as they would be sure to raze</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113140">His fortunes with the engines of disgrace. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113150">And now mayst thou perhaps come great hereby,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113160">And gracious with his greatest enemy. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113170">For such men think they have no full success:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113180">Unless they likewise gain the mistresses,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113190">Of those they master, and succeed the place,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113200">And fortunes of their loves with equal grace</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113210" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113220">Love's out alas, love such a one as he,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113230">That seeks t'undo my love▪ and in him me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113240" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Th.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113250">Tush love his fortunes, love his state, his place,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113260">Whatever greatness doth it must have grace. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113270" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113280">I weigh not greatness I must please mine eye. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113290" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Th.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113300">Th'eye nothing fairer sees than dignity. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113310" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113320">But what is dignity without our love? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113330" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Th.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113340">If we have that we cannot want our love,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113350" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113360">Why that gives but the outside of delight:</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113370">The daytime joy, what comfort hath the night? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113380" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Th.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113390">If power procure not that, what can it do? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113400" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113410">I know not how that can b'attaind unto. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113420" who="A19812_03-thais">
              <speaker>Th.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113430">Nor will I teach thee if thou knowest it not. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113440">'Tis vain I see to learn an Asian wit. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e113450">Exit.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113460" who="A19812_03-antigona">
              <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e113470">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113480">If this be that great wit that learned skill,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113490">You Greeks profess let me be foolish still,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113500"><pb facs="91"/> so I be faithful. And now being here alone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113510">Let me record the heavy notes of moan. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A19812_03-e113520">
            <head>Scaena 3.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113530" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e113540">Craterus. Ephestion. Clitus. Etc.</stage>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e113550">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113560">My lords, you see the flexible conceit,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113570">Of our endangered sovereign, and you know:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113580">How much his peril, and Philotas pride,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113590">Imports the state and us, and therefore now,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113600">We either must oppose against deceit:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113610">Or be undone. For now hath time descried,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113620">An open passage to his farthest ends,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113630">From whence if negligence now put us back,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113640">Return we never can without our wrack. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e113650">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113660">And good my lords since you conceive as much,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113670">And that we stand alike, make not me prosecute</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113680">The cause alone as if it did but touch</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113690">Only myself, and that I did both breed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113700">And urge these doubts out of a private grief. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113710">Indeed I know I might with much more ease,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113720">Sit still like others, and if dangers come:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113730">Might think to shift for one as well as they,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113740">But yet the faith the duty and respect:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113750">We owe both to our sovereign and the state,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113760">My lords, I hold, requires another care,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113770" who="A19812_03-ephestion">
              <speaker>Eph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113780">My lord, assure you we will take a time</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113790">To urge a stricter count of Dymnus' death. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113800" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <pb facs="91"/>
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e113810">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113820">My lords I say unless this be the time,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113830">You will apply your physic after death. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113840">You see the King invited hath this night</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113850">Philotas with the rest, and entertains</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113860">Him with as kind an usage to our sight,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113870">As ever, and you see the cunning strains</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113880">Of sweet insinuation that are used</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113890">T'allure the ear of grace with false reports,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113900">So that all this will come to be excused;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113910">With one remove, one action quite transports</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113920">The King's affections over to his hopes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113930">And sets him so beyond the due regard</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113940">Of his own safety, as one enterprise,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113950">May serve their turn, and may us all surprise. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e113960" who="A19812_03-clitus">
              <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e113970">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113980">But now since things thus of themselves break out</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e113990">We have advantage to prevent the worst,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114000">And every day will yield us more no doubt,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114010">For they are saved that thus are warned first. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114020" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114030">So my lord Clitus are they likewise warned. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114040">T'accelerate their plot, being thus bewrayed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114050" who="A19812_03-clitus">
              <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114060">But that they cannot now it is too late</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114070">For treason taken ere the birth, doth come</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114080">Abortive, and her womb, is made her tomb</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114090" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114100">You do not know how far it hath put forth</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114110">The force of malice, nor how far is spread</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114120">Already the contagion of this ill. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114130" who="A19812_03-clitus">
              <speaker>Clit.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114140">Why then there may some one be tortured</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114150">Of those whom ceballinus bath revealed</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114160">Whereby the rest may be discovered. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114170" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114180">That one must be Philotas from whose head</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114190"><pb facs="92"/> all this corruption flows, take him, take all. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114200" who="A19812_03-clitus">
              <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114210">Philotas is not named, and therefore may</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114220">Perhaps not be acquainted with this plot. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114230" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e114240">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114250">That his concealing of the plot betrays,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114260">And if we do not cast to find him first. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114270">His wit be sure bath laid so good a ground,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114280">As he will be the last that will be found. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114290" who="A19812_03-clitus">
              <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114300">But if he be not found: then in this case,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114310">We do him more by injuring his grace. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114320" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e114330">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114340">If that he be not found t'have dealt in this,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114350">Yet this will force out some such thoughts of his,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114360">As will undo him, for you seldom see,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114370">Such men arraigned that ever quit be:</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114380" who="A19812_03-ephestion">
              <speaker>Eph.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e114390">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114400">Well my lord Craterus we will move his grace</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114410">(Though it be late) before he take his rest,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114420">That some course may be taken in this case,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114430">And God ordain it may be for the best. </l>
              </lg>
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e114440">Exeunt</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114450" who="A19812_03-chorus">
              <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e114460">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114470">See how these greatmen clothe their private hate,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114480">In those fair colours of the public good:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114490">And to effect their ends pretend the state,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114500">As if the state by their affections stood. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114510">And arm● with power and princes jealousies,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114520">Will put the least conceit of discontent:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114530">Into the greatest rank of treacheries:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114540">That no one action shell seem innocent. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114550"><pb facs="92"/>Yea, valour, honour bounty shall be made,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114560">As accessaries unto ends unjust:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114570">And even the service of the state must lade,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114580">The needfull'st undertakings with distrust. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114590">So that base vileness idle luxury,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114600">Seem safer far, than to do worthily. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114610">Suspicion full of eyes, and full of ears,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114620">Doth thorough the tincture of her own conceit,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114630">See all things in the colours of her fears:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114640">And truth itself must look like to deceit,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114650">That what ways 'Ever the suspected take,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114660">Still, envy will most cunningly forelay</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114670">The ambush of their ruin, or will make</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114680">Their humours of themselves to take that way. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e114690">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114700">But this is still the fate of those that are,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114710">By nature or their fortunes eminent. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114720">Who either carried in conceit too far,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114730">Do work their own or others discontent:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114740">Or else are deemed sit to be suppressed. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114750">Not for they are, but that they may be ill,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114760">Since states have ever had far more unrest,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114770">By spirits of worth, than men of meaner skill:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114780">And find that those do always better prove,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114790">Who're equal to employment not above. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114800">For self opinion would be seen more wise</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114810">Than present counsels, customs, orders laws,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114820">And to the end to have them otherwise,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114830">The common wealth into combustion draws. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114840">As if ordained t'embroil the world with wit,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114850">As well as grossness to dishonour it. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A19812_03-e114860">
          <pb facs="93"/>
          <head>Actus 4.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A19812_03-e114870">
            <head>Scaena 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e114880">Attarras. Sostratus.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114890" who="A19812_03-sostratus">
              <speaker>Sost.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e114900">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114910">Can there be such a sudden change in court</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114920">As you report? is it to be believed</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114930">That great Philotas whom we all beheld</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114940">In grace last night should be arraigned today. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114950" who="A19812_03-attarus">
              <speaker>Att.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114960">It can be: and it is as I report</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114970">For states of grace are no sure holds in courts. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e114980" who="A19812_03-sostratus">
              <speaker>Sost.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e114990">But yet 'tis strange they should be overthrown</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115000">Before their certain forfeitures were known. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e115010" who="A19812_03-attarus">
              <speaker>Att.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115020">Tush it was breeding long though suddenly</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115030">This thunder-crack comes but to break out now. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e115040" who="A19812_03-sostratus">
              <speaker>Sost.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e115050">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115060">The time I waited and I waited long</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115070">Until Philotas with some other lords</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115080">Depart the presence, and as I conceived,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115090">I never saw the King in better mood,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115100">Nor yet Philotas ever in more grace</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115110">Can such storms grow and yet no clouds appear? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e115120" who="A19812_03-attarus">
              <speaker>Att.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e115130">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115140">Yea court storms grow when skies there seem most clear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115150">It was about the deepest of the night</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115160">The blackest hour of darkness and of sleep</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115170">When with some other lords comes Craterus</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115180">Falls down before the King, entreats, implores,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115190">Conjures his grace as ever he would look</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115200"><pb facs="93"/> to save his person and the state from spoil,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115210">Now to prevent Philotas' practises. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115220">Whom they had plainly found to be the man</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115230">Had plotted the destruction of them all. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e115240">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115250">The King would fain have put them off to time</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115260">And farther day, till better proofs were known</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115270">Which they perceiving pressed him still the more</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115280">And reinforced his dangers and their own. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115290">And never left him till they had obtained</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115300">Commission t'apprehend Philotas straight. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e115310">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115320">Now to make fear look with more hideous face,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115330">Or else but to beget it out of form,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115340">And careful preparations of distrust:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115350">About the palace men in armour watch</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115360">In armour men about the King attend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115370">All passages and issue were forelaid</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115380">With horse, t'interrupt whatever news</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115390">Should hence break out into Parmenio's camp. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115400">I with three hundred men in armour charged</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115410">Had warrant to attach and to commit</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115420">The person of Philotas presently:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115430">And coming to his lodging where he lay,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115440">Found him emburied in the soundest sleep</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115450">That ever man could be. where neither noise</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115460">Of clattering weapons, or our rushing in</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115470">With rude and trampling rumour, could dissolve</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115480">The heavy humour of that drowsy brow</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115490">Which held perhaps his senses now more fast</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115500">As loath to leave because it was the last. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e115510" who="A19812_03-sostratus">
              <speaker>Sost.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e115520">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115530">Attarras, what can treason sleep so sound? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115540"><pb facs="94"/>Will that loud hand of horror that still beats,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115550">Upon the guilty conscience of distrust:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115560">Permit it t'have so resolute a rest? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e115570" who="A19812_03-attarus">
              <speaker>Att.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e115580">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115590">I cannot tell but thus we found him there,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115600">Nor could we I assure you waken him:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115610">Till thrice I called him by his name, and thrice</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115620">Had shook him hard, and then at length he wakes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115630">And looking on me with a settled cheer,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115640">Dear friend Attarras, what's the news said he? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115650">What up so soon to hasten the remove,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115660">Or raised by some alarm or some distrust? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115670">I told him that the King had some distrust. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115680">Why what will Nabarzanes play saith he</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115690">The villain with the King; as he hath done</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115700">Already with his miserable lord? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115710">I seeing he would, or did not understand</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115720">His own distressed: told him the charge I had:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115730">Wherewith he rose, and rising used these words:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115740">Oh Alexander now I see my foes,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115750">Have got above thy goodness, and prevailed:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115760">Against my innocency and thy word. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115770">And as we then enchained and fettered him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115780">Looking on that base furniture of shame,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115790">Poor body, said he, hath so many alarm:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115800">Raised thee to blood and danger from thy rest,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115810">T'invest thee with this armour now at last,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115820">Is this the service I am called to now? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e115830">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115840">But we that were not to attend his plaints,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115850">Covering his head with a disgraceful weed:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115860">Took and conveyed him suddenly to ward,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115870"><pb facs="94"/> from whence he shall be instantly brought forth,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115880">Here to b'arraigned before the King, who sits,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115890">(According to the Macedonian use)</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115900">In cases capital, himself, as judge. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e115910" who="A19812_03-sostratus">
              <speaker>Sost.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115920">Well then I see who are so high above,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115930">Are never to lightning that are never to Jove. </l>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19812_03-e115940">
            <head>Scaena 2.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e115950" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e115960">Alexander with all his council, the dead body of Dymnus. the revealers of the conspiracy, Philotas. </stage>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e115970">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115980">The heinous treason of some few had like,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e115990">T'have ●ent me from you worthy soldiers,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116000">But by the mercy of th'immortal gods</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116010">I live, and joy your sight, your reverend sight,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116020">Which makes me more t'abhor those parricides,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116030">Not for mine own respect, but for the wrong,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116040">You had received, if their design had stood. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116050">Since I desire but life to do you good. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e116060">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116070">But how will you be moved when you shall know,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116080">Who were the men that did attempt this shame:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116090">When I shall show that which I grieve to show:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116100">And name such as would God I could not name,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116110">But that the foulness of their practice now:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116120">Blots out all memory of what they were</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116130">And though I would suppress them, yet I know,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116140"><pb facs="95"/> this shame of theirs will never but appear. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116150">Parmenio is the man, a man you see</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116160">Bound by so many merits both to me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116170">And to my father, our ancientest friend</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116180">A man of years, experience gravity,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116190">Whose wicked minister Philotas is</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116200">Who here Demetrius Luculaus, and</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116210">This Dymnus whose dead body here you see</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116220">With others hath suborned to slaughter me. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e116230">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116240">And, here comes Metron with Nichomacus</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116250">To whom this murdered wretch at first revealed</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116260">The project of this whole conspiracy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116270">T'aver as much as was disclosed to him. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116280">Nichomacus look here advise thee well,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116290">What dost thou know this man that here lies dead? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e116300" who="A19812_03-nichomachus">
              <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e116310">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116320">My sovereign lord: I know him very well,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116330">It is one Dymnus who did three days since</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116340">Bewray to me a treason practised</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116350">By him and others to have slain your grace. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e116360" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Al.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116370">Where or by whom, or when did he report</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116380">This wicked act should be accomplished? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e116390" who="A19812_03-nichomachus">
              <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e116400">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116410">He said within three days your majesty</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116420">Should be within your chamber murdered</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116430">By special men of the nobility</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116440">Of whom he many named, and they were these:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116450">Loceus, Demetrius, and Archelopis</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116460">Nicanor and Amyntas, luculous</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116470">Droceus with Aphebaetus and himself. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e116480" who="A19812_03-mot">
              <speaker>Mot</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116490">Thus much his brother Ceballinus did</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116500">Reveal to me from out this youth's report. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e116510" who="A19812_03-cebalinus">
              <pb facs="95"/>
              <speaker>Ceb.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116520">And so much with the circumstance of all</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116530">Did I unto Philotas intimate. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e116540" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e116550">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116560">Then what hath been his mind, who did suppress</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116570">The information of so foul a train</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116580">Yourselves my worthy soldiers well may guess,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116590">Which Dymnus' death declares not to be vain. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116600">Poor Ceballinus not a moment stays,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116610">To redischarge himself of such a weight,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116620">Philotas careless, fearless, nothing weighs</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116630">Nor ought reveals. His silence shows deceit,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116640">And tells he was content it should be done</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116650">Which though he were no party makes him one. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e116660">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116670">For he that knew upon what power he stood</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116680">And saw his father's greatness, and his own</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116690">Saw nothing in the way which now withstood</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116700">His vast desires, but only this my crown. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116710">Which in respect that I am issueless</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116720">He thinks the rather easy to b'attaind</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116730">But yet Philotas is deceived in this</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116740">I have who shall inherit all I gained. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116750">In you I have both children, kindred friends</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116760">You are the heirs of all my purchases,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116770">And whilst you live I am not issueless. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e116780">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116790">And that these are not shadows of my fears,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116800">(For I fear naught but want of enemies,)</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116810">See what this intercepted letter bears,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116820">And how Parmenio doth his son's advice:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116830">This shows their ends, hold read it Craterus. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e116840" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Crat.</speaker>
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e116850">Reads it.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116860">My sons, first have a special care unto yourselves</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116870">Then unto those which do depend on you. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116880"><pb facs="96"/>So shall you do what you intend to do. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e116890" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e116900">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116910">See but how close he writes, that if these lines</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116920">Should come unto his sons, as they are sent,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116930">They might encourage them in their designs,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116940">If enterprised, might mock the ignorant</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116950">But now you see what was the thing was meant,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116960">You see the father's care the son's intent. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e116970">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116980">And what if he as a conspirator,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e116990">Was not by Dymnus named among the rest:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117000">That shows not his innocence but his power,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117010">Whom they account too great to be suppressed:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117020">And rather will accuse themselves then him,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117030">For that whilst he shall live, there's hope for them. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117040">And how h'hath born himself in private sort. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117050">I will not stand to urge, it's too well known,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117060">Nor what hath been his arrogant report:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117070">T'embase my actions, and to brag his own. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117080">Nor how he mocked my letter which I wrote:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117090">To show him of the style bestowed on me,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117100">By th'oracle of Jove. these things I thought</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117110">But weaknesses, and words of vanity,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117120">(Yet words that read the ulcers of his heart)</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117130">Which I suppressed, and never ceased to yield</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117140">The chief rewards of worth and still compart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117150">The best degrees and honours of the field. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117160">In hope to win his love, yet now at length,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117170">There have I danger where I looked for strength:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117180">I would to God my blood had rather been</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117190">Poured out, the offering of an enemy;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117200">Then practised to be shed by one of mine,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117210"><pb facs="96"/> that one of mine should have this infamy. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117220">Have I been so reserved from fears to fall</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117230">There where I ought not to have feared at all▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117240">Have you so oft advised me to regard</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117250">The safety, which you saw me running from,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117260">When with some hot pursuit I pressed hard</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117270">My foes abroad; to perish thus at home? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e117280">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117290">But now that safety only rests in you</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117300">Which you so oft have wished me look unto. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117310">And now unto your bosoms must I fly</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117320">Without whose will I will not wish to live:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117330">And with your wills I cannot; less I give</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117340">Due punishment unto this treachery. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e117350" who="A19812_03-amyntas">
              <speaker>Amyn.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e117360">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117370">Attarras, bring the hateful prisoner forth</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117380">This traitor which hath sought t'undo us all,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117390">To give us up to slaughter, and to make</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117400">Our blood a scorn, here in a barbarous land. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117410">That none of us should have returned back,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117420">Unto our native country, to our wives</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117430">Our aged parents, kindred, and our friends. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117440">To make the body of this glorious host</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117450">A most deformed trunk without a head,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117460">Without the life or soul to guide the same</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e117470" who="A19812_03-caenus">
              <speaker>Caenus.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e117480">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117490">O thou base traitor impious parricide,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117500">Who mak'st me loathe the blood that matched with thine</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117510">And if I might but have my will. I vow</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117520">Thou shouldst not die by other hand than mine. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e117530" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e117540">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117550">Fie Caenus what a barbarous course is this</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117560">He first must to his accusation plead. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117570">And have his trial, formal to our laws</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117580"><pb facs="97"/> and let him make the best of his bad cause</l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e117590">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117600">Philotas here the Macedonians are</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117610">To judge your fact, what language wilt thou use? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e117620" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e117630">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117640">The Persian language if it please your grace,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117650">For that beside the Macedonians, here</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117660">Are many that will better understand,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117670">If I shall use the speech your grace hath used,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117680">Which was I hold unto no other end,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117690">But that the most men here might understand. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e117700" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Al.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e117710">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117720">See how his native language he disdains,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117730">But let him speak at large as he desires,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117740">So long as you remember he doth hate</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117750">Besides the speech our glory and the state. </l>
              </lg>
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e117760">Exit▪</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e117770" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e117780">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117790">Black are the colours laid upon the crime,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117800">Wherewith my faith stands charged my worthy lords</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117810">That as behind in fortune so in time,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117820">I come too late to clear the same with words. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117830">My condemnation is gone out before</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117840">My innocency, and my just defence:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117850">And takes up all your hearts, and leaves no door</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117860">For mine excuse to have an entrance. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117870">That destitute of all compassion, now,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117880">Betwixt an upright conscience of desert,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117890">And an unjust disgrace, I know not how</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117900">To satisfy the time, and mine own heart. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117910">Authority looks with so stern an eye</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117920">Upon this woeful bar, and must have still</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117930">Such an advantage over misery</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117940">As that it will make good, all that it will. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e117950">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117960">He who should only judge my cause, is gone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117970"><pb facs="97"/> and why he would not stay, I do not see,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117980">Since when my cause were heard his power alone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e117990">As well might then condemn as set me free:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118000">Nor can I by his absence now be cleared</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118010">Whose presence hath condemned me thus unheard. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118020">And though the grievance of a prisoner's tongue,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118030">May both superfluous and disgraceful seem,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118040">Which doth not sue, but shows the judge his wrong:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118050">Yet pardon me, I must not disesteem</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118060">My rightful cause for being despised, nor must</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118070">Forsake myself, though I am left of all,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118080">Fear cannot make my innocence unjust</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118090">Unto itself, to give my truth the fall. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118100">And I had rather, seeing how my fortune draws,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118110">My words should be deformed then my cause. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e118120">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118130">I know that nothing is more delicate</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118140">Than is the sense and feeling of a state:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118150">The clap, the bruit, the fear but of a hurt</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118160">In King's behalfs, thrusts with that violence</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118170">The subject's will to prosecute report,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118180">As they condemn, ere they discern th'offence. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e118190" who="A19812_03-ephestion">
              <speaker>Eph.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e118200">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118210">Philotas you deceive yourself in this</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118220">That think to win compassion, and belief</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118230">B'impugning justice and to make men guess</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118240">We do you wrong out of our heat of grief,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118250">Or that our place or passions did lay more</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118260">On your misfortunes, than your own desert</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118270">Or have not well discerned your fact before,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118280">Or would without, due proofs your state subvert,</l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e118290">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118300">These are the usual themes of traitors tongues</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118310"><pb facs="98"/> who practise mischiefs, and complain of wrongs</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118320">Your treasons are too manifestly known</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118330">To mask in other livery than their own. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e118340" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e118350">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118360">Think not, that we are set to charge you here</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118370">With bare suspicions but with open fact,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118380">And with a treason that appears as clear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118390">As is the sun, and known to be your act. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e118400" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118410">What is this treason? who accuses me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e118420" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118430">The process of the whole conspiracy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e118440" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118450">But where's the man that names me to be one? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e118460" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e118470">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118480">Here this dead traitor shows you to be one. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e118490" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118500">How can he dead, accuse me of the same</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118510">Whom living he nor did, nor yet could name. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e118520" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118530">But we can other testimony show</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118540">From those who were your chiefest complices. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e118550" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e118560">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118570">I am not too b'adjudged in law you know</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118580">By testimony, but by witnesses. <note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A19812_03-e118590">no testimonijs sine testibsu.</note></l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118600">Let them be here produced unto my face</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118610">That can avouch m'a party in this case. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118620">My lords and fellow soldiers if of those</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118630">Whom Dymnus nominated, any one</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118640">Out of his tortures will a word disclose</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118650">To show I was a party: I have done. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118660">Think not so great a number ever will</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118670">Endure their torments and themselves accuse</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118680">And leave me out. Since men in such case, still</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118690">Will rather slander others than excuse. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118700">Calamity malignant is, and he</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118710">That suffers justly for his guiltiness</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118720">Eases his own affliction, but to see</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118730"><pb facs="98"/> others 'Tormented in the same distress,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118740">And yet I fear not whatsoever they</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118750">By racks and tortures can be forest to say. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118760">Had I been one would Dymnus have concealed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118770">My name being held to be the principal?</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118780">Would he not for his glory have revealed</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118790">The best to him to whom he must tell all? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118800">Nay if he falsely then had named me one? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118810">To grace himself, must I of force be one. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e118820">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118830">Alas, if Ceballinus had not come to me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118840">And given me note of this conspiracy</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118850">I had not stood here now but been as free</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118860">From question as I am from treachery. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118870">That is the only cloud that thundereth</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118880">On my disgrace. Which had I deemed true</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118890">Or could but have divined of Dymnus' death</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118900">Philotas, had, my lords, sat therewith you. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118910">My fault was to have been too credulous</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118920">Wherein I showed my weakness I confess. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e118930" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118940">Philotas what a monarch and confess</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118950">Your imperfections and your weakness? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e118960" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e118970">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118980">O Craterus, do not insult upon calamity,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e118990">It is a barbarous grossness to lay on</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119000">The weight of scorn where heavy misery</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119010">To much already ways men's fortunes down</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119020">For if the cause be ill I undergo,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119030">The law and not reproach must make it so. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e119040" who="A19812_03-caenus">
              <speaker>Caen.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119050">There's no reproach can ever be too much</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119060">To lay on traitors, whose deserts are such. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e119070" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119080">Men use the most reproaches where they fear</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119090"><pb facs="99"/> the cause will better prove then their desire. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e119100" who="A19812_03-caenus">
              <speaker>Caen.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119110">But sir, a traitor's cause that is so clear. </l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119120">As this of yours will never need that fear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e119130" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e119140">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119150">I am no traitor but suspected one,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119160">For not believing a conspiracy. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119170">And mere suspect by law condemneth none,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119180">They are approved facts for which men die. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e119190" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e119200">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119210">The law in treasons doth the will correct. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119220">With like severeness as it doth th'effect. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119230">Th'affection is the essence of th'offence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119240">The execution only but th'accidence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119250">To have but willed it, is t'have done the same. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e119260" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119270">I did not err in will, but in belief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119280">And if that be a traitor, then am I the chief. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e119290" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119300">Yea but your will made your belief consent</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119310">To hide th'practise till th'accomplishment. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e119320" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e119330">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119340">Belief turns not by motions of our will,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119350">And it was but the event that made that ill. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119360">Some facts men may excuse, though not defend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119370">Where will and fortune have a divers end. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119380">Th'example of my father made me fear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119390">To be too forward to relate things heard. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119400">Who writing to the King, wished him forbear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119410">The potion his physician had prepared. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119420">For that he heard Darius tempted had,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119430">His faith, with many talents, to b'untrue. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119440">And yet his drugs in th'end not proving bad,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119450">Did make my father's care seem more than due. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119460">For oft by an untimely diligence,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119470">A busy faith may give a prince offence. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119480"><pb facs="99"/>So that, what shall we do? if we reveal,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119490">We are despised, suspected if conceal. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119500">And as for this wherever now thou be</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119510">Oh Alexander thou hast pardoned me. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119520">Thou hast already given me thy hand,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119530">The earnest of thy reconciled heart. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119540">And therefore now o let thy goodness stand,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119550">Unto thy word, and be thou as thou wert. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119560">If thou believed'st me then, I am absolved,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119570">If pardoned me, these fetters are dissolved. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119580">What have I else deserved since yesternight ,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119590">When at thy table I such grace did find,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119600">What heinous crime hath since been brought to light●</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119610">To wrong my faith, and to divert thy mind? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119620">That from a restful quiet most profound,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119630">Sleeping in my misfortunes, made secure</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119640">Both by thy hand, and by a conscience sound,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119650">I must be woken for gyves, for robes impure,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119660">For all disgrace that on me wrath could lay,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119670">And see the worst of shame, ere I saw day. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119680">When I least thought that others cruelty,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119690">Should have wrought more than thine own clemency. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e119700" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e119710">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119720">Philotas whatsoever gloss you lay,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119730">Upon your rotten cause, it is in vain,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119740">Your pride, your carriage, ever did bewray. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119750">Your discontent, your malice, and disdain. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119760">You cannot palliate mischief but it will,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119770">Through all the fairest coverings of deceit</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119780">Be always seen; we know those streams of ill,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119790">Flowed from that head that feed them with conceit. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119800"><pb facs="100"/>You foster malcontents, you entertain</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119810">All humours, you all factions must embrace. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119820">Ye vaunt your own exploits, and you disdain</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119830">The King's proceedings, and his style disgrace. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119840">You promise mountains, and you draw men on,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119850">With hopes of greater good then hath been seen. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119860">You bragged of late that something would be done</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119870">Whereby your concubine should be a Queen. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119880">And now we see the thing that should be done. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119890">But God be praised we see you first undone. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e119900" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e119910">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119920">Ah do not make my nature, if it had,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119930">So pliable a stern of disposition,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119940">To turn to every kindness, to be bad,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119950">For doing good to men of all condition. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119960">Make not you charity t'interpret all</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119970">Is done for favour to be done for show,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119980">And that we in our bounties prodigal. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e119990">Upon our ends not on men's needs bestow. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120000">Let not my one day's error make you tell,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120010">That all my life-time I did never well. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120020">And that because this falls out to be ill,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120030">That what I did, did tend unto this ill. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120040">It is unjust to join t'a present fact</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120050">More of time passed then it hath ever had</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120060">Before to do withal, as if it lacked</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120070">Sufficient matter to make it bad. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120080">I do confess indeed I wrote something. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120090">Against this title of the son of Jove,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120100">And that not of the King but to the King,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120110">I freely used these words out of my love,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120120"><pb facs="100"/> and thereby hath that dangerous liberty</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120130">Of speaking truth, with trust on former grace</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120140">Betrayed my meaning unto enmity</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120150">And drawn an argument of my disgrace. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120160">So that I see though I spoke what I ought,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120170">It was not in that manner as I ought. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e120180">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120190">And God forbid that ever soldiers words</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120200">Should be made liable unto misdeeds,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120210">When fainting in their march, tired in the fight,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120220">Sick in their tent, stopping their wounds that bleeds,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120230">Or haut and jolly after conquest goat</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120240">They shall out of their heat use words unkind,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120250">Their deeds deserve to have them rather thought</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120260">The passion of the season, than their mind. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120270">For soldier's joy, or wrath is measureless▪</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120280">Rapt with an instant motion, and we blame,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120290">We hate, we praise, we pity in excess</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120300">According as our present passions flame. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120310">Sometimes to pass the ocean we would feign</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120320">Sometimes to other worlds, and sometimes slack</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120330">And idle, with our conquests, entertain</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120340">A sullen humour of returning back. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120350">All which conceits one trumpets sound doth end,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120360">And each man running to his ranks doth lose</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120370">What in our tents dislike us, and we spend</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120380">All that conceived wrath upon our foes. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120390">And words, if they proceed of levity</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120400">Are to be scorned, of madness pitied</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120410">If out of malice or of injury</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120420">To be remissed or unacknowledged:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120430"><pb facs="101"/> for of themselves they vanish by disdain,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120440">But if pursued they will be thought not vain. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e120450" who="A19812_03-unassigned">
              <speaker>Cr●.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e120460">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120470">But words according to the person way,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120480">If his designs are heinous so are they,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120490">They are the tinder of sedition, still,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120500">Wherewith you kindle fierce inflame men's will. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e120510" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e120520">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120530">Craterus you have th'advantage of the day,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120540">The law is yours to say what you will say. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120550">And yet doth all your gloss but bear the sense,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120560">Only of my misfortune not offence. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120570">Had I pretended mischief to the King,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120580">Could not I have effected it without</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120590">Dimnus? did not my free access bring</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120600">Continual means t'have brought the same about? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120610">Was not I since I heard the thing descried,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120620">Alone, and armed in private with his grace,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120630">What hindered me that then I had not tried</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120640">T'have done that mischief, having time and place? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e120650" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e120660">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120670">Philotas even the providence above. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120680">Protectress of the sacred state of Kings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120690">That never suffers treachery to have</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120700">Good council, never in this case but brings</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120710">Confusion to the actors, did undo</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120720">Your hearts, in what you went about to do. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e120730" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120740">But yet despair we see doth thrust men on</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120750">Seeing no way else t'undo oer be undone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e120760" who="A19812_03-craterus">
              <speaker>Cra.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120770">That same despair doth likewise let men fall</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120780">In that amaze they can do naught at all. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e120790" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e120800">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120810">Well, well, my lords my service hath made known</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120820">The faith I owe my sovereign and the state</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120830"><pb facs="101"/> Philotas' forwardness hath ever shown</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120840">Unto all nations at how high a rate</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120850">I prized my King, and at how low my blood,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120860">To do him honour and my country good. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e120870" who="A19812_03-ephestion">
              <speaker>Eph.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e120880">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120890">We blame not what you've been, but what you are:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120900">We accuse not here your valour, but your fact,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120910">Not to have been a leader in the war,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120920">But an ill subject, in a wicked act. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120930">Although we know thrust rather with the love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120940">Of your own glory, then with duty lead</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120950">You have done much, yet all your courses prove</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120960">You tide still your achievements to the head</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120970">Of your own honour, when it had been meet,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120980">You had them laid, down at your sovereign's feet. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e120990">God gives to Kings the honour to command,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121000">To subjects all their glory to obey:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121010">Who ought in time of war as rampiers stand,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121020">In peace as th'ornaments of state array. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121030">The King hath recompensed your services</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121040">With better love than you show thankfulness. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121050">By grace, he made you greater than you were</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121060">By nature: you received that which he was not tide</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121070">To give to you: his gift was far more dear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121080">Than all you did, in making you employed. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121090">But say your service hath deserved at all,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121100">This one offence hath made it odious all. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121110">And therefore here in vain, you use that mean</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121120">To plead for life, which you have concealed clean. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e121130" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e121140">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121150">My lord you far mistake me if you deem</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121160">I plead for life, that poor weak blast of breath,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121170"><pb facs="102"/> from which so oft I ran with light esteem</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121180">And so well have acquainted me with death,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121190">No no, my lords, it is not that I fear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121200">It is mine honour that I seek to clear. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121210">And which if my disgraced cause would let</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121220">The language of my heart be understood,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121230">Is all which I have ever sought to get</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121240">And which (Oh leave me now) and take my blood. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121250">Let not your envy go beyond the bound</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121260">Of what you seek: my life stands in your way</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121270">That is your aim, take it and do not wound</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121280">My reputation with that wrong I pray. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121290">If I must needs be made the sacrifice</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121300">Of envy, and that no oblation will</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121310">The wrath, of Kings but only blood suffice,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121320">Yet let me, have something left that is not ill. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121330">Is there no way to get unto our lives</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121340">But first to have our honour overthrown? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121350">Alas though grace of Kings all greatness gives</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121360">It cannot give us virtue, that's our own</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121370">Though all be theirs our hearts and hands can do</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121380">Yet that by which we do is only ours:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121390">The trophies that our blood erects unto</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121400">Their memory to glorify their powers</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121410">Let them enjoy: yet only to have done</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121420">Worthy of grace let not that be undone. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121430">Let that high swelling river of their fame</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121440">Leave humble streams that feed them yet their name</l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e121450">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121460">Oh my dear father didst thou bring that spirit</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121470">Those hands of valour that so much have done. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121480"><pb facs="102"/>In this great work of Asia, this to merit</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121490">By doing worthily to be undone? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121500">And hast thou made this purchase of thy sword</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121510">To get so great an empire for thy lord</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121520">And so disgraced a grave for thee and thine,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121530">T'extinguish by thy service all thy line? </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e121540">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121550">One of thy sons by being to valorous</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121560">But five days since, yet o well, lost his breath</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121570">Thy dear Nicanor th'half arch of thy house,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121580">And here now the other at the bar of death</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121590">Stands overcharged with wrath in far worse case</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121600">And is to be confounded with disgrace. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121610">Thyself must give th'acquittance of thy blood</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121620">For others debts to whom thou hast done good. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121630">Which if they would a little time afford</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121640">Death would have taken it without a sword. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121650">Such the rewards of great employments are</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121660">Hate kills in peace, whom fortune spares in war. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121670">And this is that high grace of Kings we seek,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121680">Whose favour, and whose wrath consumes a like. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e121690" who="A19812_03-ephestion">
              <speaker>Eph.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e121700">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121710">Lo here the misery of Kings, whose cause</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121720">However just it be, however strong,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121730">Yet in respect they may, their greatness draws</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121740">The world to think they ever do the wrong. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121750">But this foul fact of yours you stand upon</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121760">Philotas shall beside th'apparency</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121770">Which all the world sees plain, ere we have done</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121780">By your own mouth be made to satisfy. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121790">The most stiff partialist that will not see. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e121800" who="A19812_03-philotas">
              <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e121810">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121820">My mouth will never prove so false I trust</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121830">Unto my heart, to show itself unjust:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121840"><pb facs="103"/> and what I here do speak I know my lords</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121850">I speak with mine own mouth, but other where</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121860">What may be said I say, may be the words</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121870">Not of my breath, but fame that oft doth err,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121880">Let th'oracle of Ammon be inquired</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121890">About this fact, who if it shall be true</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121900">Will never suffer those who have conspired</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121910">Against Jove's son t'escape without their due;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121920">But will reveal the truth, or if this shall</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121930">Not seem convenient: why then lay on all</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121940">The tortures that may force a tongue to tell,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121950">The secretest thought that could imagine ill. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e121960" who="A19812_03-bel">
              <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e121970">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121980">What need we send to know more than we know</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e121990">That were to give you time t'acquaint your friends</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122000">With your estate, till some combustion grow</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122010">Within the camp to hasten on your ends:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122020">And that the gold and all the treasury</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122030">Committed to your father's custody</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122040">In Media, now might arm his desperate troops</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122050">To come upon us and to cut our throats. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122060">What shall we ask of Jove that which he hath</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122070">Revealed already? but let's send to give</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122080">Thanks that by him, the King hath scaped the wrath</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122090">Of thee disloyal traitor and doth live. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e122100" who="A19812_03-guard">
              <speaker>Guard</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122110">Let's tear the wretch in pieces, let us rend</l>
              <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122120">With our own hands, the traitorous parricide. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e122130" who="A19812_03-alexander">
              <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e122140">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122150">Peace Belon, silence loving soldiers. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122160">You see my lords out of your judgements grave</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122170">That all excuses sickly colours have,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122180">And he that hath thus false and faithless bene</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122190"><pb facs="103"/> must find out other gods and other men</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122200">Whom to forswear, and whom he may deceive,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122210">No words of his can make us more believe</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122220">His impudence, and therefore seeing 'tis late,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122230">We till the morning, do dismiss the court. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A19812_03-e122240">
          <head>Actus 5.</head>
          <div type="scene" xml:id="A19812_03-e122250">
            <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e122260">Chorus. Grecian and Persian.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e122270" who="A19812_03-perdicas">
              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e122280">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122290">Well then I see there is small difference</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122300">Betwixt your state and ours, you civil Greeks</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122310">You great contrivers of free governments. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122320">Whose skill the world from out all countries seeks. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122330">Those whom you call your Kings are but the same</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122340">As are our sovereign tyrants of the East,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122350">I see they only differ but in name,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122360">Th'effects they show agree, or near at least. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122370">Your great men here as our great Satrapa's</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122380">I see laid prostrate are with basest shame,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122390">Upon the least suspect, or jealousies</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122400">Your King, t'conceive or others envies frame,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122410">Only herein they differ, that your prince</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122420">Proceeds by form of law t'effect his end;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122430">Our Persian monarch makes his frown convince</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122440">The strongest truth: his sword the process ends</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122450">With present death, and makes no more ado,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122460">He never stands to give a gloss unto</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122470">His violence, to make it to appear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122480">In other hue, then that it ought to bear▪</l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e122490">
                <pb facs="104"/>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122500">Wherein plain dealing best his course commends</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122510">For more h'offends who by the law offends</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122520">What need hath Alexander so to strive</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122530">By all these shows of form to find this man</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122540">Guilty of treason, when he doth contrive</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122550">To have him so adjudged, do what he can. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122560">He must not be acquit, though he be clear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122570">Th'offender not th'offence is punished here. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122580">And what avails the fore-condemned to speak</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122590">However strong his cause, his state is weak. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e122600" who="A19812_03-greek">
              <speaker>Gre.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e122610">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122620">Ah, but it satisfies the world, and we</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122630">Think that well done, which done by law we see. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e122640" who="A19812_03-perdicas">
              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e122650">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122660">And yet your law serves but your private ends</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122670">And to the compass of your power extends. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122680">But is it for the majesty of Kings</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122690">To sit in judgements thus themselves with you? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e122700" who="A19812_03-greek">
              <speaker>Gre.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e122710">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122720">To do men justice is the thing that brings</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122730">The greatest majesty on earth to Kings. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e122740" who="A19812_03-perdicas">
              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e122750">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122760">That by their subalternate ministers</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122770">May be performed as well, and with more grate</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122780">For to command it to be done infers</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122790">More glory than to do. It doth embase</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122800">Th'opinion of a power t'invulgar so</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122810">That sacred presence, which should never go</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122820">Never beseene, but even as gods below</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122830">Like to our Persian Kings in glorious show. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122840">And who as stars affixed to their sphere</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122850">May not descend to be from what they are. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e122860" who="A19812_03-greek">
              <speaker>Gre.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e122870">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122880">Where Kings are so like gods, there subjects are not men,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e122890" who="A19812_03-perdicas">
              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e122900">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122910">Your King begins this course, and what will you be then? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e122920" who="A19812_03-greek">
              <pb facs="104"/>
              <speaker>Gre.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e122930">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122940">Indeed since prosperous fortune gave the rain</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122950">To headstrong power and lust, I must confess</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122960">We Grecians have lost deeply by our gain,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122970">And this our greatness makes us much the l●ss●</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122980">For by th'accession of these mighty states</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e122990">Which Alexander wondrously hath got</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123000">He hath forgotten himself, and us, and rates</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123010">His state above mankind, and ours at noughs. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123020">This hath thy pompeô feeble Asia wrought,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123030">Thy base adorings hath transformed the King</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123040">Into that shape of pride, as he is brought</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123050">Out of his wits, out of acknowledging</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123060">From whence the glory of his greatness springs,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123070">And that it was our swords that wrought these things. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123080">How well were we within the narrow bounds</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123090">Of our sufficient yielding Macedon,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123100">Before our Kings enlarged then with our wounds</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123110">And made these sallies of ambition. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123120">Before they came to give the regal law</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123130">To those free states which kept their crowns in awe. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123140">They by these large dominions are made more</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123150">But we become far weaker than before. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123160">What get we now by winning but wide minds</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123170">And weary bodies with th'expense of blood? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123180">What should ill do, since happy fortune finds</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123190">But misery, and is not good, though good? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123200">Action begets still action, and retains</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123210">Our hopes beyond our wishes, drawing on</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123220">Anever ending circle of our pains</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123230">That makes us not have done, when we have done. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123240"><pb facs="105"/>What can give bounds to Alexander's ends</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123250">Who counts the world but small, that calls him great:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123260">And his desires beyond his prey distends</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123270">Like beasts that murder more than they can eat? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123280">When shall we look his travails will be done,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123290">That tends beyond the ocean and the sun? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123300">What discontentments will there still arise</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123310">In such a camp of Kings, to intershock</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123320">Each others greatness, and what mutinies,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123330">Will put him from his comforts, and will mock</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123340">His hopes, and never suffer him to have</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123350">That which he hath of all which fortune gave? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123360">And from Philotas' blood (O worthy man)</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123370">Whose body now rent on the torture lies</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123380">Will slow that vain of fresh conspiracies,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123390">As overflow him will, do what he can. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123400">For cruelty doth not embitter men</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123410">But them more wary makes, than they have been. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e123420" who="A19812_03-perdicas">
              <speaker>Per.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e123430">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123440">Are not your greatmen free from tortures then</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123450">Must they be likewise racked, as other men? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e123460" who="A19812_03-greek">
              <speaker>Gre.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e123470">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123480">Treason affords a privilege to none</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123490">Who like offends, hath punishment all one. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A19812_03-e123500">
            <pb facs="105"/>
            <head>Scaena 2.</head>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e123510" who="A19812_03-polidamas">
              <stage xml:id="A19812_03-e123520">Polidamas, Sostratus.</stage>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e123530">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123540">Frriend Sostratus, come have you ever known</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123550">Such a distracted face of court as now,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123560">Such a distrustful eye, as men are grown</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123570">To fear themselves and all: and do not know. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123580">Where is the side that shakes not, who looks best</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123590">In this foul day, th'oppressor or th'oppressed. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123600">What posting, what dispatches, what advice,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123610">What search, what running, what discoveries? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123620">What rumours, what suggestions, what device</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123630">To clear the King, please people, hold the wise,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123640">Retain the ●ude, crush the suspected sort</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123650">At unawares, ere they discern they're hurt. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123660">So much the fall of such a weighty peer</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123670">Doth shake the state, and with him tumble down,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123680">All whom his beam of favour did upbear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123690">All who to rest upon his base were known. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123700">And none that did but touch upon his love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123710">Are free from fear to perish with his love. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123720">Myself whom all the world have known t'embrace</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123730">Parmenio in th'entireness of my heart,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123740">And ever in all battles, every chase</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123750">Of danger, fought still next him on that part:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123760">Was seized on this last night, late in my bed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123770">And brought unto the presence of the King. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123780"><pb facs="106"/>To pay I thought the tribute of my head,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123790">But o 'twas for a more abhorred thing:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123800">I must redeem my danger with the blood</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123810">Of this dear friend, this dear Parmenio's blood. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123820">His life must pay for mine, these hands must gore,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123830">That worthy heart, for whom they fought before. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e123840" who="A19812_03-sostratus">
              <speaker>Sost.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e123850">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123860">What hath the King commanded such a deed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123870">To make the hearts of all his subjects bleed? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123880">Must that old worthy man Parmenio die? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e123890" who="A19812_03-polidamus">
              <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e123900">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123910">O Sostratus he hath his doom to die,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123920">And we must yield unto necessity. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e123930">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123940">For coming to the King, and there received</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123950">With unexpected grace, he thus began:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123960">Polidamas we both have been deceived</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123970">In holding friendship with that faithless man</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123980">Parmenio, who for all his glozing mine</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e123990">Thou seest hath sought to cut my throat and thine,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124000">And thou must work revenge for thee and me:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124010">And therefore haste to Media speedily,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124020">Take these two letters here, the one from me</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124030">Unto my sure and trusty servants there,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124040">The other signed with Philotas' seal,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124050">As if the same t'his father written were:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124060">Carry them both, effect what I have said,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124070">The one will give th'access, the other aid,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124080">I took the letters, vowed t'effect the same. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124090">And here I go the instrument of shame. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e124100" who="A19812_03-sostratus">
              <speaker>Sost.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e124110">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124120">But will you charge your honour with this shame? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e124130" who="A19812_03-polidamus">
              <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e124140">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124150">I must or be undone with all my name. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124160">For I have left all th'adamantive ties</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124170"><pb facs="106"/> of blood and nature, that can hold a heart</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124180">Chained to the world● my brothers and allies</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124190">The hostages to caution for my part. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124200">And for their lives must I dishonour mine. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124210">Else should the King rather have turned this sword</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124220">Upon my heart, then forced it impiously,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124230">(Having done all fair service to his lord</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124240">Now to b'employed in this foul villainy.) </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124250">Thus must we do who are enthralled to Kings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124260">Whether they will just or unlawful things. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124270">But now Parmenio, o methink I see</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124280">Thee walking in th'artificial grove</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124290">Of pleasant Susis, when I come to thee,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124300">And thou remembering all our ancient love</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124310">Hastes to embrace me. Saying o my friend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124320">My dear Polidamas, welcome my friend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124330">Well art thou come that we may sit and chat</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124340">Of all the old adventures we have run. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124350">'Tis long Polidamas since we two met,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124360">How doth my sovereign lord, how doth my son? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124370">When I vile wretch, whilst m'answer he attends</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124380">With this hand give the letter, this hand ends</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124390">His speaking joy, and stabs him to the heart. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124400">And thus Parmenio thou rewarded art</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124410">For all thy service, thou that didst agree</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124420">For Alexander to kill Attalus</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124430">For Alexander I must now kill thee. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124440">Such are the judgements of the heavenly powers,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124450">We others ruins work, and others ours. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e124460" who="A19812_03-chorus">
              <speaker>Chorus P.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e124470">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124480">Why this is right now Alexander takes</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124490"><pb facs="107"/> the course of power, this is a Persian trick,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124500">This is our way, here public trial makes</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124510">No doubtful noise, but buries clamour quick. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e124520" who="A19812_03-greek">
              <speaker>Gr.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e124530">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124540">Indeed now Persia hath no cause to rue,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124550">For you have us undone, who undid you. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e124560" who="A19812_03-nuntius">
              <speaker>Nvngivs.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e124570">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124580">This work is done, the sad catastrophe</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124590">Of this great act of blood is finished now. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124600">Philotas ended hath the tragedy. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e124610" who="A19812_03-chorus">
              <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e124620">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124630">Now good my friend I pray thee tell us how. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e124640" who="A19812_03-nuntius">
              <speaker>N.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e124650">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124660">As willing to relate as you to hear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124670">A full-charged heart is glad to find an ear. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124680">The council being dismissed from hence, and gone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124690">Still Craterus plies the King, still in his ear,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124700">Still whispering to him privately alone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124710">Urging it seemed a quick dispatch of fear:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124720">For they who speak but privately to Kings,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124730">Do seldom speak the best and fittest things. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124740">Some would have had him forthwith stoned to death. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124750">According to the Macedonian course:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124760">But yet that would not satisfy the breath</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124770">Of busy rumour; but would argue force,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124780">There must be some confessions made within,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124790">That must abroad more satisfaction win. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124800">Craterus with Caenus and Ephestion,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124810">Do mainly urge to have him tortured,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124820"><pb facs="107"/> whereto the King consents, and there upon</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124830">They three are sent to see't accomplished. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124840">Racks, irons, fires, the grisly torturers</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124850">Stand hideously prepared before his face. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124860">Philotas all unmoved, unchanged appears,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124870">As if● he would, deaths ugliest brow outface,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124880">And scorned the worst of force, and asked them why</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124890">They stayed to torture the King's enemy. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e124900" who="A19812_03-chorus">
              <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e124910">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124920">That part was acted well, God grant we hear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124930">No worse a scene then this, and all goes clear. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124940">So should worth act, and they who dare to fight</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124950">Against corrupted times should die upright:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124960">Such heart's Kings may dissolve but not defeat,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124970">A great man where he falls he should lie great</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124980">Whose ruin (Like the sacred carcasses</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e124990">Of scattered temples which still reverent lie,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125000">And the religious honour them no less</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125010">Than if they stood in all their gallantry. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125020">But on with thy report. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e125030" who="A19812_03-nuntius">
              <speaker>Nuntius</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e125040">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125050">Straight were hot-ironss applied to sear his flesh,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125060">Then wresting racks, his comely body strain:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125070">Then iron whips and then the rack afresh,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125080">Then fire again, and then the whips again:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125090">Which he endures with so resolved a look</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125100">As if his mind were of another side</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125110">Then of his body, and his sense for sooke</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125120">The part of nature, to be wholly tied</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125130">To honour, that he would not once consent</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125140">So much as with a sight 'His punishment. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e125150" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e125160">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125170">Yet doth he like himself yet all is well. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125180"><pb facs="108"/>This argument no tyrant can refel,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125190">This plea of resolution wins his cause</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125200">More right than all, more admiration draws,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125210">For we love nothing more than to renown</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125220">Men stoutly miserable, highly down. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e125230" who="A19812_03-nuntius">
              <speaker>N.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e125240">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125250">But now. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e125260" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e125270">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125280">We fear that but. O if he ought descend</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125290">Leave here, and let the tragedy here end,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125300">Let not the least act now of his at last,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125310">Mar all his act of life and glories past. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e125320" who="A19812_03-nuntius">
              <speaker>Nuntius</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e125330">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125340">I must tell all, and therefore give nigh leave,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125350">Swollen with raw tumours, ulcered with the jerks</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125360">Of iron whips, that flesh from bone had razed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125370">And no part free from wounds; it irks</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125380">His soul to see the house so foul defaced,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125390">Wherein his life had dwelled so long time clean,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125400">And therefore craves he, they would now dismiss</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125410">His grievous tortures, and he would begin</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125420">To open all wherein he'd done amiss. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125430">Straight were his tortures ceased, and after they</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125440">Had let him to recover sense he said,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125450">Now Craterus say, what you will have me say? </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125460">Wherewith as if deluded, or delayed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125470">Cratetus in wrath calls presently again,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125480">To have the tortures to be reapplied. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125490">When whatsoever secret of his heart</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125500">Which had been foreconceived but in a thought</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125510">What friend soever had but took his part</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125520">In common love h'accused; and so forgotten</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125530">Himself that now he was more forward to</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125540"><pb facs="108"/> confess, than they to urge him thereunto,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125550">Whether affliction had his spirits undone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125560">Or seeing to hide or utter was all one;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125570">Both ways lay death, and therefore he would vie</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125580">Now to be sure to say enough to die. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e125590">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125600">And then began his fortunes to deplore</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125610">Humbly besought them, whom he scorned before,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125620">That Alexander where he stood behind</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125630">A Travers, out of sight, was heard to speak:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125640">I never thought a man that had a mind</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125650">T'attempt so much, had had a heart so weak. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e125660">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125670">There he confessed that one Hegelochus,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125680">When first the King proclaimed himself Jove's son:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125690">Incensed his father's heart against him thus,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125700">By telling him that now we were undone,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125710">If we endured, that he which did disdain</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125720">To have been Philip's son, should live and reign. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125730">He that above the state of man will strain</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125740">His style, and will not be that which we are,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125750">Not only us contemns, but doth disdain</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125760">The gods themselves, with whom he would compare,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125770">We have lost Alexander, lost (Said he)</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125780">The King; and fallen on pride and vanity:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125790">And we have made a god of our own blood,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125800">That glorifies himself, neglects our good. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125810">Intolerable is this impious deed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125820">To gods, whom he would match, to men he would exceed. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e125830">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125840">Thus having overnight Hegelochus</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125850">Discoursed: my father sends next day</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125860">For me to hear the same: and there to us</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125870"><pb facs="109"/> all he had said to him made him resay. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125880">Supposing out of wine the night before</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125890">He might but idly rave. When he again</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125900">Far more enraged; in heat and passion more</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125910">Urged us to clear the state of such a stain. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125920">Conjured us to redeem the commonweal</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125930">And do like men, or else as men conceal. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e125940">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125950">Parmenio thought whilst yet Darius stood</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125960">This course was out of season; and thereby</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125970">Th'extinguishing of Alexander's blood</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125980">Would now not profit us, but th'enemy. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e125990">But he once dead; we seizing th'other's powers</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126000">Might make all th' orient, and all Asia ours,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126010">That course we liked, to that our council stands,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126020">Thereto we tied our oaths, and gave our hands. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126030">And as for this, he said, for Dymnus' plot,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126040">Though he were clear yet now it cleared him not. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126050">And yet the force of racks at last could do</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126060">So much with him, as he confessed that too. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126070">And said that fearing Bactra would detain</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126080">The King too long, he hastened on his ends,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126090">Lest that his father, lord of such a train</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126100">And such a wealth, an whom the whole depends,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126110">Should being aged, by his death prevent</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126120">These his designs, and frustrate his intent. <note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A19812_03-e126130">dum inficiatus eft facinus crudeliter torquerividebatur post confession Philotas ne amicorü guid● misericordiam meruit.</note></l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e126140" who="A19812_03-chorus">
              <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e126150">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126160">O would we had not heard this latter jar,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126170">This all his former strains of worth doth mar:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126180">Before this last his foes his spirit commends,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126190">But now he is unpitied of his friends. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e126200" who="A19812_03-nuntius">
              <speaker>Nuntius</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e126210">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126220">Then was Demetrius likewise brought in place,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126230"><pb facs="109"/> and put to torture, who denies the deed,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126240">Philotas he avers it to his face. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126250">Demetrius still denies: than he espied</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126260">A youth one calm that was standing by;</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126270">Calin said he, how long wilt thou abide,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126280">Demetrius vainly to avouch a lie. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e126290">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126300">The youth, that never had been named before</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126310">In all his tortures, gave them cause to guess</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126320">Philotas cared not now to utter more</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126330">Than had been privy to his practises. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126340">And seeing they had as much as they desired,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126350">They with Demetrius stoned him unto death,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126360">And all whom Dymnus named to have conspired,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126370">With grievous tortures now must lose their breath:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126380">And all that were allied which could not fly,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126390">Are in the hands of justice now to die. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e126400" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e126410">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126420">What must the punishment arrive beyond</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126430">Th' offence, not with th'offender make an end? </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e126440" who="A19812_03-nuntius">
              <speaker>Nuntius</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e126450">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126460">They all must die who may be feared in time</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126470">To be the heirs unto their kindred's crime,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126480">All other punishments end with our breath,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126490">But treason is pursued beyond our death,</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A19812_03-e126500" who="A19812_03-chalisthenes">
              <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
              <lg xml:id="A19812_03-e126510">
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126520">The wrath of Kings doth seldom measure keep,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126530">Seeking to cure bad parts they lance too deep:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126540">When punishment like lightning should appear</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126550">To few men's hurt, but unto all men's fear. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126560">Great elephants, and lion's murder least,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126570">Th' ignoble beast is the most cruel beast,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126580">But all is well if by the mighty fall</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126590">Of this great man, the King be safely freed:</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126600"><pb facs="110"/> but if this Hydra of ambition shall</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126610">Have other heads, to spring up in his stead</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126620">Then hath he made but way for them to rise,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126630">Who will assault him with fresh treacheries. </l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126640">The which may teach us to observe this strain,</l>
                <l xml:id="A19812_03-e126650">T'admire high hills, but live within the plains</l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer xml:id="A19812_03-e126660">Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="110"/>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A19812_03"><item xml:id="A19812_03-philotas" n="39">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-philotas</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">39</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-craterus" n="26">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-craterus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">26</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-alexander" n="20">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-alexander</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">20</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-antigona" n="19">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-antigona</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">19</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-chalisthenes" n="17">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-chalisthenes</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">17</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-thais" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-thais</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-cebalinus" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-cebalinus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-chorus" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-chorus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-sostratus" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-sostratus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-nuntius" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-nuntius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-perdicas" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-perdicas</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-greek" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-greek</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-ephestion" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-ephestion</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-clitus" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-clitus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-attarus" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-attarus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-unassigned" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-caenus" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-caenus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-guard" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-guard</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A19812_03-polidamus" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-polidamus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-nichomachus" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-nichomachus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-polidamas" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-polidamas</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-mot" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-mot</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-amyntas" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-amyntas</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-servant" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-servant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-bel" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-bel</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A19812_03-metron" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A19812_03-metron</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

