<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>1 Youth's Glory and Death's Banquet<date type="creation_date">1662</date></title>
        <author>Cavendish, Margaret</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nayoon Ahn</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A53060_04.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>356 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">11861873</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing N868.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">50022</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53060</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Playes written by the thrice noble, illustrious and excellent princess, the Lady Marchioness of Newcastle.</title>
            <author>Newcastle, Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of, 1624?-1674.</author>
            <author>Newcastle, William Cavendish, 1592-1676.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[24], 679 [i.e. 675], [4] p. : ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by A. Warren, for John Martyn, James Allestry, and Tho. Dicas ...,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1662.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>First edition.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Errata: p. [4] at end.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A53060_04-e100010">
    <body xml:id="A53060_04-e100020">
      <div n="1" type="play" xml:id="A53060_04-e100030">
        <pb facs="72"/>
        <pb facs="72" n="121"/>
        <div type="prologue" xml:id="A53060_04-e100040">
          <head>Prologue.</head>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100050">The poetress says, that if the play be bad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100060">She's very sorry, and could wish she had</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100070">A better plot, more wit and skill to make</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100080">A play that might each several humour take;</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100090">But she says, if your humours are not fixed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100100">Or that they are extravagantly mixed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100110">Impossible a play for to present</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100120">With such variety, and temperament;</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100130">But some will think it tedious, or find fault,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100140">Say the design or language is stark naught;</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100150">Besides, the loose unsettled brains, she fears</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100160">Seeth with squint eyes, and hears with asses ears;</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100170">But she is confident all in this round,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100180">Their understandings clear, and judgements sound;</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100190">And if her play deserves not praise, she knows</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100200">They'll neither scoff in words, nor preposterous shows:</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100210">Without disturbance, you will let it die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A53060_04-e100220">And in the grave of silence let it lie. </l>
        </div>
        <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A53060_04-e100230">
          <pb facs="73" n="122"/>
          <head>Youths glory, and death's banquet.</head>
          <head type="sub">The first part.</head>
          <list xml:id="A53060_04-e100240">
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100250">1. The lord de l'amour. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100260">2. Sir Thomas father love. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100270">3. Master comfort, sir Thomas father loves friend. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100280">4. Master charity, the lord de L'amour's friend. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100290">5. Adviser, the lord de L'amour's man. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100300">6. A justice of peace. </item>
          </list>
          <list xml:id="A53060_04-e100310">
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100320">1. The Queen attention. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100330">2. The lady incontinent, mistress to the lord de l'amour. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100340">3. The lady mother love, wife to sir Thomas father love. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100350">4. The lady Sanparelle, daughter to sir Thomas father, and lady mother love. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100360">5. The lady innocence, the affianced mistress or wife to the lord de l'amour. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100370">6. Passive, the lady Innocence's maid:</item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100380">7. Falsehood, an informer to maids of the lady incontinent. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100390">Physicians. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100400">Natural philosophers, moral philosophers, young students. </item>
            <item xml:id="A53060_04-e100410">Soldiers, lovers, mourners, virgins, servants and others. </item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A53060_04-e100420">
          <pb facs="73" n="123"/>
          <head>Act i.</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e100430">
            <head>Scene 1.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e100440">Enter sir Thomas father love, and his wife, the mother lady love.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100450" who="A53060_04-mother_love">
              <speaker>Mother love,</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100460">Husband, you have a strange nature, that having but one child, and never like to have more, and this your child a daughter; that you should breed her so strictly, as to give her no time for recreation, nor no liberty for company, nor freedom for conversation, but keeps her as a prisoner, and makes her a slave to her book, and your tedious moral discourses, when other children have playfellows, and toys to sport and pass their time withal.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100470" who="A53060_04-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100480">Good wife be content, doth not she play when she reads books of poetry, and can there be nobler, amiabler, finer, usefuller, and wiser companions than the sciences, or pleasanter playfellows than the muses; can she have freer conversation, than with wit, or more various recreations than scenes, sonnets and poems; tragical, comical, and musical, and the like; or have prettier toys to sport withal, than fancy, and hath not the liberty so many hours in the day, as children have to play in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100490" who="A53060_04-mother_love">
              <speaker>Mother love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100500">Do you call this playing? which sets her brain a working to find out the conceits, when perchance there is none to find out, but are cheats, and cozens the readers with empty words, at best, it fills her head but with strange phantasms, disturbs her sleep with frightful dreams of transformed bodies of monsters, and ugly shaped vices of hells and furies, and terrifying gods of wars and battles, of long travels, and dangerous escapes, and the pleasantest is but dark groves, gloomy fields, and the happiest condition; but to walk idly about the Elysium fields; and thus you breed your daughter, as if your posterity were to be raised from a poet's fantastical brain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100510" who="A53060_04-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100520">I wish my posterity may last but as long as Homer's lines.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100530" who="A53060_04-mother_love">
              <speaker>Mother love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100540">Truly, it will be a fine airy brood! No no, I will have her bred, as to make a good housewife, as to know how to order her family, breed her children, govern her servants, entertain her neighbours, and to fashion herself to all companies, times and places, and not to be mewed and moped up, as she is from all the world, insomuch, as she never saw twenty persons in one company in all her life, unless it be in pictures, which you set her to stare on above an hour everyday: besides, what father doth educate their daughters, that office belongs to me; but because you have never a son to tutor, therefore you will turn cotquean, and teach your daughter, which is my work.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100550" who="A53060_04-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100560">Let me tell you, wife, that is the reason all women are fools; for women breeding up women, one fool breeding up another, and as long as that custom lasts there is no hopes of amendment, and ancient customs<pb facs="74" n="124"/> being a second nature, makes folly hereditary in that sex, by reason their education is effeminate, and their times spent in pins, points and laces, their study only vain fashions, which breeds prodigality, pride and envy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100570" who="A53060_04-mother_love">
              <speaker>Mother love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100580">What? would you have women bred up to swear, swagger, gaming, drinking, whoring, as most men are?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100590" who="A53060_04-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100600">No, wife, I would have them bred in learned schools, to noble arts and sciences, as wise men are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100610" who="A53060_04-mother_love">
              <speaker>Mother love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100620">What arts? to ride horses, and fight duels.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100630" who="A53060_04-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100640">Yes, if it be to defend their honour, country and religion; for noble arts makes not base vices, nor is the cause of lewd actions, nor is unseemly for any sex; but baseness, vice and lewdness, invents unhandsome and undecent arts, which dishonours by the practice either sex.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100650" who="A53060_04-mother_love">
              <speaker>Mother love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100660">Come, come, husband, I will have her bred, as usually our sex is, and not after a new fashioned way, created out of a self-opinionated, that you can alter nature by education: no, no, let me tell you, a woman will be a woman, do what you can, and you may as soon create a new world, as change a woman's nature and disposition.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e100670">Enter the lady sanspareille, as to her father, as not thinking her mother was there. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100680" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sanspareille.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100690">O, father! I have been in search of you, to ask you a question concerning the sun.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e100700">When she sees her mother, she starts back.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100710" who="A53060_04-mother">
              <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100720">What have you to do with the sun, and lives in the shade of the world's obscurity.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100730" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100740">Why, madam? where would you have me live? can I live in a more serene air, than in my father's house, or in a purer, or clearer light, than in my parents eyes, or more splendorous, than in my parent's company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100750" who="A53060_04-mother">
              <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100760">I would have you live at court there, to have honour, favour and grace; and not to lose your time ignorantly, knowing nothing of the world, nor the world of you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100770" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100780">Can I live with more honour, than with my father, and you, or have more favour than your loves; or is there a greater grace, than to be daughter of virtuous parents; can I use, or employ my time better, than to obey my parents commands? need I know more than honesty, modesty, civility and duty: as for the world, mankind is so partial to each self, as they have no faith on the worth of their neighbour, neither doth they take notice of a stranger, but to be taken notice of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100790" who="A53060_04-mother_love">
              <speaker>Mother love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100800">Yes, yes, your beauty will attract eyes and ears, which are the doors to let in good opinion, and admiration.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100810" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100820">Had I a tongue like a circes-wand to charm all ears that heard me, it would straight transform men from civil obligers, to spiteful detractors, or false slanderers; my beauty may only serve but as a bribe to tempt men, to entrap my youth, and to betray my innocency.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100830" who="A53060_04-mother">
              <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100840">To betray a fools-head of your own! Lord! Lord! how the<pb facs="74" n="125"/> dispositions of youth is changed since I was young! for before I came to your age, I thought my parents unnatural, because they did not provide me a husband.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100850" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sanspareille.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100860">If all youth were of my humour, their dispositions are changed indeed; for heaven knows, it is the only curse I fear, a husband.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100870" who="A53060_04-mother_love">
              <speaker>Mother love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100880">Why? than you think me cursed in marrying your father.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100890" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100900">No madam, you are blessed, not only in being a wife, (A condition you desired) but being married to such a man that wishes could not hope for.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100910" who="A53060_04-mother_love">
              <speaker>Mother love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100920">Why then, my good fortune may encourage you, and raise a hope to get the like.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100930" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100940">O no! it rather drives me to despair, believing there is no second.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100950" who="A53060_04-mother_love">
              <speaker>Mother love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100960">Come, come, you are an unnatural child to flatter your father so much, and not me, when I endured great pains to breed, bear, and nurse you up.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100970" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e100980">I do not flatter, madam, for I speak nothing but my thoughts, and that which love and duty doth allow, and truth approve of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e100990" who="A53060_04-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101000">Come, come wife, the jeerals wit will out-argue both ours.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e101010">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e101020">
            <head>Scene 2.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e101030">Enter the lord de l' Amour, and the lady incontinent. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101040" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101050">Have I left my husband, who was rich, and used me well? and all for love of you! and with you live as a wanton! by which I have lost my esteem, and my honest reputation, and now to be forsaken, and cast aside, despised and scorned! O, most base! for what can be more unworthy, than for a man to profess friendship to a lady, and then forsake her?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101060" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l' Amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101070">Madam, you do me wrong, for my heart is as firmly yours, as ever it was, and burns with as clear a flame, as ever it did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101080" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101090">It is not like it will continue so, since you now are resolved to marry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101100" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l' Amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101110">The reasons are so powerful, that persuades me, by reason there is none lest of my family besides myself; and my father's commands so terrifying, and my vows so binding, as I know not how to avoid it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101120" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101130">But since your father is dead, what need you fear his commands, and for your vows, those may be dispensed with, for a sum of money to the church for the poor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101140" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l' Amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101150">But would you have me cut off the line of my posterity by never marrying?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101160" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101170">Perchance, if you marry, you may have no children, or your wife may prove barren, or if you have children, they may prove fools; for she you are affianced to, is none of the wisest.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101180" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <pb facs="75" n="126"/>
              <speaker>Lord de l' Amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101190">That is none of my fault.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101200" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101210">But why will you marry so soon?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101220" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l' Amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101230">I will not marry yet, for my affianced is young, and well may stay two or three years.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101240" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101250">But if you will not marry her this two or three years, why must she come to live with you in your house.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101260" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l' Amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101270">By reason her father is newly dead, and hath left her to my protection, as having right to her, and by her, to her estate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101280" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101290">And when she comes, I must deliver up the rule and government of your house and family to her; for I suppose you will make her the mistress to command, dispose and order as she pleaseth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101300" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l' Amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101310">By no means, for you that are the mistress of my heart, shall also be mistress of my estate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101320" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101330">Then pray give her to my charge and education; for I hear she is of a high spirit, and a proud heart, being spoilt with self-will, given her by the fondness of her father.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101340" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l' Amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101350">Pray order her as you think good, she shall be your handmaid.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e101360">Exeunt</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e101370">
            <head>Scene 3.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e101380">Enter the lady sanspareille, repeating some verses of her own making. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101390" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sanspareille.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e101400">Here flows a sea, and there a sire doth flame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e101410">Yet water and fire still is but the same:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e101420">Here the sixth earth, and there the air streams out,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e101430">All of one matter moving round about;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e101440">And thus the earth, and water, sire and air,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e101450">Out of each others shapes transformed are. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e101460">Enters her mother, and hears her last verse.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101470" who="A53060_04-mother">
              <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101480">I am sure you are transformed from what you should be, from a sober, young maid, to a stage-player, as to act parts, speak speeches, rehearse verses, sing sonnets, and the like,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101490" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101500">Why, madam; stages and public theatres, were first ordained and built, for the education of noble youth, where they might meet to practise how to behave themselves civilly, modestly, gently, comely, gracefully, manly, and majestically; to speak properly, timely, fitly, eloquently, elegantly, tunably, tonably, readily, sagely, wittily. Besides, theaters were not only schools to learn or practise in, but public patterns to take example from; thus theatres were profitable, both to the actors and spectators; for as these theatres were public schools, where noble principles were taught, so it was the dressing rooms of virtue, where the actors, as her servants did help to set her forth. Also these theatres were as scaffolds, whereon vices were publicly executed; and, madam, if you please but to consider,<pb facs="75" n="127"/> you will perceive, that thrones are but glorious theatres, where Kings and princes, and their courtiers acts their parts; likewise places of judicature, are but places where judges and lawyer's acts their parts; nay, even churches are but holy theatres, where the priest and people acts their devout parts. But, madam, you mistake, making no difference betwixt the noble and base, the generous and mercenary; for, shall all noble persons that fights duels of honour, be called fencers; or shall a King, when he runs at the ring, or tilt, shall he be called a jockey, or post, when he rides horses of manage, shall he be a equerry, or a rider; or shall Kings, princes or noble persons, that dances, sings, or plays on music, or presents themselves in masks, be thought, or called dancers, or fiddlers, morris-dancers, stage-players, or the like, as in their masking attire: no those are riders, fencers, dancers, fiddlers, stage-players, and the like, that are mercenary, setting vertuosus to sale, making a mercenary profit, and living thereof; but if such opinions should be held, then no vertuosus should be learned of noble persons, because there are mercenary tutors and teachers, nor no arts understood, because of mechanics, nor no sciences understood, because of pedants, nor no manners, nor graceful behaviours practised because of players, nor none must write, because of clerks, nor none must pray because of beneficed priests, nor there must none understand the laws, or plead their own causes, because of feed lawyers; if these opinions or rules were followed, all the nobler and better sort, would be boars, clowns and fools, nor no civility, good manners, nor virtues would be known amongst them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101510" who="A53060_04-mother">
              <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101520">Well, well, I will have you show yourself, and be known, and I known by you; for why should not I be as ambitious to be praised in your beauty, as your father in your wit; but by that time you have gotten a sufficient stock of wit to divulge to the world, your beauty will be dead and buried, and so my ruins will have no restoration, or resurrection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101530" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101540">Madam, I do humbly and dutifully acknowledge, that what beauty or wit I have, it was derived from my parents.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101550" who="A53060_04-mother">
              <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101560">Wherefore you ought to do, as your parents will have you, and I say, I will have you be a courtier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101570" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101580">Would you have me go to live at the court, madam?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101590" who="A53060_04-mother">
              <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101600">Yes marry would I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101610" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101620">And to do as courtiers do?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101630" who="A53060_04-mother">
              <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101640">Yes marry would I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101650" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101660">Alas, madam, I am unpractised in their arts, and shall be lost in their subtle and strange ways.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101670" who="A53060_04-mother">
              <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101680">Therefore I would have you go to learn them, that you may be as expert as the best of them, for I would have you shoot such sharp darts through your eyes, as may wound the hardest and obduratest hearts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101690" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101700">Amorous affections, madam, and wanton glances are strangers to my eyes and heart; neither can I persuade nor command them to be otherwise than they are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101710" who="A53060_04-mother">
              <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101720">Why, I would not have you either wanton, or amorous, but to be kind and civil, to invite a rich, noble husband.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101730" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101740">Why, say I had the power to pick and choose amongst the noblest and the richest men, a husband out, you cannot promise me a happy life, fortune may set a crown of diamonds on my head, yet prick my heart with thorns, bind up my spirits with strong chained fears, my thoughts imprisoned in dark melancholy, and thus my mind may prove<pb facs="76" n="128"/> a hell unto my life, and my husband's actions devils to torment it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101750" who="A53060_04-mother">
              <speaker>Mother.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101760">No disputing, but let my will be obeyed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101770" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101780">It is fit it should be by me, although it brings my ruin.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e101790">Lady mother goes out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e101800">Sanspareille alone.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101810" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sanspareille.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e101820">Joy gave me wings, and made my spirits fly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e101830">Hope gave me strength to set ambition high;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e101840">Fear makes me old, as palsy shakes each limb,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e101850">My body weak, and both my eyes are dim:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e101860">Like to a ball, which rackets beats about,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e101870">So is my heart strucken twixt hope and doubt. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e101880">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e101890">
            <head>Scene 4.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e101900">Enter the lady incontinent, and one of her women. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101910" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101920">I observe, the lord de l'amour useth the lady innocence with more respect than he was used to do; and I observe his eyes meets her when she comes in place where he is, and follows her wheresoever she goeth, and when she stands still, they are sixth upon her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101930" who="A53060_04-woman">
              <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101940">Truly she hath power, if she will put it in force to command a heart, at least to persuade a heart to love her; for certainly, she is very beautiful, if it were not obscured under a sad countenance, as the sun behind a dark cloud; but sometimes, do what she can in despite of her sadness, it will keep out, and the other day when you were gone abroad, I saw her dance, sing and play on a Gitturn, all at one time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101950" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101960">And how did it become her?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101970" who="A53060_04-woman">
              <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e101980">Truly, she sung so sweetly, played so harmoniously, danced so gracefully, and looked so beautifully, that if I had been a man, I should have been in love with her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e101990" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102000">I charge you break her guitar, tell her she sings not well, and that her dancing doth ill-become her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102010" who="A53060_04-woman">
              <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102020">Perchance she will not believe me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102030" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102040">O yes, for youth are credulous, even against themselves.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e102050">Exeunt.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A53060_04-e102060">
          <pb facs="76" n="129"/>
          <head>Act ii.</head>
          <div n="5" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e102070">
            <head>Scene 5.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e102080">Enter the lady sanspareille, and walks a turn or two, as contemplating. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102090" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sanspareille.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e102100">Ambitious thoughts flies high, yet never tires,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e102110">Winged with the swiftest thoughts of desires;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e102120">Then thoughts of hopes runs busily about,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e102130">Yet oft are stopped with thoughts of fear and doubt,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e102140">And thoughts of mirth and melancholy strives,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e102150">All thoughts are restless till the body dies. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e102160">Enter sir father love.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102170" who="A53060_04-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102180">My child, it is a sign you are melancholy, that you are in a poetical vain.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e102190">She weeps.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102200" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102210">Why do you weep?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102220" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102230">Melancholy thoughts makes tears to flow through my eyes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102240" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102250">Melancholy! why, thou art not come to the years of melancholy; 'tis aged brows on which sad Saturn sets, and tired thoughts on which he reigns, and on grieved heart his heavy taxes lays; but those that are young, he leaves to other powers, neither hath fortune set her turning foot upon thy head, for thou art in the same worldly condition that thou wert born to; wherefore thy mind may be quiet, and thy thoughts merry and free.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102260" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102270">Surely, sir, it is not always age, nor yet cross fortunes that clouds the mind, for some are old and mean, poor and despised, yet merry, and humours gay, and some are young and fairer, and rich, and well esteemed, honoured and loved, and yet their thoughts dejectedly doth move, and humour dull as lead; 'tis nature makes melancholy, neither age nor evil fortune brings it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102280" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102290">But what makes thee sad, my child?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102300" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102310">Ambition, sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102320" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102330">What doth your ambition aim at? If it be honour, I have an estate will buy thee an honourable husband; if it be riches, I will be saving, and live thriftily, if it be gallantry, or bravery, I will maintain thee at the height of my fortune, wear frieze myself, and adorn thee in diamonds, silver and gold.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102340" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sanspareille.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102350">Heaven forbid! that my vanity should prodigally spend your estate, or my covetousness pinch and starve your life, or that my pride should be matched with noble honour, which should be as humble as great.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102360" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102370">It cannot be for wit and beauty, for, surely nature hath made herself poor, by giving you so much.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102380" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <pb facs="77" n="130"/>
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102390">My dear father, know it is fame I covet, for which were the ambitions of Alexander and Caesar joined into one mind, mine doth exceed them, as far as theirs exceeded humble spirits, my mind being restless to get the highest place in fame's high tower; and I had rather fall in the adventure, than never try to climb; wherefore, it is not titled honour, nor wealth, nor bravery, nor beauty, nor wit that I covet, but as they do contribute to adorn merit, which merit is the only foundation whereon is built a glorious fame, where noble actions is the architectour thereof, which makes me despairingly melancholy, having not a sufficient stock of merit, or if I had, yet no ways to advance it; but I must die like beasts, forgotten of mankind, and be buried in oblivion's grave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102400" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102410">If it be fame my child covets, it is a noble ambition; and heaven pardon me, if I speak vaingloriously of what is my own, yet I speak but my opinion, when I say, I do believe there is none so fit to raise a fame, as thou art.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102420" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102430">Sir, your love speaks, as willing to encourage me; but know sir; it is not a vulgar fame I covet, for those that goeth with equal space, and even heights, are soon lost, as in a crowd or multitude; but when fame is enthroned, all ages gazes at it; and being thus supremely placed up high; like as an idol, gets idolatry: thus singularity as well as merit, advances fame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102440" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102450">Child, thou speakest always reason, and were my life the only singular way to raise thy fame, thou shouldst have it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102460" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102470">Heaven forbid! For that would raise my infamy, if I should build upon my father's noble life. But, sir, do you love me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102480" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102490">Yes, above my life! for thou art the life of my life!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102500" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102510">Do you love me as well as you think you could your grandchildren?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102520" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102530">No comparison can be made, for thou art come immediately from my loins, those but from the joins of my issue, which is estranged from me, and for their affections, grandchildren's is but weak, only they keep alive my name, not love, for that dies in the second descent, and many times the first.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102540" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102550">But, sir; would not you think me strangely unnatural, and unworthy of your love, to wish or desire you to break the line of your posterity, and bury succession in my grave?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102560" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102570">Unnatural! no, for your virtue can ask nothing of me, that my love will think unreasonable to give, and for my posterity, I had rather it should end with merit, than run on in follies; or who knows but their evil or base actions may blemish all their predecessors; besides, it is with succession, as with a married pair; for if the wife be chaste, the world will give the honour only to the woman, but if she be false, the world will lay the disgrace on the husband, and think she sees some defect, which makes her prefer another before him. So in succession, if their succession proves fools, cowards, avaricious, treacherous, vicious, or the like, the world straight judges these imperfections and vices were in hereditary, and that they were attaint, or stained from the root or stock, but if they prove wise, valiant, generous, just, or the like, they think they were particular gifts of nature, or education, thus the faults of succession many descents after, may darken like black clouds, the bright light of their predecessors worth and merit; besides, there is no certainty of a continued line, nor doth many children give an assurance to their father at the day of his death; for when he dies, doubts closes his<pb facs="77" n="131"/> eyes, and fears blows out life's fire, therefore I had rather live in thy fame, than live or die in an infamous and foolish succession.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102580" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102590">Heaven make me thankful that my desires and my father's approvement agrees. Sir, you have not only bred me with a tender love, but with a prudent industry. And I have followed your instruction with a religious ceremony. Kept to your principles with a pious conscience, and since nature and education hath joined together in my tender years, to make my life propitious; if fortune favour me, and opportunity promote me; but we are to consider which way I shall steer the course of my life, and if you will please I will tell you how I have designed my voyage.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102600" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102610">Heaven prosper thee through it, and send the a safe passage, wheresoever thou adventurest.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102620" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102630">Then first, it is to be considered, I am but a small and weak vessel, and cannot swim upon the rough and boisterous seas, which are pitched fields, and fighting armies, wherein I shall be shattered in the crowd, and drowned in the confusion of disorder, wherefore I must swim in the calm rivers of peace where their is no such storms, nor high billows, only some cross winds may chance to rise, which may hinder me but not drown me; this calm river is a theater, and the rough sea as I said a pitched field; myself the ship, you the steerage, and fame the port, then thus I will relate how I have designed the voyage of my life; first never to marry, if I may have your consent to live a single life, for that time which will be lost in a married condition, I will study and work with my own thoughts, and what new inventions they can find out, or what probabilities they conceive, or fancies they create, I will publish to the world in print before I make them common by discourse, but if I marry, although I should have time for my thoughts and contemplations, yet perchance my husband will not approve of my works, were they never so worthy, and by no persuasion, or reason allow of there publishing; as if it were unlawful, or against nature, for women to have wit. And strives always if their wives have wit, to obscure it. And I am of that opinion, that some men are so inconsiderately wise, gravely foolish and lowly base, as they had rather be thought cuckolds, than their wives should be thought wits, for fear the world should think their wise, the wiser of the two; and that she rules, and governs all the affairs at home; for most men, rather than they will not show their power, and authority, will appear a quat-queen, that is an effeminate scold. Secondly, I will not receive, nor give private visits, or entertainments; but from those, and to those, that duty, and gratitude and loyalty enjoins me; for in private visits, or entertainments, is only so much time stuffed with senseless, vain, idle, light discourses, or flattering compliments, wherein time and life is unprofitably lost. Thirdly, I would never speak but in public, for if nature, and education, have given me wit, I would not willingly bury it in private discourses; besides, private hearers are secret thieves, and boldly steals, having no witnesses, to betray, or reveal the truth, or divulge their thefts; and so they will adorn their discourses with my wit, which they steal from me. Fourthly, I will never speak of any considerable matter, or subject, or of any new conception; but I will have them ready writ to print them, so soon as my discourse of them is past, or else print them before I discourse of them; and afterwards explain them by my tongue, as well as by my pen, lest they should mistake the sense of my works, through ignorance; for those subject; that are only discoursed off, in speech, flies away in words; which vanisheth as smoke, or<pb facs="78" n="132"/> shadows, and the memory or remembrance of the author, or orator, melts away as oil, leaving no sign in present life, or else moulders as dust, leaving no monument to after-posterity, to be known or remembered by; when writing, or printing, fixes it to everlasting time, to the public view of the world; besides, a passing discourse makes the tongue, but as an almoner, to give wit to poor sharks to feed them; which sharks eats, without giving praise or thanks, never acknowledging at whose cost they live at: nay, so unthankful they are, that they will bely the authors and themselves; saying, it was their own; and it is a certain rule, that those authors they steal most from, they will dispraise, and rail most at: and some are so foolish, and of such short memories, that they will repeat the author's wit, to the author's self; and as confident, as it had been created, or invented, out of their own brains. Fifthly, I will select times, for several discourses and subjects, to discourse in public, to several audiences; to which, you may, if you please, invite the grave and wise, to hear me, and being a woman orator, the singularity will advance my fame the more; besides, many accidents may we chance to meet, which may prove as steps to ascend, or mount up. Thus sir, if you please to approve of my design, I shall follow the means, or ways unto it; if not, I shall submit to what you shall think will be better for me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102640" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102650">I do approve of your design so well, as I cannot but admire it. And I believe the best designer that ever was, never cast such a mould, or laid such a plot, or drew such a draught, to raise a fame on; or to work a fame out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102660" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102670">But sir, you must arm yourself against all oppositions, and baracodo your ears against all cross persuaders; and muster your forces of hopes, drawing them into a body of confidence, and march with a resolution, either to die in the adventure, or to triumph with victory, and to live everlastingly, in a glorious fame; for sir, we shall meet wranglers, and jesters, scorners, and scoffers, disputers, and opposers, contradictors and liars; which envy and malice will bring against us, but consider sir, that when the foot of fame hath trod upon the tongue of envy, it will be silent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102680" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102690">Never fear me child, if thou faintest not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102700" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102710">I fear not myself, for I have an undoubted faith, that the child of such a father can neither be a coward, nor a fool; for from you I receive a value or prize, although of myself I should be worth nothing; and parents and children may speak freely their thoughts, let them move which way they will, for children ought not to conceal them; but if deceit must be used: let it be with strangers not friends.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102720" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102730">O child! thou hast spoke but what I thought on, and the very same I wished; finding thy tongue volable, thy voice tuneable, thy speech eloquent, thy wit quick, thy expressions easy, thy conceits and conceptions new, thy fancies curious and fine, thy inventions subtle, thy dispositions sweet and gentle, thy behaviour graceful, thy countenance modest, thy person beautiful, thy years young; all this I thought to myself might raise the a trophy, when a husband would bury thee in his arms; and so thou to become thy own fame's tomb.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102740" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102750">Oh! but how shall we pacify my mother, who is resolved not to be quiet, until I go to live at the court; as likewise to marry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102760" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102770">I have thought of that, and you know that your mother is well bred, a tender mother and a chaste wife; yet she is violent, and is not to be altered from her opinions, humours, and will, till time wearies her out of<pb facs="78" n="133"/> them, wherefore we must not oppose her; but rather soothe her in her humour, and for marrying, we will always find some fault in the man, or his estate, person or breeding, or his humour; or his wit, prudence, temperance, courage, or conduct, or the like, which we may truly do without dissembling; for I believe there is no man, but that some exceptions may be justly found to speak against him; but you and I will sit in council about it.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e102780">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="6" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e102790">
            <head>Scene 6.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e102800">Enter the lord de l' Amour, and meets the lady innocence.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102810" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l' Amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102820">Well met, for if accident had not befriended me, you would not have been so kind as to have met me; for I perceive you strived to shun me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102830" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102840">The reason is, I was afraid my presence would not be acceptable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102850" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l' Amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102860">You never stay to try whether it would or not, but surely if your conversation be answerable to your beauty, your company cannot but be pleasing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102870" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102880">I doubt I am too young to be handsome, for time hath not shaped me yet into a perfect form, for nature hath but laid the draught, and mixed the colours, for time to work with, which he as yet hath neither placed, nor drawn them right, so that beauty in me is not as yet fully finished; and as my beauty, so I doubt my wit, is imperfect, and the ignorance of youth makes a discord in discourse, being not so experiencedly learned, nor artificially practised, as to speak harmoniously, where the want makes my conversation dull with circumspection and fear; which makes my words flow through my lips, like lead, heavy and slow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102890" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l' Amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102900">Thy wit sounds as thy beauty appears, the one charms the ears, the other attracts the eyes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102910" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102920">You have been more bountiful to me in your praises, than nature in her gifts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102930" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l' Amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e102940">Since I perceive you to be so pleasing, we will be better acquainted.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e102950">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="7" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e102960">
            <pb facs="79" n="134"/>
            <head>Scene 7.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e102970">Enter 2. or 3. Philosophers. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e102980">This scene of the philosophers the lord marquess writ.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e102990" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103000">Come my learned brothers, are we come now to hear a girl to read lectures of natural philosophy to teach us? Are all our studies come to this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103010" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103020">Her doting father is to blame, he should be punished for this great affront, to us that's learned men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103030" who="A53060_04-yyyy_3">
              <speaker>3. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103040">Philosopher's should be men of years, with grave and austere looks, whose countenances should like rigid laws affright men from vanities; with long wise beards, sprinkled with grey, that every hair might teach, the bare young chins for to obey. And every sentence to be delivered like the law, in flames and lightning, and flashes with great thunder, a foolish girl to offer for to read: oh times! O manners!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103050" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103060">Beauty and favour and tender years, a female which nature hath denied hair on her chin, so smooth her brow, as not to admit one philosophical wrinkle, and she to teach, a monster 'tis in nature; since nature hath denied that sex that fortitude of brain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103070" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103080">Counsel her father that her mother may instruct her in high housewifry, as milking kine, as making cheese, churning butter, and raising past, and to preserve confectionary, and to teach her the use of her needle, and to get her a husband; and then to practise natural philosophy without a lecture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103090" who="A53060_04-yyyy_3">
              <speaker>3. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103100">'Tis a prodigious thing, a girl to read philosophy; oh divine Plato! how thy soul will now be troubled, Diogenes repents his tub, and Seneca will burn his books in anger. And old Aristotle wish he had never been the master of all schools, now to be taught, and by a girl.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103110" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103120">Have patience and but hear her, and then we shall have matter store to speak and write against her, and to pull down her fame; indeed her very lecture will disgrace her more than we can write, and be revenged thus by her tongue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103130" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103140">Content, let us then go and hear her, for our sport, not being worth our anger.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103150">Ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103160">Here ends the lord marquess of Newcastle.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A53060_04-e103170">
          <pb facs="79" n="135"/>
          <head>Act iii.</head>
          <div n="8" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e103180">
            <head>Scene 8.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103190">Enter the lady innocence and her maid. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103200" who="A53060_04-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103210">By my truth mistress the lord de l' Amour is a fine person.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103220" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103230">The truth is, that he seems as if nature had given to time the finest and richest stuff in her shop, to make his person off, and time as the tailor hath wrought and shaped his person into the most becoming fashion; but yet, if his soul be not answerable to his person, he is fine no otherways; but as a fashionable and gay suit of cloth on a deformed body, the clothes may be fine and handsome, but the body ill favoured; so the body may be handsome, but the soul a foul deformed creature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103240" who="A53060_04-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103250">But a fine and handsome body may hide a deformed soul, although a fine suit of clothes will not hide a deformed body; for a deformed body will be perceived in despite of the fine clothes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103260" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103270">So will a deformed soul in the despite of a handsome body, for the soul will appear in the actions, as the body in the shape; being as crooked in vice as the body in limbs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103280" who="A53060_04-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103290">What is the actions of the soul?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103300" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103310">The passions and will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103320" who="A53060_04-maid">
              <speaker>Maid.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103330">But man obscures the passions and restrains the will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103340" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103350">So man may obscure his body, and bombast his clothes; but it is as impossible to restrain an evil will, as to make a crooked body straight.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103360">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="9" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e103370">
            <head>Scene 9.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103380">Enter sir Thomas father love, bringing in the auditors into a large room, nobly furnished, where at one end or side is a place raised and railed with guilt rails; for the lady sanspareille to stand on. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103390" who="A53060_04-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103400">Gentlemen, pray do not think me rude by drawing you from your serious studies, by an intruding invitation; to hear a young student discourse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103410" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103420">'Tis true sir, we should have been glad to have heard you discourse, for you might instruct us, where as a young student is rather to be instructed; for it is time that brings knowledge or gets wit, or speaks eloquently.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103430" who="A53060_04-father_love">
              <speaker>Father love.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103440">'Tis true, but yet in some natural ingenuity it is as strong as time, and produceth that which time of itself could not do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103450" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <pb facs="80" n="136"/>
              <speaker>2. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103460">Sir, if your young student's wit, be as fine as her standing place, it will be delightful.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103470" who="A53060_04-yyyy_3">
              <speaker>3. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103480">Sir, you have adorned her theater to enthrone her wit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103490" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103500">Gentlemen. I wish her wit may furnish, and so adorn your understanding, but if you please to sit, such as it is, shall be presented to you.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103510">Being all placed, the lady sanspereille enters upon the mounted place, dressed all in black; fit for the gravity of the company. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103520">The company upon her entrance seems to be struck with amaze of her beauty, they speak to her father.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103530" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103540">Sir, we perceive now, you have invited us to feast our eyes, not our ears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103550" who="A53060_04-father">
              <speaker>Father.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103560">Gentlemen, if you please to give her so much patience to hear her, than judge, or censure, as you please.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103570">Then they all cry whist, whist.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103580">After the lady by her civil bows had given respect to all the company, with a modest and amiable countenance, with a gentle and well pleased eye, and a graceful and winning behaviour, thus speaks.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103590" who="A53060_04-sanspareile">
              <speaker>Lady Sanspareile.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103600">The majesty of age, and sage gravity, are objects able to put unexperienced and unpractised youth out of countenance; and bashfulness is the greatest enemy to discourse, for it discomposes the countenance, disturbs the thoughts, disorders the words, and confounds the sense therein; but youth hath many times this advantage, that it apprehends not the disgrace, that experienced years and deeper judgement doth; for the truth is, bashfulness proceeds from too great an apprehension; but I not apprehending far enough, may commit errors through a confident ignorance, but if you think my confidence too much, for my youth; yet pray judge not my modesty too little for my sex, for speaking belongs as much to the female sex as to the masculine; so as it be on sober subjects, and to grave fathers, and wise men, or intruth to any degree of age, or sex, or birth; so as it be timely, suitably, rationably, and modestly delivered; and why may not women speak in public and to public assemblies, as well as in private visits, and particular entertainments, and to particular persons and acquaintance? And in reason it should be more commendable, that women's discourse and actions are such, as they fear no witness. Nay, they ought never to speak or show themselves to those persons that are not domestic, without sufficient witness, for private discourses, which are like whisperings, and secret meetings, and particular entertainments, are subject to loose customs, rude behaviours, and lascivious discourses, mischievous designs, and dangerous plots, all which takes leave without warrant, and assaults without warning; yet it is probable this auditory will think my father is too indulgent to his child, to let her to make public orations, or that he is too vain glorious, as to believe or hope his child may get applause, or esteem in the world, by her discourses. But first, I must remember them, that it is natural for parents to be fond of their children; secondly, it is no crime nor indiscretion, for a father to believe or think his child may have as much wit as any other man's child, if he have given as good education: thirdly, it is not against nature and reason, but<pb facs="80" n="137"/> that women may discourse of several subjects as well as men, and that they may have as probable opinions, and as profitable inventions, as fresh fancies, as quick wits, and as easy expressions, as men; if their education be answerable to their natural capacities and ingenuities; as for myself, I must tell this assembly, I have been bred industriously, for I have been instructed with as much knowledge as my years was capable to understand; but the truth is, that my educators strove to ripen my understanding, before the natural time, like those that hastens fruit to be ripe, forcing it by artificial means, not staying for the natural heat of the sun, so was my understanding, like as the tree, and my wit as the fruit, by which it wants the aromatical, and delicious relish, that natural time gives; which makes me fear, my wit will relish to the ears of the hearers, as such forced fruits to the taste of the eaters: I have only this request, that, though you may dislike it for want of the natural sweetness; yet pray esteem of it for the rarity, as being not usual for one of my years and sex, to speak, argue, and make orations in a public assembly; but it is likely, this assembly may think this is a vain glorious prologue, to my following discourse; but I must tell this worthy, grave, and learned, assembly, that I am not bound to follow a vain custom, nay, I may say, a dishonest one, as when orators do dissemble, as on my conscience most do, self love being natural to all; besides, many times they disgrace their birth, by a dissembling humbleness, and bely their thoughts, knowledge and education, whenas they say, they are unworthy to speak to such an assembly; and that they are unlearned, their knowledge is little, their understanding dull, their judgement weak; their capacity narrow, and that they are unexperienced and unfurnished of expressions, to deliver the subject, or matter of their discourse; if this or the like which they say be true, they abuse the auditory, and themselves, to invite them or draw them, to hear that, they think is not worth the listening to, and if they be not so (As they say) they bely the nature, and education, which heaven forbid I should be so ungrateful to nature, so base to my birth, so undutiful to my educator, and so unthankful to the gods. No, no, I will not be so, for I will publicly acknowledge nature's favours, who hath given me more wit, than time hath given me years; she hath furnished me with ingenuity, beyond an ordinary proportion, and hath drawn the plat form of my mind mathematically, and pencil me with her best coloured dyes, for which I am bound morally to serve her; as for my birth, as I am of the same kind of mankind; I am equal with the rest, let my condition be never so poor, I have no reason to be ashamed of the kind; but my birth is honourable by length of time, as for my education, it hath been singular, having not been bred as other children accustomarily are, who hath liberty to fling away their youthful time in idle sports, or useless learning's, and those that they are taught by, are young and unexperienced tutors; but I must tell this worthy and experienced assembly, that I was not bred with powdered curls, but silver hairs, age, I bowed to, and obeyed with duty, age, I viewed with respects, and listened to with attention; age, directed my senses, manured my brain; pulled up, or out, the roots of ignorance, and weeds of errors, sowed knowledge, and planted understanding; for, my educator, which was my dear father, hath been industrious, careful, prudent, bountiful, and studious, for my improvement; for which my treble duty doth attend his life, and my prayers supplicates for to prolong it, which heaven knows, I desire beyond my own; as for the gods which gives all good, let those that dare be unthankful, I dare not, such as atheists that believes in<pb facs="81" n="138"/> none; but pardon me for intruding one your patiences, with a tedious and self discourse, although I could not well avoid it, but now, with your leave, most noble auditors, I shall first treat of nature, although nature is an endless theme to treat of; for though that the principles of nature, or nature's principles may be easily numbered, yet the varieties which change doth make on those principles are infinite; for well may nature, if man by art can make infinite varieties, by change of few principles, as for example in music, from 8. Notes, by change, infinite tunes, are, or can be made; from the figure of 1. to 9. what multiplication? From 24. letters, how far can the mind dictate itself in, numerous words, and different languages? Thus nature the tutoress to man, and only man, have taught him to imitate her; for, though she is the mother to all other creatures, yet man is her beloved child; for she, like as a fond parent, leads and directs man to discoveries, and as it were, points and marks out their ways, and as a diligent tutoress, explains and expounds herself by her works, and her several works, like as several books hath several prints, and are bound in several volumes, and are kept safe in several libraries, of several ages, by aged time; but sometimes nature behaves herself like a huntress, and makes mankind as her hounds, to hunt out the hidden effects of unknown causes, leading mankind by three several strings, as by the string of observation, the string of conception, and the string of experience, and as hounds snuffs and snuffles on the paths they tread, so man's thoughts, like as hounds noses, are busily employed. And as hounds springs out upon a following sent, and with open mouth makes a loud cry; so men, when they make any new discoveries, divulges it with their voices, or noises of the tongue and pen; yet man at this hath no reason to take exceptions, because he gaineth knowledge thereby, and nature may use her own as she pleases; but sometimes nature is as a paintress, and the mind of man is as the copy of nature, drawn by herself; for the mind of man is as infinite as nature's self, having no dimension, nor extension, and the thoughts are the infinite creatures therein, and the brain is the ground to paint on, and the motions of life are the pencils to work, or draw with. And in these copies nature views herself, yet all animal creatures, especially mankind, seems of a middle mixture, as, not so gross as the earth, nor so pure as the heavens, which is the cause man is difficult to some things, and easy to others; as it is easier for the eyes to look down on the earth, than to stare up to the heavens, and for the feet to step down on steps, than to step up on stairs, or for the whole body to slide down a hill, than to clamber up a hill, so it is easier for life to slide down to vice, than to mount up to virtue, for what is purest is still placed highest, that is the reason that the celestial bodies are placed over us, as the terrestrial body under us; and we being mixed, are placed in the midst: upon this text give me leave to treat of the two globes, the celestial, and the terrestrial, in the celestial, there are seven worlds, where the sun is the centre world, which being a flame, streams forth in lines of light, upon the other six worlds; and as those six worlds, or the seventh world, moves, so have they light or darkness; but the sun which is the flaming world, or the world of flame, is fed as a lamp with an oily substance, from the other six worlds, which oily substance the sun sucks to him, from thence, by attracting motions, these six worlds I will similar to six udders, paps, or breasts, from which the sun, like as a young greedy appetite sucks, and draws out, each in their turns, and as I said by attraction, this oily moisture, which oily moisture is as the<pb facs="81" n="139"/> milk; the worldly udders, or udder worlds, doth as all udders doth, which as soon as they are drawn dry fills again, and if they be not sufficiently drawn, their moisture grows thick and gross; like as curdled milk, which corrupts and becomes ulcerous, from whence runs venomous matter, which falling down breeds amongst animals, many diseases as the rot murring, and the like amongst beasts; and amongst men the small pox, measles, and all sorts of fevers, even to the plague, and according as the corruptions are, or runs, the diseases are more dangerous, or less violenter, or weaker, lasts longer, or ends sooner; and if these udders be drawn faster than they can be naturally filled, they become chopped and dry, empty and shrunk, which causeth dearth and famine; and though we cannot see a dearth in the face of the moon, and the rest of the planets, as on the face of the earth, nor see famine in the face of the moon, as in the face of a man; yet for all we know, there may be dearths, plagues, and wars in those planets, as in particular kingdoms; although the planets have no such intelligences from each other, as particular kingdoms hath; yet questionless they have traffic and commerce, though mankind cannot visibly perceive, which way, or by what means. Also the planets, by their circular motions, may draw up vapours from the sea, and earth, like as the wheels of water Mils. As for the terrestrial globe, it turns upon a pole, as a big upon a spit, and the sun is the fire that roasts it; but when the sun is scorching hot, the earth like overroasted meat, it burned and black, and when that over cold moist vapours, quenches out the heat of these fiery beams, then is the earth as raw; but whenas equal heat, at equal distance, by equal motions, agrees simpathetically, then is the terrestrial globe well dressed, and full of gravy, which causes nourishing health; but to draw to a conclusion of my philosophical lecture, I will similar the celestial, and terrestrial globes, which globes, are as man and wife; the celestial as the husband, the terrestrial as the wife, which breeds and bears, what the celestial begets, for the celestial and the terrestrial globes are nature's working houses, where, animals, vegetables, and minerals, are wrought into several figures, shaped, and formed into divers fashions, like as smiths makes divers fashioned things out of metals, so nature is as the smith, the earth as the metal, the sun as the fire, the sea as the quenching water, the air as the bellows, youth is the furnace; time is the forge, and motion is the hammer, both to shape, and break asunder; but for fear I should break your patience, I shall desist from speaking any more at this time.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103610">After a modest and humble respective bow to the assembly.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103620">She goeth out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103630">The whilst the audience holds up their hands in admiration.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103640" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103650">Now you have heard her, what do you say?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103660" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103670">I say let us go home and make a funeral pile of our books,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A53060_04-e103680">this written by my lord marquess.</note> that are philosophy, burn them to ashes, that none may file as phenix like out of that dust.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103690" who="A53060_04-yyyy_3">
              <speaker>3. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103700">No, throw them at those foolish men that walk in black, who would be thought learned by the outside; although they are unlettered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103710" who="A53060_04-yyyy_4">
              <speaker>4. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103720">Take heed of that, for so they may have hopes of a resurrection, and so rise again in ragged covers, and tattered torn sheets, in old Duck-lane, and quack their to be bought.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103730" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <pb facs="82" n="140"/>
              <speaker>1. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103740">No, no, we will all now send for barbers, and in our great philosophies despair, shave of our reverend beards, as excrements, which once did make us all esteemed as wife, and stuff boys footballs with them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103750" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103760">Nature, thou dost us wrong, and art too prodigal to the effeminate sex; but I forgive thee, for thou art a she, dame nature thou art; but never showed thy malice until now, what shall we do?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103770" who="A53060_04-yyyy_3">
              <speaker>3. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103780">Faith all turn gallants, spend our time in vanity and sin, get hawks and hounds, and running horses, study the card and dye, rich clothes and feathers, waste our time away with what this man said, or what that man answered, backbite and rail at all those that are absent, and then renounce it with new oaths alamode.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103790" who="A53060_04-yyyy_4">
              <speaker>4. Philosopher. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103800">No, no, honour this virgin whose wit is supreme, whose judgement is serene as is the sky, whose life is a law unto herself and us, virtue her handmaid, and her words so sweet, like to harmonious music in the air, that charms our senses and delights the soul, and turns all passions in our hearts to love, teaches the aged, and instructs the youth, no sophister, but mistress still of truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103810">Ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103820">Here ends my lord marquess's.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="10" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e103830">
            <head>Scene 10.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e103840">Enter the lord de l'amour, and the lady innocence.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103850" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103860">I begin to be so fond of your company, as I cannot be long absent therefrom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103870" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103880">'Tis your favours to me, which favours are above my merits, indeed I have no merits, but what your favour creates.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103890" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103900">You seem so virtuous, and sweetly dispositioned, and are so beautiful and witty, as I cannot but admire, and love you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103910" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103920">I dare not be so rude, not yet so ungrateful, to speak against myself, now you have praised me, for your words are like to Kings, which makes all currant coin they set their stamp on; although the substance should be mean and of no value.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103930" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103940">Thy words are musical.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103950" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103960">I wish I could speak as eloquently upon every subject, as several birds sings sweety in several tunes, to please you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103970" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e103980">Do you love me so well, as to wish it only for my sake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e103990" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104000">Yes, and how should I do otherwise, for my affections to you was ingrafted into the root of my infancy, by my father's instructions and persuasions; which hath grown up with my age.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104010">The lady incontinent peeps in, and sees them together, (Speaks to herself) in the mean time they seem to whisper. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104020" who="A53060_04-incontinent">
              <speaker>Lady incontinent.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104030">Are you both so serious in discourse, I will break your friendship, or I will fall to the grave of death in the attempt.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104040">Lady incontinent goes out.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104050" who="A53060_04-delamour">
              <pb facs="82" n="141"/>
              <speaker>Lord de l'amour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104060">Heaven make you as virtuous as loving, and I shall be happy in a wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104070">Lord de l'amour goes out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104080">Lady innocence alone.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104090" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104100">Heaven make him as constant, as I virtuous, and I shall be sure of a gallant man to my husband.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104110">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A53060_04-e104120">
          <head>Act iv.</head>
          <div n="11" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e104130">
            <head>Scene 11.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104140">Enter the lady sanspareille, and takes her place, her father, and her audience about her, being all moral philosophers. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104150">When she had done her respects speaks.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104160" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sansp.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104170">By my father's relation to me, I understand, that all this worthy assembly, are students in morality; wherefore I shall treat this time of passions, wherein I make no question, being all sage, that you have not only learned to distinguish them, but have practised, how to temper, and govern them; but perchance you will say to yourselves, what need she speak of that, which have been so often treated of, only to make repetitions of former authors; but you all know without my telling you, that new applications may be made, on often preached texts, and new arguments may be drawn from old principles, and new experiences may be learned from former follies; but howsoever, my discourse shall not be very long, least tedious impertinencies should make it unpleasant to your ears, and cause too great a loss of time, to your better employments; but my discourse is, as I said on the passions, which I will first divide, as the ancient philosophers, into two, love, and hate. First, I will treat of pure love, which is self-love, for love to all other things is but the effects thereof. And is derived therefrom, self-love is the sole passion of the soul, it is a passion pure in itself, being unmixed, although all other passions do attend it, this passion, called self-love, is the legitimated child of nature, being bred in infinite, and born in eternity; yet this passion of self-love, being the mother of all other love is oftentimes mistaken for a fond, or a facile disposition, bred from a weak constitution of the body, or a strong, or rather extravagant appetite of the senses; or from a gross constitution, or evil habit, or custom of life, or an ill example of breeding; but these childish humours, facile, and easy dispositions, foolish and earnest desires, gross, and greedy appetites, inconstant, and evil natures, these are not pure love, as the effects of self-love, for it doth itself hurt; but they are the effects of the body, and nor of the soul, for some of them proceeds from a gross strength of body, hot, and active spirits, others from a tenderness, and weakness of body, and faint spirits; but the true passions of love, which is self-love, but mistake me not, for when I say self-love, , as is appertaining<pb facs="83" n="142"/> thereto, as love of honour, love of virtue, humane love, natural love, pious love, sympathetic love, which are the true begotten children of self-love: this love, hath no other object, but perfection, it hath an absolute command over life, it conquers death, and triumphs over torments, but every soul hath not this pure love, for there is a seeming self-love, and a real self-love; but as I said, every soul hath it not, for it is with souls, and the passions therein, as with bodies, and the sensual life, some are more healthful, and strong, others infirm and weak, some are fair, and well favoured, others foul and ill favoured, some are straight and well shaped, others crooked and deformed, some high, some low, some are of long life, others of short life, some lives have more actions than others, some more sensitive relishes, than others, some good natures, some bad, and all of that sort of animals, we call mankind, and as the body and sensitive spirits, so for the soul and rational spirits, for some hath (As I may say) more soul than others, as some hath larger souls than others, some purer than others, as being more serene; and some hath more ingenuity, and understanding than others. So passions, although one and the same sorts of passions, yet in some souls, they are more serene, and elevated than others; but many times the pure passions of the soul is so allied, with the gross humours of the body, as they become base, and of no good use; but in the passion of pure love, for the most part, dwells naturally melancholy: I mean, not that dry, cold, sharp humour, bred in the body, which makes it insipid, enclosing the soul, (As it were,) within walls of stone, which causeth a dull, heavy, and stupid disposition, as it oppresseth, and lies, like a heavy burden on the soul, hindering the active effects thereof; but this natural melancholy, dwells not in every soul, but only in the noblest; for it is the noblest effect, of the noblest passion, in the noblest soul. As for the passion of hate, it is not that loathing, or aversion, which is caused by a full, or sick stomach, or surfeited senses, or glutted appetites, or cross humours, or an antipathy of dispositions, or evil fortunes, or the like; but the true passion of hate, is, in the soul, not bred in the body; yet hate is a bastard passion of self-love, begotten by opposition, bred from corruption, and born with disturbance, this hate as it is derived, from the bowels, and loins of self-love, so it pursues self-loves enemies, which is suspect falsehood, and neglect: with this passion of hate, anger is a great companion; these two passions being seldom asunder; but anger is oftentimes mistaken, as all the rest of the passions are, but this passion of anger, is one of the useless passions of the soul, and is so far from assisting fortitude, as many think it doth; as it is an opposite enemy to it, for it cannot suffer patiently, and oft-times knows not what it acts, or on what it acts, or when it acts; this passion is one of the furies of the soul, which oft-times deposes reason; but a choleric disposition, is sooner to be pardoned, and less to be feared, being bred in the body, and as the humour ebbs, and flows, this disposition is less, or more. But to return to the two principle passions, which is love, and hate; I will at this time similar them, to two several kingdoms, or regions, love being the largest, for it reaches to the shades of death, and strongest, for it can endure, and hold out the assaults of any torment, being entrenched with fidelity, fortified with constancy, embattled with courage, victualled with patience, and armed, or manned with resolution; and were it not for the many labyrinths of feats, running in and out, with continual doubts, wherein, the content of the mind, is oftentimes lost, otherways it would be as pleasant a kingdom as it is a strong one, having large prospects of honour, and landscapes<pb facs="83" n="143"/> of perfection; green meadows of hopes, wherein grows sweet primroses of joy, and clear springs of desires, runs in swift streams of industry, by the banks of difficulty, besides this kingdom is always serene, for the sun of fervency of always shines there: in this large kingdom of love, reigns natural melancolly, who is the heroic royalest, soberest, and wisest prince born, in the mind, he directs his actions with prudence, defends his kingdom with courage, endures misfortunes with patience, moderates his desires with temperance, guides his senses with judgement, orders his speech with sense, and governs his thoughts with reason, he is the commander of the appetites; living in the court of imaginations, in the city of silences, in the kingdom of love, in the little world called man; and the greatest favourite to this prince, is wit, and the Muses, are his mistresses, to whom he applies his courtship, recreating himself in their delightful! Company, entertaining himself with balls, masks, pastorills, comedies, tragedies, and the like, presenting them in the bowers of fancy, built in the gardens of oratory, wherein grows flowers of rhetoric; but the greatest enemies to this prince, is unseasonable mirth, which oft-times disturbs his peace, by bringing in an army of empty words, sounding their loud trumpets of laughter, shooting of bald jests, beating the drums of idleness, with the sticks of ridiculous actions. But hate, although it be a kingdom that is very strong, by reason it hath high mountainous designs, hard rocks of cruelties, deep pits of obscurity, many quagmires of subtlety, by which advantages, this kingdom is impregnable; yet the kingdom of its self is barren, and insipid, bearing nothing but thorny bushes, of mischief and moss, of ill nature, no noble thoughts, or worthy actions, the climate is various, for the air of the mind is gross, having thick mists of envy, which causeth several sicknesses of discontent, other whiles it is very cold and sharp with spite, other times it is sulphury hot, with malice, which flashes lightning of revenge, which in a thundery fury breaks out: in this kingdom of hate, reigns anger, who is a tyrant, and strikes at every small offence, and many times on innocence, and so unjust, as he seldom takes witnesses, pride, and jealousy, are his favourites, which governs all with scorn, and executes with fury; he imposes taxes of slander, and gathers levies of detraction; exception is his secretary, to note both words and actions, he accuseth the senses with mistakes, and beheads the appetites, on the scaffolds of dislike, he strangles truth, with the cords of erroneous opinions, and tortures the thoughts one wheels of foul suspicion, whipping imagination with disgrace, he confounds the speech with disordered haste, that neither sense, nor words, can take their right places; but anger dies as most tyrants doth, being killed by repentance, and is buried in salt tears; betwixt these two kingdoms of love, and hate, runs a salt sea, of sorrow, which sometimes breaks into the kingdom of love, and sometimes into the kingdom of hate, from this sea arises thick vapours of grief, which gathers into dark clouds of sadness, which clouds dissolves into showering tears, or windy sighs; but if this sea be rough with the storms of misfortunes, or fomented with the tempest of impatience, it makes a dolorous noise of complaints, and laments, rolling with restless bellows of discontent, this is the kingdom of love, but when this sea breaks into the kingdom of hate, it makes a hideous noise, a roaring, with exclamations, and cursings. Also from this sea flows four rivers, quite through these two kingdoms; two through the kingdom of hate, and two through the kingdom of love, those two<pb facs="84" n="144"/> through the kingdom of love, are pity, and compassion; which when they meet makes a full tide, of charity, and overflows with bounty; but those that runs through the kingdom of hate, are the two rivers, of fury, and despair, when these two rivers meet, they make a full tide of madness, and overflows with mischief; but fearing I should drown your patience with my overflowing discourse, I shall desist for this time.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104180">After a civil respects</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104190">She goeth out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104200">And one of the company after she was gone speaks thus.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104210">My lord marquess writ this following speech.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104220" who="A53060_04-missing">
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104230">Were all dead morals writers, risen again, and their each several souls crushed into one, that soul would languish, till it stead the earth, in deep despair, to see their glories last, and all their vaster writings, so despised. <quote xml:id="A53060_04-e104240"><l xml:id="A53060_04-e104250">Thus by the music of a lady's tongue,</l><l xml:id="A53060_04-e104260">Whose cords, with wit, and judgement, is thus strung. </l></quote></p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104270">Ex.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104280">Here ends my lord marquess.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="12" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e104290">
            <head>Scene 12.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104300">Enter the lady innocence and adviser, an old man, of the lord de l'amours, as following the lady innocence.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104310" who="A53060_04-adviser">
              <speaker>Adviser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104320">Pray young lady stay, and take good counsel along with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104330" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104340">Good counsel is a guest I would willingly entertain, and be glad of his acquaintance, and endeavour, to make a perfect friendship with, and a constant companion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104350" who="A53060_04-adviser">
              <speaker>Adviser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104360">Then pray madam have a care of the lady incontinent, for she is full of designs against you, as I perceive by what I hear her say to my lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104370" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104380">Your lord is a person of so much worth, and merit, as he will not yield to plots of destruction, to destroy the innocent, he hath more charity to heal a wound, than cruelty to make one; his tender nature, and compassionate disposition, will strive to dry wet eyes, not force dry eyes to weep.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104390" who="A53060_04-adviser">
              <speaker>Adviser.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104400">My lord, madam, is a generous, and noble lord, but she is a dissembling crafty lady, and knows how to attract my lord, and to win him, to be of her belief, and I give you warning as a faithful servant, both to my lord and you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104410" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104420">I thank you friend, for your advertising me of this lady; but I shall trust myself to heaven's protection, fortune's favour, and your deeds noble, and just nature.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104430">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="13" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e104440">
            <pb facs="84" n="145"/>
            <head>Scene 13.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104450">Enter two men.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104460" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104470">The lady Sanspareile's wit, is as if it would overpower her brain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104480" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104490">O no, for her brain seems so well tempered, as if there were no conceptions, which springs therein, or propositions, or knowledge, presented thereunto; but it doth digest them with great ease, into a distinguishing understanding, otherwise she could not deliver her mind, and express her conceits, or opinions, with such method, and facility, as she doth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104500" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104510">She hath a monstrous wit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104520" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104530">No, her wit is not a monstrosity, but a generosity of nature, it is nature's bounty to her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104540" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104550">Certainly, nature was never so bountiful, to any of that sex, as she hath been to her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104560" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104570">The truth is, she favours the female sex, for the most part, more than she doth the masculine sex; because she is of the female kind herself.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104580" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104590">Faith, I could wish that I never wished before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104600" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104610">What wish is that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104620" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104630">Why, I wish, I were a woman, but such a woman as the lady sanspareille. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104640" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104650">Ovid speaks of a woman, that wished herself a man, and the gods granted her with, and she became a man; but I never heard of a man that was changed into a woman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104660" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104670">That was, by reason they never wished that change.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104680" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104690">That is a sign they thought the change would be far the worse.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104700" who="A53060_04-yyyy_1">
              <speaker>1. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104710">Indeed, generally it would be so.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104720" who="A53060_04-yyyy_2">
              <speaker>2. Gentleman. </speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104730">Well, for thy sake, I wish thou hadst thy wish.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104740">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
          <div n="14" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e104750">
            <head>Scene 14.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104760">Enter the lady innocence, as musing by herself alone. </stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104770">Then enter her maid passive.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104780" who="A53060_04-passive">
              <speaker>Passive.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104790">My dear mistress, what makes you so studious, as you are become pale with musing?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104800" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104810">The reason is, that my soul is flown out of my body, with the wings of desire, to seek for love; and my thoughts laboriously wanders after it, leaving my senses, to a solitary life, and my life to a melancholy musing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104820" who="A53060_04-passive">
              <speaker>Passive.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104830">Faith, I had rather be buried under the ruins of hate, than have a melancholy life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104840" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <pb facs="85" n="146"/>
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104850">And I am melancholy, for fear I should be so buried.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104860" who="A53060_04-passive">
              <speaker>Passive.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104870">If you would have love, you must give love.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104880" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104890">Indeed love is like a coy-duck, it goeth out to invite, or draw in others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104900" who="A53060_04-passive">
              <speaker>Passive.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104910">Nay faith, a coy-woman cannot do so, for the coyer she is, the fewer lovers she will have, for coins starves lovers, wherefore, if you would not starve your beloved, you must be free, and twine about him, as the ivy doth the oak.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104920" who="A53060_04-innocence">
              <speaker>Lady innocence.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104930">Modesty forbids, it but were it lawful, and that it did not infringe the laws of modesty, I could hang about his neck, as the earth to the centre, but I had rather starve my delights, than do an act immodest, or surfeit his affection.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104940">Ex.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A53060_04-e104950">
          <head>Act v.</head>
          <div n="15" type="scene" xml:id="A53060_04-e104960">
            <head>Scene 15.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e104970">Enter the lady sanspareille, and her father, with the audience, she takes her place, and, after a civil respects to the company, speaks:</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e104980" who="A53060_04-sanspareille">
              <speaker>Sanspareille.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e104990">Noble gentlemen, you are welcome, and, though I cannot promise to feast your ears, with an eloquent banquet; yet I hope it will prove so, as I hope it will not cause a dislike; for the several dishes of my discourse shall neither be bitter with railing, nor sharp with spite, nor salt brined with satyr, nor luscious with flattery, and, though it may prove tasteless to the gusto of your humour, yet it will not be disagreeing to the stomach of your reason, nor dangerous to the life of your understanding; but, by reason this worthy assembly is mixed, as orators, poets, young students, and soldiers, it will be hard for me to divide my discourse so, as to give each company a civil entertainment, but howsoever my endeavour shall not be wanting; for that wit I have, I shall wait upon you, I shall first speak to the young students, because youth, and learning, is the beginning of life, and knowledge, and young brains are like plain paper books, where time as a hand, experience as a pen, and practice as ink, writes therein; and these books contains several and divers chapters. The first, is of knowledge. The second, and third chapters, are of memory and understanding; these chapters are but short. The fourth, and fifth chapters, are conceptions and imaginations; this chapter contains more than half the book. The last chapter, is remembrance, which is also a very long chapter, and the variety of thoughts are the several letters, in which these chapters are writ; but they, are not all writ after one kind of writing, neither are they writ with one, and the same language; for knowledge is writ in great and plain letters, memory and understanding, in finer, and smaller letters; conceptions, and imaginations, after the manner of way, as like hieroglyphics, remembrance is writ, as after the like way of characters; knowledge is writ, in the original language<pb facs="85" n="147"/> as we may liken to hebrew; memory and understanding, are writ, in a language derived therefrom: conception, and imagination, are written in heathen Greek; remembrance is writ in a mixed, or compounded language, like as English, but yet it is most like, that we call old English: but the most profitablest school is consideration; and the best tutor is reason, and when the mind is distempered, or obstructed with ignorance, education is the best physic which purges it, cleanses and freeth it, from all gross, and foul, and filthy errors; but the educators, which are the physicians, should be well chosen; for the plain truth is, that youth should be taught by those that are grave, and sage, that they may learn experience by the second hand, otherways age only knows, but hath no time to practise in; but if that youth be taught good principles, their life grows high by noble deeds, and broadly spreads with honours, but when that youth have liberty to sport, and play, casting their learning time away, they grow like poisonous plants, or weeds, which makes their life swell big, with venomous passions, and dispositions, and burst with evil deed, but youth, their understanding is like their years, and bodies, little and weak, for the soul is improved by the senses, but educators, their physicians presents to their senses, the most wholesome, and nourishing meat; for, as the body is nourished and grows strong, by good digestion, so doth the soul gain knowledge by information, but, if the food be unwholesome, or more than the stomach be able to digest, or that the body is not fed sufficiently, the body becomes lean, weak, saint, and sick, so the soul, or mind; if the senses be imperfect, or the objects more than can be well disenst, or too many for the temper of the brain, or that the brain be too cold, or too hot, than the soul or mind, like the body, decays, for, like as the bodily senses, so the senses of the soul decays; for the understanding as the spirits, grows saint, the judgement as the liver, wan, and weak, the memory as the eyes, grows dim and blind, the thoughts as the several limbs, grows feeble and lazy; but some remedy is for those diseases; for the speculative notes helps the dull memory, cordial learning, the faint understanding, purging, and opening, experience, the wan and obstructed judgement, and necessity exercises the lazy thoughts; but if the brain be defective, or the soul imperfect from the birth, there is no remedy, for then the reason proves a dwarf, and the understanding a fool; but if the soul be perfect, and the brain well tempered, than the soul is like the serene and azure sky, wherein reason as the sun, gives light to all the animal world, where the thoughts, as several creatures, lives therein; some being bred in the deep, and restless ocean, of imagination, others, as from the fixed earth of knowledge, springs; and, as the gods governs the world, and the creatures therein, so the soul should govern the body, and the appetites thereof; which governing, is to govern still to the best: as for the continuance of the world, so for the prolonging of the life of the body, which government I wish to the soul of every young student here. In the next place, I shall speak to orators, whose study, and practice is language, and language, although it is not born with man, yet it is bred with man, or in man, either by their education, or their own invention; for, if language had a beginning, it was invented by the creature, if no beginning, it was taught them by the gods; for, though that nature made such organs, as was proper to express language with, yet it seems as if she did not create language, as a principal work, but if she did, than orators tongues are natures musical instruments; but the best musical instruments were better to lie unplayed<pb facs="86" n="148"/> with, than to sound out of tune, or to strike jarring discord, which displeaseth more than the harmony can delight, so likewise it were better not to speak, than to speak to no purpose, or to an evil design, but oratory, or rhetoric, is as all other music is, which lives more in sound than in substance, it charms the ear, but it cannot inchant the reason, it may enslave the passions, but not conquer the understanding, it may obstruct truth, and abuse virtue, but it can neither destroy the one, nor corrupt the other, it can flatter up hopes, and raise up doubts, but it cannot delude experience, it can make factions, and raise tumults; but seldom rectify disorders; for it is to be observed, that in those states, or nations, where oratory, and rhetoric flourisheth most, the commonwealth is for the most part distempered, and justice loses her seat, and many times the state loses its former government, customs and laws, witness the Romans, Athens, and Lacedmonians, and others, that were ruined by their flourishing rhetoric, and factious oratory; but it is thought that the flowers of rhetoric is much vaded since the time of the Athens, through the whole world, and that the lively cullours are quite lost, if it be so, then surely the defect is much in the first education, of children; for in infancy is a time, these should take a good print, but their nurses is their grammar, and her tongue is their first tutor, which most commonly learns them the worst part of speech, which parts are eight; as impertinent questions, cross answers, broken relations, false reports, rude speeches, mistaking words, misplaccing words, new words of their own making without a signification: wherefore, parents that would bring up their children elegantly, and eloquently, they must have a learned grammar, and a wise tutor at the first, to teach them, for the mouth as the press, prints the breath as the paper, with words, as the ink, and reason, and sense, binds them up into a book, or volume of discourses; but certainly the orators of this age for eloquence, and elegancy, comes not short of the eloquent orators of Athens, or any other state, they only use it to better designs, than to make wars on their neighbours, to banish their citizens, or those that ought to be rewarded, to alter their government, and ruin their state; no worthy orators, you use your eloquence for peace, love, and unity, and not for faction war and ruin; for which, may the gods of eloquence assist you. But there is two sorts of orators, the one bred up in schools of art, to rules, forms and tenses, the other is bred up in the school of nature, which only observes her rules, and studies her works; for though all orators are not poets, yet all poets are natural orators, and hath a natural, eloquent, and elegant, and easy expression; for, if a man should have a poetical brain, if he had not a full expression to deliver his conceits, they would be as if they were not, for, as their may be several fancies, and conceits, raised from one object or subject, so there requires several significant words, to express them; for, as time is the marks of eternity, so words are the marks of things, but indeed poet's hath a harder task than orators, for orators builds their discourse upon solid grounds, when poets builds their discourse upon airy foundations, but the two principles of poetry, is similising, and distinguishing, which are fancy, and judgement, and some poets' brains are so happy, that as soon as they have bred, or created any fancy, the tongue is ready to deliver them; but some brains are a long time in breeding, and some fancies puts the brain into great pains, and hot, and painful throws; and some tongues as ill midwives, strangles strong fancies in the birth, but a<pb facs="86" n="149"/> volable tongue, is like an expert, and understanding midwife, which makes easy, safe, and quick dispatch, for wit and judgement, are both the children of the brain, begotten by nature; being both twin sisters, and so ingenious, and inventive they are, that they build their arguments so curiously, and compile the sense into so small a compass, that there is no waste room, nor superfluous words, nor painted phrases, nor useless parentheses, nor obstructed sentences, for they build with fancy, and compile with similising cut, and carved, with allegories, polished with numbers, and oft-times adorned with rhyme, the persons to which wit, and judgement; the children of nature are placed, as sojourners, or borders, are poets, who are nature's favourites, and for the education of her children, she rewards them, by enriching their minds, though not their purses; for she leaves that to fortune, but fortune through envy to nature, is seldom their friend: also nature, gives her favourite poets delights; for poets takes more delight, and pleasure in their own thoughts and conceptions, than an absolute monarch in his power and supremacy; for like as birds, that hops from bough to bough, whereon they sit and sing; so poets' thoughts moves, from theme, to theme, making sweet melody; and as hen's brood's chickens, which chickens, are not hatched, until they have strength to pick a passage through their shells, with their bills, and when they are fledged, flies from their nest on a high perching branch, so the brain lays imaginations, and brood, fancies, and the tongue as a bill, picks a passage through the lips, and being feathered with words, winged with verse, flies up even with numbers, to fame's high tower; but the muses the handmaids to nature, doth as all other maidens, loves the courtship of the masculine sex, which is the cause, or reason they seldom visit their own sex, but passes their time in the company, and conversation of men; by some men, they are only admired, and loved, by others, they are saed to, and enjoyed, which happy suitors, are poets; but the Muses, as all other female takes a delight to enjoy their lovers alone, that makes them separate themselves from other company; and poets as all lovers, doth love solitude: wherefore, poets the lovers of the Muses, and the Muses lovers of the poets, oft-times chooseth a solitary life, as being a paradise, for innocent delight, wherein the senses lies on soft banks of repose, the whilst the mind with a sober, and serious peace, walks in the silent shades of contemplation, shunning the hot and burning sun of high ambition, and there the active thoughts; the children of the mind, in harmless sports, doth with the muse's play, and on their heads garlands of fancy wear, made all of rhetorics choicest flowers, whose cullours fresh and gay, thus are the thoughts adorned and decked, as the fair month of May; about this paradise, which paradise is a solitary life, the calm smooth river of safety flows, which winds, or circles in the life, from suffering, or acting injury, or wrong: and from this river of safety, runs many streams of pleasures, wherein the mind refreshing baths, secure and free, no false witness to accuse their innocency; no tempestuous storms, nor dreadful thunders hard, nor flashing lightning there appears, all is their serene and clear, unless sometimes thin clouds of melancholy falls in fresh showering tears, or from the heart ariseth some gentle sighs, which breathing out fans, like to Zephyrus winds; and in this solitary life 3. Trees doth grow, peace, rest, and silence, are they named, the fruits they bore, is plenty, ease, and quite.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105000"><pb facs="87" n="150"/>On which the mind deliciously cloth seed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105010">Whose luscious juice, tranquillity as fat doth breed;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105020">Reason the nerves, and gristles of the mind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105030">Grows strong, and cures the understanding blind;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105040">There's none but fools, this happy life would shun,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105050">Such as would seek in rugged ways to run:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105060">Oh fools! O fools! to love their torments so,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105070">That they will rather choose to hell, than heavens go. </l>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e105080">But there is no man can enjoy this worldly paradise, without a defence; for none can live in peace, that is not prepared as ready for war, for both the theological, civil, common, and accustomary laws, are protected by the martial law, and the martial power, is the supreme authority, placing, and displacing, and is the monarchical power, that doth not only protect all other laws, but commands them with threats, and is obeyed with terror and fear, honoured for the fame, and hated for the tyranny; but soldiery is a painful, careful, and dangerous, although noble profession, but as I said, 'tis one of the safest, and securest protections; for it is protection to the weak, and infirm, to the decrepit, and aged, to the shiftless youth, and to the saint, fearful, and tender effeminate sex, it is a guard unto the ashes of the dead, to the monuments of the meritorious, and to the temples of the gods. And were it not for martial-discipline, there could be no peace kept, truth and right would be torn from the owners, justice would be pulled out of her seat, monarchy thrown out of his throne, and though a soldier may lose his life sooner than nature did ordain; yet in recompense, honour buries him, and fame builds him a glorious monument over his sleeping ashes; but by reason that fame is a soldier's chief reward, I ought not to pass it by, without mentioning it; as for fame, it is a second life, and as I may say, the soul of merit; but there is a difference, betwixt the records of time, fame, and infamy; for there are many things, that are writ in the records of time, that is, neither in fame's tower, nor infamies dungeon, that which is writ in the records of time, is strange accidents, unlucky chances; unusual objects, unexpected preferments, or advancements, by fortune's favour, or partial affections, also great ruins, losses, and crosses, also plagues, deaths, famines, wars, earthquakes, meteors, comets, unusual seasons, extraordinary storms, tempests, floods, fires, likewise great strength, very old age, beauty, deformities, unnatural births, monsters, and such like, which time records: but fame is the goddess, of eminent, and meritorious actions, and her palace is the heaven, where the renowns which are the souls of such actions, lives; I say eminent, and meritorious actions; for all meritorious actions, are not eminent, but those that transcends an usual degree, as extraordinary valour, patience, prudence, justice, temperance, constancy, gratitude, generosity, magnanimity, industry, fidelity, loyalty, piety, also extraordinary wisdom, wit, ingenuities, speculations, conceptions, learning, oratory, and the like; but it is not sufficient to be barely endued with those virtues, and qualities, but these virtues, and qualities, must be elevated, beyond an ordinary degree, insomuch, as to produce some extraordinary actions, so as to be eminent; for fame dwells high, and nothing reaches her, but what is transcendent, either in worth, or power; for it is to be observed, that none but Jove's mansion is<pb facs="87" n="151"/> purely free, from deceit, and corruptions, for nature is artified, and fame is often forced by fortune, and conquering power, and sometimes bribed by flattery, and partiality, and in times records there is more false reports than true, and in infamous dungeon, which is deep, although not dark, being enlightened by the eye of knowledge, and the lamp of memory, or remembrance, which divulges, and shows to several, and after ages, the evil deeds which lies therein, as thefts, murder, adultery, sacrilege, injustice, evil government, foolish counsels, tyranny, usurpation, rapine, extortion, treason, broken promises, treachery, ingratitude, cozening, cheating, sherking, lying, deluding, defrauding, factions, disobedience, follies, errors vices, fools, whores, knaves, sycophants, Sloth, idleness, injury, wrong, and many hundreds the like; yet many innocent virtues, and well deserving deeds, at least good intentions, lies in the dungeon of infamy, cast therein by false constructions, evil events, malice, envy, spite, and the like; sometimes some gets out by the help of right interpretation, friendly assistance, or eloquent pleading: but yet these are very seldom, by reason the dungeon is so deep, that it almost requires a supernatural strength, to pull out any dead therein, for therein, they are oftener buried in oblivion, than translated by pleading; but as I said, many innocents are unjustly cast into infamies dungeon, and lies for ever therein, and many a false report is writ in times records, and never blotted thereout: and many vain, and unworthy actions, feigned virtues, and vicious qualities, hath got not only into fame's palace, but are placed high in fame's tower; and good successes, although from evil designs, and wicked deeds, doth many times usurp, the most chiefest, and highest places, as to be set upon the pinnacle, for fortune conquering, power and partiality, forceth, carries, and throws more into fame's palace, than honest industry, leads, or merit advances therein, or unto which is unjust, yet not to be avoided; for fortune, and victory, are powerful, and so powerful, as many times they tread down the meritorious, and upon those pure footstool, they raise up the unworthy and base; thus fame's base born, thrust out the legitimate heirs, and usurp the right, and lawful inheritance, of the right owners of fame's palace: wherefore worthy heroics, you cannot enjoy fame, when you will, nor make her sound out so loud, as you would, nor so long as you would, nor where you would have her, unless you force her, which is only to be done by the assistance of time, the providence of forecast, the diligence of prudence, the ingenuity of industry, the direction of opportunity, the strength of power, the agility of action, the probability of opinion, the verity of truth, the favour of fortune, the esteem of affection, the guilts of nature, and the breeding of education; besides that, fame is of several humours, or natures, and her palace stands on several soils, and her trumpet sounds out several notes, airs, strains, or ditties; for some airs, or strains, are pleasant, and cheerful, others sad and melancholy; and sometimes she sounds marches of war, some to charge, some to retreat; also sometimes her palace stands on rocks of adversity, other times on the flat soils of prosperity, sometimes in the sun shine of plenty, other times in the shade of poverty, sometimes in the flowery gardens of peace, other times in the bloody fields of war; but this is to be observed, that fame at all times sounds out a soldier's renown louder than any others; for the sound of heroic actions spreads furthest, yet the renown of poets sounds sweetest; for fame takes a delight to sound strains of wit, and airs of fancies, and time takes pleasure to record them; but worthy heroics, give<pb facs="88" n="152"/> me leave to tell you, that if time and occasion doth not fit, or meet your noble ambitions; you must fashion your noble ambitions to the times, and take those opportunities that are offered you; for if you should slip the season of opportunity, wherein you should so the seeds of industry, you will lose the harvest of honourable deeds, so may starve, wanting the bread of report, which should feed the life of applause; but noble heroics, when you adventure, or set forth, for the purchase of honour, you must be armed with fortitude, and march along with prudence, in an united body of patience, than pitch in the field of fidelity, and fight with the sword of justice, to maintain the cause of right, and to keep the privileges of truth, for which, you will be entailed the heirs, and sons of fame; and my wishes and prayers shall be, that you may be all crowned with laurel.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e105090">After she had made her respects.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e105100">She goeth out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e105110">My lord marquess, writ these following speeches.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e105120" who="A53060_04-soldier">
              <speaker>A soldier.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e105130">Silence all thundering drums, and trumpets loud, with glistering arms, bright swords, and waving plumes.</p>
              <lg xml:id="A53060_04-e105140">
                <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105150">And the feared cannon powdered, shall no more,</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105160">Force the thin air with horror for to roar;</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105170">Nor the proud steeds, with hollow hooves to beat</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105180">The humble earth, till echoes it repeat. </l>
              </lg>
              <lg xml:id="A53060_04-e105190">
                <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105200">This lady makes Greek tactics to look pale,</l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105210">And Caesar's commentaries blush for shame. </l>
                <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105220">The Amazonian dames, shakes at her name. </l>
              </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e105230" who="A53060_04-poets">
              <speaker>Poets.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e105240">The lady muses are deposed, unthroned from their high palace of Parnassus-hill.</p>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105250">Where she in glory, with poetic flames, there sits,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105260">In triumph, emperess of wits;</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105270">Where her bright beams, our poets doth inspire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105280">As humble mortals, from her gentle fire:</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105290">She is the only muses, gives fancy slore,</l>
              <l xml:id="A53060_04-e105300">Else, all our poets, they could write no more. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A53060_04-e105310" who="A53060_04-oratour">
              <speaker>Oratour.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A53060_04-e105320">Were the oiled tongue of Tully now alive, and all the rest of glib tongued orators, with their best arguments, to force a truth, or else with subtlety of slight to avoid it; those tongues with trembling palsies, would be all struck dumb, with wonder and amazement, to hear truth clothed so gently, as to move all orators, their passions into love, admired virgin.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e105330">Then all the auditory goeth out.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A53060_04-e105340">Here ends my lord marquess's.</stage>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A53060_04-e105350">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A53060_04"><item xml:id="A53060_04-sanspareille" n="35">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-sanspareille</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">35</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-innocence" n="19">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-innocence</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">19</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-delamour" n="17">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-delamour</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">17</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-father" n="17">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-father</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">17</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-yyyy_1" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-yyyy_2" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-yyyy_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-incontinent" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-incontinent</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-mother" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-mother</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-mother_love" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-mother_love</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-father_love" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-father_love</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-yyyy_3" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-yyyy_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A53060_04-maid" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-maid</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-passive" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-passive</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-adviser" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-adviser</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-woman" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-woman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-yyyy_4" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-yyyy_4</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-sanspareile" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-sanspareile</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-oratour" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-oratour</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-soldier" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-soldier</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-missing" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-missing</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A53060_04-poets" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A53060_04-poets</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

