<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A07326">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Heir <date type="creation_date">1620</date></title>
        <author>May, Thomas</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Hannah Bredar</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A07326.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The heire an excellent comedie. As it was lately acted by the Company of the Reuels. Writren [sic] by T.M. Gent.</title>
            <author>May, Thomas, 1595-1650.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>32 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2006 February (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99845578</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 17713.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 384(a).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">10485</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07326</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The heire an excellent comedie. As it was lately acted by the Company of the Reuels. Writren [sic] by T.M. Gent.</title>
            <title type="alt">Excellent comedy called the heire.</title>
            <author>May, Thomas, 1595-1650.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[72] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by B[ernard] A[lsop] for Thomas Iones, and are to bee sold at his shop in Chancery-lane, ouer-against the Roles, and in Westminster Hall,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1622.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>By Thomas May, whose name appears on A3r.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's name from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-I4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: An excellent comedy called the heire.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A07326-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A07326-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A07326-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A07326-e100040">The heir an excellent comedy.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07326-e100050">As it was lately acted by the company of the revels.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07326-e100060">Written by T. m. gent.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07326-e100070">London, printed by B. A. for Thomas Jones, and are to be sold at his shop in Chancery-lane, over-against the rolls, and in Westminster hall.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="encomium" xml:id="A07326-e100080">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To my honoured friend, master Thomas may, upon his comedy, the heir. </head>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100090">The heir being born, was in his tender age</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100100">Rocked in the cradle of a private stage,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100110">Where lifted up by many a willing hand,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100120">The child doth from the first day fairly stand,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100130">Since, having gathered strength, he dares prefer</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100140">His steps into the public theater</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100150">The world: where he despairs not but to find</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100160">A doom from men more able, but less kind. </l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100170">I but his usher am, yet if my word</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100180">May pass, I dare be bound he will afford</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100190">Things must deserve a welcome, it well known</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100200">Such as best writers would have wished their own. </l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100210">You shall observe his words in order meet,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100220">And often stealing on, with equal feet</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100230">Slide into equal numbers, with such grace</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100240">As each word had been moulded for that place. </l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100250">You shall perceive an amorous passion, spun</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100260">Into so smooth a web, as had the sun,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100270">When he pursued the swiftly flying maid,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100280">Courted her in such language she had stayed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100290">A love so well expressed must be the same,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100300">The author felt himself from his fair flame. </l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100310">The whole plot doth like itself disclose</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100320">Through the five acts, as doth a look, that goes</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100330">With letters, for till every one be known,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100340">The lock's as fast as if you had found none. </l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100350">And where his sportive muse doth draw a thread</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100360">Of mirth, chaste matrons may not blush to read. </l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100370"><pb facs="3"/>〈◊〉 have I thought it fitter to reveal</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100380">〈◊〉 want of art (Dear friend) then to conceal</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100390">〈…〉 it did appear I did not mean</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100400">〈…〉 thy well-wrought comic-scene,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100410">〈…〉 might judge my 〈◊〉 rather to be,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100420">〈…〉 myself, th●● give it thee;</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100430">〈…〉 thee none but what thou hast</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100440">〈…〉 ▪ and what must my faint breath outlast. </l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100450">〈…〉 this garment (Though 〈…〉 be</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100460">〈…〉 measure) only made for thee,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100470">〈…〉 to 〈◊〉, 'tis cause the stuff</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e100480">〈…〉 allowed me, was not large enough. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A07326-e100490">
          <signed xml:id="A07326-e100500">Thomas Caron</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A07326-e100510">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A07326-e100520">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>An excellent comedy called the heir.</head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A07326-e100530">
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e100540">Enter Polimetes, Roscio.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e100550" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e100560">Roscio. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e100570" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e100580">My lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e100590" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100600">Hast thou divulged the news</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100610">That my son died at Athens. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e100620" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100630">Yes my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100640">With every circumstance, the time, the place,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100650">And manner of his death; that it is believed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100660">And told for news with as much confidence</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100670">As if 'twere writ in Gallobelgicus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e100680" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100690">That's well, that's very well, now Roscio</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100700">Follows my part, I must express a grief</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100710">Not usual, not like a well left heir</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100720">For his dead father, or a lusty widow</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100730">For her old husband, must I counterfeit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100740">But in a deeper, a far deeper strain</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100750">Weep like a father for his only son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100760">Is not that hard to do, ha, Roscio? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e100770" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100780">O no my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100790">Not for your skill, has not your lordship seen</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100800">A player personate Jeronimo? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e100810" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100820">By th'mass 'tis true, I have seen the knave paint grief</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100830">In such a lively colour, that for false</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100840">And acted passion he has drawn true tears</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100850">From the spectator's eyes, ladies in the boxes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100860">Kept time with sighs, and tears to his sad accents</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100870">As had he truly been the new man he seemed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100880">Well then I'll ne'er despair; but tell me thou</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100890">Thou that hast still been privy to my bosom,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100900">How will this project take? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e100910" who="A07326-roscio">
            <pb facs="4"/>
            <speaker>Rosc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100920">Rarely my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100930">When now my thinks, I see your lordship's house</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100940">Is with suitors of the noblest rank,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100950">And my young lady your supposed heir</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100960">Tired more with wooing then the Grecian Queen</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100970">In the long absence of her wand'ring lord. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100980">There's not a ruinous nobility</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e100990">In all this kingdom, but conceives a hope</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101000">Now to rebuild his fortunes on this match. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101010" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101020">Those are not they I look for, no, my ne●●</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101030">Are spread for other game, the rich and greedy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101040">Those that have wealth enough, yet gape for more</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101050">They are for me,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101060" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101070">Others will come my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101080">All sorts of fish will press upon your nets,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101090">Then in your lordship's wisdom it must lie</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101100">To cull the great ones, and reject the fry. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101110" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101120">Nay fear not that, there's none shall have access</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101130">To see my daughter, or to speak to her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101140">But such as I approve, and aim to catch. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101150" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101160">The jest will be, my lord, when you shall see</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101170">How your aspiring suitors will put on</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101180">The face of greatness, and bely their fortunes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101190">Consume themselves in show, wasting like merchants</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101200">Their present wealth in rigging a fair ship</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101210">For some ill venture de voyage, that undoes 'em. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101220">Here comes a youth with letters from the court,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101230">Bought of some favourite at such a price</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101240">As will for ever sink him, yet alas</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101250">All's to no purpose, he must lose the prize. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101260" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101270">This was a jest well thought of, the conceit</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101280">Will feed me fat, with sport that it shall make,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101290">Besides the large adventures it brings home</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101300">Unto my daughter. How now.<stage xml:id="A07326-e101310">Enter servant</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101320" who="A07326-servant">
            <speaker>Sir </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e101330">My lord, count Virro is come to see you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101340" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101350">Conduct him in; so, so, it takes already</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101360">See Roscio see, this is the very man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101370">My project aimed at, the rich count that knows</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101380"><pb facs="4"/> no end of his large wealth, yet gapes for more</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101390">There was no other loadstone could attract</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101400">His iron heart, for could beauty have moved him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101410">Nature has been no niggard to my girl,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101420">But I must to my grief, here comes the count. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e101430">Enter count Virro.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101440" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e101450">Is your lord asleep ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101460" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101470">No sir. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101480">I think not, my lord, count Virro. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101490" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e101500">How do you sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101510" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e101520">I do entreat your lordship pardon, my grief and some want of sleep have made me at this time unmannerly, not fit to entertain guests of your worth.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101530" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e101540">Alas sir I know your grief.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101550" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e101560">'Twas that that fetched you hither.<stage xml:id="A07326-e101570">Aside.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101580" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101590">You've lost a worthy and a hopeful son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101600">But heaven that always gives, will sometimes take</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101610">And that the best, there is no balsam left us</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101620">To cure such wounds as these but patience,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101630">There's no disputing with the acts of heaven,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101640">But if there were, in what could you accuse</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101650">Those powers that else have been so liberal to you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101660">And left you yet one comfort in your age:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101670">A fair and virtuous daughter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101680" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e101690">Now it begins.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101700" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e101710">Your blood is not extinct, nor your age childless, from that fair branch that's left may come much fruit to glad posterity, think on that my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101720" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101730">Nay heaven forbid I should repine at what the</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101740">Justice of those powers ordain, it has pleased</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101750">Them to confine my care only to one, and to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101760">See her well bestowed is all the comfort I now</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101770">Must look for, but if it had pleased heaven that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101780">My son, ah my Eugenio. <stage xml:id="A07326-e101790">He weeps.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101800" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e101810">Alas good gentleman.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101820" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e101830">Fore heaven he does it rarely.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101840" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101850">But sir, remember yourself, remember your</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101860">Daughter, let not your grief for the dead make</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101870"><pb facs="5"/> you forget the living, whose hopes, and fortunes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101880">Depend upon your safety. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101890" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e101900">O my good lord, you never had a soon.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101910" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101920">Unless they were bastards, and for them no</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101930">Doubt but he has done as other lords do. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101940" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101950">And therefore cannot tell what 'tis to lose</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101960">A son, a good son, and an only son. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e101970" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101980">I would, my lord, I could as well redress</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e101990">As I can take compassion of your grief</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102000">You should soon find an ease. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102010" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102020">Pray pardon me my lord, if I forget myself towards you at this time, if it please you visit my house ofter you shall be welcome.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102030" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102040">You would fain sleep my lord, I'll take my leave heaven send you comfort, I shall make bold shortly to visit you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102050" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102060">You shall be wondrous welcome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102070">Wait on my lord out there.<stage xml:id="A07326-e102080">Exit Virro. </stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102090">So now he's gone, how thinkst thou Roscio,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102100">Will not this gudgeon bite? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102110" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102120">No doubt my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102130">So fair a bait would catch a cunning fish. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102140" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Po●.. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102150">And such a one is he, he ever loved</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102160">The beauty of my girl, but that's not it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102170">Can draw the earth bred thoughts of his gross soul</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102180">Gold is the god of his idolatry,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102190">With hope of which I'll feed him, till at length</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102200">I make him fasten, and Ixion like</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102210">For his loved Juno grasp an empty cloud. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102220" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102230">How stands my young lady affected to him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102240" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102250">There's all the difficulty, we must win her to love 〈◊〉, I doubt the peevish girl will think him too 〈◊〉, he's well near threescore: in this business I must leave somewhat to thy wit and care, praise him beyond all measure.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102260" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102270">Your lordship ever found me trusty.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102280" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102290">If thou effect it, I will make thee happy.<stage xml:id="A07326-e102300">Exeunt</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e102310">Enter Philocles, Clerimont.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102320" who="A07326-philocles">
            <pb facs="5"/>
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102330">Eugenio's sister then is the rich heir</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102340">By his decease. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102350" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102360">Yes, and the fair one too,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102370">She needs no gloss that fortune can set on her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102380">Her beauty of itself were prize enough</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102390">To make a King turn beggar for. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102400" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102410">Hoy day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102420">What in love Clerimont, I lay my life 'tis so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102430">Thou couldst not praise her with such passion else. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102440" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102450">I know not, but I slept well enough last night,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102460">But if thou sawest her once, I would not give</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102470">A farthing for thy life, I tell thee Philocles'</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102480">One fight of her would make thee cry, ay me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102490">Sigh, and look pale, methinks I do imagine</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102500">How like an idolatrous lover thou wouldst look</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102510">Through the eyelids, know nobody . </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102520" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102530">'Tis very well, but how did your worship scape</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102540">You have seen her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102550" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102560">True, but I have an</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102570">Antidote, and I can teach it thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102580" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102590">When</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102600">I have need on't I'll desire it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102610" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102620">And 'twill</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102630">Be worth thy learning, when thou shalt see the</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102640">Tyranny of that same scurvy boy, and what fools</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102650">He makes of us; shall I describe the beast? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102660" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102670">What beast?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102680" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102690">A lover.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102700" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102710">Do.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102720" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102730">Then to be brief, I will pass over the opinion of your ancient fathers, as likewise those strange loves spoken of in the authentic histories of chivalry Amadis du Gaul, Parismus, the knight of the sun, or the witty knight don Quixot de la Manca, where those brave men, neither enchantments, giants, windmills, nor flocks of sheep could vanquish, are made the trophies of triumphing love.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102740" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102750">Prithee come to the matter.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102760" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102770">Neither will I mention the complaints of sir Guy for the fair Phelis, nor the travels of Parismus for the love of the beauteous Laurana, nor lastly, the most sad penance of the ingenious knight don Quixot upon the mountains of Sierra Morenna, moved by the unjust disdain of the lady Dulcinea del Toboso, 〈◊〉 or our modern authors, I<pb facs="6"/> will not so much as name them, no not that excellent treatise of Tully's love, written by the master of art.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102780" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102790">I would thou wouldst pass over this passing over of authors, and speak thine own judgement.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102800" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102810">Why then to be brief, I think a lover looks like an ass.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102820" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102830">I can describe him better than so myself, he looks like a man that had sitten up at cards all night, or a stale drunkard wakened in the midst of his sleep.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102840" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102850">But Philocles, I would not have thee see this lady, she has a bewitching look.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102860" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102870">How darest thou venture man, what strange medicine hast thou found, Ovid near taught it thee, I doubt I guess thy remedy, for love, go to a bawdy house or so, is't not?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102880" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102890">Faith, and that's a good way I can tell you, we younger brothers are beholding to it, alas we must not fall in love and choose whom we like best, we have no jointures for 'em, as you blessed heirs can have.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102900" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102910">Well I have found you sir, and prithee tell me, how gottest thou wenches?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102920" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e102930">Why I can want no panders, I lie in the constable's house.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102940" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102950">And there you may whore by authority,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102960">But Clerimont, I doubt this paragon</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102970">That thou so praisest, is some ill favoured wench</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e102980">Whom thou wouldst have me laugh at for commending. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e102990" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103000">By heaven I spoke in earnest, trust your eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103010">I'll show you her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103020" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103030">How canst thou do it? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103040">Thou knowest this lady's father is to mine</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103050">A deadly enemy, nor is his house,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103060">Open to any of our kindred. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103070" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103080">That's no matter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103090">My lodging's the next door to this lords house,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103100">And my back window looks into his garden,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103110">There every morning fair Leucothoe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103120">(For so I hear her named) walking alone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103130">To please her senses makes Aurora blush,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103140">To see on brighter than her soft appear. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103150" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103160">Well I will see her there ▪<stage xml:id="A07326-e103170">Exeunt.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e103180"><pb facs="6"/>Enter Franklin, Fancisco, Luce gravida.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103190" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103200">Yet for her sake be advised better sir,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103210" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103220">Impudent rascal, canst look me i'th face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103230">And know how thou hast wronged me, thou hast</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103240">Dishonoured my daughter, made a whore on her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103250" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103260">Gentle sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103270">The wrong my love has made to your fair daughter</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103280">'Tis now too late to wish undone again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103290">But if you please, it may be yet closed up</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103300">Without dishonour, I will marry her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103310" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103320">Marry her, she has a hot catch of that, marry a beggar, what jointure canst thou make her?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103330" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103340">Sir I am poor I must confess,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103350">Fortune has blessed you better, but I swear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103360">By all things that can bind, 'twas not your wealth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103370">Was the foundation of my true built love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103380">It was her single uncompounded self,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103390">Herself without addition that I loved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103400">Which shall for ever in my sight outweigh</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103410">All other women's fortunes, and themselves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103420">And were I great, as great as I could wish</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103430">Myself for her advancement, no such bar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103440">As fortune's inequality should stand</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103450">Betwixt our loves. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103460" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luce.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103470">Good father hear me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103480" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103490">Dost thou not blush to call me father, strumpet I'll make thee an example.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103500" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luce.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103510">But hear me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103520">Sir, my shame will be your own. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103530" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103540">No more I say, Francisco leave my house, I charge you come not here.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103550" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103560">I must obey and will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103570">Dear Luce be constant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103580" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luce.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103590">Till death</l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e103600">Exit Francisco.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103610" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103620">Here's a fine wedding towards, the</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103630">Bridegroom when he comes for his bride,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103640"><pb facs="7"/> shall find her great with child by another man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103650">Passion a me minion, how have you hid it so long? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103660" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103670">Fearing your anger sit, I strived to hide it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103680" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103690">Hide it one day more then, or be damned,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103700">Hide it till shallow be married to thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e103710">And then let him do his worst. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103720" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103730">Sir I should too much wrong him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103740" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103750">Wrong him, there be great ladies have done the like, 'tis no news to see a bride with child.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103760" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103770">Good sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103780" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103790">Then be wise, lay the child to him, he's a rich man, tother's a beggar.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103800" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103810">I dare not sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103820" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103830">Do it I say, and he shall father it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103840" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103850">He knows he never touch me sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103860" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103870">That's all one, lay it to him, we'll out face him 'tis his: but hark, he is coming, I hear the music, swear thou wilt do thy best to make him think 'tis his, swear quickly.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103880" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103890">I do.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103900" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103910">Go step aside, and come when thy que is, thou shalt hear us talk. <stage xml:id="A07326-e103920">Luce aside.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e103930">Enter shallow with music.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103940" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103950">Morrow father.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103960" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103970">Son bridegroom welcome, you have been looked for here.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e103980" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e103990">My tailor a little disappointed me, but is my bride ready.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104000" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104010">Yes long ago, but you and I will talk a little, send in your music.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104020" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104030">Go wait within, and tell me father, did she not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104040">Think it long till I came. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104050" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104060">I warrant</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104070">Her she did, she loves ▪ you not a little. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104080" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104090">Nay that I dare swear, she has given me many</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104100">Tastes of her affection. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104110" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104120">What before you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104130">Were married. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104140" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104150">I mean, in the way</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104160">Of honesty father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104170" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104180">Nay that I doubt,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104190">Young wits love to be trying, and to say</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104200">Truth, I see not how a woman can deny a man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104210">Of your youth and person upon those terms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104220"><pb facs="7"/> you'll not be known on't now. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104230" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104240">I have kissed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104250">Her or so. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104260" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104270">Come, come, I know you are no</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104280">Fool, I should think you a very ass, nay I tell</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104290">You plainly, I should be loath to marry my</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104300">Daughter to you if I thought you had not tried</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104310">Her in so long acquaintance, but you have tried</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104320">Her, and she poor soul could not deny you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104330" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104340">Ha ha hae.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104350" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104360">Faith tell me son, 'tis but a</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104370">Merry question, she's yours. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104380" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104390">Upon my</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104400">Virginity father. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104410" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104420">Swear not by that,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104430">I'll ne'er believe you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104440" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104450">Why then as I am</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104460">A gentleman I never did it that I remember. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104470" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104480">That you remember, o is't thereabouts.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104490" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104500">He'll take it upon him presently.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104510" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104520">You have been so familiar with her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104530">You have forgotten the times, but did you never</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104540">Come in half fuddled, and then in a kind humour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104550">Caetera quis nescit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104560" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104570">Indeed I was wont to serve my mother's maids so when I came half foxed as you said, and then next morning I should laugh to myself.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104580" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104590">Why there it goes, I thought to have chid you son shallow, I knew what you had done, 'tis too apparent, I would not have people take notice of it pray God she hide her great belly as she goes to church today.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104600" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104610">Why father is she with child?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104620" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104630">As if you knew not that, fie, fie, leave your dissembling now.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104640" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104650">Sure it cannot be mine.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104660" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104670">How's this, you would not make my daughter a whore, would you? this is but to try if you can stir my choler, your wits have strange tricks, do things over night when you are merry, and then deny 'em. But stay, here she comes alone, step aside, she shall not see us,</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e104680">They step aside.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104690" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104700">Ah my dear shallow, thou needst not have made</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104710">Such haste, my heart thou knowest was firm enough</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104720">To thee, but I may blame my own fond love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104730"><pb facs="8"/> that could not deny thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104740" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104750">She's with child indeed, it swells,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104760" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104770">You would not believe me, 'tis a good wench,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104780">She does it handsomely. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104790" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104800">But yet I know if</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104810">Thou hadst been thyself, thou wouldst near have</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104820">Offered it, 'twas drink that made thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104830" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104840">Yes sure, I was drunk when I did it, for I had</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104850">Forgotten it ▪ I lay my life 'twill prove a girl</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e104860">Because 'twas got in drink. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104870" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104880">I am ashamed to see anybody .</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104890" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104900">Alas poor wretch, go comfort her, Luce. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104910" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104920">Sweet heart, nay never be ashamed, I was a little too hasty, but I'll make thee amends, we'll be married presently.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104930" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104940">Be cheery Luce, you were man and wife before, it wanted but the ceremony of the church, and that shall be presently done.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104950" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104960">I ay, sweet heart, as soon as may be.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104970" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e104980">But now I think on't son shallow, your wedding must not now be public, as we intended it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e104990" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e105000">Why so?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105010" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e105020">Because I would not have people take notice of this fault, we'll go to church, only we three, the minister and the clerk, that's witnesses enough, so the time being unknown, people will think you were married before.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105030" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e105040">But will it stand with my worship to be married in private.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105050" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e105060">Yes, yes, the greatest do it, when they have been 〈◊〉 before hand, there is no other way to save your bride's credit.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105070" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e105080">Come let's about it presently.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105090" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e105100">This is closed up beyond our wishes.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e105110">Exeunt, manet Luce.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105120" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105130">I am undone, unless, thy wit Francisco,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105140">Can find some means to free me from this fool,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105150">Who would have thought the sot could be so gross</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105160">To take upon him what he never did,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105170"><pb facs="8"/> to his own shame, I'll send to my Francisco,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105180">And I must lose no time, for I am dead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105190">If not delivered from this loathed bed. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A07326-e105200">
          <head>Actus secundus.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e105210">Enter Philocles, Clerimont at the window.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105220" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105230">See Philocles, yonder's that happy shade,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105240">That often veils the fair Lucothoe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105250">And this her usual hour, she'll not be long,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105260">Than thou shalt tell me, if so rare an object</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105270">Ere blessed thine eyes before. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105280" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105290">Well, I would see her once,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105300">Wert but to try thy judgement Cleremont. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105310" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105320">And when thou dost, remember what I told thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105330">I would not be so sick, but soft look to thy heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105340">Yonder she comes, and that's her waiting woman. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A07326-e105350">Leucothoe and Psecas in the garden.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105360">Now gaze thy fill, speak man how likest thou her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105370" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e105380">Psecas. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105390" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Psecas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e105400">Madam.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105410" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105420">What flower was that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105430">That thou wert telling such a story of</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105440">Last night to me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105450" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Pse.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105460">'Tis call Narcissus madam ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105470">It bears the name of that too beauteous boy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105480">That lost himself by loving of himself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105490">Who viewing in affair and crystal stream</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105500">Those lips that only he could never kiss,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105510">Dotes on the shadow, which to reach in vain</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105520">Striving, he drownes thus scorning all beside</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105530">For the loved shadow the fairer substance died. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105540" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105550">Fie fie, I like not these impossible tales,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105560">A man to fall in love with his own shadow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105570">And died for love, it is most ridiculous. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105580" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Pse.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105590">Madam I know not, I have often seen</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105600"><pb facs="9"/> both men and women court the looking glass</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105610">With so much seeming contentation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105620">That I could think this true, nay wear it about 'em</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105630">As lovers do their mistress counterfeit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105640" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105650">That's not for love, but to correct their beauties</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105660">And draw from others admiration,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105670">For all the comfort that our faces give</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105680">Unto ourselves is but reflection</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105690">Of that fair liking that another takes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105700" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105710">I would we were a little nearer 'em</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105720">We might but hear what talk these wenches have</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105730">When they are alone, I warrant some good stuff. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105740" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105750">'Tis happiness enough for me to see</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105760">The motion of her lips. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105770" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105780">I'faith is't thereabouts . </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105790">Why Philocles, what lost already man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105800">Struck dead with one poor glance, look up for shame</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105810">And tell me how thou likest my judgement now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105820">Now thou dost see. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105830" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105840">Ah Cleremont too well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105850">Too well I see what I shall never taste,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105860">You lady's beauty: she must needs be cruel</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105870">(Though her fair shape deny it) to the son</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105880">Of him that is her father's enemy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105890">That, Cleremont, that fatal difference</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105900">Cheques my desire, and sinks my rising hopes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105910">But love's a torrent violent if stopped,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105920">And I am desperately mad: I must</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105930">I must be hers, or else I must not be. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e105940" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105950">Contain that passion that will else overwhelm</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105960">All virtue in you, all that is called man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105970">And should be yours, take my advice my heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105980">My life to second you, let us consult,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e105990">You may find time to speak to her and woe her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106000" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106010">May, nay I will in spite of destiny,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106020">Let women and faint hearted fools complain</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106030">In languishing despair, a manly love</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106040"><pb facs="9"/> dares show itself and press to his desires</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106050">Through thickest troops of horrid opposites,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106060">Were there a thousand waking dragons set</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106070">To keep that golden fruit: I would attempt</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106080">To pluck and taste it, 'tis the danger crowns</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106090">A brave achievement: what if I should go</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106100">And boldly woo her in her father's house</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106110">In spite enmity, what could they say? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106120" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106130">'Twere madness that not wisdom rash attempts</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106140">Betray the means, but never work the end. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106150" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106160">She would not hate a man for loving her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106170">Or if she did, better be once deemed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106180">Then live for ever hapless. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106190" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106200">But take time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106210">The second thoughts our wise men say are best. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106220" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Pli.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106230">Delay's a double death, no I have thought</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106240">A means, that straight I'll put in execution,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106250">I'll write a letter to her presently,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106260">Take how it will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106270" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e106280">A letter, who shall carry it?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106290" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Pli.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e106300">I'll tell thee when I have done, hast thou pen and ink in thy chamber.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106310" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e106320">Yes, there is one upon the table, I'll stay here at the window, and watch whether she stay or not, what a sudden change is this.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106330" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106340">Did not count Virro promise to be hear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106350">Today at dinner. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106360" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Pse.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106370">Yes madam that he did, and I dare swear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106380">He will not break. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106390" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106400">He needs not, he is rich enough, unless</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106410">He should break in knavery, as some of our merchants do now adays. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106420" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Pse.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106430">Break promise madam I mean, and that he will not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106440">For your sake, you know his business. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106450" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106460">I would I did not, he might spare his pains</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106470">And that unusual cost, that he bestows</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106480">In pranking up himself, and please me better</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106490"><pb facs="10"/> he would not please his tailor and his barber,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106500">For they got more for your sake by their lord</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106510">Then they got this twenty years before. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106520" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106530">Ah Psecas, Psecas, can my father think</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106540">That I can love count Virro, one so old</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106550">(That were enough to make a match unfit)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106560">But one so base, a man that never loved</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106570">For any thing called good, but dross and pelf,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106580">One that would never, had my brother lived</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106590">Have moved this suit, no I can never love him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106600">But canst thou keep a secret firmly Psecas. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106610" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Pse.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e106620">Doubt me not madam.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106630" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106640">Well I'll tell thee then,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106650">I love, alas, I dare not say I love him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106660">But there's a young and noble gentleman,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106670">Lord Euphues son, my father's enemy. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106680">A man whom nature's prodigality</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106690">Stretched even to envy in the making up,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106700">Once from a window my pleased eye beheld</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106710">This youthful gallant as he road the street,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106720">On a curvetting courser, who it seemed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106730">Knew his fair load, and with a proud disdain</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106740">Checked the base earth, my father being by</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106750">I asked his name, he told me Philocles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106760">The son and heir of his great enemy:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106770">Judge Psecas then, how my divided breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106780">Suffered between two meeting contraries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106790">Hatred and love, but loves a deity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106800">And must prevail against mortals, whose command</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106810">Not Jove himself could ever yet withstand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106820" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e106830">What is the letter done already, I see these lovers have nimble inventions, but how will you send it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106840" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e106850">What a question's that, seest thou this stone.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106860" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106870">Ah, than I see your drift, this stone must guide your</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106880">Fleeting letter in the air, and carry it to that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106890">Fair mark you aim at. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106900" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e106910">Hard by her.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106920" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <pb facs="10"/>
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106930">I think you would not hit her with such stones as this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106940">Lady look to yourself, he that now throws one</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106950">Stone at you, hopes to hit you with two. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106960" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e106970">But prithee tell me what dost think this letter may do.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e106980" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e106990">Well I hope,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107000">'Tis ten to one this lady oft hath seen you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107010">You never lived obscure in Syracuse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107020">Nor walked the streets unknown, and who can tell</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107030">What place you bear in her affections,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107040">Loved or misliked; if bad, this letter sent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107050">Will make her show her scorn, if otherwise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107060">Fear not a woman's wit, she'll find a time</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107070">To answer your kind letter, and express</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107080">What you desire she should, then send it boldly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107090">You have a fairer make there. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107100" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107110">Cupid guide my arm,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107120">O be as just blind God as thou art great,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107130">And with that powerful hand, that golden shaft</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107140">That I was wounded, wound you tender breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107150">There is no salve but that, no cure for me,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107160" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e107170">See what a wonder it strikes 'em in, how it should come.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107180" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e107190">She'll wonder more to see what man it comes from.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107200" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107210">I like her well, yet she is not afraid to open it:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107220">She starts, stay mark her action when she has read the letter. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A07326-e107230">She reads</stage>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:id="A07326-e107240">
              <body xml:id="A07326-e107250">
                <l xml:id="A07326-e107260">"Let it wrong this letter that it came,</l>
                <l xml:id="A07326-e107270">" from one that trembled to subscribe his name,</l>
                <l xml:id="A07326-e107280">"Fearing your hate, oh let not hate descend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A07326-e107290">" nor make you cruel to so vowed a friend,</l>
                <l xml:id="A07326-e107300">"If you'll not promise love, grant but access,</l>
                <l xml:id="A07326-e107310">" and let me know my woes are passed redress,</l>
                <l xml:id="A07326-e107320">"Be just then beauteous judge, and like the laws</l>
                <l xml:id="A07326-e107330"><pb facs="11"/>" condemn me not till you have heard my cause,</l>
                <l xml:id="A07326-e107340">"Which when you have, from those fair lips return</l>
                <l xml:id="A07326-e107350">" either my life in love, or death in scorn. </l>
                <closer xml:id="A07326-e107360">
                  <signed xml:id="A07326-e107370">Yours or not, Philocles. </signed>
                </closer>
              </body>
            </floatingText>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107380">Am I awake or dream I, is it true</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107390">Or does my flattering fancy but suggest</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107400">What I most covet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107410" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Pse.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107420">Madam the words are there,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107430">I'll swear it canna be, nor be illusion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107440" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e107450">It is too good for truth.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107460" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107470">Mock me not fortune,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107480">She kissed it, sawest thou her, by heaven she kissed it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107490" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107500">And with a look that relished love, not scorn,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107510" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e107520">This letter may be forged, I much desire to know the certainty, Psecas thy help must further me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107530" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Pse.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e107540">I'll not be wanting.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107550" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e107560">Here comes my father, he must not see this.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107570" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Pse.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e107580">No nor your tother sweet heart, he is with him yonder.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e107590">Enter Polimetes, Virro, Roscio. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107600" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107610">Nay noble count you are too old a soldier</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107620">To take a maid's first no, for a denial,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107630">They will be nice at first, men must pursue</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107640">That will obtain, woe her my lord and take her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107650">You have my free consent if you can get hers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107660">Yonder she walks alone, go comfort her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107670" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Virro</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107680">I'll do the best I may, but we old men</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107690">Are but cold comfort, I thank your lordship's love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107700" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107710">I wonder Roscio that the peevish girl</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107720">Comes on so slowly on persuasions</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107730">That I can use, do move the setting forth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107740">Count Virro's greatness, wealth and dignity</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107750">Seems not to affect her, Roscio. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107760" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Roscio.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107770">I doubt the cause my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107780">For were not that, I dare engage my life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107790"><pb facs="11"/> she would be won to love him, she has placed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107800">Already her affections on some other. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107810" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107820">How should I find it out</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107830" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107840">Why thus my lord</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107850">There's never man nor woman that ere loved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107860">But chose some bosom friend whose close converse,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107870">Sweeten their joys, and ease their burdened minds</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107880">Of such a working secret, thus no doubt</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107890">Has my young lady done, and but her woman,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107900">Who should it be, 'tis she must out with it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107910">Her secrecy if wit cannot o'erreach,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107920">Gold shall corrupt, leave that to me my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107930">But if her lady's heart do yet stand free</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107940">And unbequeathed to any, your command</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107950">And father's jurisdiction interposed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107960">Will make her love the count, no kind of means</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107970">Must want to draw her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e107980" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e107990">Thou art my oracle,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108000">My brain, my soul, my very being Roscio,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108010">Walk on and speed whilst I but second thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108020" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108030">It is even so, count Virro is your rival,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108040">See how the old ape smugs up his mouldy chaps</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108050">To seize the bit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108060" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108070">He must not if I live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108080">But yet her father brings him that has the means</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108090">That I should ever want. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108100" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108110">If he do marry her</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108120">Revenge it nobly, make him a cuckold boy,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108130" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108140">Thou jests that feels it not, prithee let's go,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108150" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108160">Stay, I'll not curse him briefly for thy sake,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108170">If thou dost marry her mayest thou be made</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108180">A cuckold without profit, and ne'er get</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108190">An office by it, nor favour at the court,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108200">But may thy large ill got treasury</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108210">Be spent in her bought lust, and thine own gold</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108220">Bring thee adulterers, so farewell good count. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e108230">Exeunt Phiocles.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e108240"><pb facs="12"/>Enter servant. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108250" who="A07326-servant">
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108260">My lord, there's a messenger within</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108270">Desire's access, has business of import,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108280">Which to no ear but yours he must impart. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e108290">Enter Eugenio disguised.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108300" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e108310">Admit him, now friend, your business with me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108320" who="A07326-servant">
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e108330">If you be the lord Polimetes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108340" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e108350">The same.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108360" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Euge.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108370">My lord, I come from Athens with such news</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108380">As I dare say is welcome though unlooked for,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108390">Your son Eugenio lives whom you so long</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108400">Thought dead and mourned for. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108410" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e108420">How, lives.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108430" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Euge.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108440">Upon my life my lord I saw him well</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108450">Within these few days. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108460" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108470">Thanks for thy good news,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108480">Towards him Roscio, but now tell me friend</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108490">Hast thou revealed this news to any man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108500">In Syracuse but me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108510" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108520">To none my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108530">At every place where I have stayed in town,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108540">Enquiring for your lordship's house, I heard</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108550">These tragic, but false news, the contrary</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108560">I still concealed, though knew, intending first</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108570">Your lordship's ear should drink it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108580" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108590">Worthy friend. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108600">I now must thank your wisdom as your love</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108610">In this well carried action, I'll requite it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108620">Mean time pray use my house, and still continue your</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108630">Silence in this business, Roscio make him welcome, and</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108640">Part as little from him as you can for fear. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108650" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e108660">Think it done, my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108670" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e108680">Psecas come hither.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108690" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vi●</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108700">Be like yourself, let not a cruel doom</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108710">Pass those fair lips, that never were ordained</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108720"><pb facs="12"/> to kill, but to revive. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108730" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108740">Neither my lord</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108750">Lies in the power to do. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108760" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108770">Yes sweet to me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108780">Whom your scorn kills, and pity will revive. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108790" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e108800">Pity is showed to men in misery.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108810" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e108820">And so am I, if not relieved by you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108830" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e108840">'Twere pride in me, my lord, to think it so.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108850" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e108860">I am your beauties captive.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108870" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108880">Then my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108890">What greater gift than freedom can I give,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108900">'Tis that that captives most desires, and that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108910">You shall command, you're free from me my lord,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108920" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e108930">Your beauty contradicts that freedom lady.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108940" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108950">Come noble count, I must for this time interrupt you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e108960">You'll find time enough within to talk. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e108970" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e108980">I'll wait upon your lordship.<stage xml:id="A07326-e108990">Exeunt manet Euge. solus.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109000" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Euge.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109010">Thus in disguise I have discovered all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109020">And found the cause of my reported death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109030">Which did at first amaze me, but 'tis well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109040">'Tis to draw on the match between my sister</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109050">And this rich count, heaven grant it be content</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109060">As well as fortune to her, but I fear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109070">She cannot love his age, how it succeeds</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109080">I shall perceive, and whilst unknown I stay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109090">I cannot hurt the project, help I may. <stage xml:id="A07326-e109100">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e109110">Enter Francisco, Sumner.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109120" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109130">This will make good work for you in the spiritual</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109140">Court, shallow is a rich man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109150" who="A07326-summoner">
            <speaker>Summoner</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109160">I marry sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109170">Those are the men we look for, there's somewhat</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109180">To be got, the court has many businesses at this</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109190">Time, but they are little worth, a few waiting</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109200">Women got with child by serving-men or so, scarce</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109210">Worth the citing. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109220" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109230">Do not their masters get</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109240">'Em with child sometimes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109250" who="A07326-summoner">
            <speaker>Summoner</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109260">Yes no doubt, but</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109270">They have got a trick to put 'em off upon their</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109280">Men, and for a little portion save their</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109290"><pb facs="13"/> own credits; besides, these private marriages</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109300">Are much out of our way, we cannot know when</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109310">There is a fault. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109320" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109330">Well, these are no</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109340">Starters I warrant you, shallow shall not deny it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109350">And for the wench she need not confess it, she has</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109360">A mark that will betray her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109370" who="A07326-summoner">
            <speaker>Summoner</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109380">I thank you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109390">Sir for your good intelligence, I hope 'tis certain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109400" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109410">Fear not that, is your citation ready.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109420" who="A07326-summoner">
            <speaker>Summoner</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109430">I have it here.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109440" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109450">Well step aside, and come when I call, I hear 'em coming. <stage xml:id="A07326-e109460">Exit Sumner.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e109470">Enter Franklin, shallow, Luce, parson. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109480" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109490">Set forward there, Francisco what make you here.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109500" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109510">I come to claim my right, parson take heed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109520">Thou art the author of adultery</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109530">If thou conjoin this couple, she's my wife. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109540" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109550">You saucebox.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109560" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109570">Father, I thought she had been mine, I hope I shall not lose her thus.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109580" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109590">Francisco, dare not to interrupt us, for I swear thou shalt endure the law's extremity</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109600">For thy presumption. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109610" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109620">Do your worst, I fear not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109630">I was contracted to her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109640" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109650">What witness have you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109660" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109670">Heaven is my witness, whose imperial eye saw our contract.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109680" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109690">What an ass is this to talk of contracting, he that will get a wench, must make her bigger as I have done, and not contract.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109700" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109710">Sir, you are abused.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109720" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109730">Why so.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109740" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109750">The wife you go to marry is with child, and by another.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109760" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109770">A good jest i'faith, make me believe that.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109780" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109790">How comes this fool possessed, he never touched her I dare swear.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109800" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109810">No more Francisco as you will answer it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109820">Parson set forward there. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109830" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109840">Stay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109850">If this will not suffice, Sumner come forth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109860" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e109870">A sumner, we are all betrayed. <stage xml:id="A07326-e109880">Enter Sumner.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109890" who="A07326-summoner">
            <speaker>Summoner</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109900">God save you all, I think you guess my business,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109910"><pb facs="13"/> these are to cite to the spiritual court</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109920">You master shallow, and you mistress Luce,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109930">Ask not the cause, for 'tis apparent here,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109940">A carnal copulation, ante matrimonium. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109950" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109960">This was a bar unlooked for, spiteful Francisco</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e109970" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109980">Injurious franklin, could the laws divine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e109990">Or humane suffer, such an impious act,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110000">That thou shouldst take my true and lawful wife,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110010">And great with child by me, to give t'another,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110020">Gulling his poor simplicity. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110030" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e110040">Do you mean me sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110050" who="A07326-summoner">
            <speaker>Summoner</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e110060">Gallants farewell, my writ shall be obeyed.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110070" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e110080">Summer it shall.<stage xml:id="A07326-e110090">Exit summer</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110100" who="A07326-parson">
            <speaker>Parson</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110110">I'll take my leave, there's nothing now for me to do</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110120" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e110130">Farewell good master parson. <stage xml:id="A07326-e110140">Exit parson</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110150" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e110160">Francisco canst thou say thou ever lovedst my daughter, and wouldst thou thus disgrace her openly.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110170" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110180">No, I would win her thus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110190">And did you hold her credit half so dear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110200">As I, or her content, you would not thus</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110210">Take her from me, and thrust her against her will</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110220">On this rich fool. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110230" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e110240">You are very bold with me sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110250" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e110260">Let me have news what happens dearest luce. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110270" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e110280">Else let me die.<stage xml:id="A07326-e110290">Exit Francisco.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110300" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110310">This was your doing Luce, it had been</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110320">Unpossible he should ere have known the time</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110330">So truly else, but I'll take an order next time</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110340">For you babbling. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110350" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e110360">What's the matter father.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110370" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110380">We may</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110390">Thank you for it, this was your haste that will</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110400">Now shame us all, you must be doing a fore your</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110410">Time. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110420" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110430">'Twas but a trick of youth father,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110440" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110450">And therefore now you must e'en stand in a</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110460">White sheet for all to gaze at. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110470" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110480">How,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110490">I would be loath to wear a surplice now, 'tis a</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110500">Disgrace the house of the shallows never knew ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110510" who="A07326-francisco">
            <pb facs="14"/>
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e110520">All the hope is, officers may be bribed, and so they will, 'twere a hard world for us to live in else.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110530" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e110540">You say true father, if 'twere not for corruption, every poor rascal might have justice as well as one of us, and that were a shame.<stage xml:id="A07326-e110550">Exeunt Shal. Luce</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110560" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110570">This was a cunning stratagem well laid,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110580">But yet Francisco thou'st not won the prize:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110590">What should I do, I must not let this cause</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110600">Proceed to trial in the open court,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110610">For then my daughter's oath will cast the child</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110620">Upon Francisco: no, I have found a better,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110630">I will before the next court day provide</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110640">Some needy parson, one whose poverty</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110650">Shall make him fear no cannons, he shall marry</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110660">My daughter to rich shallow, when 'tis done</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110670">Our gold shall make a silence in the court. <stage xml:id="A07326-e110680">Exit ▪</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e110690">Enter Philocles, Psecas.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110700" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Pse.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110710">I must return your answer to my lady,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110720">He tell her you will come. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e110730" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110740">Come,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110750">And such a angel call, I should forget</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110760">All offices of nature, all that men</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110770">Wish in their second thoughts, ere such a duty</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110780">Commend my service to her, and to you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110790">My thanks for this kind message.<stage xml:id="A07326-e110800">Exit Psecas.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110810">I never breathed till now, never till now now</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110820">Did my life relish sweetness, break not heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110830">Crack not ye feeble ministers of nature</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110840">With inundation of such swelling joy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110850">Too great to bear without expression:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110860">The lady writes that she has known me long</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110870">By sight, and loved me, and she seems to thank</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110880">Her stars she loves, and is beloved again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110890">She speaks my very thoughts, by heaven 'tis strange</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110900">And happy when affections thus can meet;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110910">She further writes at such an hour today,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110920"><pb facs="14"/> her father's absence, and all household spies</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110930">Fitly removed, shall give access to me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110940">Unmarked to visit her, where she alone</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110950">Will entertain discourse and welcome me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110960">I hope 'tis truly meant, why should I fear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110970">But wisdom bids me fear: fie, fie, 'tis base,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110980">To wrong a creature of that excellence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e110990">With such suspicion I should injure her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111000">I will as soon suspect an angel false,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111010">Treason ne'er lodged within so fair a breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111020">No, if her hand betray me, I will will run</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111030">On any danger, 'tis alike to me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111040">To die, or find her false, for on her truth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111050">Hangs my chief being, well I'll lose no time</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111060">No not a minute, dearest love I come,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111070">To meet my sweetest wishes I will fly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111080">Heaven and my truth, shield me from treachery. <stage xml:id="A07326-e111090">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A07326-e111100">
          <head>Actus tertius.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e111110">Enter Polimetes, Roscio, Eugenio, Psecas.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111120" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111130">I cannot credit it, nor think that she</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111140">Of all the noble youth in Sicily,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111150">Should make so strange a choice, that none but he,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111160">None but the son of my vowed enemy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111170">Must be her mate, it strikes me to amaze,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111180">Minion take heed, do not belie your mistress. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111190" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Pse.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111200">Mercy forsake me if I do my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111210">You charged me to confess the truth to you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111220">Which I have fully done, and presently</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111230">I'll bring you where concealed, you shall both see</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111240">Their privacy and hear their conference. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111250" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111260">Well I believe thee wench, and will reward</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111270">Thy trust in this, go get thee in again</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111280">And bring me word when Philocles is come,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111290"><pb facs="15"/> sir you'll be secret to our purpose. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111300" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Euge.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e111310">As your own breast my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111320" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111330">I shall rest thankful to you:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111340">This stranger must be soothed lest he mar all. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111350" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Rosc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e111360">This was well found out my lord, you now have means to take your enemy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111370" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111380">With blessed occasion I will so pursue</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111390">As childless Euphes shall for ever rue. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111400">Rise in thy blackest look direst Nemesis</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111410">Assistant to my purpose, help me glut</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111420">My thirsty soul with blood. This bold young man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111430">To his rash love shall sacrifice his life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111440" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e111450">What course you intend, to ruin him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111460" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e111470">Why kill him presently.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111480" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111490">O no my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111500">You'll rue that action, think not that the law</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111510">Will let such murder sleep unpunished. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111520" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111530">Should I now let him go now I have caught him</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111540" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e111550">Yes sir, to catch him faster, and more safely.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111560" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e111570">How should that be? speak man.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111580" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111590">Why thus my lord;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111600">You know the law speaks death to any man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111610">That steals an heir without her friend's consent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111620">This must he do, his love will prompt him to it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111630">For he can never hope by your consent</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111640">To marry her, and she 'tis like will give</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111650">Content, for women's love is violent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111660">Then mark their passage you shall easily find</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111670">How to surprise them at your will my lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111680" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111690">Thou art my oracle dear Roscio,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111700">Here's Psecas come again; how now what news? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111710" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Pse.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e111720">My lord they both are coming please you withdraw, you shall both hear and see what you desire.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e111730">Enter Philocles and Leucothoe. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111740" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111750">Ye are welcome noble sir and did my power,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111760">Answer my love your visitation,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111770"><pb facs="15"/> should be more free, and your deserved welcome</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111780">Expressed in better fashion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111790" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111800">Best of ladies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111810">It is so well, so excellently well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111820">Coming from your wished love, my barren thanks</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111830">Wants language for't, there lies in your fair looks</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111840">More entertainment than in all the pomp</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111850">That the vain Persian ever taught the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111860">Your presence is the welcome I expected,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111870">That makes it perfect. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111880" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111890">'Tis your noble thought</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111900">Makes good what's wanting here, but gentle friend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111910">For so I now dare call you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111920" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111930">'Tis well minion you are bold</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111940">Enough I see to choose your friends without my leave. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111950" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e111960">'Tis my ambition ever to be yours.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e111970" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111980">Think me not light, dear Philocles, so soon</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e111990">To grant thee love, that others might have sought</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112000">With eagerest pursuit, and not obtained,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112010">But I was yours by fate, and long have been,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112020">Before you wood Leucothoe was won,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112030">And yours without resistance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112040" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112050">O my stars</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112060">'Twas your kind influence, that whist I slept</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112070">In dullest ignorance, contrived for me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112080">The way to crown me with felicity. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112090" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112100">You may be deceived though,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112110">You have no such great reason</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112120">To thank your stars if you knew all. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112130" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112140">And know fair mistress you have met a love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112150">That time, nor fate, nor death can ever change,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112160">A man that but in you can have no being:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112170">Let this kiss seal my faith. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112180" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e112190">And this mine.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112200" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e112210">Nay to't again, your sweet meat shall have sour sauce.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112220" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112230">But sweet, 'mongst all these roses there's one thorn</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112240">That pricks and galls me, our parents enmity</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112250">Will cross our loves, I do assure my son</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112260">This father never will give his consent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112270" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <pb facs="16"/>
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112280">No so I think, he moves me still to Virro</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112290">That old crazed count, and with such vehemency</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112300">I dare scarce bide his presence if I deny him;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112310">Therefore we must be speedy in our course,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112320">And take without his leave what he denies. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112330" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e112340">I thank you for that good daughter.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112350" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e112360">I told you sir 'twould come to this at last.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112370" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112380">O thou hast spoke my wishes, and hath showed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112390">Thyself in love as true as beautiful;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112400">Then let's away dearest Leucothoe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112410">My fortunes are not poor, then fear no want,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112420">This constant love of ours may prove so happy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112430">To reconcile our parents enmity. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112440" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e112450">Heaven grant it may.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112460" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Po.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e112470">Never by this means youngster.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112480" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e112490">But soft now I think better on't I'll not go.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112500" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e112510">Why dearest, is thy love so quickly cold?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112520" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112530">No, but I'll not venture thee, thine is the danger,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112540">Thou knowest 'tis death by law to steal an heir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112550">And my dear brothers most untimely death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112560">Hath lately made me one, what if thou shouldst be taken. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112570" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112580">O fear not that, had I a thousand lives,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112590">They were too small a venture for such prize,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112600">I tell thee sweet, a face not half so fair</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112610">As thine, hath armed whole actions in the field,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112620">And brought a thousand ships to Tenedos,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112630">To sack lamented Troy, and should I fear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112640">To venture one poor life, and such a life</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112650">As would be lost in nor possessing thee:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112660">Come come, make that no scruple, when shall we go. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112670" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112680">This present evening, for tomorrow morning</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112690">My father looks that I should give consent</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112700">To marry with the count,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112710" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112720">Best of all, would 'twere this present hour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112730">I'll go prepare, but shall I call thee here. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112740" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e112750">O no, we'll meet.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112760" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e112770">Where dearest.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112780" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112790">East from the city by a river's side,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112800"><pb facs="16"/> not distant half a mile there stands a grove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112810">Where often riding by I have observed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112820">A little hermitage, there I will stay</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112830">If I be first, if you, do you the like,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112840">Let th'hour be ten, then shall I best escape. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112850" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112860">Ne'er sweeter comfort came from angels lips</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112870">I know the place, and will be ready there</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112880">Before the hour: I'll bring a friend with me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112890">As true as mine own heart, one Clerimont,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112900">That may do us good if danger happen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112910" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e112920">Use your pleasure.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112930" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112940">Dearest farewell,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112950">Hours will seem years till we are met again.<stage xml:id="A07326-e112960">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e112970" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112980">Ah sirrah, this gear goes well, god a mercy girl</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e112990">For thy intelligence, why this is as much as a</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113000">Man could desire, the time, place, and every thing;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113010">I warrant 'em they pass no further, well</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113020">Go thou in and wait upon thy mistress, she's</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113030">Melancholy till she see her sweet heart again, but</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113040">When she does, she shall not see him long,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113050">Not a word of what's passed among us for your life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113060" who="A07326-psecas">
            <speaker>Pse.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e113070">I warrant you my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113080" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113090">I'll not so much as show an angry look,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113100">Or any token that I know any of their proceedings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113110">But Rosio, we must lay the place strongly, if they</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113120">Should scape us, I were prettily fooled now after all</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113130">This. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113140" who="A07326-roscio">
            <speaker>Ros.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113150">Why 'tis impossible my lord, we'll go</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113160">Strong enough, besides I think it fit we took</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113170">An officer along with us to countenance it the</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113180">Better. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113190" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113200">Thou sayest well, go get one,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113210">I'll go myself along with you too, I love</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113220">To see sport though I am old, you'll go</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113230">Along with us to sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113240" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113250">I sir, you shall</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113260">Command my service when you are ready. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113270" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113280">Now Euphues, what I did but barely act</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113290">Thy bleeding heart shall feel, loss of a son</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113300">If law can have his course, as who can let it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113310">I know thou think'st mine dead, and in thy heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113320"><pb facs="17"/> laughest at my falling house, but let them laugh</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113330">That win the prize, things ne'er are known till ended. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e113340">Exeunt. Pol. and Ros.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e113350">Eugenio solus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113360" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113370">Well I like my sister's choice, she has taken a man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113380">Whose very looks and carriage speak him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113390">Worthy, besides he is noble, his fortunes sufficient,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113400">They both love each other, what can my father</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113410">More desire, that he gapes so after this old</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113420">Count ▪ that comes for the estate, as tother upon</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113430">My soul does not, but pure spotless love, but</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113440">Now his plot is for revenge upon his old enemy:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113450">Fie, fie 'tis bloody and unchristian, my soul</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113460">Abhors such acts, this match may rather</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113470">Reconcile our houses, and I desire where worth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113480">Is to have friendship, as on my soul 'tis there. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113490">Well Philocles I hope to call thee brother. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113500">Somewhat I'll do, I'll go persuade count Virro</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113510">Not to love her, I know the way, and I'll but</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113520">Tell him truth her brother lives, that will</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113530">Cool his love quickly; but soft, here comes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113540">The count as fit as may be. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e113550">Enter Virro.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113560" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113570">She loves me not yet, but that's no matter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113580">I shall have her, her father says I shall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113590">And I dare take his word, maids are quickly</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113600">Overruled, ah, ah, methinks I am grown younger</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113610">Than I was by twenty years, this fortune</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113620">Cast upon me, is better than Medea's charm, to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113630">Make an old man young again, to have a</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113640">Lord's estate freely bestowed, and with it such</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113650">A beauty as should warm Nestor's blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113660">Make old Priam lusty. Fortune I see thou lovest me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113670">Now, I'll build a temple to thee shortly, and</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113680"><pb facs="17"/> adore thee as the greatest deity. Now what are you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113690" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Euge.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113700">A poor scholar my lord, one that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113710">Am little beholding to fortune. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113720" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113730">So are most of your profession,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113740">Thou shouldst take some more thriving</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113750">Occupation, to be a judge's man, they are</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113760">The bravest now adays, or a Cardinal's</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113770">Pander, that were a good profession and gainful. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113780" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Euge.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e113790">But not lawful, my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113800" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Verro.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113810">Lawful,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113820">That Cardinal may come to be Pope, and</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113830">Then he could pardon thee and himself too. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113840" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113850">My lord I was brought up a scholar. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113860">And I thank your counsel, my</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113870">Lord, I have some for you, and therefore I</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e113880">Came. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113890" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e113900">For me, what I prithee.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113910" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e113920">'Tis weighty and concerns you near.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113930" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e113940">Speak, what is't?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113950" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e113960">My lord, you are to marry old Polimetes daughter.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113970" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e113980">And heir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e113990" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114000">No heir</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114010">My lord, her brother is alive. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114020" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e114030">How, thou art mad.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114040" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114050">My lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114060">What I speak is true, and to my knowledge</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114070">His father gives it out in policy to marry his</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114080">Daughter the better, to hook in suitors, and</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114090">Specially aimed at you, thinking you rich</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114100">And covetous, and now he has caught you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114110" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e114120">But dost thou mock me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114130" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114140">Let me be ever miserable if I speak</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114150">Not truth, as sure as I am here Eugenio lives,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114160">I know it, and know him, where he is. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114170" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e114180">Where prithee.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114190" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114200">Not a day's journey hence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114210">Where his father enjoined him to stay till your</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114220">Match, and sends word to him of this plot:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114230">Besides, I overheard the old lord and his man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114240">Roscio, laughing at you for being caught thus. </l>
          </sp>
          <pb facs="18"/>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114250" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114260">Why, wert thou at the house then. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114270" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114280">Yes, but had scurvy entertainment</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114290">Which I have thus revenged</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114300" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114310">Beshrew my heart I know not what</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114320">To think on't, till like enough, this lord was</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114330">Always cunning beyond measure, and it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114340">Amazed me that he should grow so extreme</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114350">Kind to me on the sudden to offer me all this:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114360">Besides this fellow is so confident, and on</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114370">No ends of cozenage that I can see; well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114380">I would fain enjoy her, the wench is</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114390">Delicate, but I would have the estate too, and</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114400">Not be gulled, what shall I do, now brains</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114410">If ever you will, help your master. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114420" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114430">It stings him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114440" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114450">Well, so, sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114460">What may I call your name? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114470" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114480">Irus my lord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114490" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114500">Your name as well as your attire</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114510">Speakers you poor. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114520" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114530">I am so. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114540" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114550">And very poor. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114560" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114570">Very poor. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114580" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114590">Would you not gladly take a course</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114600">To get money, and a great some of money. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114610" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114620">Is gladly if your lordship would but</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114630">Show me the way. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114640" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114650">Hark ye. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114660" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114670">O my lord, conscience. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114680" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114690">Fie, never</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114700">Talk of the conscience, and for law thou art</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114710">Free, for all men think him dead, and</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114720">His father will be ashamed to follow it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114730">Having already given him for dead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114740">And then who can know it, come be wise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114750">Five hundreth crowns I'll give. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114760" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114770">Well, 'tis poverty that does it, and not I,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114780">When shall I be paid. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114790" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114800">When thou hast done it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114810" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114820">Well give me your</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114830">Hand for it my lord</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114840" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114850">Thou shalt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114860" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114870">In writing, to be paid when I have</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114880">Poisoned him, and think it done. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e114890" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114900">Now thou</l>
            <pb facs="18"/>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114910">But love has made me bold, the time has been,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114920">In such a place as this I should have feared</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114930">Each rolling leaf, and trembled at a reed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114940">Stirred in the moonshine, my fearful fancy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114950">Would frame a thousand apparitions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114960">And work some fear out of my very shadow:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114970">I wonder Philocles is tardy thus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114980">When last we parted every hour, he said,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e114990">Would seem a year till we were met again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115000">It should not seem so by the haste he makes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115010">I'll sit and rest me, come I know he will. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e115020">Enter Philocles and Clerimont.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115030" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115040">This Clerimont this is the happy place</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115050">Where I shall meet the sum of all my joys,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115060">And be possessed of such a treasury</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115070">As would enrich a monarch. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115080" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115090">This is his voice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115100">My Philocles. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115110" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115120">My life, my soul, what here before me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115130">O thou dost still out go me, and dost make</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115140">All my endeavours poor in the requital</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115150">Of thy large favours, but I forget myself. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115160">Sweet bid my friend here welcome, this is he</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115170">That I dare trust next mine own hearth with secrets. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115180">But why art thou disguised thus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115190" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115200">I durst not venture else to make escape. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115210" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115220">Even now methinks I stand as I would wish</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115230">With all my wealth about me, such a love</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115240">And such a friend, what can be added more</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115250">To make a man live happy, thou dark grove</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115260">That hast been called the seat of melancholy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115270"><pb facs="19"/> and shelter for the discontented spirits;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115280">Sure thou art wrong, thou seemst to me a place</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115290">Of solace and content, a paradise</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115300">That givest me more than ever court could do</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115310">Or richest palace, blessed be thy fair shades,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115320">Let birds of music ever chant it here,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115330">No croaking raven, or ill boding owl</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115340">Make here their baleful habitation</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115350">Frighting thy walks, but mayst thou be a grove</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115360">Where loves fair Queen may take delight to sport:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115370">For under thee two faithful lovers meet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115380">Why is my fair Leucothoe so sad. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115390" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e115400">I know no cause, but I would fain be gone.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115410" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e115420">Whether sweet.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115430" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115440">Any whether from hence. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115450">My thoughts divine of treason, whence I know not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115460">There is no creature knows our meeting here</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115470">But one, and that's my maid, she has been trusty</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115480">And will be still I hope, but yet I would</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115490">She did not know it, prithee let's away</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115500">Anywhere else, we are secure from danger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115510" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115520">Then let's remove, but prithee be not sad. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A07326-e115530">Noise within.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115540">What noise is that. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115550" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e115560">Ay me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115570" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e115580">O fear not love.<stage xml:id="A07326-e115590">Draw.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e115600">Enter Polimedes', Roscio, Eugenio and officers.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115610" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e115620">Upon 'em officers, yonder they are.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115630" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e115640">Thieves, villains.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115650" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115660">Thou art the thief and the villain too,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115670">Give me my daughter thou ravisher. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115680" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e115690">First take my life.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115700" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115710">Upon 'em I say.<stage xml:id="A07326-e115720">Fight.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115730">Knock 'em down officers if they resist,<stage xml:id="A07326-e115740">They are taken.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115750" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115760">O they are lost, ah wicked, wicked Psecas;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115770" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e115780">So keep 'em fast, we'll have 'em faster shortly, and for you minion, I'll tie a clog about your neck for running<pb facs="19"/> away any more.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115790" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e115800">Yet do but hear me father.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115810" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115820">Call me not father thou disobedient wretch,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115830">Thou runaway, thou art no child of mine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115840">My daughter ne'er wore breeches. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115850" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115860">O sir, my mother would have done as much</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115870">For love of you, if need had so required,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115880">Think not my mind transformed as my habit. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115890" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115900">Officers away with 'em, peace strumpet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115910">You may discharge him, he's but an assistant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e115920" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115930">O stay and hear me yet, hear but a word</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115940">And that my last it may be, do not spill</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115950">The life of him in whom my life subsists,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115960">Kill not two lives in one, remember sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115970">I was your daughter once, once you did love me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115980">And tell me then, what fault can be so great,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e115990">To make a father murderer of his child,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116000">For so you are in taking of his life. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116010">O think not sir that I will stay behind him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116020">Whilst there be asps, and knives, and burning coals ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116030">No Roman dame shall in her great example</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116040">Outgo my love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116050" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116060">O where will sorrow stay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116070">Is there no end in grief or in my death</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116080">Not punishment enough for my offence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116090">But must her grief be added to afflict me;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116100">Dry up those pearls dearest Leucothoe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116110">Or thou wilt make me doubly miserable,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116120">Preserve that life, that I may after death</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116130">Live in my better part, take comfort dear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116140">People would curse me, if such beauty should</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116150">For me miscarry, no, live happy thou,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116160">And let me suffer what the law inflicts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116170" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116180">My offence was as great as thine,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116190">And why should not my punishment. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116200" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116210">Come have you done, officers away with him. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A07326-e116220">Exit Philocles.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116230"><pb facs="20"/>I'll be your keeper, but I'll look better to you. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116240">But rosy you and I must about the business:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116250">Sir let it be your charge to watch my daughter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116260">And see she send no message any whither,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116270">Nor receive any. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116280" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116290">It shall my lord.<stage xml:id="A07326-e116300">Exeunt manet Eu. and Leu.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116310">I'll be an Argus, none shall come here I warrant you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116320">My very heart bleeds to see two such lovers so</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116330">Faithfully parted so. I must condemn my father,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116340">He's too cruel in this hard action, and did not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116350">Nature forbid it, I could rail at him, to reek</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116360">His long fostered malice against lord Euphues thus</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116370">Upon his son, the faithful lover of his own</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116380">Daughter, and upon her, for should it come to pass</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116390">As he expects it shall, I think to would kill her</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116400">Too, she takes it —: see in what strange amazement</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116410">Now she stands, her grief has spent itself so</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116420">Far that it has left her senseless, it grieves</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116430">Me thus to see her, I can scarce forbear revealing</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116440">Of myself to her, but that I keep it for a</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116450">Better occasion when things shall better answer to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116460">My purpose: lady. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116470" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e116480">What are you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116490" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116500">In that my lord your father has appointed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116510">To give attendance on you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116520" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116530">On me, alas I need no attendance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116540">He might bestow his care better for me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116550" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116560">I came but lately to him, nor do I mean</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116570">Long to stay with him, in the mean time lady</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116580">Might I but do you any service. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116590" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e116600">All service is too late, my hopes are desperate.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116610" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116620">Madam, I have a feeling of your woe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116630">A greater your own brother could not have,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116640">And think not that I come suborned by any</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116650">To undermine your secrets, I am true,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116660">By all the gods I am, for further trial</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116670">Command me any thing, send me on any message</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116680">I'll do it faithfully, or any thing else</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116690">That my poor power can compass. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116700" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <pb facs="20"/>
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116710">O strange fate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116720">Have I lost pity in a father's heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116730">And shall I find it in a stranger: sir</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116740">I shall not live to thank you, but my prayers</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116750">Shall go with you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116760" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116770">'Tis not for thanks or need</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116780">But for the service that I owe to virtue</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116790">I would do this. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116800" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116810">Surely this man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116820">Is nobly bred, howe'er his habit give him:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116830">But sir, all physic comes to me too late,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116840">There is no hope my Philocles should live ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116850" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116860">Unless the King were pleased to grant his pardon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116870">'Twere good that he were moved. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116880" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116890">Ah who should do it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116900">I fear me 'tis in vain, count Virro</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116910">And my father both will cross it, but I would venture</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116920">If I could get but thither. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116930" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116940">That's in my power</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116950">To give you liberty, your father left me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116960">To be your keeper, but in an act</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116970">So meritorious as this, I will not hinder you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e116980">Nay I will wait upon you to the court. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e116990" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117000">A thousand thanks to you, well I'll go,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117010">Grant o you powers above, if virgin's tears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117020">If a true love's prayers had ever power</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117030">To move compassion grant it now to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117040">Armed with so strong a vigour, my weak words</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117050">They may pierce deep into his kingly breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117060">And force out mercy in spite of all opposers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117070" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e117080">Come let's away.<stage xml:id="A07326-e117090">Exeunt.</stage></p>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A07326-e117100">
          <pb facs="21"/>
          <head>Actus quartus.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e117110">Enter Francisco reading a letter.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117120" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117130">My dearest luce, were thy old sire as just</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117140">As thou art truly constant, our firm love</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117150">Had never met these oppositions,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117160">All my designs as yet, all practises</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117170">That I have used, I see are frustrated,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117180">For as my fair intelligencer writes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117190">He will before the next court day provide</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117200">Some careless person ▪ that in spite of laws</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117210">Shall marry her to shallow, this being done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117220">He means to hold the court's severity</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117230">To by a golden bit, and so he may,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117240">Alas it is too true, I must prevent it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117250">And that in time, before it grow too far;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117260">But how, there lies the point of difficulty:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117270">But what strange sight is this that greets mine eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117280">Alphonso my old captain, sure 'tis he. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e117290">Enter Allphonso. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117300" who="A07326-alphonso">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117310">Thus once again from twenty years exile,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117320">Tossed by the storms of fortune to and fro,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117330">Has gracious heaven given me leave to tread</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117340">My native earth of Sicily and draw</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117350">That air that fed me in my infancy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117360" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117370">'Tis he, most noble captain, o what power</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117380">Has been so gracious as to bless mine eyes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117390">Once more with sight of my most honoured master. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117400" who="A07326-alphonso">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117410">Kind youth the tears of joy that I have spent</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117420">To greet my native country have quite robbed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117430">Mine eyes of moisture, and have left me none</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117440">To answer thy affection, but tell me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117450">Tell me how thou hast lived in Syracuse</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117460">These five years here, since that unluckily storm</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117470">Divided us at sea. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117480" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117490">Faith poorly sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117500"><pb facs="21"/> as one that knows no kindred nor alliance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117510">Unknown of any have I shifted out,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117520">But I have heard you say that I was born</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117530">In Syracuse, tell me what stock I come of,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117540">What parentage, how mean soe'er they be,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117550">They cannot well be poorer than myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117560">Speak, do you know them sir? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117570" who="A07326-alphonso">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117580">Yes very well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117590">And I am glad the fates have brought me home,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117600">For thy dear sake, that I may now disclose</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117610">Thy honourable birth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117620" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e117630">Honourable?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117640" who="A07326-alphonso">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117650">Yes noble youth, thou art the second son</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117660">To old lord Euphues, a man more worthy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117670">And truly noble never drew this air;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117680">Thy name's Lysandro, this discovery</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117690">Will be as welcome to your friends as you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117700" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e117710">You do amaze me sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117720" who="A07326-alphonso">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117730">I'll tell you all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117740">It was my fortune, twenty a year ago,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117750">Upon the Tyrrhene shore, whose sea divides</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117760">This I'll from Italy, to keep a fort</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117770">Under your noble father, where yourself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117780">Then but a child, was left to my tuition,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117790">When suddenly the rude assailing force</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117800">Of strong Italian pirates so prevailed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117810">As to surprisal of the fort and us.</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117820">Your name and noble birth I then concealed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117830">Fearing some outrage from the enmity</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117840">Of those fell pirates, and since from yourself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117850">I purposely have kept the knowledge of it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117860">As loath to grieve your present misery</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117870">With knowledge of what fortunes you had lost,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117880">That this is true, you straight shall see th'effect,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117890">I'll go acquaint your father with the tokens,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117900">And make his overjoyed heart leap to embrace</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117910">Thee his new found and long forgotten son:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117920" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117930">Worthy captain, your presence was always</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117940">Welcome to me, but this unlooked for news, I</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e117950">Cannot suddenly digest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117960" who="A07326-alphonso">
            <pb facs="22"/>
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e117970">Well I'll go to him presently.<stage xml:id="A07326-e117980">Exit Alphonso.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e117990" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118000">Now my dear luce, I shall find means to quite</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118010">Thy love, that couldst descend so low as I</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118020">When I was nothing, and with such affection,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118030">This was my suit still to the powers above,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118040">To make me worthy of thy constant love. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118050"><stage xml:id="A07326-e118060">Exit Francisco.</stage>but I'll about the project I intended. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e118070">Enter Virro and Polimetes.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118080" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e118090">Why now my lord you are nearer to her love then ever you were yet, your rival by this accident shall be removed out of the way, for before the scornful girl would never fancy any man else.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118100" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e118110">I conceive you sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118120" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118130">I laboured it for your sake as much as for my</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118140">Own, to remove your rival and my enemy, you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118150">Have your love, and I have my revenge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118160" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118170">I shall live my lord to give you thanks, but<stage xml:id="A07326-e118180">Aside.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118190">'Twill be after a strange manner, if Irus has</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118200">Dispatched what he was hired too, than my kind</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118210">Lord I shall be a little too cunning for you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118220" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e118230">My lord you are gracious with the King.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118240" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e118250">I thank his majesty, I have his care before another man.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118260" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e118270">Then see no pardon be granted, you may stop any thing; I knew Euphues will be soliciting for his son.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118280" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e118290">I warrant you my lord no pardon passes whilst I am there, I'll be a bar betwixt him and the King, but hark the King approaches.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e118300">Enter the King with attendants.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118310" who="A07326-ambo">
            <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e118320">Health to your majesty.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118330" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118340">Count Virro, and lord Polimetes welcome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118350">You have been strangers at the court of late;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118360">But I can well excuse you count, you are about a wife,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118370">A young one and a fair one too they say,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118380"><pb facs="22"/> get me young soldiers count, but speak</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118390">When is the day, I mean to be your guest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118400">You shall not steal a marriage. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118410" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e118420">I thank your majesty, but the marriage that I intended is stolen to my hand, and by another.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118430" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e118440">Stolen, how man.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118450" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118460">My promised wife</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118470">Is lately stolen away by Philocles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118480">Lord Euphues son against her father's will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118490">Who followed 'em and apprehended them,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118500">The law may right us sir, if it may have course. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118510" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e118520">No reason but the law should have his course.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e118530">Enter Euphues.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118540" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e118550">Pardon dread sovereign, pardon for my son.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118560" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e118570">Your son, lord Euphues, what is his offence.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118580" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118590">No heinous one my liege, no plot of treason</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118600">Against your royal person or your state,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118610">These aged cheeks would blush to beg a pardon</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118620">For such a foul offence, no crying murder</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118630">Hath stained his innocent hands, his fault was love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118640">Love my dear liege, unfortunately he took</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118650">The daughter and heir of lord Polimetes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118660">Who follows him and seeks extremity. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118670" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118680">I seek but law, I am abused my liege,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118690">Justice is all I beg, my daughters stolen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118700">Staff of my age, let the law do me right,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118710" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118720">To his just prayers do I bend my knee</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118730">My promised wife is stolen, and by the son</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118740">Of that injurious lord, justice I crave. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118750" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118760">Be like those powers above, whose place on earth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118770">You represent, show mercy gracious King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118780">For they are merciful. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118790" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118800">Mercy is but the King's prerogative,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118810">'Tis justice is his office, doing that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118820">He can wrong no man, no man can complain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118830">But mercy showed oft takes way relief</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118840">From the wronged party that the law would give him:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118850" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118860">The law is blind and speaks in general terms,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118870"><pb facs="23"/> she cannot pity where occasion serves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118880">The living law can moderate her rigour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118890">And that's the King. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118900" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118910">The King I hope in this will not do so,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e118920" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118930">'Tis malice makes thee speak,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118940">Hard hearted lord, hadst thou no other way</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118950">To wreak thy cankered and long fostered hate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118960">Upon my head but thus, thus bloodily</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118970">By my son's suffering, and for such a fault</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118980">As thou shouldst love him rather, is thy daughter</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e118990">Disparaged by his love, is his blood base,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119000">Or are his fortunes sunk, this law was made</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119010">For such like cautions, to restrain the base</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119020">From wronging noble persons by attempts</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119030">Of such a kind, but where equality</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119040">Meets in the match, the fault is pardonable. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119050" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e119060">Mercy my sovereign, mercy gracious King.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119070" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119080">Minion who sent for you, 'twere more modesty</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119090">For you to be at home. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119100" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119110">Let her alone, speak lady,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119120">I charge you no man interupt her. <stage xml:id="A07326-e119130">Enter Leucothoe</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119140" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119150">If ever pity touched that princely breast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119160">If ever virgins tears had power to move,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119170">Or if you ever loved and felt the pangs</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119180">That other lovers do, pity great King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119190">Pity and pardon two unhappy lovers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119200" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e119210">Your life is not in question.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119220" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119230">Yes royal sir</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119240">If law condemn my Philocles, he and I</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119250">Have but one heart, and can have but one fate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119260" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e119270">Excellent virtue thou hadst not this from thy father.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119280" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119290">There's music in her voice, and in her face</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119300">More than a mortal beauty ▪ o my heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119310">I shall be lost in passion if I hear her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119320">I'll here no more, convey her from my presence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119330">Quickly I say. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119340" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e119350">This is strange.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119360" who="A07326-virro">
            <pb facs="23"/>
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119370">I told you what he would do, I knew</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119380">He would not here of a pardon, and I against it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119390">He respects me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119400" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119410">No doubt he does my lord ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119420">I like this passage well. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119430" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119440">But stay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119450">Stay lady, let me hear you, beshrew my heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119460">My mind was running of another matter. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119470" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119480">Where the devil hath his mind been all this while,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119490">Perhaps he heard none of us neither,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119500">We may e'en tell our tales again. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119510" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e119520">No sure he heard us, but 'tis very strange.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119530" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119540">'Tis such a tempting poison I draw in,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119550">I cannot stay my draught, rise up lady. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119560" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119570">Never until your grace's pardon raise me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119580">There's pity in your eye, o show it sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119590">Say pardon gracious King, 'tis but a word</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119600">And short, but welcome as the breath of life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119610" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119620">I'll further here the manner of this fact,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119630">Avoid the presence all, all but the lady,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119640">And come not till I send. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119650" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e119660">I like not this.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119670" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e119680">Nor I hear is mad dancing.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119690" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119700">Heaven bless thy suit thou mirror of thy sex,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119710">And best example of true constant love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119720">That in the sea of thy transcendent virtues</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119730">Drownest all thy father's malice, and redeemest</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119740">More in my thoughts then all thy kin can lose.<stage xml:id="A07326-e119750">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119760" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119770">Now lady what would you do to save the life</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119780">Of him you love so dear. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119790" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119800">I cannot think that thought I would not do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119810">Lay it in my power, and beyond my power</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119820">I would attempt. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119830" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119840">You would be thankful then</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119850">To me if I should grant his pardon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119860" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119870">If ever I were thankful to the gods</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119880">For all that I call mine, my health and being,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119890"><pb facs="24"/> could I to you be unthankful for a gift</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119900">I value more than those, without which</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119910">These blessings were but wearisome. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119920" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119930">Those that are thankful study to requite</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119940">A courtesy, would you do so? would you requite</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119950">This favour ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e119960" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119970">I cannot sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119980">For all the service I can do your grace</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e119990">Is but my duty, you are my sovereign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120000">And all my deeds to you are debts not merits,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120010">But to those powers above that can requite,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120020">That from their vastless treasures hope rewards,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120030">More out of grace then merit on us mortals,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120040">To those I'll ever pray that they would give you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120050">More blessings than I have skill to ask. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120060" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e120070">Nay but Leucothoe, this lies in thy power to requite, thy love will make requital, wilt thou love me?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120080" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120090">I ever did my lord. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120100">I was instructed from my infancy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120110">To love and honour you my sovereign. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120120" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e120130">But in a nearer bond of love.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120140" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120150">There is no nearer nor no truer love</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120160">Than that a loyal subject bears a prince. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120170" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120180">Still thou wilt not conceive me ▪ I must deal plain</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120190">With you, wilt thou lie with me, and I will seal his</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120200">Pardon presently; nay more, I'll heap upon you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120210">Both all favours, all honours that a prince can give. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120220" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120230">O me unhappy, in what a sad dilemma stands my choice. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120240">Either to lose the man my soul most loves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120250">Or save him by a deed of such dishonour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120260">As he will ever loathe me for, and hate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120270">To draw that breath that was so basely kept. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120280">Name any thing but that to save his life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120290">I know you do but tempt my frailty sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120300">I know your royal thoughts could never stoop</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120310">To such a soul dishonourable act. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120320" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120330">Bethink yourself, there is no way but that,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120340"><pb facs="24"/> I swear by heaven never to pardon him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120350">But upon those conditions. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120360" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e120370">O I am miserable.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120380" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120390">Thou art not if not wilful, yield Leucothoe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120400">It shall be secret, Philocles for his life</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120410">Shall thank thy love, but never know the price</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120420">Thou paidst for it; be wise thou heardst me swear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120430">I cannot now show mercy, thou mayst save him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120440">And if he die, 'tis thou that art the tyrant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120450" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120460">I should be so if I should save him thus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120470">Nay I should be a traitor to your grace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120480">Betray your soul to such a foe as lust,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120490">But since your oath is past, dear Philocles</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120500">I'll show to thee an honest cruelty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120510">And rather follow thee in spotless death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120520">Then buy with sinning a dishonoured life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120530" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120540">Yet pity me Leucothoe, cure the wound</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120550">Thine eyes hath made, pity a begging King,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120560">Uncharm the charms of thy bewitching face,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120570">Or thou wilt leave me dead: will nothing move thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120580">Thou art a witch, a traitor, thou hast sought</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120590">By unresisted spells thy sovereign's life:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120600">Who are about us there, call in the lords again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120610">Lord Polemetes, take your daughter to you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120620">Keep her at home. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120630" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e120640">I will my liege, Rosio see her there I wonder what is done.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120650" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120660">Euphues I have ta'en a solemn oath</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120670">Never to grant a pardon to thy son. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120680" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120690">O say not so my liege, your grace I know</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120700">Has mercy for a greater fault than this. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120710" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e120720">My oath is past and cannot be recalled.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120730" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e120740">This is beyond our wishes.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120750" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e120760">What made him swear this I wonder.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120770" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120780">A heavy oath to me and most unlooked for,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120790">Your justice sir has set the period</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120800">Unto a loyal house, a family</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120810">That have been props of the Sicylian crown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120820"><pb facs="25"/> that with their bloods in many an honoured field,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120830">'Gainst the hot French, and neopolitan</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120840">Have served for you and your great ancestors,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120850">Their children now can never more do so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120860">Farewell my sovereign, whilst I in tears</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120870">Spend the sad remnant of my childless age,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120880">I'll pray for your long life and happy reign,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120890">And may your grace and your posterity</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120900">At need find hands as good and hearts as true</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120910">As ours have ever been. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120920" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e120930">Farewell good old man.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120940" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120950">For you my lord, your cruelty has deserved</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120960">A curse from me, but I can utter none,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120970">Your daughter's goodness has weighed down your malice</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e120980">Heaven prosper her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e120990" who="A07326-polymetes">
            <speaker>Poly.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121000">Amen.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121010" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121020">He is an honest man and truly noble,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121030">O my rash oath, my lust, that was the cause,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121040">Would any price would buy it in again. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121050" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121060">Your majesty is just.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121070" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121080">'Tis a happy land</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121090">Where the King squares his actions by the law. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121100" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121110">Away, you are base and bloody,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121120">That feeds your malice with pretence of justice,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121130">'Tis such as you make princes tyrannous,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121140">And hated of their subjects, but look to't,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121150">Look your own heads stands fast for if the law</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121160">Do find a hole in your coats, beg no mercy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121170" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121180">Pardon us my lord, we were wronged.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121190" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121200">And sought redress but by a lawful course.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121210" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121220">Well leave me alone.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121230" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121240">Fare well my liege, now let him chafe alone.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121250" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121260">Now we have our ends.<stage xml:id="A07326-e121270">Exeunt.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121280" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121290">Is there no means to save him no way,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121300">To get a dispensation for an oath,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121310">None that I know except the court of Rome</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121320">Will grant one, that's well thought on,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121330">I will not spare for gold, and that will do it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121340">Nicanor. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121350" who="A07326-nicanor">
            <speaker>Nica.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121360">Sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121370" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121380">What book is that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121390"><pb facs="25"/> thou hadst from Paris about the price of sins. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121400" who="A07326-nicanor">
            <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121410">'Tis called the texes of the apostolical chancery.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121420" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121430">Is there a price for any sin set down.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121440" who="A07326-nicanor">
            <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121450">A my sir, how heinous ere it be,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121460">Or of what nature, for such a sum of money</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121470">As is set down there, it shall be remitted</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121480" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121490">That's well, go fetch the book presently.<stage xml:id="A07326-e121500">Exit Nic.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121510" who="A07326-nicanor">
            <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121520">I will my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121530" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121540">Sure there is perjury</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121550">Among the rest, and I shall know what rate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121560">It bears before I have committed it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121570">How now hast brought it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121580" who="A07326-nicanor">
            <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121590">Yes sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121600" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121610">Read, I would know the price of perjury,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121620" who="A07326-nicanor">
            <speaker>Nic</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121630">I shall find it quickly, here's an index.<stage xml:id="A07326-e121640">He reads</stage>imp. For murder of all kinds of a clergy man, of a lay man, of father, mother, son, brother, sister, wife.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121650" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121660">Read till you come at perjury.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121670" who="A07326-nicanor">
            <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121680">Item, for empoisoning, enchantments, witchcraft,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121690">Sacrilege, simony, and their kind and</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121700">Branches. Item, pro lapsu carnis, fornication</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121710">Adultery, incest without any exception or</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121720">Distinction; for sodomy, brutality, or any of</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121730">That kind. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121740" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121750">My heart shakes with horror</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121760">To hear the names of such detested sins,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121770">Can these be bought for any price of money,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121780">Or do these merchants but deceive the world</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121790">With their false wares ▪ no more of that foul book,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121800">I will know what I came to know,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121810">I would not for the world redeem my oath</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121820">By such a course as this, no more Nicanor</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121830">Unless thou find a price for atheism. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121840" who="A07326-nicanor">
            <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121850">Here's none for that my lord, his holiness</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121860">Can pardon that in no man but himself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121870" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121880">Well this is not the way,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121890">I have thought of another that may prove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121900">And both discharge my oath and save his life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121910">Nicanor run presently, call Matho hither,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121920">Matho the lawyer, command him to make haste,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121930"><pb facs="26"/> I long to be resolved. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121940" who="A07326-nicanor">
            <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e121950">I run sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e121960" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121970">He is a subtle lawyer, and may find</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121980">Some point, that in the law's obscurity</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e121990">He's hid from us, some point may do us good,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122000">I have seen some of his profession</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122010">Out of case as plain, as clear as day</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122020">To our weak judgements, and no doubt at first</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122030">Meant like our thoughts by those that made the law,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122040">Pick out such hard inextricable doubts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122050">That they have spun a suit of seven year long,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122060">And lead their hood wink clients in a wood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122070">A most irremovable labyrinth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122080">Till they have quite consumed 'em, this they can do</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122090">In other cases, why not as well in this. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122100">I have seen others could extend the law</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122110">Upon the wrack, or cut it short again</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122120">To their own private profits, as that thief</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122130">Cruel Procrustes served his hapless guests,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122140">To fit them to his bed; well I shall see,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122150">I would Nicanor were returned again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122160">I would fain ease my conscience of that oath,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122170">That rash and inconsiderate oath I took,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122180">But see, here they are coming. <stage xml:id="A07326-e122190">Enter Matho.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122200" who="A07326-matho">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e122210">Health to my sovereign.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122220" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122230">Matho, welcome. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122240">I sent for thee about a business</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122250">I would entreat thy help in. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122260" who="A07326-matho">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122270">Your highness may command my service</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122280">In that, or any thing lies in my power. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122290" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e122300">'Tis to decide a case that troubles me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122310" who="A07326-matho">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122320">If it lie within the compass of my knowledge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122330">I will resolve your highness presently. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122340" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122350">Then thus it is, lord Euphues son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122360">Young Philocles, has lately stolen away</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122370">The daughter and heir of lord Polimetes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122380">Who is his enemy, he following him hard</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122390">Has apprehended him, and brings him to his trial</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122400"><pb facs="26"/> tomorrow morning: thou hast heard this news. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122410" who="A07326-matho">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122420">I have my liege, and every circumstance</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122430">That can be thought on in the business. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122440" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e122450">And what will be the issue by the law.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122460" who="A07326-matho">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122470">He must die for it, the case is plain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122480">Unless your grace will grant his pardon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122490" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122500">But can there be no means thought upon</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122510">To save him by the law. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122520" who="A07326-matho">
            <speaker>Matho.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e122530">None my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122540" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122550">Surely there may, speak man, I'll give thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122560">Double fees. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122570" who="A07326-matho">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e122580">It cannot be my liege, the statutes is plain.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122590" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122600">Nay now thou art too honest, thou shouldst do</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122610">As other lawyers do, first take my money,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122620">And then tell me thou canst do me good. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122630" who="A07326-matho">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122640">I dare not undertake it, could it be done,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122650">I'd go as far as any man would do. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122660" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122670">Yes if 'twere to cut a poor man's throat you could,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122680">For some rich griping landlord you could grinned</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122690">The face of his poor tenant, stretch the law</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122700">To serve his turn, and guided by his angels,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122710">Speak oracles more than the tongues of men,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122720">Than you could find exceptions, reservations,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122730">Stand at a word, a syllable, a letter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122740">Or coin some scruples out of your own brains,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122750">But in a cause so full of equity</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122760">So charitable as this, you can find nothing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122770">I shall for ever hate all your profession. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122780" who="A07326-matho">
            <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122790">I do beseech your highness to excuse me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122800">I cannot do more than your laws will let me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122810">Nor falsify my knowledge nor my conscience. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122820" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122830">Then I am miserable, rise Matho rise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122840">I do not discommend thy honesty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122850">But blame my own hard fate, ay Philocles</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122860">I would redeem thy life at any price,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122870">But the stars cross it, cruel fate condemns thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e122880">Exeunt.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e122890"><pb facs="27"/>Enter constable and watch. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122900" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e122910">Come fellow watchmen, for now you are my fellows,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122920" who="A07326-watchman">
            <speaker>Watchman</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e122930">It pleases you to call us so master constable.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122940" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e122950">I do it to encourage you in your office, it is a trick that we commanders have, your great captains call your soldier's fellow soldiers to encourage them.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122960" who="A07326-watch_2">
            <speaker>2. watchman </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e122970">Indeed and so they do, I heard master curate trading a story book tother day to that purpose.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e122980" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e122990">Well I must show now what you have to do, for I myself before I came to this prefermity, was as simple as one of you, and for your better destruction, I will deride my speech into two parts. First, what is a watchman. Secondly, what is the office of a watchman. For the first, if any man ask me what is a watchman, I may answer him, he is a man as others are, nay a tradesman, as a vintner, a tailor, or the like, for they have long bills.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123000" who="A07326-UNASSIGNED">
            <speaker>●. Wat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123010">He tells us true neighbour, we have bills indeed.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123020" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123030">For the second, what is his office; I answer, he may by virtue of his office reprehend any person, or persons, that walk the streets too late at a seasonable hour.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123040" who="A07326-yyyy_4">
            <speaker>4. Wat</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123050">May we indeed master constable.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123060" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123070">Nay, if you meet any of those rogues at seasonable hours, you may by virtue of your office commit him to prison, and then ask him whither he was going.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123080" who="A07326-UNASSIGNED">
            <speaker>●. watchman </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123090">Why that's as much as my lord mayor does.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123100" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123110">True, my lord maior can do no more than you in that point.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123120" who="A07326-watch_2">
            <speaker>2. Wat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123130">But master constable what if he should resist us.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123140" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123150">Why if he do resist, you may knock him down, and then bid him stand, and come afore the constable. So 〈…〉 you are sufficiently constructed concerning you office take your stands, you shall hear rogues walking at these seasonable hours, I warrant you, stand close.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e123160">Enter Eugenio.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123170" who="A07326-missing">
            <pb facs="27"/>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123180">Purpose, now do I take as much care to be apprehended,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123190">As others do to scape the watch, I must speak</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123200">To be overheard, and plainly too, or else these dolts</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123210">Will never conceive me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123220" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123230">Hark who goes by?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123240" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123250">O my conscience, my conscience, the terror of a guilty conscience.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123260" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123270">How, conscience talks he of,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123280">He's an honest man, I warrant him, let him pass</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123290" who="A07326-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Wa.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123300">I ay, let him pass, good night honest gentleman.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123310" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123320">These are wise officers, I must be plainer yet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123330">That gold, that cursed gold, that made me poison him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123340">Made me poison Eugenio. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123350" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123360">How made me poison him, he's a knave I warrant him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123370" who="A07326-yyyy_3">
            <speaker>3. Wa.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123380">M. Constable has found him already,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123390" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123400">I warrant you a knave cannot pass me, go reprehend him, I'll take his excommunication myself.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123410" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Wa.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123420">Come afore the constable</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123430" who="A07326-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Wa.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123440">Come afore the constable.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123450" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123460">Sirrah, sirrah, you would have scaped</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123470">Would you, no sirrah you shall know the King's</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123480">Officers have eyes to hear such rogues as you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123490">Come sirrah, confess who it was you poisoned, he</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123500">Looks like a notable rogue. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123510" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Wa.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123520">I do not like</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123530">His looks. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123540" who="A07326-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Wa.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123550">Nor I.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123560" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123570">You would deny it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123580">Would you sirrah, we shall sift you,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123590" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123600">Alas master</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123610" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123620">I cannot now deny what I have said</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123630">You over heard me, I poisoned Eugenio son to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123640">Lord Polimetes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123650" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Wa.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123660">O rascal.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123670" who="A07326-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Wa.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123680">My</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123690">Young landlord. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123700" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123710">Let him alone, the law</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123720">Shall punish him, but sirrah where did you poison</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123730">Him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123740" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123750">About a day's journey hence, as he was</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123760">Coming home from Athens I met him, and</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123770">Poisoned him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123780" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123790">But sirrah who set you a work</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123800">Confess, I shall find out the whole nest of their</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123810">Rogues, speak. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123820" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123830">Count Virro hired me to do it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123840" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123850">O lying rascal.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123860" who="A07326-watch_1">
            <speaker>1. Wat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123870">Nay he that will steal will lie.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123880" who="A07326-watch_2">
            <speaker>2. Wat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123890">I'll believe nothing he says.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123900" who="A07326-watch_3">
            <pb facs="28"/>
            <speaker>3. Wat.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e123910">Be lie a man of worship.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123920" who="A07326-watch_4">
            <speaker>4. Wat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123930">A noble man</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e123940" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123950">Away with him, I'll hear no more, remit him to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123960">Prison; sirrah, you shall hear of these things</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123970">Tomorrow, where you would be loath to hear 'em. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e123980">Come let's go.<stage xml:id="A07326-e123990">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A07326-e124000">
          <head>Actus quintus.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e124010">Enter Franklin, shallow, Luce, Francisco in a parson's habit, and a true parson otherwise attired.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124020" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124030">I'll take your counsel sir, I'll not be seen in't, but meet you when 'tis done, you'll marry them.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124040" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124050">Fear not that sir, I'll do the deed.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124060" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124070">I shall rest thankful to you, till then I'll leave you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124080" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Sha.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124090">I pray father leave us, we know how to behave ourselves alone, methinks Luce we are too many by two yet.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124100" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luce.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124110">You are merry sir.<stage xml:id="A07326-e124120">Exeunt manet Franklin.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124130" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124140">Now they are sure or never, poor Francisco</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124150">Thou metst thy match, when thou durst undertake</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124160">To overreach me with tricks, where's now your sumner? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124170">Fore heaven I cannot but applaud my brain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124180">To take my daughter even against her will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124190">And great with child by another, her shame published,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124200">She cited to the court, and yet bestow her</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124210">On such a fortune as rich shallow is,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124220">Nay that which is the masterpiece of all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124230">Make him believe 'tis his, though he ne'er touched her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124240">If men never met with crosses in the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124250">There were no difference twixt the wise and fools,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124260">But I'll go meet 'em, when 'tis done, I fear not.<stage xml:id="A07326-e124270">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e124280">Enter Francisco, parson, shallow, Luce.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124290" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124300">Nay fret not now, you have been worse abused</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124310"><pb facs="28"/> if you had married her, she never loved you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124320" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luce.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124330">I ever scorned thy folly and hated thee, though</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124340">Sometimes afore my father I would make an ass</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124350">Of thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124360" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124370">O women, monstrous women,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124380">Little does her father know who has married her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124390" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luce.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124400">Yes, he knows the parson married me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124410">And you can witness that. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124420" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124430">And he shall know the parson will lie with her.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124440" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124450">Well parson, I will be revenged on all thy coat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124460">I will not plough an acre of ground for you to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124470">Tithe, I'll rather pasture my neighbour's cattle</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124480">For nothing. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124490" who="A07326-parson">
            <speaker>Parson</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124500">O be more charitable sir, bid God give 'em joy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124510" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124520">I care not greatly if I do, he is not the first</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124530">Parson that has taken a gentleman's leavings. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124540" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124550">How mean you sir?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124560" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124570">You guess my meaning, I hope to have good luck</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124580">To horseflesh now she is a parson's wife. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124590" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124600">You have lain with her then sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124610" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124620">I cannot tell you that, but if you saw a woman with child without lying with a man, than perhaps I have not.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124630" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luce.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124640">Impudent coxcomb, darest thou say that ever thou layst with me, didst thou ever so much as kiss my hand in private.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124650" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124660">These things must not be spoken of in company.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124670" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luce.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124680">Thou knowest I ever hated thee.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124690" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124700">But when you were i'th good humour you would tell me another tale.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124710" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luce.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124720">The fool is mad, by heaven my Francisco I am wronged. <stage xml:id="A07326-e124730">He discovers himself.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124740" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124750">Then I must change my note, sirrah, unsay</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124760">What you have spoken, swear here before</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124770">The parson and myself, you never touched her, or</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124780">I'll cut thy throat, it is Francisco threatens thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124790" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124800">I am in a sweet case, what should I do now, her</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124810">Father thinks I have lain with her, if I deny it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124820">He'll have about with me, if I say I have, this</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124830">Young rogue will cut my throat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124840" who="A07326-francisco">
            <pb facs="29"/>
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124850">Come will you swear.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124860" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124870">I would I were fairly off, I would lose my wench with all my heart, I swear.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124880" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124890">So, now thou art free from any imputation that his tongue can stick upon thee.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e124900">Enter Franklin.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124910" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e124920">Well now I see 'tis done.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124930" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124940">Here's one</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124950">Shall 〈◊〉 with you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e124960" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124970">God give you joy son</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e124980">
              <gap extent="1" unit="lines" xml:id="A07326-e124990" n="29-a-0770"/>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125000" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125010">I thank you father.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125020" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125030">How's this, Francisco in the parson's habit,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125040" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125050">I have married her as you bade me sir, but this</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125060">Was the truer parson of the two, he tied the</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125070">Knot and this gentleman is our witness ▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125080" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125090">〈…〉 undone, strumpet thou hast betrayed thy 〈…〉 beggary, to shame besides, and that in open court, 〈…〉 what thou hast sought, hang, beg, and starve, I'll 〈…〉.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125100" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125110">Good sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125120" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>S●●l.. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125130">I told you what would come on't.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125140" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125150">How did your wisdom lose her?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125160" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125170">〈…〉 you see ▪ I was beguiled, and so were you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125180" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125190">〈◊〉 take her, thou seest the portion thou art like to have.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125200" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125210">'Tis such a portion as will ever please 〈…〉 for her sake be not unnatural.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125220" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125230">Do not reject me father.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125240" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125250">But for the fault 〈…〉 were for, or shame she should endure in 〈◊〉, behold her yet an untouched virgin, cushion come 〈…〉 shallow, take your child unto you, make 〈…〉 prove as wise as the father.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e125260">He the cushion at him. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125270" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125280">This is more strange than tother, ah Luce, we●●</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125290">〈◊〉 so subtle to deceive thyself, and me; well</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125300">〈…〉, 'tis thine own choice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125310" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125320">Sir we can force no bounty from you, and there●●●● must rest content with what your pleasure is.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e125330">Enter Euphues, Alphonso.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125340" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125350">〈…〉 he is my lord, that's he in the parsons 〈…〉 thus disguised about the business I told you of<pb facs="29"/> Lysandro, see your noble father.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125360" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125370">Welcome my long lost son from all the storms</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125380">Of frowning fortune that thou hast endured</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125390">Into thy father's arms. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125400" who="A07326-luce">
            <speaker>Luce.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125410">I● my Francisco noble.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125420" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125430">Lord Euphues son, I am amazed.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125440" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125450">I hear Lysandro that you are married.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125460" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Francisco.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125470">Yes my lord, this is my bride, the daughter and heir of this rich gentleman, 'twas only she that when my state was nothing, my poor self and parentage unknown, vouchsafed to know, nay grace me with her love, her constant love.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125480" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125490">Such merit must not be forgotten my son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125500">Daughter much joy attend upon your choice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125510" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125520">Now wants but your consent.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125530" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125540">Which with a willing heart I do bestow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125550">Pardon me worthy son, I have so long</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125560">Been hard to you, 'twas ignorance</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125570">Of what you were, and care I took for her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125580" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125590">Your care needs no apology.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125600" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125610">But now Lysandro I must make thee sad</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125620">Upon thy wedding day, and let thee know</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125630">There is no pure and uncompounded joy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125640">Lent to 〈◊〉, in depth of woe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125650">Thou 〈◊〉 the knowledge of thy parentage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125660">Thy elder 〈…〉 Philocles must die,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125670">And 〈…〉, our name and house</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125680">Had 〈…〉 ever, had not gracious heaven</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125690">Sent as a courtier to my childless age,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125700">Thy long lost self supporter of the name. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125710" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125720">But can there be no means to save his life.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125730" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125740">〈…〉 none, the King has ta'en an oath</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125750">Never to 〈◊〉 him, but since they say</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125760">His majesty repents, and fain would save him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125770" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Franc,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125780">Then up I wretched, like a man long blind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125790">That comes at last to see the wished for son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125800">But find it in eclipse, such is my case,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125810">To meet in this dark woe my dearest friends,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125820" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <pb facs="30"/>
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e125830">Had you not heard this news before Lysandro?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125840" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125850">Yes sir, and did lament,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125860">As for a worthy stranger, but ne'er knew</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125870">My sorrow stood engaged by such a tie</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125880">As brotherhood, where may we see him sir? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125890" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125900">This morning he's arraigned, put of that habit</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125910">You are in, and go along with me, leave your</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125920">Friends hear awhile. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125930" who="A07326-francisco">
            <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125940">Farewell father,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125950">Dear luce till soon farewell, naught but so sad</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125960">A chance, could make me cloudy now.<stage xml:id="A07326-e125970">Exeunt</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e125980" who="A07326-franklin">
            <speaker>Frank:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e125990">Well Luce thy choice has proved better than we</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126000">Expected, but this cloud of grief has dimmed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126010">Our mirth, but will I hope blow over,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126020">Heaven grant it may. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126030">And signior shallow, though you have missed what</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126040">My love meant you once, pray be my guest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126050" who="A07326-shallow">
            <speaker>Shal.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e126060">I thank you sir, I'll not be strange.<stage xml:id="A07326-e126070">Exeunt</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e126080">Enter King, Nicanor.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126090" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126100">Nicanor, I would find some privy place</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126110">Where I might stand unseen, unknown of any,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126120">To hear the arraignment of young Philocles. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126130" who="A07326-nicanor">
            <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126140">The judges are now entering, please you sir</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126150">Here to ascend, you may both hear and see. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126160" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126170">Well I'll go up,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126180">And like a jealous husband here and see</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126190">That that will strike me dead, am I a King</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126200">And cannot pardon such a small offence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126210">I cannot do't, nor am I Caesar now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126220">Lust has uncrowned me, and my rash ta'e oath</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126230">H●s' 〈◊〉 of a King's prerogative,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126240">Come come Nicanor, help me to ascend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126250">And ●ee that fault that I want power to mend.<stage xml:id="A07326-e126260">Ascendant</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e126270">Enter ▪ judges, Virro, Polimetes, Euphues, Francisco, Leucothoe, Clerimont, Roscio. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126280" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Judge</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e126290">Bring forth the prisoner, where are the witnesses?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126300" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126310">Here my lords, I am the wronged party,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126320">And the fact my man, here besides the officers</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126330"><pb facs="30"/> that took them can justify. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126340" who="A07326-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Judge</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e126350">That's enough.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e126360">Enter Philocles with a guard.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126370" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Judge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126380">Philocles stand to the bar, and answer to such</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126390">Crimes as shall be here objected against thy life. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126400">Read the enditement. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126410" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126420">Spare that labour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126430">I do confess the fact that I am charged with,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126440">And speak as much as my accusers can,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126450">As much as all the witnesses can prove,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126460">'Twas I that stole away the daughter and heir</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126470">Of the lord Polimetes, which wert to do again</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126480">Rather than lose her, I again would venture,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126490">This was the fact, your sentence honoured fathers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126500" who="A07326-cleremont">
            <speaker>Cler.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e126510">'Tis brave and resolute.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126520" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Judge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126530">A heavy sentence noble Philocles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126540">And such a one, as I could wish myself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126550">Off from this place, some other might deliver,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126560">You must die for it, death is your sentence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126570" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126580">Which I embrace with willingness, now my lord,<stage xml:id="A07326-e126590">To Pol.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126600">Is your hate glutted yet, or is my life</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126610">Too poor a sacrifice to appease the rancour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126620">Of your inveterate malice, if it be to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126630">Invent some scandal that may after blot</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126640">My reputation, father dry your tears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126650">Weep not for me, my death shall leave no stain</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126660">Upon your blood, nor blot on your fair name ▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126670">The honoured ashes of my ancestors</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126680">May still rest quiet in their tear wet urns</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126690">For any fact of mine, I might have lived</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126700">If heaven had not prevented it, and found</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126710">Death for some foul dishonourable act. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126720">Brother farewell, no sooner have I found<stage xml:id="A07326-e126730">To Francisco</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126740">But I must leave thy wished for company. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126750">Farewell my dearest love, live thou still happy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126760">And may some one of more desert than I,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126770">Be blessed in the enjoying what I lose,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126780">I need not wish him happiness that has thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126790"><pb facs="31"/> for 〈…〉 bring it may he prove as good</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126800">〈…〉 worthy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126810" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126820">Dearest Philocles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126830">〈…〉 for any man but thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126840">〈…〉 good my lords</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126850">〈…〉 both together</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126860">〈…〉 alike, why should the law</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126870">〈…〉 and lay it all on him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126880">〈…〉 would we could as lawfully</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126890">〈…〉 he should not die for this,</l>
            <stage xml:id="A07326-e126900">〈…〉 constable leading Eugenio. </stage>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126910">〈…〉, who's that you have brought there? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126920">〈…〉 a benefactor, if it please your lordships,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126930">〈…〉 him in my watch last night. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e126940">
              <gap extent="1" unit="lines" xml:id="A07326-e126950" n="31-a-0920"/>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126960" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e126970">What's his offence?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e126980" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e126990">Murder.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127000" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127010">No master constable, 'twas but poisoning of a man.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127020" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127030">〈…〉 a fool.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127040" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127050">〈…〉 for ever, all will out.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127060" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127070">What proofs have you against him?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127080" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127090">His own profession if it please your honour.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127100" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127110">And 〈…〉 ill profession, to be a murderer, thou</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127120">〈…〉 has confessed the fact. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127130" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127140">Yes my lord, he cannot deny it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127150" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127160">Did he not name the party who it was that he had 〈…〉</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127170" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127180">Marry with reverence be it spoken. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127190">〈…〉 my lord Polimetes his son. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127200" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127210">How's this</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127220" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. ju</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127230">He died long sense at Athens. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127240" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127250">I cannot tell what I should think of it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127260">〈…〉 the man that lately brought me news</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127270">
              <gap extent="1" unit="lines" xml:id="A07326-e127280" n="31-a-2460"/>
            </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127290" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127300">〈…〉 to the bar, thou hearest thy accusation</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127310">〈…〉 say. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127320" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127330">Ah my good lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127340">〈…〉 deny what I have said,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127350">〈…〉, as my bleeding heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127360">Was making confession of my crime. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127370" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>C●n. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127380">I told him an● shall please your lordship's</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127390">〈…〉 King's officers had eyes to hear such rascals. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127400" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <pb facs="31"/>
            <speaker>1. Judge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127410">You have been careful in your office constable,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127420">You may now leave your prisoner,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127430" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127440">I'll leave the fell on with your lordship.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127450" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Judge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127460">Farewell good</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127470" who="A07326-constable">
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127480">Murder I see will out.<stage xml:id="A07326-e127490">Exit Con.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127500">Why didst thou poison him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127510" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127520">I was poor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127530">And want made me be hired. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127540" who="A07326-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Judge</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127550">Hired, by whom?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127560" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127570">By count Virro,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127580">There he stands. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127590" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127600">I do beseech your lordships not to credit</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127610">What this base fellow speaks, I am innocent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127620" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Judge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127630">I do believe you are, sirrah speak truth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127640">You have not long to live. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127650" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127660">Please it your lordship</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127670">I may relate the manner. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127680" who="A07326-yyyy_3">
            <speaker>3. Judge</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127690">Do.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127700" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eug.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127710">Eugenio was alive when first the news</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127720">Was spread in Syracuse he was dead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127730">Which false report count Virro crediting,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127740">Became an earnest suitor to his sister</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127750">Thinking her heir, but finding afterwards</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127760">Her brother lived, and coming home</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127770">Not a day's journey hence, he sent me to him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127780">And with a promise of five hundred crowns</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127790">Hired me to poison him, that this is true</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127800">Here's his own hand to witness it against him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127810">Please it your lordships to peruse the writing. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127820" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Judge</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127830">This is his hand.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127840" who="A07326-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Judge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127850">Sure as I live,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127860">I have seen warrants from him with just these</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127870">Characters. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127880" who="A07326-yyyy_3">
            <speaker>3. Judge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127890">Besides methinks this fellow's</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127900">Tale is likely. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127910" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127920">'Tis too true,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127930">This fellows sudden going from my house</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127940">Put me into a fear. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127950" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Judge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127960">Count Virro, stand to the bar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e127970">What can you say to clear you of this murder? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e127980" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e127990">Nothing my lords, I must confess the fact.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128000" who="A07326-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Judge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128010">Why then against you both do I pronounce. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128020">Sentence of death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128030" who="A07326-ambo">
            <speaker>Amb.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e128040">The law is just.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128050" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128060">Wretch that I am, is my dissembled grief</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128070">Turned to true sorrow, were my acted tears</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128080"><pb facs="32"/> but prophecies of my ensuing woe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128090">And is he truly dead. o pardon me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128100">De●ie ghost of my Eugenio, 'twas my fault</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128110">That called this hasty vengeance from the gods,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128120">And shortened thus thy life, for whilst with tricks</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128130">Brought to fasten wealth upon our house,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128140">Thought a cannibal to be the grave</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128150">Of me and mine, base bloody murderous count. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128160" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>V●r.. </speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e128170">Vile cozener, cheating lord, dissembler.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128180" who="A07326-UNASSIGNED">
            <speaker>●. Judge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128190">Peace, stop the mouth of malediction there,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128200">This is no place to rail in. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128210" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128220">Ye just powers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128230">That to the quality of man's offence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128240">●●●pe your correcting rods, and punish there</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128250">Where he has sinned, did not my bleeding heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128260">〈◊〉 such a heavy share in this day's woe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128270">Woes could with a free soul applaud your justice. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128280" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128290">Lord Euphues and Philocles forgive me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128300">To make amends, I know's impossible</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128310">For what my malice wrought, but I would fain</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128320">〈…〉 that might testify my grief</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128330">〈…〉 Repentance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128340" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e128350">This is that I looked for.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128360" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128370">You're kind too late my lord, had you been thus</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128380">〈…〉 required, y'had saved yourself and me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128390">〈…〉 sons, but if your grief be true</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128400">〈…〉 you heartily. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128410" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128420">And I,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128430" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128440">Now comes my que, my lord Polimetes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128450">〈…〉 correction let me ask one question. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128460" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e128470">What question? speak.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128480" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128490">If this young lord</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128500">〈…〉, would you bestow your daughter</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128510">〈…〉 upon him, would you lord? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128520" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e128530">As willingly as I would breathe myself.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128540" who="A07326-unassigned">
            <speaker>〈◊〉</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128550">Then dry all your eyes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128560">〈…〉 hear shall have a cause to week,<stage xml:id="A07326-e128570">To Phil.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128580">〈…〉, Leucothoe is no heir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128590">〈…〉 lives, and that clears you count Virro</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128600">〈…〉 Murder. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128610" who="A07326-all">
            <speaker>All.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e128620">How, lives?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128630" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <pb facs="32"/>
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e128640">Yes lives to call thee brother Philocles. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07326-e128650">He discovers himself.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128660" who="A07326-leucothoe">
            <speaker>Leu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e128670">O my dear brother.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128680" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128690">My son,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128700">Welcome from death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128710" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128720">Pardon me good my lord that I thus long</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128730">Have from your knowledge kept myself concealed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128740">My end was honest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128750" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128760">I see 'twas,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128770">And now son Philocles give me thy hand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128780">Here take thy wife, she loves thee I dare swear,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128790">And for the wrong that I intended thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128800">Her portion shall be double what I meant it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128810" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e128820">I thank your lordship.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128830" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128840">Brother Euphues,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128850">I hope all enmity is now forgotten</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128860">Betwixt our houses. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128870" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e128880">Let it be ever so, I do embrace your love.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128890" who="A07326-virro">
            <speaker>Vir.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128900">Well my life is saved yet, though my wench be lost,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128910">God give you joy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128920" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e128930">Thanks good my lord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128940" who="A07326-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Judge</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128950">How suddenly this tragic scene is charged,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e128960">And turned to comedy</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e128970" who="A07326-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Judge</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e128980">'Tis very strange. <stage xml:id="A07326-e128990">The King speaks from 〈◊〉</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129000" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e129010">Let us conclude within.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129020" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129030">Stay,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129040">And take my joy with you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129050" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129060">His majesty</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129070">Is coming down, let us attend. <stage xml:id="A07326-e129080">Enter King.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129090" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129100">These jars are well closed up, now Philocles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129110">What my rash oath denied me, this blessed how●e</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129120">And happy accident has brought to pass,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129130">The saving of thy life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129140" who="A07326-philocles">
            <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129150">A life my liege,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129160">That shall be ever ready to be spent</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129170">Upon your service. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129180" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129190">Thanks good Philocles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129200">But where's the man whose happy presence brought</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129210">All this unlooked for sport: where is Eugenio? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129220" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e129230">Here my dread liege.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129240" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129250">Welcome to 〈…〉</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129260">Welcome Eugenio, prithee ask some boon</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129270">That may requite the good that thou hast done. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129280" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129290">I thank your majesty, what I have done</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129300">Needs no requital, but I have a suit</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129310">Unto lord Euphues, please it your majesty</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129320">To be to him an intercessor for me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129330"><pb facs="33"/> I make no question but I shall obtain. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129340" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e129350">What is it? speak, it shall be granted thee.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129360" who="A07326-eugenio">
            <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129370">That it would please him to bestow on me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129380">His niece, the fair and virtuous lady Leda. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129390" who="A07326-euphues">
            <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129400">With all my heart, I know 'twill please her well,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129410">I have often heard her praise Eugenio,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129420">It shall be done within. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129430" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129440">Then here all strife ends,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129450">I'll be your guest myself today, and help</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129460">To solemnize this double marriage. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129470" who="A07326-polimetes">
            <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A07326-e129480">Your royal presence shall much honour us.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07326-e129490" who="A07326-king">
            <speaker>King.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129500">Then lead away, the happy knot you tie,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07326-e129510">Concludes in love two houses enmity. </l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A07326-e129520">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A07326-e129530">
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="A07326-e129540">
        <pb facs="33"/>
        <head>Epilogus.</head>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e129550">Our author's heir if it be legitimate</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e129560">'Tis his, if not, he dares the worst of fate,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e129570">For if a bastard, charity is such,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e129580">That what you give, it cannot be too much,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e129590">And he, and we, vow if it may be shown,</l>
        <l xml:id="A07326-e129600">To do as much for yours, as for our own. </l>
        <trailer xml:id="A07326-e129610">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A07326"><item xml:id="A07326-polimetes" n="77">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-polimetes</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">77</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-leucothoe" n="58">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-leucothoe</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">58</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-eugenio" n="58">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-eugenio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">58</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-philocles" n="57">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-philocles</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">57</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-virro" n="54">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-virro</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">54</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-king" n="53">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-king</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">53</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-francisco" n="51">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-francisco</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">51</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-franklin" n="50">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-franklin</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">50</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-shallow" n="42">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-shallow</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">42</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-cleremont" n="33">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-cleremont</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">33</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-unassigned" n="27">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">27</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A07326-roscio" n="24">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-roscio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">24</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-constable" n="23">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-constable</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">23</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-luce" n="22">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-luce</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">22</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-euphues" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-euphues</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-psecas" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-psecas</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-yyyy_1" n="13">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">13</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-nicanor" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-nicanor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-matho" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-matho</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-yyyy_2" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-yyyy_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-summoner" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-summoner</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-alphonso" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-alphonso</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-yyyy_3" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-yyyy_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-servant" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-servant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-watch_2" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-watch_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-UNASSIGNED" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-UNASSIGNED</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-ambo" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-ambo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-parson" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-parson</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-yyyy_4" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-yyyy_4</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-watch_1" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-watch_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-missing" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-missing</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-watch_3" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-watch_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-all" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-watch_4" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-watch_4</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-watchman" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-watchman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07326-polymetes" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07326-polymetes</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

