<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A31672">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Revenge for Honor (The Parricide) <date type="creation_date">1640</date></title>
        <author>Glapthorne, Henry</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Hannah Bredar</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A31672.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Revenge for honour a tragedie / by George Chapman.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>32 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">12260930</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Wing C1948.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">57887</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31672</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Revenge for honour a tragedie / by George Chapman.</title>
            <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
            <author>Glapthorne, Henry.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>63 p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1654.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The ascription to Chapman is not generally accepted. Has been identified with "The paraside, or, Revenge for honour", a play registered 1653 as the work of Henry Glapthorne. Cf. Parrott, T.M., ed. Plays and poems of George Chapman, the tragedies, p. 713-720; Thomas, D.L. Modern philology, Apr. 1908, p. 617-636; Cambridge hist. of Engl. lit., v. 6.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of original in British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A31672-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A31672-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A31672-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A31672-e100040">Revenge for honour. A tragedy, by George Chapman.</p>
        <p xml:id="A31672-e100050">London, printed in the year 1654.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A31672-e100060">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>The persons acting.</head>
        <list xml:id="A31672-e100070">
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100080">Almanzor caliph of Arabia.</item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100090">Abilqualit his eldest son.</item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100100">Abrahen his son by a second wife, brother to Abilqualit. </item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100110">Tarifa an old general, conqueror of Spain, tutor to Abilqualit. </item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100120">Mura a rough lord, a soldier, kinsman by his mother, to Abrahen. </item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100130">Simanthes a court-lord, allied to Abrahen. </item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100140">Selinthus an honest, merry court lord.</item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100150">Mesithes a court eunuch, attendant on Abilqualit. </item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100160">Osman a captain to Tarifa.</item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100170">Gaselles another captain.</item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100180">Caropia wife to Mura, first beloved of Abrahen, then of Abilqualit. </item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100190">Perilinda her woman.</item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100200">Soldiers, guard.</item>
          <item xml:id="A31672-e100210">Muts, attendants.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="prologue" xml:id="A31672-e100220">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>Prologue.</head>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100230">Our author thinks 'tis not i'th power of wit,</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100240">Invention, art, nor industry, to fit</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100250">The several fantasies which in this age</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100260">With a predominant humour rule the stage. </l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100270">Some men cry out for satyr, others choose</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100280">Merely to story to confine each muse;</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100290">Most like no play, but such as gives large birth</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100300">To that which they judiciously term mirth. </l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100310">Nor will the best works with their liking crown,</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100320">Except 't be graced with part of fool or clown. </l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100330">Hard and severe the task is then to write,</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100340">So as may please each various appetite. </l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100350">Our author hopes well though, that in this play,</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100360">He has endeavoured so, he justly may</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100370">Gain liking from you all, unless those few</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100380">Who will dislike, be't never so good, so new;</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100390">The rather gentlemen, he hopes, cause I</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100400">Am a main actor in this tragedy:</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100410">You've graced me sometimes in another sphere,</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e100420">And I do hope you'll not dislike me here. </l>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A31672-e100430">
      <head><pb facs="3" n="5"/>Revenge for honour.</head>
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A31672-e100440">
        <head>Actus primus.</head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A31672-e100450">
          <head>Scaena i.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e100460">Enter Selinthus, Gaselles, and Osman.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100470" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100480">No murmurings, noble captains.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100490" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100500">Murmurings, cousin? this peace is worse to men of war and action then fasting in the face o'th' foe, or lodging on the cold earth. Give me the camp, say I, where in the sutler's palace on payday we may the precious liquor quaff, and kiss his buxom wife; who though she be not clad in Persian silks, or costly Tyrian purples, has a clean skin, soft thighs, and wholesome corpse, fit for the trailer of the puissant pike, to solace in delight with.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100510" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100520">Here in your lewd city, the harlots do avoid us sons o'th' sword, worse than a severe officer. Besides, here men o'th' shop can gorge their musty maws with the delicious capon, and fat limbs of mutton large enough to be held shoulders o'th' ram anco●ge the 1● signs, while for pure want your soldier oft dines at the charge o'th' dead, among tombs in the great mosque.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100530" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100540">'Tis believed coz, and by the wisest few too, that i'th' camp you do not feed on pleasant: poults; a salad,<pb facs="4" n="6"/> and without oil or vinegar, appeases sometimes your guts, although they keep more noise than a large pool full of engendering frogs. Then for accoutrements, you wear the buff, as you believed it heresy to change for linen: surely most of yours is spent in lint, to make long tents for your green wounds after an onslaught.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100550" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100560">Coz. these are sad truths, incident to frail mortals!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100570" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100580">You yet cry out with more eagerness still for new wars, than women for new fashions.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100590" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100600">'Tis confessed, peace is more opposite to my nature, than the running ache in the rich usurer's feet, when he roars out, as if he were in hell before his time. Why, I love mischief, coz, when one may do't securely; to cut throats with a licentious pleasure; when good men and true o'th jury, with their frosty beards shall not have power to give the noble weasand, which has the steel defied, to th' hanging mercy of the ungracious cord.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100610" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100620">Gentlemen both, and cozens mine, I do believe 't much pity, to strive to reconvert you from the faith you have been bred in: though your large discourse and praise, wherein you magnify your mistress, war, shall scarce drive me from my quiet sheets, to sleep upon a turf. But pray say, cozens. How do you like your general, prince, is he a right Mars?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100630" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100640">As if his nurse had leapt him in swaddling clouts of steel; a very Hector and Alcibiades. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100650" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100660">It seems he does not relish these boasted sweets of war: for all his triumphs, he is reported melancholy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100670" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100680">Want of exercise renders all men of actions, dull as dormice; your soldier only can dance to the drum, and sing a hymn of joy to the sweet trumpet: there's no music like it.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e100690"><pb facs="4" n="7"/>Enter Abrahen, Mura, and Simanthes.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100700" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100710">I'll know the cause, he shall deny me hardly else.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100720" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100730">His melancholy, known whence it rises once, 't may much conduce to help our purpose.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100740" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100750">Pray coz. what lords are these? they seem as full of plot, as generals are in siege, they're very serious.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100760" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100770">That young stripling is our great emperor's son, by his last wife: that in the rich imbroidery's, the court Hermes; one that has hatched more projects, than the ovens in Egypt chickens; the other, though they call friends, his mere opposite planet Mars, one that does put on a reserved gravity, which some call wisdom, the rough soldier Mura ▪ governor o'th 'Moroccos. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100780" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100790">Him we've heard of before: but cousin, shall that man of trust, thy tailor, furnish us with new accoutrements? hast thou ta'en order for them?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100800" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100810">Yes, yes, you shall flourish in fresh habiliments; but you must promise me not to engage your corporal oaths you will see't satisfied at the next press, out of the profits that arise from ransom of those rich yeoman's heirs, that dare not look the fierce foe in the face.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100820" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100830">Doubt not our truths, though we be given much to contradictions, we will not pawn oaths of that nature.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100840" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100850">Well then, this note does fetch the garments: meet me cozens anon at supper.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e100860">Exeunt Gas. Os.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100870" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100880">Honourable coz ▪ we will come give our thanks.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e100890">Enter abilqualit.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100900" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100910">My gracious brother, make us not such a stranger to your thoughts, to consume all your honours in close retirements; perhaps since you from Spain returned a victor, with (The world's conqueror) Alexander, you grieve nature ordained no other earths to vanquish; if't be so, princely brother, we'll bear part<pb facs="5" n="8"/> in your heroic melancholy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100920" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100930">Gentle youth. press me no farther, I still hold my temper free and unshaken, only some fond thoughts of trivial moment, call my faculties to private meditations.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100940" who="A31672-simanthes">
            <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100950">Howsoe'er your highness does please to term them, 'tis mere melancholy, which next to sin, is the greatest malady that can oppress man's soul.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100960" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100970">They say right: and that your grace may see what a mere madness, a very midsummer frenzy, 'tis to be melancholy, for any man that wants no money, I (With your pardon) will discuss unto you all sorts, all sizes, persons and conditions, that are infected with it; and the reasons why it in each arises.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e100980" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e100990">Learned Selinthus, let's taste of thy philosophy</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101000" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101010">Pish, 'tis unwelcome to any of judgement, this fond prate ▪ I marvel that our emperor dos permit fools to abound ith' court!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101020" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101030">What makes your grave lordship in it, I do beseech you? But sir, mark me, the kernel of the text enucleated, I shall confute, refute, repel, refel, explode, exterminate, expunge, extinguish like a rush candle, this same heresy, that is shot up like a pernicious mushroom, to poison true humanity.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101040" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101050">You shall stay and hear a lecture read on your disease; you shall, as I love virtue.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101060" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101070">First the cause then from whence this flatus hypocondriacus, this glimmering of the gizzard (For in wild fowl, 'tis termed so by Hippocrates) arises, is as Averroes and Avicen, with Abenbucar, Baruch and aboflii, and all the Arabic writers have affirmed, a mere defect, that is as we interpret ▪ a want of —</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101080" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101090">Of what, Selinthus? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101100" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101110">Of wit, and please your highness,<pb facs="5" n="9"/> that is the cause in general, for particular and special causes, they are all derived from several wants; yet they must be considered, pondered, perpended, or premeditated.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101120" who="A31672-simanthes">
            <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101130">My lord, y'ad best be brief, your patient will be weary else.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101140" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101150">I cannot play the fool rightly, I mean ▪ the physician without I have licence to explicate on the disease. But (My good lord) more briefly, I shall declare to you like a man of wisdom and no physician, who deal all in simples, why men are melancholy. First, for your courtier,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101160" who="A31672-simanthes">
            <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101170">It concerns us all to be attentive, sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101180" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101190">Your sage and serious courtier, who does walk with a state face, as he had dressed himself ith' emperor's glass, and had his beard turned up by the irons royal, he will be as pensive as stallion after catum, when he wants suits, begging suits, I mean ▪ methinks , (My lord) you are grown something solemn on the sudden; since your monopolies and patents, which made your purse swell like a wet sponge, have been reduced to th' last gasp. Troth, it is far better to confess here, then in a worser place. Is it not so indeed?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101200" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101210"> whate'er he does by mine, I'm sure has hit the cause from whence your grief springs, lord Simanthes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101220" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101230">No Egyptian soothsayer has truer inspirations, than your small courtiers from causes and wants manifold; as when the emperor's countenance with propitious noise does not cry chink in pocket, no repute is with mercer, nor with tailor; nay sometimes too the humour's pregnant in him, when repulse is given him by a beauty: I can speak this though from no Memphian priest, or sage Caldean, from the best mistress (Gentlemen) an experience. Last night I had a mind t'a comely sempstress, who did refuse me, and behold, ere since how like an ass I look.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e101240">Enter Tarifa.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101250" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101260">What, at your counsels, lords? the great Almanzor requires your presence, Mura; has decreed<pb facs="6" n="10"/> the war for Persia. You (My gracious lord) prince Abilqualit, are appointed chief: and you, brave spirited Abrahen, an assistant to your victorious brother: you, lord Mura, destined lieutenant general.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101270" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101280">And must I march against the foe, without thy company? I relish not th' employment.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101290" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101300">Alas, my lord, Tarifa's head's grown white beneath his helmet; and your good father thought it charity to spare mine age from travel: though this ease will be more irksome to me then the toil of war in a sharp winter.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101310" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101320">It arrives just to our wish. My gracious brother, I anon shall wait on you: mean time, valiant Mura, let us attend my father.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e101330">Exeunt Ab. Mura, Sim.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101340" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101350">Good Selinthus, vouchsafe a while your absence, I shall have employment shortly for your trust.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101360" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101370">Your grace shall have as much power to command Selinthus, as his best fancied mistress. I am your creature.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A31672-e101380">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101390" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101400">Now, my lord, I hope you're clothed with all those resolutions that usher glorious minds to brave atchievements. The happy genius on your youth attendant declares it built for victories and triumphs; and the proud Persian monarchy, the sole emulous opposer of the Arabic greatness, courts (Like a fair bride) your imperial arms, waiting to invest you sovereign of her beauties. Why are you dull (My lord?) Your cheerful looks should with a prosperous augury presage a certain victory: when you droop already, as if the foe had ravished from your crest the noble palm. For shame (Sir) be more sprightly; your sad appearance, should they thus behold you, would half unsoul your army,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101410" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101420">'Tis no matter, such looks best suit my fortune. Know (Tarifa) I'm undisposed to manage this great voyage, and must not undertake it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101430" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101440">Must not, sir! Is't possible a lovesick youth, whose hopes are fixed on marriage, on his bridal night<pb facs="6" n="11"/> should in soft slumbers languish? that your arms should rust in ease, now when you hear the charge, and see before you the triumphant prize destined to adorn your valour? You should rather be furnished with a power above these passions; and being invoked by the mighty charm of honour, fly to achieve this war, not undertake it. I'd rather you had said, Tarifa lied, then uttered such a sound, harsh and unwelcome.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101450" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101460">I know thou lovest me truly, and durst I to any born of woman, speak my intentions, the fatal cause which does withdraw my courage from this employment, which like health I covet, thou shouldst enjoy it fully. But (Tarifa) the said discovery of it is not fit for me to utter, much less for thy virtue to be acquainted with.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101470" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101480">Why (My lord?) my loyalty can merit no suspicion from you of falsehood: whatsoever the cause be or good, or wicked, 't meets a trusty silence, and my best care and honest counsel shall endeavour to reclaim, or to assist you if it be good, if ill, from your bad purpose.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101490" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101500">Why, that I know (Tarifa.) 'tis the love thou bearest to honour, renders thee unapt to be partaker of those resolutions that by compulsion keep me from this voyage: for they with such inevitable sweetness invade my sense, that though in their performance my fame and virtue even to death do languish, I must attempt, and bring them unto act, or perish i'th' pursuance.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101510" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101520">Heaven avert a mischief so prodigious. Though I would not with over-saucy boldness press your counsels; yet pardon (Sir) my loyalty, which timorous of your loved welfare, must entreat, beseech you with ardent love and reverence, to disclose the hidden cause that can estrange your courage from its own Mars, withhold you from this action so much allied to honour: pray reveal it: by all your hopes of what you hold most precious, I do implore it; for my faith in breeding<pb facs="7" n="12"/> your youth in wars great rudiments, relieve Tarifa's fears, that wander into strange unwelcome doubts, left some ambitious frenzy 'gainst your imperial father's dignity has late seduced your goodness.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101530" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101540">No, Tarifa, I never durst aim at that unholy height in viperous wickedness; a sinless, harmless (If't can be truly termed one) 'tis my soul labours even to despair with: t'feign would out, did not my blushes interdict my language: 'tis unchaste love, Tarifa; nay, take't all, and when thou hast it, pity my misfortunes, to fair Caropia, the chaste, virtuous wife to surly Mura. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101550" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101560">What a fool desire is! with giant strengths it makes us court the knowledge of hidden mysteries, which once revealed, far more inconstant than the air, it fleets into new wishes, that the coveted secret had slept still in oblivion.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101570" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101580">I was certain 'twould fright thy innocence, and look to be besieged with strong dissuasions from my purpose: but be assured, that I have tired my thoughts with all the rules that teach men moral goodness, so to reclaim them from this lovesick looseness; but they (Like wholesome medicines misapplied) faced their best operation, fond and fruitless. Though I as well may hope to kiss the sunbeams 'cause they shine on me, as from her to gain one glance of comfort; yet my mind, that pities itself with constant tenderness, must needs revolve the cause of its calamity, and melt i'th' pleasure of so sweet a sadness.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101590" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101600">Then you're undone for ever; sir, undone beyond the help of council or repentance. 'tis most ignoble, that a mind unshaken by fear, should by a vain desire be broken; or that those powers no labour e'er could vanquish, should be o'ercome and thralled by sordid pleasure. Pray (Sir) consider, that in glorious war, which makes ambition (By base men termed sin) a big and gallant virtue, you've been nursed,<pb facs="7" n="13"/> lulled (As it were) into your infant sleeps by th' surly noise o'th' trumpet, which now summons you to victorious use of your endowments: and shall a mistress stay you! such a one too, as to attempt, than war itself's more dangerous!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101610" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101620">All these persuasions are to as much purpose, as you should strive to reinvest with peace, and all the joys of health and life, a soul condemned to perpetuity of torments. No (My Tarifa) though through all disgraces, loss of my honour, fame, nay hope for empire, I should be forced to wade to obtain her love; those seas of mischief would be pleasing streams, which I would haste to bathe in, and pass through them with that delight thou wouldst to victory, or slaves long chained to'th' oar, to sudden freedoms.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101630" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101640">Were you not Abilqualit, from this time then our friendships (Like two rivers from one head rising) should wander a dissevered course, and never meet again, unless to quarrel. Nay, old and stiff, now as my iron garments, were you my son, my sword should teach your wildness a swift way to repentance. You're my prince, on whom all hopes depend; think on your father, that lively image of majestic goodness, who never yet wronged matron in his lust, or man in his displeasure. Pray conjecture your father, country, army, by my mouth beseech your piety to an early pity of your yet unslain innocence. No attention! Farewell: my prayers shall wait you, though my counsels be thus despised. Farewell prince!</p>
            <stage xml:id="A31672-e101650">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101660" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101670">Alas good man, he weeps. Such tears I've seen fall from his manly eyes once when ye lost a battle. Why should I put off my reason, valour, honour, virtue, in hopes to gain a beauty, whose possession renders me more uncapable of peace, than I am now I want it? Like a sweet, much coveted banquet, 'tis no sooner tasted, but it's delicious luxury's forgotten. Besides, it is unlawful. Idle fool, there is no law, but what's prescribed by love, nature's first moving organ; nor can ought<pb facs="8" n="14"/> what nature dictates to us be held vicious. On then, my soul, and destitute of fears, like an adventurous mariner, that knows storms must attend him, yet dares court his peril, strive to obtain this happy port. Methises (Loves cunning advocate) does for me besiege (With gifts and vows) her chastity. She is compassed with flesh, that's not invulnerable, and may by Love's sharp darts be pierced. They stand firm, whom no art can bring to Love's command.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e101680">Enter Abrahen,</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101690" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101700">My gracious brother!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101710" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101720">Dearest Abrahen, welcome. 'tis certainly decreed by our dread father, we must both march against th' insulting foe. How does thy youth, yet uninjured to travel, relish the employment?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101730" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101740">War is sweet to those that never have experienced it. My youth cannot desire in that big art a nobler tutor than you (My Brother●) like an eglet following her dam, I shall your honoured steps trace through all dangers, and be proud to borrow a branch, when your head's covered o'er with laurel, to deck my humbler temples.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101750" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101760">I do know thee of valiant active soul; and though a youth, thy forward spirit merits the command of chief, rather than second in an army. Would heaven our royal father had bestowed on thee the charge of general.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101770" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101780">On me, sir! Alas, 'tis fit I first should know those arts that do distinguish valour from wild rashness. A general (Brother) must have abler nerves of judgement, then in my youth can be hoped for. Yourself already like a flourishing spring teeming with early victories, the soldier expects should lead them to new triumphs, as if you had vanquished fortune.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101790" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101800">I am not so ambitious (Abrahen) of particular glories, but I would have those whom I love partake them. This Persian war, the last of the whole East<pb facs="8" n="15"/> left to be managed, if I can persuade the great Almanzor, shall be the trophy of thy yet maiden valour. I have done enough already to inform succession, that Abilqualit durst on fiercest foes run to fetch conquest home, and would have thy name as great as mine in arms, that history might register, our family abounded with heroes, born for victory.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101810" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101820">'Tis an honour, which, though it be above my powers, committed to my direction, I would seek to manage with care above my years, and courage equal to his, that dares the horrid'st face of danger: but 'tis your noble courtesy would thrust this masculine honour (Far above his merits) on your regardless brother; for my father, he has no thought tending to your intentions; nor though your goodness should desire, would hardly be won to yield consent to them.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101830" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101840">Why, my Abrahen, we're both his sons, and should be both alike dear to's affections; and though birth hath given me the larger hopes and titles, 'twere unnatural, should he not strive to endow thee with a portion apted to the magnificence of his offspring. But thou perhaps art timorous, lest thy first essays of valour should meet fate disastrous. The bold are fortune's darlings. If thou hast courage to venture on this great employment, doubt not, I shall prevail upon our father to ordain thee chief in this brave hopeful voyage.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101850" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101860">You imagine me beyond all thought of gratitude; and doubt not that I'll deceive your trust. The glorious ensigns waving i'th' air once, like so many comets, shall speak the Persians funerals, on whose ruins we'll build to fame and victory new temples, which shall like pyramids preserve our memories, when we are changed to ashes.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101870" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101880">Be sure, continue in this brave mind; I'll instantly solicit our father to confirm thee in the charge of general, I'll about it.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A31672-e101890">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101900" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <pb facs="9" n="16"/>
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101910">Farewell gracious brother. This haps above my hopes. Alas, good dull fool, I see through thy intents, clear, as thy soul were as transparent as thin air or crystal. He would have me removed, march with the army, that he mean time might make a sure defeat on our aged father's life and empire: 't must be certain as the light. Why should not this with equal heat, be like my thoughts, ambitious? Be they as harmless as the prayers of virgins, I'll work his ruin out of his intentions. He like a thick cloud stands 'twixt me and greatness: greatness, the wise man's true felicity, honour's direct inheritance. My youth will quit suspicion of my subtle practice: then have I surly Mura and Simanthes, my allies by my dead mother's blood, my assistants, his eunuch too Mesithes at my service. Simanthes shall inform the King, the people desire prince Abilqualit's stay; and Mura whose blunt demeanour renders him oraculous, make a shrewd inference out of it. He is my half brother, th' other's my father; names, mere airy titles! Sovereignty's only sacred, greatness goodness, true self-affection justice, every thing righteous that's helpful to create a King.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e101920">Enter Mura, Simanthes.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101930" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101940">My trusty friends, you're welcome: our fate's above our wishes; Abilqualit by whatsoever power moved to his own ruin, would fain enforce his charge of general on me, and stay at home.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101950" who="A31672-simanthes">
            <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101960">Why, how can this conduce to advance our purpose?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e101970" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e101980">'Tis the mainest engine could ever move to ruin him. Simanthes, you shall inform our father, 'tis the people out of their tender love desires his stay. You (Mura) shall infer my brother's greatness with people; out of it, how nice it is and dangerous. The air is open here; come, we'll discourse with more secure privacy our purpose. Nothing's unjust, unsacred, tends to advance us to a kingdom; that's the height of chance.</p>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A31672-e101990">
        <pb facs="9" n="17"/>
        <head>Actus secundus.</head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A31672-e102000">
          <head>Scaena i.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e102010">Enter Almanzor, Mura, and Simanthes.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102020" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102030">How? not go, Simanthes? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102040" who="A31672-simanthes">
            <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102050">My dread sovereign, I speak but what the well affected people out of their loyal care and pious duty enjoined me utter: they do look upon him as on your eldest son, and next successor, and would be loath the Persian war should rob their eyes of light, their souls of joy and comfort, this flourishing empire leave as it were widowed of its loved spouse: they humbly do beseech your majesty would therefore destine some more fitting general, whose loss (As heaven avert such a misfortune) should it happen, might less concern the state.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102060" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102070">'Tis not the least among the blessings heaven has showered upon us, that we are happy in such loving subjects, to govern whom, when we in peace are ashes, we leave them a successor whom they truly reverence: a loving people and a loving sovereign makes kingdoms truly fortunate and flourishing. But I believe (Simanthes) their intents, though we confirm them, will scarce take effect: my Abilqualit (Like a princely lion, in view of's prey) will scarcely be o'ercome to leave the honour of the Persian war, in's hopes already vanquished by his valour ▪ and rest in lazy quiet, while that triumph is ravished by another.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102080" who="A31672-simanthes">
            <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102090">With the pardon of your most sacred majesty, 'tis fit then your great commands forbid the prince's voyage: boldness enforces youth to hard achievements before their time, makes them run forth like lapwings from their warm nest, part of the shell yet sticking unto their downy heads. Sir, good success is oft more fatal far than bad; one winning ●●st from a flattering die tempting a gamester<pb facs="10" n="18"/> to hazard his whole fortunes.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102100" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mur.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102110">This is dull, fruitless philosophy, he that falls nobly wins as much honour by his loss, as conquest.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102120" who="A31672-simanthes">
            <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102130">This rule may hold well among common men, but not among princes. Such a prince as ours is, who knows as well to conquer men's affections as he does enemies, should not be exposed to every new cause, honourable danger. Prince Abilqualit's fair and winning carriage has stolen possession of the people's hearts, they dote on him since his late Spanish conquest, as new made brides on their much coveted husbands; and they would pine like melancholy turtles, should they so soon lose the unvalued object both of their love and reverence: howsoe'er, whate'er your awful will (Sir) shall determine, as heaven, is by their strict obedience held sacred and religious.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102140" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102150">Good Simanthes, let them receive our thanks for their true care of our dear Abilqualit. We'll consider of their request, say.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102160" who="A31672-simanthes">
            <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102170">Your highness' humblest creature.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A31672-e102180">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102190" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102200">I do not like this.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102210" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102220">Like what? Valiant Mura, we know thy counsels so supremely wise, and thy true heart so excellently faithful, that whatsoever displeases thy sage judgement, Almanzor's wisdom must account distasteful. What is't dislikes thee?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102230" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102240">Your majesty knows me a downright soldier, I affect not words; but to be brief, I relish not your son should (As if you were in your tomb already) engross so much the giddy people's favours. 'tis neither fit for him, nor safe for you to suffer it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102250" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102260">Why, how can they, Mura, give a more serious testimony of reverence to me, then by conferring their affections, their pious wishes, zealous contemplations on him that sits the nearest to my heart, my Abilqualit, in whose hopeful virtues my age more glorious than in all my conquests?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102270" who="A31672-mura">
            <pb facs="10" n="19"/>
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102280">May you prove fortunate in your pious care of the prince Abilqualit. But (My lord) Mura is not so prone to idle language (The parasites best ornament) to utter o●ght, but what (If you'll please to give him audience he'll show you a blunt reason for.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102290" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102300">Come, I see into thy thoughts, good Mura; too much care of us, informs thy loyal soul with fears the princes too much popularity may breed our danger: banish those suspicions; neither dare they who under my long reign have been triumphant in so many blessings, have the least thought may tend to disobedience: or if they had, my Abilqualit's goodness would never consent with them to become impious.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102310" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102320">'Tis too secure a confidence betrays minds valiant to irreparable dangers. Not that I dare invade with a foul thought the noble prince's loyalty; but (My lord) when this same many headed beast (The people) violent, and so not constant in affections, subject to love of novelty, the sickness proper t'all humane specially light natures, do magnify with too immoderate praises the prince's actions, dote upon his presence, nay chain their souls to th'shadow of his footsteps, as all excesses ought to be held dangerous, especially when they do aim at sceptres, their too much dotage speaks, you in their wishes are dead already, that their darling hope the prince might have the throne once.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102330" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102340">'Tis confessed, all this a serious truth.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102350" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102360">Their mad applauses oth' noble prince, though he be truly virtuous, may force ambition into him, a mischief seizing the soul with too much craft and sweetness, as pride or lust does minds unstayed and wanton: 'tmakes men like poisoned rats, which when they've swallowed the pleasing bane, rest not until they drink, and can rest then much less, until they burst with't.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102370" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102380">Thy words are still oraculous.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102390" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102400">Pray then think with what an easy toil the haughty prince,<pb facs="11" n="20"/> a demi God by th' popular acclamations, nay, the world's sovereign in the vulgar wishes, had he a resolution to be wicked, might snatch this diadem from your aged temples? What law so holy, tie of blood so mighty, which for a crown, minds sanctified and religious have not presumed to violate? How much more than may the soul dazzling glories of a sceptre work in his youth, whose constitution's fiery, as overheated air, and has to fan it into a flame, the breath of love and praises blown by strong thought of his own worth and actions.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102410" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102420">No more of this, good Mura. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102430" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102440">They dare already limit your intentions, demand (As 'twere) with cunning zeal (Which rightly interpreted, is insolence) the prince's abode at home. I will not say it is, but I guess, 'tmay be their subtle purpose while we abroad fight for new kingdom's purchase deprived by that means of our faithful succours, they may deprive you of this crown, enforce upon the prince this diadem; which however he may be loath to accept, being once possessed of't and tasted the delights of supreme greatness, he'll be more loath to part with. To prevent this, not that I think it will, but that may happen, 'tis fit the prince march. I've observed in him too of late a sullen melancholy, whence rising I'll not conjecture; only I should grieve, sir, beyond a moderate sorrow, traitorous practice should take that from you which with loyal blood ours and your own victorious arms have purchased. and now I have discharged my honest conscience censure on't as you please; henceforth I'm silent.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102450" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102460">Would thou hadst been so now, thy loyal fears have made me see how miserable a King is, whose rule depends on the vain people suffrage. Black now and horrid as the face of storms appears all Abilqualit's lovely virtues, because to me they only make him dangerous, and with great terror shall behold those actions which with delight before we viewed, and dotage; like mariners that bless the peaceful seas, which when suspected to grow up tempestuous,<pb facs="11" n="21"/> they tremble at. Though he may still be virtuous, 'tis wisdom in us, to him no injustice, to keep a vigilant eye o'er his proceedings and the wild people's purposes.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e102470">Enter Abil.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102480" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102490">Abilqualit! come to take your leave, I do conjecture.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102500" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102510">Rather, sir, to beg your gracious licence, I may still at home attend your dread commands, and that you'd please to nominate my hopeful brother Abrahen (In lieu of me) chief of your now raised forces for th' Persian expedition.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102520" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102530">Dare you (Sir) presume to make this suit to us?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102540" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102550">Why? (My royal lord) I hope this cannot pull your anger on your most obedient son: a true affection to the young prince my brother, did beget this my request; I willingly would have his youth adorned with glory of this conquest. No tree bears fruit in autumn, 'Less it blossom first in the spring; 'tis fit he were acquainted in these soft years with military action, that when grown perfect man, he may grow up too perfect in warlike discipline.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102560" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102570">Hereafter we shall by your appointment guide our counsels. Why do you not entreat me to resign my crown, that you the people's much loved minion may with't impale your glorious brow? Sir, henceforth or know your duty better, or your pride shall meet our just waked anger. To your charge, and march with speed, or you shall know what 'tis to disobey our pleasure. When you're King, learn to command your subjects; I will mine (Sir.) You know your charge, perform it.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e102580">Exit Alm. and Mura.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102590" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102600">I have done. Our hopes (I see) resemble much the sun, that rising and declining cast large shadows; but when his beams are dressed in's midday brightness, yields none at all: when they are farthest from success, their guilt reflection does display the largest shows of events fair and prosperous. With what a settled confidence did I promise<pb facs="12" n="22"/> myself, my stay here, Mura's wished departure? when stead of these, I find my father's wrath destroying mine intentions. Such a fool is self-compassion, soothing us to faith of what we wish should hap ▪ while vain desire of things we have not, makes us quite forget those we're possessed of.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e102610">Enter Abrahen.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102620" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102630">Alone the engine works beyond or hope or credit. How I hug with vast delight, beyond that of stolen pleasures forbidden lovers taste, my darling mistress, my active brain! If I can be thus subtle while a young serpent, when grown up a dragon how glorious shall I be in cunning practice? My gracious brother!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102640" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102650">Gentle Abrahen. I am grieved my power cannot comply my promise: my father's so averse from granting my request concerning thee, that with angry frowns he did express rather a passionate rage, than a refusal civil, or accustomed to his indulgent disposition.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102660" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102670">He's our father, and so the tyrant custom doth enforce us to yield him that which fools call natural, when wise men know 'tis more than servile duty, a slavish, blind obedience to his pleasure, be it nor just, nor honourable.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102680" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102690">O my Abrahen, these sounds are unharmonious, as unlooked for from thy unblemished innocence: though he could put off paternal piety, 't gives no privilege for us to wander from our filial duty: though harsh, and to our natures much unwelcome be his decrees, like those of heaven, we must not presume to question them.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102700" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102710">Not, if they concern our lives and fortunes? 'tis not for myself I urge these doubts; but 'tis for you, who are my brother, and I hope, must be my sovereign, my fears grow on me almost to distraction: our father's age betrays him to a dotage, which may be dangerous to your future safety;<pb facs="12" n="23"/> he does suspect your loyalty.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102720" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102730">How, Abrahen? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102740" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102750">I knew 'twould start your innocence; but 'tis truth, a sad and serious truth; nay his suspicion almost arrived unto a settled faith that you're ambitious.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102760" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102770">'Tis impossible.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102780" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102790">The glorious shine of your illustrious virtues are grown too bright and dazzling for his eyes to look on as he ought, with admiration; and he with fear beholds them, as it were, through a perspective, where each brave action of yours surveyed though at remotest distance, appears far greater than it is. In brief, that love which you have purchased from the people that sing glad hymns to your victorious fortunes, betrays you to his hate; and in this voyage which he enforces you to undertake, he has set spies upon you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102800" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102810">'Tis so: afflictions do fall like hailstones, one no sooner drops, but a whole shower does follow. I observed indeed, my Abrahen, that his looks and language was dressed in unaccustomed clouds, but did not imagine they'd presaged so fierce a tempest. Ye gods, why do you give us gifts and graces, share your own attributes with men, your virtues, when they betray them to worse hate than vices? But Abrahen, prithee reconfirm my fears by testimonial how this can be truth; for yet my innocence with too credulous trust soothes up my soul, our father should not thus put that off which does make him so, his sweetness, to feed the irregular flames of false suspicions and soul tormenting jealousies.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102820" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102830">Why, to me, to me (My lord) he did with strong injunctions give a solicitous charge to overlook your actions. My Abrahen (Quoth he) I'm not so unhappy, that like thy brother thou shouldst be ambitious, who does affect, 'fore thy aged father's ashes, with greedy lust my empire. Have a strict and cautious diligence to observe his carriage, 'twil be a pious care. Moved with the base<pb facs="13" n="24"/> indignity, that he on 'Me should force the office of a spy; your spy, my noble and much loved brother: my best manhood scarce could keep my angry tears in; I resolved I was in duty bound to give you early intelligence of his unjust intentions, that you in wisdom might prevent all dangers might fall upon you from them, like swift lightning, killing 'cause they invade with sudden fierceness</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102840" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102850">In afflicting me, misery is grown witty.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102860" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102870">Nay besides (Sir) the sullen Mura has the self same charge too consigned and settled on him; which his blind duty will execute. O brother, your soft passive nature, does like jet on fire when oils cast on't, extinguish: otherwise, this base suspicion would inflame your sufferance, nay make the purest loyalty rebellious. However, though your too religious piety forces you endure this foul disgrace with patience, look to your safety, brother, that dear safety which is not only yours, but your whole empires: for my part, if a faithful brother's service may ought avail you, though against our father, since he can be so unnaturally suspicious, as your own thoughts, command it.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e102880">Enter Selinthus and Mesithes. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102890" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102900">Come, I know, although thou'st lost some implements of manhood may make thee gracious in the sight of woman, yet thou'st a little engine, called a tongue, by which thou canst o'ercome the nicest female, in the behalf of friend. Insooth, you eunuchs may well be styled pimps-royal, for the skill you have in quaint procurement.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102910" who="A31672-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102920">Your lordship's merry, and would enforce on me what has been your office far oftener than the cunningest squire belonging to the smock transitory. May't please your highness.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102930" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102940">Ha! Mesithes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102950" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102960">His countenance varies strangely, some affair the eunuch gives him notice of, 't should seem, begets much pleasure in him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102970" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e102980">Is this truth? <pb facs="13" n="25"/>Mes. Else let me taste your anger.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e102990" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103000">My dear Abrahen, we'll march tonight , prithee give speedy notice to our lieutenant Mura, to collect the forces from their several quarters, and draw them into battalions on the plain behind the city, lay a strict command he stir not from the ensigns till ourselves arrive in person there. Be speedy, brother, a little hasty business craves our presence. We will anon be with you, my methises. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e103010">Exeunt Abil. and Mes.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103020" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103030">Can your grace imagine whether his highness goes now?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103040" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103050">No, Selinthus; canst thou conjecture at the eunuch's business? whate'er it was, his countenance seemed much altered: I'd give a talon to have certain knowledge what was Mesithes message.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103060" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103070">I'll inform you at a far easier rate. Mesithes business certes concerned a limber petticoat, and the smock soft and slippery; on my honour, has been providing for the prince, some female that he takes his leave of lady's flesh ere his departure.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103080" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103090">Not improbable, it may be so.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103100" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103110">Nay, certain (Sir) it is so: and I believe, your little body earns after the same sport. You were once reported a wag would have had business of engendering with surly Mura's lady: and men may conjecture you're no chaster than a votary: yet though she would not solace your desires, there are as handsome ladies will be proud to have your grace inoculate their stocks with your graft-royal.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103120" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103130">Thou art Selinthus still, and wilt not change thy humour. I must go and find out Mura; so farewell Selinthus, thou art not for these wars, I know.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A31672-e103140">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103150" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103160">No truly, nor yet for any other, 'Less't be on a naked yielding enemy; though there may be as hot service upon such a foe<pb facs="14" n="26"/> as on those clad in steel: the little squadron, we civil men assault body to body, oft carry wildfire ▪ about them privately, that singes us ith' service from the crown even to the sole, nay sometimes hair and all off. But these are transitory perils. <stage xml:id="A31672-e103170">Enter Gasilles, Osman.</stage>cousins, I thought you had been dancing to the drum. Your general has given order for a march this night, I can assure you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103180" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103190">It is cousin, something of the soonest; but we are prepared at all times for the journey.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103200" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103210">Tomorrow morning may serve the turn though. Hark you, cousins mine; if in this Persian war you chance to take a handsome she captive, pray you be not unmindful of us your friends at home; I will disburse her ransom, cousins, for I've a months mind to try if strange flesh, or that of our own country has the completer relish.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103220" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103230">We will accomplish thy pleasure, noble cozen.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103240" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103250">But prey do not take the first say of her yourselves. I do not love to walk after any of my kindred ith' path of copulation.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103260" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103270">The first fruits shall be thy own, dear couz. But shall we part (Never perhaps to meet again) with dry lips, my right honoured coz?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103280" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103290">By no means, though by the Alcharon wine be forbidden, you soldiers in that case make't not your faith. Drink water in the camp, when you can purchase no other liquor; here you shall have plenty of wine, old and delicious. I'll be your leader, and bring you on, let who will bring you off. To the encounter, come let us march, cousins.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e103300">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e103310">Song.</stage>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A31672-e103320">
          <pb facs="14" n="27"/>
          <head>Scaena secunda.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e103330">Enter Abilqualit, Caropia, and Mesithes, Perilinda.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103340" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103350">No more, my gracious lord, where real love is needless are all expressions ceremonious: the amorous turtles, that at first acquaintance strive to express in murmuring notes their loves, do when agreed on their affections change their chirps to billing ▪</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103360" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103370">And in feathered arms encompass mutually their gawdy necks.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103380" who="A31672-mesithes">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103390">How do you like these love tricks, Perilinda? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103400" who="A31672-perilinda">
            <speaker>Per.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103410">Very well; but one may sooner hope from a dead man to receive kindness, than from thee, an eunuch. ● you are the coldest creatures in the bodies, no snowballs like you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103420" who="A31672-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103430">We must needs, who have not that which like fire should warm our constitutions, the instruments of copulation, girl, our toys to please the ladies.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103440" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103450">Caropia, in your well becoming pity of my extreme afflictions and stern sufferings, you've shown that excellent mercy as must render whatever action you can fix on, virtuous. But lady, I till now have been your tempter, one that desired hearing, the brave resistance you made my brother, when he wooed your love, only to boast the glory of a conquest which seemed impossible, now I have gained it by being vanquisher, I myself am vanquished your everlasting captive.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103460" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103470">Then the thraldom will be as prosperous as the pleasing bondage of palms, that flourish most when bowed down fastest; constraint makes sweet and easy things laborious, when love makes greatest miseries seem pleasures. Yet 'twas ambition (Sir) joined with affection that gave me up a spoil to your temptations. I was resolved, if ever I did make a breach on matrimonial faith, 't should be<pb facs="15" n="28"/> with him that was the darling of kind fortune as well as liberal nature; who possessed the height of greatness to adorn his beauty; which since they both conspire to make you happy, I thought 't would be a greater sin to suffer your hopeful person, born to sway this empire, in love's hot flames to languish, by refusal to a consuming fever ▪ than t'infringe a vow which never proceeded from my heart when I unwillingly made it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103480" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103490">And may break it with confidence, secure from the least guilt, as if 't had only in an idle dream been by your fancy plighted. Madam, there can be no greater misery in love, than separation from the object which we affect; and such is our misfortune we must ith' infancy of our desires breathe at unwelcome distance; ith' mean time, let's make good use of the most precious minutes we have to spend together.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103500" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103510">Else we were unworthy to be titled lovers; but I fear loathed Mura may with swift approach disturb our happiness.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103520" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103530">By my command he's mustering up our forces. Yet Mesithes, go you to Abrahen, and with intimations from us, strengthen our charge. Come my Caropia, love's wars are harmless, for who ere does yield, gains as much honour as who wins the field.</p>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A31672-e103540">
        <head>Actus tertius</head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A31672-e103550">
          <head>Scaena i.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e103560">Enter Abilqualit and Caropia, as rising from bed, Abrahen without, Perilinda.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103570" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103580">Open the door, I must and will have entrance unto the prince my brother, as you love your life and safety and that lady's honor, whom you are lodged in amorous twines ▪ with, do not deny me entrance to you, I am Abrahen, your loyal brother Abrahen. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103590" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103600">'Tis his voice,<pb facs="15" n="29"/> and there can be no danger in't, Caropia, be not dismayed, though we're to him discovered. your fame shall taste no blemish by't. Now brother, 'tis something rude in you, thus violently to press upon our privacies.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103610" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103620">My affection shall be my advocate, and plead my care of your loved welfare, as you love your honour, haste from this place, or you'll betray the lady to ruin most inevitable. Her husband has notice of your being here, and's coming on wings of jealousy and desperate rage to intercept you in your close delights. In brief, I over heard a trusty servant of his ith' camp come and declare your highness was private with Caropia: at which tidings the sea with greater haste when vexed with tempests, so sudden and boisterous, flies not towards the shore, than he intended homewards. He by this needs must have gained the city; for with all my power I hasted hitherward, that by your absence you might prevent his view of you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103630" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103640">Why? the slave dare not invade my person, had he found me in fair Caropia's arms: 'twould be ignoble, now I have caused her danger, should I not defend her from his violence. I'll stay though he come armed with thunder.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103650" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103660">That will be a certain means to ruin her: to me count that cure, I'll stand between the lady, and Mura's fury, when your very sight, giving fresh fire to th'injury, will incense him 'gainst her beyond all patience.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103670" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103680">Nay, besides his violent wrath breaking through his allegiance, may riot on your person. Dear my lord withdraw yourself, there may be some excuse when you are absent thought on, to take off Mura's suspicion: by our loves, depart I do beseech you. Hapless I was born to be most miserable.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103690" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103700">You shall overrule me ▪ better it is for him with unhallowed hands<pb facs="16" n="30"/> to act a sacrilege on our prophet's Tom then to profane this purity with the le●●● offer of injury; be careful Abrahen, to thee I leave my heart. Farewell Caropia, your tears enforce my absence.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A31672-e103710">Exit. Abil.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103720" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103730">Pray haste my lord lest you should meet the enraged mur. now madam where are the boasted glories of that virtue, which like a faithful fort withstood my batteries? demolished now, and ruined they appear; like a fair building tottered from its b●●● by an unruly whirlwind, and are no instead of love the objects of my pity</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103740" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103750">I'm bound to thank you sir yet credit me; my sin's so pleasing't 'Cannot meet repentance. Were Mura here, and armed with all the horror's ●age could invest his powers with; not forgiven hermits with greater peace shall haste to death, than I to be the martyr of this cause, which I so love and reverence.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103760" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103770">'Tis a noble and well becoming constancy, and merits a lover of those supreme eminent graces, that do like full winds swell the glorious sails of Abilqualit's dignity and beauty! yet madam, let me tell you, though I could not envy my brother's happiness, if he could have enjoyed your priceless love with safety, free from discovery, I am afflicted beyond a moderate sorrow, that my youth which with as true a zeal, courted your love, should appear so contemptible to receive a killing scorn from you: yet I forgive you, and do so much respect your peace, I wish you had not sinned so carelessly to be betrayed ith' first fruitions of your wishes to your suspicious husband.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103780" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103790">'Tis a fate sir, which I must stand, though it come dressed in flames, killing as circular fire, and as prodigious as death presaging comets: there's that strength in love, can change the pitchy face of dangers to pleasing forms, make ghastly fears seem beauteous; and I'm resolved, since the sweet prince is free<pb facs="16" n="31"/> from Mura's anger, which might have been fatal if he should here have found him, unresistless I dare his utmost fury.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103800" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103810">'Twil bring death with't sure as stifling damp; and 'twere much pity so sweet a beauty should unpitied fall, betrayed to endless infamy; your husband knows only that my brother in your chamber was entertained; the servant that betrayed you, curse on his diligence, could not affirm he saw you twined together: yet it is death by the law, you know, for any lady at such an hour, and in her husband's absence ▪ to entertain a stranger.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103820" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103830">'Tis considered sir, and since I cannot live to enjoy his love, I'll meet my death as willingly as I met Abilqualit's dear embraces.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103840" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103850">That were too severe a cruelty. Live Caropia, till the kind destinies take the loathed Mura to their eternal mansions, till he fall either in war a sacrifice to fortune, or else by stratagem take his destruction from angry Abilqualit, whose fair empress you were created for: there is a mean yet to save th' opinion of your honour spotless, as that of virgin innocence, nay to preserve, (Though he doth know (As certainly he must do) my brother have enjoyed thee) thee still precious in his deluding fancy.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103860" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103870">Let me adore you if you can give effect to your good purpose. But 'tis impossible.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103880" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103890">With as secure an ease 't shall be accomplished as the blessed desires of uncrossed lovers: you shall with one breath dissolve these mists that with contagious darkness threaten the lights both of your life and honour. Affirm my brother ravished you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103900" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103910">How my lord?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103920" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103930">Obtained by violence entry into your chamber where his big lust seconded by force, despite of yours and your maids weak resistance surprised your honour: when 't shall come to question,<pb facs="17" n="32"/> my brother cannot so put off the truth, he owes his own affection and your whiteness, but to acknowledge it a rape.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103940" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103950">And so by saving mine, betray his fame and safety, to the law's danger, and your father's justice, which with impartial doom will most severely sentence the prince, although his son.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103960" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e103970">Your fears and too affectionate tenderness will ruin all that my care has builded. Sure, Mesithes has (As my charge enjoined him) made relation<stage xml:id="A31672-e103980">Enter Mura.</stage>to him of Abilqualit's action. See your husband, resolve on't, or you're miserable.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e103990" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104000">Furies, where is this lustful prince, and this lascivious strumpet? ha Abrahen, here?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104010" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104020">Good● cousin Mura, be not so passionate, it is your prince has wrought your injury; resolve to bear your crosses like a man: the greatest afflictions should have the greatest fortitude in their sufferings from minds resolved and noble. Alas poor lady, 'twas not her fault; his too unruly lust 'tis, has destroyed her purity.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104030" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104040">Ha, in tears! Are these the livery of your fears and penitence, or of your sorrows (Minion) for being robbed so soon of your adulterer?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104050" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104060">Fie, your passion is too unmannerly; you look upon her with eyes of rage, when you with grief and pity ought to survey her innocence. My brother, degenerate as he is from worth, and merely the beast of lust, (What fiends would fear to violate) has with rude insolence destroyed her honour, by him inhumane ravished,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104070" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104080">Good sir be so merciful as to set free a wretch from loathed mortality, whose life's so great and hateful burden now sh'as lost her honour: 'twil be a friendly charity to deliver her from the torment of it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104090" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104100">That I could contract the soul of universal rage<pb facs="17" n="33"/> into this swelling heart, that it might be as full of poisonous anger as a dragon's when in a toil ensnared. Caropia ravished! Methinks the horror of the sound should fright to everlasting ruin, the whole world, start nature's genius.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104110" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104120">Gentle madam, pray withdraw yourself, your sight, till I have wrought a cure upon his temper, will but add to his affliction.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104130" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104140">You're as my good angel, I'll follow your directions.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A31672-e104150">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104160" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104170">Cousin Mura, I thought a person of your masculine temper, in dangers fostered, where perpetual terrors have been your playfellows, would not have resented with such effeminate passion a disgrace, though never so huge and hideous.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104180" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104190">I am tame, collected now in all my faculties, which are so much oppressed with injuries, they've lost the anguish of them: can you think, sir, when all the winds fight, the enraged billows that use to imprint on the black lips of clouds a thousand briny kisses, can lie still, as in a lethargy? that when baths of oil are poured upon the wild irregular flames in populous cities, that they'll then extinguish? Your mitigations add but seas to seas, give matter to my fires to increase their burning, and I ere long enlightened by my anger shall be my own pile, and consume to ashes.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104200" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104210">Why, then I see indeed your injuries have ravished hence your reason and discourse, and left you the mere prostitute of passion. Can you repair the ruins you lament so with these exclaims? was ever dead man called to life again by fruitful sighs? or can your rage re-edify Caropia's honour, slain and betrayed by his foul lust? Your manhood, that heretofore has thrown you on all dangers, methinks should prompt you to a noble vengeance, which you may safely prosecute with justice, to which this crime, although he be a prince,<pb facs="18" n="34"/> renders him liable.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104220" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104230">Yes, I'll have justice or I'll awake the sleepy deities, or like the ambitious giants wage new wars with heaven itself, my wrongs shall steel my courage, and on this vicious prince like a fierce sea-breach my just waked rage shall riot till it sink in the remorceless eddy, sink where time shall never find his name but with disgrace to taint his hateful memory.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104240" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104250">This wildness neither befit your wisdom nor your courage, which should with settled and collected thoughts walk on to noble vengeance. He before was by our plots proscribed to death and ruin to advance me to the empire; now with ease we may accomplish our designs</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104260" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104270">Would heaven I ne'er had given consent, o'ercome by love to you to have made a forfeit on my allegiance, 'tis a just punishment, I by him am wronged, whom for your sake I fearless sought to ruin.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104280" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104290">Are you repentant grown, Mura? this softness? ill suits a person of your great resolves, on whom my fortunes have such firm dependence. Come, let Caropia's fate invoke thy vengeance to gain full mastery o'er all other passions, leave not a corner in the spacious heart unfurnished of a noble rage, which now will be an attribute of glorious justice: the law you know with loss of sight doth punish all rapes, though on mean persons; and our father is so severe a justicer, not blood can make a breach upon his faith to justice. Besides, we have already made him dangerous in great Almanzor's thoughts, and being delinquent he needs must suffer what the meanest offender merits for such a trespass.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104300" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104310">I'm awake now, the lethargy of horror and amaze that did obscure my reason, like those dull and lazy vapours that o'ershade the sun, vanish, and it resumes its native brightness. And now I would not but this devil prince had done this act upon Caropia's whiteness,<pb facs="18" n="35"/> since't yields you free access unto the empire, the deprival of's sight does render him incapable of future sovereignty.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104320" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104330">Thou'rt in the right, and hast put on manly considerations: Caropia (Since she's in her will untainted) has not foregone her honour: he dispatched once, as we will have him shortly, 't shall go hard else ▪ a tenant to his marble, thou agen● wedded in peace mayst be to her pure virtues, and live their happy owner.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104340" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104350">I'll repair to great Almanzor instantly, and if his partial piety do descend to pity, I will awake the executioner of justice, death, although in sleep more heavy than he can borrow from his natural coldness; on this good sword I'll wear my cause's justice till he do fall its sacrifice.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104360" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104370">But be sure you do't with cunning secrecy, perhaps, should he have notice of your just intentions, he would repair to th' army, from which safeguard our best force could not pluck him without danger to the whole empire.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104380" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104390">Doubt not but I'll manage with a discreet severity my vengeance, invoke Almanzor's equity with sudden and private haste.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104400" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104410">Mean time I will go put a new design in practice that may be much conducing to our purpose. Like clocks, one wheel another on must drive, affairs by diligent labour only thrive.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e104420">Exeunt.</stage>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A31672-e104430">
          <head>Scaena secunda.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e104440">Enter Selinthus, Gaselles, Osman, and soldiers.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104450" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104460">No quarrelling good cousins, lest it be with the glass, 'cause 'tis not of size sufficient to give you a magnificent draught. You will have ●●ighting work enough● when you're i'th' wars, do not fall out among yourselves.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104470" who="A31672-osman">
            <pb facs="19" n="36"/>
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104480">Not pledge my peerless mistress health? Soldier, thou'rt mortal, if thou refuse it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104490" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104500">Come, come, he shall pledge it, and 'twere a tun. Why, we're all as dull as dormice in our liquor: here's a health to the prince Abilqualit. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104510" who="A31672-soldier">
            <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104520">Let go round: I'd drink't, were it an ocean of warm blood flowing from th'enemy. Pray, good my lord what news is stirring?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104530" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104540">It should seem, soldier, thou canst not read; otherwise the learned pamphlets that fly about the streets, would satisfy thy curiosity with news; they're true ones, full of discreet intelligence.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104550" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104560">Cousins, shall's have a song? here is a soldier in's time hath sung a dirge unto the foe oft in the field.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104570" who="A31672-soldier">
            <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104580">Captain, I have a new one, the soldier's joy 'tis called.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104590" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104600">That is an harlot. Prithee be musical, and let us taste the sweetness of thy voice.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e104610">A song.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104620" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104630">Whist, give attention.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104640" who="A31672-soldier">
            <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104650">How does your lordship like it?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104660" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104670">Very well. And so here's to thee. There's no drum beats yet, and 'tis clear day; some hour hence 'twill be<stage xml:id="A31672-e104680">Enter Abr. Mes.</stage>time to break up the watch. Ha! young lord Abrahen, and trim Mesithes with him! what the devil does he make up so early? He has been a batfowling all night after those birds, those ladybirds termed wagtails; what strange business can he have here, trow?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104690" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104700">'Twas well done, Mesithes! and trust me, I shall find an apt reward, both for thy care and cunning. Prithee hast to lord Simanthes, and deliver this note to him with best diligence, my dear eunuch; thou'rt half the soul of Abrahen:</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104710" who="A31672-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104720">I was born to be entitled your most humble vassal; I'll haste to the lord Simanthes. </p>
            <stage xml:id="A31672-e104730">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104740" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <pb facs="19" n="37"/>
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104750">How he cringes! These youths that want the instruments of manhood, are very supple in the hams.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104760" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104770">Good-morrow to noble lord Selinthus: what companions have you got here thus early?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104780" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104790">Blades of metal, tall men of war, an't please your grace, of my own blood and family, men who gathered a salad on the enemy's ground, and eaten it in bold defiance of him; and not a soldier here but's an Achilles, valiant as stoutest Myrmidon. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104800" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104810">And they never had juster cause to show their valour; the prince my dearest brother, their lord general's became a forfeit to the stern law's rigour; and 'tis imagined, our impartial father, will sentence him to lose his eyes.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104820" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104830">Marry heaven defend, for what, and 't like your grace!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104840" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104850">For a fact which the severe law punishes with loss of natures precious lights; my tears will scarce permit me utter 't: for a rape committed on the fair wife of Mura. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104860" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104870">Was it for nothing else, and please your grace? ere he shall lose an eye for such a trifle, or have a hair diminished, we will lofe our heads; what, hoodwink men like sullen hawks for doing deeds of nature! I'm ashamed the law is such an ass.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104880" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104890">Some eunuch judge, that could not be acquainted with the sweets due to concupiscential parts, invented this law, I'll be hanged else. Is life, a prince, and such a hopeful one, to lose his eyes, for satisfying the hunger of the stomach beneath the waist, is cruelty prodigious, not to be suffered in a commonwealth of ought but geldings.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104900" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104910">'Tis vain to soothe our hopes with these delusions, he will suffer less he be rescued. I would have you therefore<pb facs="20" n="38"/> if you owe any service to the prince, my much lamented brother, to attend without least tumult about the court, and if there be necessity of your aid, I'll give you notice when to employ it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104920" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104930">Sweet prince, we'll swim in blood to do thee or thy brother service. Each man provide their weapons.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104940" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104950">You will win my brother's love for ever, nay my father, though he'll seem angry to behold his justice deluded, afterwards when his rage is past, will thank you for your loyalties: pray be there with all speed possible, by this my brothers commanded 'fore my father, I'll go learn the truth, and give you notice: pray be secret and firm to your resolves.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A31672-e104960">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e104970" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e104980">For him that flinches in such a cause, I'll have no more mercy on him. Here's Tarifa<stage xml:id="A31672-e104990">Enter Tarifa and Mura</stage>the princes sometimes tutor, Mura with him a walking towards the court, let's take no notice of them, lest they discover our intentions by our grim looks. March fair and softly cousins, we'll be at court before them.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105000" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105010">You will not do this, Mura! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105020" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105030">How Tarifa? will you defend him in an act so impious? Is't fit the drum should cease his surly language, when the bold soldier's marches, or that I should pass o'er this affront in quiet silence, which gods and men invoke to speedy vengeance? which I will have, or manhood shall be tame as cowardice.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105040" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105050">It was a deed so barbarous, that truth itself blushes as well as justice to hear it mentioned: but consider Mura, he is our prince, the empire's hope, and pillar of great Almanzor's age how far a public regard should be preferred before your private desire of vengeance! which if you do purchase from our impartial emperor's equity, his loss of sight, and so of the succession, will not restore Caropia to the honour<pb facs="20" n="39"/> he ravished from her. But so foul the cause is, I rather should lament the prince's folly than plead in his behalf.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105060" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mur.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105070">'Tis but vain, there is your warrant, as you are high marshal, to summon him to make his speedy appearance 'fore the tribunal of Almanzor; so pray you execute your office.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A31672-e105080">Exit.</stage>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105090" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105100">How one vice can like a small cloud when't breaks forth in showers, black the whole heaven of virtues! O my lord,<stage xml:id="A31672-e105110">Enter Abilqualit, Muts, whispering, seem to make protestations. Exeunt.</stage>that face of yours which once with angel brightness cheered my faint sight, like a grim apparition frights it with ghastly terror: you have done a deed that startles virtue till it shakes as it got a palsy. I'm commanded to summon you before your father, and hope you'll obey his mandate.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105120" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105130">Willingly, what's my offence, Tarifa? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105140" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105150">Would you knew not, I did presage your too unruly passions would hurry you to some disastrous act, but never imagined you'd have been so lost to masculine honour, to commit a rape on that unhappy object of your love, whom now you've made the spoil of your foul lust, the much wronged wife of Mura. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105160" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105170">Why, does Mura charge me with his Caropia's rape?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105180" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105190">This warrant sent by your angry father, testifies he means to appeach you of it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105200" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105210">'Tis my fortune, all natural motions when they approach their end, haste to draw to't with accustomed swiftness. Rivers with greedier speed run near their outfalls, than at their springs. But I'm resolved, let what happen that will, I'll stand it, and defend Carpoia's honour, though mine own I ruin; who dares not die to justify his love, deserves not to enjoy her. Come, Tarifa, whate'er befall, I'm resolute. He dies glorious, that falls loves innocent sacrifice.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e105220">Exeunt.</stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A31672-e105230">
        <pb facs="21" n="40"/>
        <head>Actus quartus.</head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A31672-e105240">
          <head>Scaena i.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e105250">Enter Almanzor, Abilqualit, Tarifa and Mura.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105260" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105270">No more Tarifa, you'll provoke our anger, if you appear in this cause so solicitous, the act is too apparent: nor shall you need (Injured Mura) to implore our justice, which with impartial doom shall fall on him more rigorously, then on a strange offender. O Abilqualit, (For the name of son, when thou forsookst thy native virtue, left thee;) were all thy blood, thy youth and fortune's glories of no more value, than to be exposed to ruin for one vice; at whose name only the furies start, and bashful fronted justice hides her amazed head? But it is now bootless to show a father's pity, in my grief for thy amiss. As I'm to be thy judge, be resolute, I'll take as little notice, thou art my offspring, as the wandering clouds do of the showers, which when they've bred to ripeness, they straight disperse through the vast earth forgotten.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105280" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105290">I'm sorry sir, that my unhappy chance should draw your anger on me; my long silence declares I have on that excelling sweetness, that unexampled pattern of chaste goodness; Caropia acted violence. I confess, I loved the lady, and when no persuasions served to prevail on her, too stubborn, incensed, by force I sought my purpose and obtained it; nor do I yet (So much I prize the sweetness of that unvalued purchase) find repentance in any abject thought; whate'er falls on me from your stern rigor in a cause so precious, will be a pleasing punishment.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105300" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105310">Yond are grown a glorious malefactor, that dare brave thus the awful rod of justice! Lost young man, for thou'rt no child of mine; dost not consider to what a state of desperate destruction thy wild lust has betrayed thee! What rich blessings<pb facs="21" n="41"/> (That I may make thee sensible of thy sins by showing thee thy suffering) hast thou lost by thy irregular folly! First my love, which never more must meet thee, scarce in pity; the glory flowing from thy former actions stopped up for ever; and those lustful eyes, by whose deprival (Thou'rt deprived of being capable of this empire) to the law, which will exact them, forfeited. Call in there a surgeon, and our mutts to execute this act<stage xml:id="A31672-e105320">Enter Surg. Muts.</stage>of justice on the unworthy traitor, upon whom my just waked wrath shall have no more compassion, than the incensed flames have on perishing wretches that wilfully leap into them.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105330" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105340">O my lord, that which on others would be fitting justice, on him your hopeful though offending son, will be exemplar cruelty; his youth sir, that hath abounded with so many virtues ▪ is an excuse sufficient for one vice: he is not yours only. he's your empires, destined by nature and succession's privilege, when you in peace are shrouded in your marble, to wield this sceptre after you. O do not, by putting out his eyes, deprive your subjects of light, and leave them to dull mournful darkness.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105350" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105360">'Tis but in vain, I am inexorable. If those on which his eyes hang, were my heart strings, I'd cut them out rather than wound my justice; nor dost befit thy virtue intercede for him in this cause horrid and prodigious; the crime 'gainst me was acted; 'twas a rape upon my honour, more than on her whiteness; his was from mine derivative, as each stream is from its spring; so that he has polluted by his soul fact, my fame, my truth, my goodness, strucken through my dignity by his violence: nay, started in their peaceful urns, the ashes of all my glorious ancestors; defiled the memory of their still descendent virtues; nay with a killing frost, nipped the fair blossoms, that did presage such goodly fruit arising from his own hopeful youth.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105370" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mur.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105380">I ask but justice;<pb facs="22" n="42"/> those eyes that led him to unlawful objects, 'tis fit should suffer for't a lasting blindness; the sun himself, when he darts rays lascivious, such as engender by too piercing fervence intemperate and infectious heats, straight wears obscurity from the clouds his own beams raises. I have been your soldier sir, and fought your battles; for all my services, I beg but justice, which is the subjects best prerogative, the prince's greatest attribute; and for a fact, than which, none can be held more black and hideous, which has betrayed to an eclipse the brightest star in th' heaven of virtues: the just law does for 't ordain a punishment, which I hope you the law's righteous guider, will according to equity see executed.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105390" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105400">Why! that law was only made for common malefactors, but has no force to extend unto the prince, to whom the law itself must become subject. This hopeful prince, look on him, great Almanzor; and in his eyes, those volumes of all graces, which you like erring meteors would extinguish ▪ read your own lively figure, the best story of your youths noblest vigour; let not wrath (Sir) o'ercome your piety, nay your humane pity. 'tis in your breast, my lord, yet to show mercy; that precious attribute of heavens true goodness, even to yourself, your son! methinks that name should have a power to interdict your justice in its too rigorous progress.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105410" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105420">Dear Tarifa, I'm more afflicted at the intercessions, then at the view of my approaching torments, which I will meet with fortitude and boldness, too base to shake now at one personal danger, when I've encountered thousand perils fearless; nor do I blame my gracious father's justice, though it precede his nature. I'd not have him (For my sake) forfeit that for which he's famous, his uncorrupted equity, nor repine I at my destiny; my eyes have had delights sufficient in Caropia's beauties, to serve my thought● for after contemplations;<pb facs="22" n="43"/> nor can I ever covet a new object, since they can never hope to encounter any of equal worth and sweetness. Yet hark Tarifa, to thy secrecy I will impart my dearest, inmost counsels; if I should perish, as 'tis probable I may, under the hands of these tormentors; thou mayst unto succession show my innocence; Caropia yielded without least constraint, and I enjoyed her freely.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105430" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105440">How my lord?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105450" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105460">No words on't, as you respect my honour! I'd not lose the glory I shall gain by these my sufferings; come grim fures, and execute your office. I will stand you, unmoved as hills at whirlwinds, and amid the torments you inflict, retain my courage.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105470" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105480">Be speedy villains.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105490" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105500">O stay your cruel hands, you dumb ministers of injured justice, and let me speak his innocence ere you further afflict his precious eyesight.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105510" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105520">What does this mean, Tarifa! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105530" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105540">O my lord, the too much bravery of the prince's spirit 'tis has undone his fame, and pulled upon him this fatal punishment; 'twas but to save the lady's honour, that he has assumed her rape upon him, when with her consent the deed of shame was acted.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105550" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mur.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105560">'Tis his fears makes him traduce her innocence: he who did not stick to commit a riot on her person, can make no conscience to destroy her fame by his untrue suggestions.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105570" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105580">'Tis a baseness beyond thy other villainy (Had she yielded,) thus to betray for transitory torture, her honour, which thou wert engaged to safeguard even with thy life. A son of mine could never show this ignoble cowardice: proceed to execution, I'll not hear him speak, he is made up of treacheries and falsehoods.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105590" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105600">Will you then<pb facs="23" n="44"/> be to the prince so tyrannous? Why, to me just now he did confess his only motive to undergo this torment, was to save Caropia's honour blameless.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105610" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105620">I am more troubled ▪ sir, with his untimely frenzy, then with my punishment; his too much love to me, has spoilt his temperate reason. I confess Caropia yielded! Not the light is half so innocent as her spotless virtue. 't was not well done, Tarifa, to betray the secret of your friend thus: though she yielded, the terror of ten thousand deaths shall never force me to confess it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105630" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105640">Again, my lord, even now he does confess, she yielded, and protests that death shall never make him say she's guilty: the breath scarce passed his lips yet.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105650" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105660">Hapless man, to run into this lunacy! Fie Tarifa, so treacherous to your friend!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105670" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105680">Again, again. Will no man give me credit?</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e105690">Enter Abrahen.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105700" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105710">Where is our royal father?: where our brother? As you respect your life and empire's safety, dismiss these tyrannous instruments of death and cruelty unexemplified. O brother, that I should ever live to enjoy my eyesight, and see one half of your dear lights endangered. My lord, you've done an act, which my just fears tells me, will shake your sceptre! O for heaven's sake, look to your future safety; the rough soldier hearing their much loved general, my good brother was by the law betrayed to some sad danger, have in their piety beset the palace; think on some means to appease them, ere their fury grow to its full unbridled height; they threaten your life, great sir: pray send my brother to them, his sight can only pacify them.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105720" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105730">Have you your champions! We will prevent their insolence, you shall not boast, you have got the empire by our ruin. <pb facs="23" n="45"/>Muts, strangle him immediately.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105740" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105750">Avert such a prodigious mischief, heaven. Hark, hark<stage xml:id="A31672-e105760">Enter, enter.</stage>they're entered into th' court; desist you monsters, my life shall stand betwixt his and this violence, or I with him will perish. Faithful soldiers, haste to defend your prince, curse on your slowness. He's dead; my father's turn is next. O horror, would I might sink into forgetfulness ▪ what has your fury urged you to?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105770" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105780">To that which whoso murmurs at, is a faithless traitor<stage xml:id="A31672-e105790">Enter Simanthes.</stage>to our tranquillity. Now sir, your business?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105800" who="A31672-simanthes">
            <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105810">My lord, the city is up in arms, in rescue of the prince; the whole court throngs with soldiers.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105820" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105830">'T was high time to cut this viper off, that would have eat his passage through our very ●owels to our empire. Nay, we will stand their furies, and with terror of majesty strike dead these insurrections. <stage xml:id="A31672-e105840">Enter soldiers.</stage>traitors, what means this violence?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105850" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105860">Oh dear soldiers, your honest love's in vain; my brother's dead, strangled by great Almanzor's dire command, ere your arrival. I do hope they'll kill him in their hot zeal.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105870" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105880">Why do you stare so, traitors? 'twas I your emperor that have done this act, which who repines at, treads the self same steps of death that he has done. Withdraw and leave us, we'd be alone. No motion ▪ are you statues? Stay you, Tarifa here. For your part, Mura, you cannot now complain but you have justice; so quit our presence.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105890" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105900">Faces about, gentlemen.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e105910">Exeunt.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105920" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105930">It has happened above our wishes, we shall have no need now to employ your handkercher. Yet give it me. You're sure 'tis right, Simanthes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105940" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105950">Tarifa, I know the love thou bearest prince Abilqualit makes thy big heart swell as 't had drunk the foam of angry dragons. Speak thy free intentions,<pb facs="24" n="46"/> deserved he not this fate?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105960" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105970">No: you're a tyrant, one that delights to feed on your ▪ own bowels, and were not worthy of a son so virtuous. Now you have ta'en his, add to your injustice, and take Tarifa's life, who in his death, should it come flying on the wings of torments, would speak it out as an apparent truth ▪ the prince to me declared his innocence, and that Caropia yielded.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e105980" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e105990">Rise Tarifa; we do command thee, rise: a sudden chillness, such as the hand of winter casts on brooks, thrills our aged heart. I'll not have thee engross sorrow alone for Abilqualit's death: I loved the boy well, and though his ambition and popularity did make him dangerous, I do repent my fury, and will vie with thee in sorrow. How he makes death lovely! Shall we fix here, and weep till we be statues?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106000" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106010">Till we grow stiff as the cold alabasters must be erected over us ▪ your rashness has robbed the empire of the greatest hope it ere shall boast again. Would I were ashes.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106020" who="A31672-almanzo">
            <speaker>Al.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106030">He breathes ( methinks :) the overhasty soul was too discourteous to forsake so fair a lodging, without taking solemn leave first of the owner. Ha, his handkercher! Thou'rt liberal to thy father even in death, leavest him a legacy to dry his tears, which are too slow; they should create a deluge. O my dear Abilqualit! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106040" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106050">You exceed now as much in grief as you did then in rage, one drop of this pious paternal softness had ransomed him from ruin. Dear sir, rise: my grief's divided, and I know not whether I should lament you living, or him dead. Good sir, erect your looks. Not stir! His sorrow makes him insensible. Ha, there's no motion left in his vital spirits: the excess of grief has stifled up his powers, and cracked (I fear) his aged heart's cordage. Help, the emperor, he emperor's dead; help, help.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e106060"><pb facs="24" n="47"/>Abrahen, Simanthes, Mesithes, Muts</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106070" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106080">What dismal outcry's this? our royal father dead! The handkercher has wrought I see.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106090" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106100">Yes; his big heart vanquished with sorrow, that in's violent rage, he doomed his much loved son to timeless death, could not endure longer on its weak strings, but cracked with weight of sorrow. Their two spirits, by this, are met in their delightful passage to the blessed shades; we in our tears are bound to call you our dread sovereign.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106110" who="A31672-omnes">
            <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106120">Long live Abrahen great caliph of Arabia. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106130" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106140">'Tis a title we cannot covet, lords, it comes attended with so great cares and troubles, that our youth start at the thought of them, even in our sorrows which are so mighty on us; our weak spirits are ready to relinquish the possession they've of mortality, and take swift flight after our royal friends. Simanthes, be it your charge to see all fitting preparation provided for the funerals.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e106150">Enter Selinthus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106160" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106170">Where's great Almanzor? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106180" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106190">O Selinthus, this day is the hour of funerals grief; for his cruelty to my brother, has translated him to immortality.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106200" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106210">He'll have attendants to wait on him to our great prophet's paradise, ere he be ready for his grave. The soldiers all mad with rage for the prince's slaughter, have vowed by all oaths soldiers can invent, (And that's no small store) with death and destruction, to pursue sullen Mura. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106220" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106230">Tarifa, use your authority to keep their violence in due obedience. We're so fraught with grief, we have no room for any other passion in our distracted bosom. Take these royal bodies and place them on that couch; here where they fell, they shall be embalmed. Yet put them out of our sight, their views draw fresh drops from our heart. <pb facs="25" n="48"/>Anon we'll show ourselves to cheer the afflicted subject.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e106240">A sho●t.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106250" who="A31672-omnes">
            <speaker>Omnes</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106260">Long live Abrahen, great caliph of Arabia.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e106270">Exeunt</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106280" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106290">And who can say now, Abrahen is a villain? I am saluted King with acclamations that deaf the heavens to hear, with as much joy as if I had achieved this sceptre by means fair and virtuous. 'twas this handkercher that did to death Almanzor; so infected, it's least insensible vapour has full power; applied to th' eye, or any other organ, can drink its poison in to vanquish nature, though ne'er so strong and youthful. 'twas Simanthes devised it for my brother, and my cunning transferred it to Almanzor; 'tis no matter, my worst impiety is held now religious. Betwixt Kings and their inferiors there's this odds, these are mere men, we men, ye● earthly gods. <stage xml:id="A31672-e106300">Exit.</stage></p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106310" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106320">'Twas well the muts proved faithful, otherwise I'd lost my breath with as much speed and silence as those who do expire in dreams, their health seeming no whit abated. But 'twas wisely considered of me, to prepare those sure instruments of destruction: the suspicion I had by Abrahen of my father's fears of my unthought ambition, did instruct me by making them mine, to secure my safety. Would the inhumane surgeon had ta'en these blessed lights from me; that I had lived for ever doomed to perpetual darkness, rather than Tarifa's fears had so appeached her honour. Well, villain brother, I have found, that by my seeming death, which by my lives best arts I never should have had knowledge of. Dear father, though thou to me wert pitiless, my heart weeps tears of blood, to see thy age thus like a lofty pine fall, eaten through by th' gin from its own stock descending: he has agents in his ungracious wickedness: Simanthes he has discovered: were they multitudes as numerous as collected sands, and mighty in force as mischief, they should from my justice meet their due punishment. Abrahen by this is proclaimed Caliph, yet my undoubted right ▪<pb facs="25" n="49"/> when 't shall appear I'm living, will reduce the people to my part; the army's mine, whither I must withdraw unseen: the night will best secure me. What a strange chimaera of thought possesses my dull brain! Caropia, thou hast a share in them: fate, to thy mercy I do commit myself; who scapes the snare once, has a certain caution to beware. <stage xml:id="A31672-e106330">Exit.</stage></p>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A31672-e106340">
          <head>Scen. 2.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e106350">Enter Caropia and Perilinda.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106360" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106370">Your lord is not returned yet!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106380" who="A31672-perilinda">
            <speaker>Per.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106390">No, good madam: pray do not thus torment yourself, the prince (I warrant you) will have no injury by saving of your honour; do you think his father will be so extreme outrageous for such a trifle, as to force a woman with her good liking?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106400" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106410">My ill boding soul beats with presages ominous. Would heaven I'd stood the hazard of my incensed lords fury, rather than he had run this imminent danger. Could you never learn, which of the slaves it was betrayed our close loves to loathed Mura's notice?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106420" who="A31672-perilinda">
            <speaker>Per.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106430">No indeed could I not; but here's my lord, pray madam do not grieve so!</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e106440">Enter Mura.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106450" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106460">My Caropia, dress up thy looks in their accustomed beauties, call back the constant spring into thy cheeks, that droop like lovely violets, o'er charged with too much morning's dew; shoot from thy eyes a thousand flames of joy. The lustful prince, that like a foul thief, robbed thee of thy honour by his ungracious violence ▪ has met his royal father's justice.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106470" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106480">Now my fears carry too sure an augury! you would fain soothe me, my lord, out of my flood of sorrows ▪ what reparation can that make my honour, though he have tasted punishment?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106490" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106500">His life is fallen the offspring of thy chastity, which his hot lust polluted: nay, Caropia,<pb facs="26" n="50"/> to save himself, when he but felt the torment applied to his lascivious eyes; although at first he did with impudence acknowledge thy rape, he did invade thy spotless virtue, protested, only 'twas to save thy honour, he took on him thy rape, when with consent and not constrained, thou yieldedst to the looseness of his wild vicious flames.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106510" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106520">Could he be so unjust, my lord?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106530" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106540">He was, and he has paid for't; the malicious soldier, while he was a losing his eyes, made violent head to bring him rescue, which pulled his ruin on him. But no more of such a prodigy; may his black memory perish even with his ashes. My Caropia, the flourishing trees widowed by winter's violence of their fair ornaments, when 'tis expired once, put forth again with new and virgin freshness, their bushy beauties; it should be thy emblem. Display again those chaste immaculate glories ▪ which the harsh winter of his lust had withered; and I'll again be wedded to thy virtues, with as much joy, as when thou first enriched me with their pure maiden beauties. Thou art dull, and dost not gratulate with happy welcome ▪ the triumphs of thy vengeance.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106550" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106560">Are you sure, my lord, the prince is dead?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106570" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106580">Pish, I beheld him breathless. Take comfort best Caropia, thy disgrace did with his loathed breath vanish.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106590" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106600">I could wish though, that he had fallen by your particular vengeance, rather than by th' law's rigor; you're a soldier of glory, great in war for brave performance: methinks 't had been far nobler, had you called him to personal satisfaction: had I been your husband, you my wife, and ravished by him; my resolution would have armed my courage to've stroke him thus: the dead prince sends you that.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e106610">Stab him ▪</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106620" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106630">O, I am slain!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106640" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106650">Would it were possible to kill even thy eternity. Sweet prince, how shall I satisfy thy unhappy ruins! Ha, ● not yet breathless! To increase thy anguish<pb facs="26" n="51"/> even to despair, know, Abilqualit was more dear to me, than thy foul self was odious, and did enjoy me freely.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106660" who="A31672-mura">
            <speaker>Mu.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106670">That I had but breath enough to blast thee.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106680" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106690">'Twas his brother (Curse on his art) seduced me to accuse him of my rape. Do you groan, prodigy! take this as my last bounty.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e106700">Stab again.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e106710">Enter Perilinda.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106720" who="A31672-perilinda">
            <speaker>Per.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106730">O madam, madam, what shall we do? the house is round beset with soldiers; madam, they do swear they'll tear my lord, for the sweet prince's death, in pieces.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106740" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106750">This hand has saved their fury that just labour: yet I'll make use of their malice, help to convey him into is chamber.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e106760">Enter Osman, Gasselles, soldiers.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106770" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106780">Where is this villain, this traitor Mura? </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106790" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106800">Heaven knows what violence their fury may assault me with; be't death, 't shall be as welcome, as sound healthful sleeps to men oppressed with sickness. What's the matter? what means this outrage?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106810" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106820">Marry, lady gay, we're come to cut your little throat; pox on you, and all your sex; you've caused the noble prince's death, wildfire take you fort, we'll talk with you at better leisure: you must needs be ravished! and could not like an honest woman, take the courtesy in friendly sort!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106830" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106840">We trifle: her husband may escape us. Say, where is he? or you shall die, ere you can pray</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106850" who="A31672-unassigned">
            <speaker>Soldier ▪</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106860">Here, here I have found the villain! what, do you sleep so soundly? never wake more, this for the prince, you rogue: let's tear him piecemeal. Do you take your death in silence, dog!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106870" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106880">You appear endowed with some humanity, you have ta'en his life; let not your hate last after death; let me embalm his body with my tear, or kill me with him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106890" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106900">Now you have said the word,<pb facs="27" n="52"/> we care not if we do.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e106910">Enter Tarifa.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106920" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106930">Slaves, unhand the lady, who dares offer her least violence, from this hand meets his punishment. Gaselles, Osman, I thought you had been better tempered, then thus to raise up mutinies. In the name of Abrahen our now caliph, I command you, desist from these rebellious practises, and quietly retire into the camp, and there expect his pleasure.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106940" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106950">Abrahen Caliph! There is some hopes then, we shall gain our pardons: long live great Abrahen. Soldiers, slink away, our vow is consummate.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106960" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106970">O my dear lord!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e106980" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e106990">Be gone.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107000" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107010">Yes, as quietly as if we were in flight before the foe; the general pardon at the coronation, will bring us off ▪ i' me sure.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107020" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107030">Alas, good madam! I'm sorry that these miseries have fallen with so much rigor on you; pray take comfort ▪ your husband prosecuted with too much violence prince Abilqualit's ruin.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107040" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107050">It appeared so! what worlds of woes have hapless I given life to, and yet survive them!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107060" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107070">Do not with such fury torment your innocent self. I'm sure the emperor Abrahen, will number 't amongst his greatest sorrows, that he has lost your husband. I must give him notice of these proceedings. Best peace keep you, and settle your distractions.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107080" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107090">Not until I'm settled in my peaceful urn. This is yet some comfort to me, 'Midst the floods of woes, that do overwhelm me for the prince's death, that I revenged it safely; though I prize my life at no more value than a foolish ignorant Indian does a diamond, which for a bead of jet or glass, he changes: nor would I keep it, were it not with fuller, more noble bravery, to take revenge for my lord Abilqualit's timeless slaughter. <pb facs="27" n="53"/>I must use craft and mystery. Dissembling is held the natural quality of our sex, nor wil't be hard to practise. This same Abrahen, that by his brother's ruin wields the sceptre, whether out of his innocence or malice, 'twas that persuaded me to accuse him of my rape. The die is cast, I am resolved to thee my Abilqualit will come. A death for love, is no death but martyrdom.</p>
            <stage xml:id="A31672-e107100">Exit</stage>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A31672-e107110">
        <head>Actus quintus.</head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A31672-e107120">
          <head>Scaena 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e107130">Enter Abilqualit, Selinthus, Gasselles, Osman, soldiers, and Muts ▪</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107140" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107150">No more, good faithful soldiers; thank the powers divine, has brought me back to you in safety; the traitorous practises against our life, and our dear fathers, poisoned by our brother; we have discovered, and shall take just vengeance on the unnatural parricide: retire into your tents, and peacefully expect the event of things, you Osman and Gasselles shall into th' city with me.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107160" who="A31672-osman">
            <speaker>Os.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107170">We will march through the world with thee, dear sovereign, great Abilqualit. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107180" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107190">Selinthus, give you our dear Tarifa speedy notice we are again among the living: pray him to let our loyal subjects in the city, have sure intelligence of our escape; and dearest friends and fellows, let not your too loud expressions of your joy, for our unlooked for welfare, subject to discovery our unexpected safety.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107200" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107210">Never fear: they're trusty Myrmidons, and will stick close to you their dear Achilles; but my lord, the wisest may imagine it were safer for you to rest here among your armed legions, than to intrust your person in the city, whereas it seems by the passed story, you'll not know friends from enemies.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107220" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <pb facs="28" n="54"/>
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107230">Selinthus, thy honest care declares the zealous duty thou owest thy sovereign: but what danger can assault us there, where there is none suspects we are alive? we'll go survey the state of things, i'th' morning we will seize the palace, and then proclaim our right. Come, valiant captains, you shall be our companions.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107240" who="A31672-gaselles">
            <speaker>Gas.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107250">And we'll guard you safe, as you were encompassed with an army.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107260" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107270">You guard your own fools heads: is 't fit his safety, on which our lives and fortunes have dependence, should be exposed unto your single valour? Pray once let your friends rule you, that you may rule them hereafter. Your good brother Abrahen has a strong faction, it should seem i'th' court: and those these bloodhounds followed the sent ho●ly till they had worried Mura he has other allies of no mean consequence; your eunuch Mesithes his chief favourite, and Simanthes. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107280" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107290">It was that villain that betrayed my love to him and slaughtered Mura. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107300" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107310">Very likely. An arranter, falser parasite, never was cut like a colt. Pray sir, be wife this once, at my entreaties; and for ever after use your discretion as you please: these night works I do not like; yet ere the morning I will bring Tarifa to you.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107320" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107330">You shall o'er rule us. Poor Caropia, these thoughts are thy votaries; love thy active fire, ●●ames out when present, absent in desire.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e107340">Exeunt.</stage>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A31672-e107350">
          <head>Scen. 2.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e107360">Enter Abrahen, Simanthes and Mesithes.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107370" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107380">What state and dignity's like that of sceptres? With what an awful majesty resembles it the powers above? the inhabitants of that superior world are not more subject to them, than these to us; they can but tremble when they do speak in thunder; at our frowns these shake like lambs at lightning . Can it be impiety by any means to purchase this earthly deity ▪ sovereignty ▪ I did sleep<pb facs="28" n="55"/> this night with as secure and calm a peace, as in my former innocence. Conscience, thou'rt but a terror, first devised by th' fears of cowardice, a sad and fond remembrance, which men should shun, as elephants clear springs, lest they behold their own deformities,<stage xml:id="A31672-e107390">Enter Mesithes.</stage>and start at their grim shadows. Ha, Mesithes! </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107400" who="A31672-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107410">My royal lord!</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107420" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107430">Call me thy friend, Mesithes, thou equally dost share our heart, best eunuch; there is not in the stock of earthly blessings another I could wish to make my state completely fortunate, but one; and to achieve possession of that bliss, thy diligence must be the fortunate instrument.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107440" who="A31672-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107450">Be it dangerous as the affrights sea men do fain in tempests, I'll undertake it for my gracious sovereign, and perish, but effect it,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107460" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107470">No, there is not the least show of peril in't; 'tis the want of fair Caropia's long coveted beauties that doth afflict thy Abrahen. Love, Mesithes, is a most stubborn malady in a lady, not cured with that felicity, that are other passions, and creeps upon us by those ambushes, that we perceive ourselves sooner in love, than we can think upon the way of loving. The old flames break more brightly from th'ashes where they have long lain hid, like the young phoenix that from her spi●le pile revives more glorious. Nor can I now extinguished; it has passed the limits of my reason, and intend my will, where like a fixed star 't settles, never to be removed thence.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107480" who="A31672-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107490">Cease your fears; I that could win her for your brother, who could not boast half your masculine perfections, for you will vanquish her.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e107500">Enter Simanthes.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107510" who="A31672-simanthes">
            <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107520">My lord, the widow of slaughtered Mura, fair Caropia does humbly entreat access to your dread presence; shall we permit her entrance?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107530" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107540">With all freedom<pb facs="29" n="56"/> and best regard. Mesithes, this arrives beyond our wish. I'll try my eloquence in my own cause; and if I fail, thou then shalt be my advocate.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107550" who="A31672-messenger">
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107560">Your humblest vassal.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107570" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107580">Withdraw and leave us, and give strict order none approach our presence till we do call. It is not fit her sorrows<stage xml:id="A31672-e107590">Enter Car.</stage>should be surveyed by common eye. Caropia, welcome; and would we could as easily give thee comfort as we allow thee more than moderate pity. In tears those eyes cast forth a greater lustre, than sparkling rocks of diamonds enclosed in swelling seas of pearl.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107600" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107610">Your majesty is pleased to wanton with my miseries, which truly you, if you have nature in you, ought to bear equal part in your dear brothers untimely loss, occasioned by my falsehood, and your improvident counsel: 'tis that calls these hearty sorrows up, I am his murderess.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107620" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107630">'Twas his own destiny, not our bad intentions took him away from earth; he was too heavenly, fit only for th' society of angels, amongst whom he sings glad hymns to thy perfections, celebrating with such eloquence thy beauties, that those immortal essences forget to love each other by intelligence, and dote on the idea of thy sweetness.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107640" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107650">These gentle blandishments ▪ and his innocent carriage had I as much of malice as a tigress robbed of her young, would melt me into meekness. But I'll not be a woman.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107660" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107670">Sing out, angel, and charm the world (Were it at mortal difference) to peace with thine enchantments. What soft murmurs are those that steal through those pure rosy organs, like aromatic west-winds, when they fly through fruitful mists of fragrant morning's dew, to get the spring with child of flowers and spices? Disperse these clouds, that like the vail of night, with unbecoming darkness shade thy beauties, and strike a new day from those orient eyes, to gild the world with brightness.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107680" who="A31672-caropia">
            <pb facs="29" n="57"/>
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107690">Sir, these flatteries neither befit the ears of my true sorrows, nor yet the utterance of that real sadness should dwell in you. Are these the funeral rites you pay the memory of your royal father, and much lamented brother?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107700" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107710">They were mortal, and to lament them, were to show I envied th' immortal joys of that true happiness their glorious souls (Disfranchised from their flesh) possess to perpetuity and fullness. Besides, (Caropia) I have other griefs more near my heart, that circle 't with a sickness will shortly number me among their fellowship ▪ if speedier remedy be not applied to my most desperate malady.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107720" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107730">I shall (If my hand fail not my determined courage) send you to their society far sooner than you expect or covet. Why, great sir, what grief, unless your sorrow for their loss, is't can afflict you, that command all blessings men witty in ambition of excess can wish, to please their fancies?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107740" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107750">The want only of that which I've so long desired; thy love thy love, Caropia, without which my empire, and all the pleasures flowing from its greatness, will be but burdens, soul-tormenting troubles. There's not a beam shot from those grief drowned comets but (Like the sun's, when they break forth of showers) dart flames more hot and piercing. Had I never doted before on thy divine perfections, viewing thy beauty thus adorned by sadness, my heart, though marble, actuated to softness, would burn like sacred incense, itself being the altar, priest, and sacrifice.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107760" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107770">This is as unexpected, as unwelcome, sir. Howe'er you're pleased to mock me and my griefs with these impertinent, unmeant discourses, I cannot have so prodigal a faith, to give them the least credit; and it is unkindly done; thus to deride my sorrows.<pb facs="30" n="58"/> the virgin turtles hate to join their pureness with widowed mates; my lord, you are a prince, and such as much detest to utter falsehoods, as saints do perjuries: why should you strive then to lay a bait to captivate my affections, when your greatness conjoined with your youths masculine beauties, are to a woman's frailty, strong temptations? You know the story too of my misfortunes, that your dead brother, did with vicious looseness, corrupt the chaste streams of my spotless virtues, and left me soiled like a long plucked rose, whose leaves dissevered, have foregone their sweetness</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107780" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107790">Thou hast not (My Caropia;) thou to me art for thy sent still fragrant, and as precious as the prime virgins of the spring, the violets, when they do first display their early beauties, till all the winds in love, do grow contentious, which from their lips should ravish the first kisses. Caropia, thinkst thou I should fear the nuptials of this great empire, 'cause it was my brothers? As I succeeded him in all his glories, 'tis fit I do succeed him in his love. 'tis true, I know thy fame fell by his practice, which had he lived, he'd have restored by marriage, by it repaired thy injured honours ruins. I'm bound to do it in religious conscience; it is a debt his incensed ghost would quarrel me living for, should I not pay't with fullness.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107800" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107810">Of what frail temper is a woman's weakness! words writ in waters, have more lasting essence, than our determinations.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107820" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107830">Come, I know, thou must be gentle, I perceive a combat in thy soft heart, by th' intervening blushes that strive to adorn thy cheek with purple beauties, and drive the lovely livery of thy sorrows, the ivory paleness, out of them. Think, Caropia, with what a settled unrevolting truth I have affected thee; with what heat, what pureness; and when upon mature considerations, I found I was unworthy to enjoy a treasure of such excellent grace and goodness, I did desist, smothering my love in anguish; anguish! to which the soul of humane torments,<pb facs="30" n="59"/> compared, were pains not easy, but delicious; yet still the secret flames of my affections, like hidden virtues in some bashful man, grew great and ferventer by those suppressions. Thou wert created only for an empress; despise not then thy destiny, now greatness, love, empire, and whate'er may be held glorious, courts thy acceptance like obedient vassals.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107840" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107850">I have considered, and my serious thoughts tell me, 'tis folly to refuse these proffers: to put off my mortality, the pleasures of life, which like full streams, do flow from greatness, to wander i'th' unpeopled air, to keep society with ghastly apparitions, where's neither voice of friends, nor visiting suitors breathes to delight our ears, and all this for the fame of a fell murderess. I have blood enough already on my soul, more than my tears can e'er wash off. My royal lord, if you can be so merciful and gracious, to take a woman laden with afflictions, big with true sorrow, and religious penitence for her amiss, her life and after actions, shall study to deserve your love. But surely this is not serious.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107860" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107870">Not the vows which votaries make to the powers above, can be more fraught with binding sanctity. This holy kiss confirms our mutual vows: never till now was I true caliph of Arabia. </p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e107880">Enter, enter, enter,</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107890" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107900">Ha, what tumult's that! Be you all furies, and thou the greatest of devils, Abrahen will stand you all, unmoved as mountains. This good sword if you be air, shall disenchant you from your borrowed figures.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107910" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107920">No, ill-natured monster, we're all corporeal, and survive to take revenge on thy inhumane acts, at name of which, the bashful elements do shake as if they teemed with prodigies. Dost not tremble at thy inhumane villains? Dear Caropia,<pb facs="31" n="60"/> quit the infectious viper, lest his touch poison thee passed recovery.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107930" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107940">No, she shall not; nor you, until this body be one wound. Lay a rude hand upon me! Abilqualit, howe'er thou scap'st my practises with life, I am not now to question; we were both sons to one father, whom, for love of empire, when I believed thee strangled by those muts, I sent to his eternal rest; nor do I repent the fact yet, I have been titled caliph a day, which is to my ambitious thoughts, honour enough to eternize my big name to all posterity. I know thou art of valiant noble soul; let not thy brother fall by ignoble hands, oppressed by number; draw thy bright weapon; as thou art in empire, thou art my rival in this lady's love, whom I esteem above all joys of life: for her and for this monarchy, let's try our strengths and fates: the impartial fates to him, who has the better cause, in justice must needs design the victory.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107950" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107960">In this offer, though it proceed from desperateness, not valour; thou show'st a masculine courage, and we will not render our cause so abject as to doubt, but our just arm has strength to punish thy most unheard of treacheries</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107970" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e107980">But you shall not be so unjust to us and to your right, to try your causes most undoubted justice, 'gainst the dispairing ruffian; soldiers, pull the lady from him, and disarm him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e107990" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108000">Stay! though he doth merit multitudes of death, we would not murder his eternity by sudden execution; yield yourself, and we'll allow you liberty of life, till by repentance you have purged your sin; and so if possible, redeem your soul from future punishment.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108010" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108020">Pish, tell fools of souls, and those effeminate cowards that do dream<pb facs="31" n="61"/> of those fantastic other worlds: there is not such a thing in nature; all the soul of man is resolution, which expires never from valiant men, till their last breath, and then with it like to a flame extinguished for want of matter, 't dos not die, but rather ceases to live. Enjoy in peace your empire, and as a legacy of Abrahen's love, take this fair lady to your bride.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e108030">Stab her.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108040" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108050">Inhuman butcher! has slain the lady. Look up, best Caropia, run for our surgeons: I'll give half my empire to save her precious life.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108060" who="A31672-abrahen">
            <speaker>Abr.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108070">She has enough, or mine aim failed me, to procure her passage to the eternal dwellings: nor is this cruelty in me; I alone was worthy to have enjoyed her beauties. Make good haste Caropia, or my soul, if I have any, will hover for thee in the clouds. This was the fatal engine which betrayed our father to his untimely death, made by Simanthes for your use, Abilqualit: and who has this about him and would be a slave to your base mercy, deserved death more than by daily tortures; and thus I kissed my last breath. Blast you all.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e108080">Dies.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108090" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108100">Damned desperate villain.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108110" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108120">O my dear Caropia, my empire now will be unpleasing to me since I must lose thy company. This surgeon, where's this surgeon?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108130" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108140">Drunk perhaps.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108150" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108160">'Tis but needless, no humane help can save me: yet methinks I feel a kind of pleasing ease in your embraces. I should utter something, and I have strength enough, I hope, lest yet to effect my purpose. In revenge for your supposed death, my loved lord, I slew my husband,</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108170" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108180">I'm sorry thou hast that sin to charge thy soul with, 'twas rumoured by the soldiers.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108190" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108200">Cousins mine, your necks are safe again now.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108210" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108220">And came hither with an intent to have for your sake slain your brother<pb facs="32" n="62"/> Abrahen, had not his courtesy and winning carriage altered my resolution, with this poniard I'd struck him here about the heart.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e108230">Stabs Abil.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108240" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108250">O I am slain, Caropia, and by thy hand. Heavens, you are just, this is revenge for thy dear honour which I murdered, though thou were't consenting to it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108260" who="A31672-caropia">
            <speaker>Car.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108270">True, I was so, and not repent it yet, my sole ambition was to have lived an empress, which since fate would not allow, I was resolved no woman after myself should ere enjoy that glory, you dear Abilqualit: which since my weak strength has served me to perform, I die willingly as an infant. O now I faint, life's death to those that keep it by constraint.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e108280">Dye.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108290" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108300">My dear lord, is there no hopes of life? must we be wretched?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108310" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108320">Happier, my Tarifa, by my death: but yesterday I played the part in jest which I now act in earnest my Tarifa, the empire's thine, I'm sure thou'lt rul't with justice, and make the subject happy. Thou hast a son of hopeful growing virtues to succeed thee, commend me to him, and from me entreat him to shun the temptings of lascivious glances.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108330" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108340">Alas good prince! he'll die indeed. I fear, he is so full of serious thoughts and counsels.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108350" who="A31672-abilqualit">
            <speaker>Abil.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108360">For this slaughtered body, let it have decent burial with slain Muras, but let not Abrahen's corpse have so much honour to come ith' royal monument: lay mine by my dear fathers: for that treacherous eunuch, and lord Simanthes, use them as thy justice tells thee they have merited; for lord Selinthus, advance him (My Tarifa) he's of faithful and well deserving virtues.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108370" who="A31672-unassigned">
            <speaker>S●l:</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108380">So I am, I thought 'twould come to me anon: poor prince, I e'en could die with him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108390" who="A31672-unassigned">
            <speaker>Ab●l.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108400">And for those soldiers, and those our most faithful muts, that my life once saved, let them be well rewarded; death and I are almost now<pb facs="32" n="63"/> at unity. Farewell.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e108410">Dies.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108420" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108430">Sure I shall not survive these sorrows long. Muts, take those traitors to prison; we will shortly pass their sentence, which shall be death inevitable. Take up that fatal instrument of poisonous mischief, and see it burned, Gaselles. Gentlemen, fate has made us your King against our wishes.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108440" who="A31672-selinthus">
            <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108450">Long live Tarifa, caliph of Arabia. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A31672-e108460" who="A31672-tarifa">
            <speaker>Tar.</speaker>
            <p xml:id="A31672-e108470">We have no time now for your acclamations ▪ these are black sorrows festival. Bear off in state that royal body; for the other, since 'twas his will, let them have burial, but in obscurity. By this it may, as by an evident rule be understood, they're only truly great, wh 'Are truly good.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e108480">Recorders flourish.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A31672-e108490">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
          <trailer xml:id="A31672-e108500">Finis.</trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A31672-e108510">
      <div type="epilogue" xml:id="A31672-e108520">
        <head>Epilogue.</head>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108530">I'm much displeased the poet has made me</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108540">The epilogue to his sad tragedy. </l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108550">Would I had died honestly amongst the rest,</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108560">Rather than live to th' last, now to be pressed</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108570">To death by your hard censures. Pray you say,</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108580">What is it you dislike so in this play,</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108590">That none applauds? Believe it, I should faint,</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108600">Did not some smile, and keep me by constraint</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108610">From the sad qualm. What power is in your breath,</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108620">That you can save alive, and doom to death,</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108630">Even whom you please? thus are your judgements free,</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108640">Most of the rest are slain, you may save me. </l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108650">But if death be the word, I pray bestow it</l>
        <l xml:id="A31672-e108660">Where it best fits. Hang up the poet. </l>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A31672"><item xml:id="A31672-abilqualit" n="70">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-abilqualit</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">70</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-abrahen" n="64">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-abrahen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">64</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-selinthus" n="42">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-selinthus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">42</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-tarifa" n="36">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-tarifa</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">36</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-caropia" n="35">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-caropia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">35</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-mura" n="29">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-mura</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">29</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A31672-almanzo" n="26">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-almanzo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">26</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-gaselles" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-gaselles</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-osman" n="14">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-osman</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">14</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-simanthes" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-simanthes</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-messenger" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-perilinda" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-perilinda</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-soldier" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-soldier</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-unassigned" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-omnes" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-omnes</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A31672-mesithes" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A31672-mesithes</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

