<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A21328">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Fair Em<date type="creation_date">1590</date></title>
        <author>anon.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Nicole Sheriko</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A21328.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A pleasant commodie, of faire Em the Millers daughter of Manchester vvith the loue of William the Conqueror: As it was sundrietimes publiquely acted in the honourable citie of London, by the right honourable the Lord Strange his seruaunts.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>25 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99846931</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 7675.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg I, 113.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">11928</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21328</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A pleasant commodie, of faire Em the Millers daughter of Manchester vvith the loue of William the Conqueror: As it was sundrietimes publiquely acted in the honourable citie of London, by the right honourable the Lord Strange his seruaunts.</title>
            <author>Wilson, Robert, d. 1600,</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[48] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>[By J. Danter] for T. N[ewman] and I. VV[innington] and are to be solde in S. Dunstones Churchyarde in Fleete-streete,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>[1591?]</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Fair Em.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's and publishers' names from STC; publication date estimated by STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Sometimes attributed to Robert Wilson; misattributed to William Shakespeare and to Robert Greene.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Last leaf blank?--Greg.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-F4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>William, -- I, -- King of England, -- 1027 or 8-1087 -- Drama -- Early works to 1800.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A21328-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A21328-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A21328-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <head>A pleasant comedy, of fair Em the miller's daughter of Manchester: with the love of William the conqueror:</head>
        <p xml:id="A21328-e100040">As it was sundry times publicly acted in the honourable city of London, by the right honourable the lord strange his servants.</p>
        <p xml:id="A21328-e100050">Imprinted at London for T.n. and I.w. and are to be sold in s. Dunstone's churchyard in Fleetstreet.</p>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A21328-e100060">
      <div type="masque" xml:id="A21328-e100070">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>A pleasant comedy of fair Em the miller's daughter of Manchester. With the love of William the conqueror.</head>
        <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A21328-e100080">
          <head>Actus primus</head>
          <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A21328-e100090">
            <head>Scaena prima.</head>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e100100">Enter William the conqueror: marquess Lubeck, with a picture: Mountney: Manville: Valingford: and Duke Dirot.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e100110" who="A21328-denmark">
              <speaker>Marquess.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100120">What means fair Britain's mighty conqueror</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100130">So suddenly to cast away his staff? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100140">And all in passion, to forsake the tilt. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e100150" who="A21328-dirot">
              <speaker>D. Dirot.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100160">My lord, this triumph we solemnise here,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100170">Is for mere love to your increasing joys:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100180">Only expecting cheerful looks for all. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100190">What sudden pangs then moves your majesty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100200">To dim the brightness of the day with frowns? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e100210" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>W. conqueror.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100220">Ah: good my lords, misconstrue not the cause:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100230">At least, suspect not my displeased brows</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100240">I amorously do bear to your intent:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100250">For thanks and all that you can wish I yield. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100260">But that which makes me blush and shame to tell,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100270">Is cause why thus I turn my conquering eyes</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100280">To coward's looks and beaten fantasies. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e100290" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100300">Since we are guiltless, we the less dismay</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100310">To see this sudden change possess your cheer:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100320">For if it issue from your own conceits,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100330">Bred by suggestion of some envious thoughts:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100340">Your highness' wisdom may suppress it straight. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100350">Yet tell us (Good my lord) what thought it is,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100360">That thus bereaves you of your late content,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100370">That in advice we may assist your grace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100380">Or bend our forces to revive your spirits. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e100390" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>W Con.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100400">Ah marquess Lubeck, in thy power it lies</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100410">To rid my bosom of these thralled dumps:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100420">And therefore, good my lords forbear awhile,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100430">That we may parley of these private cares,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100440"><pb facs="4"/> whose strength subdues me more than all the world. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e100450" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100460">We go and wish thee private conference,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100470">Public affects in this accustomed peace. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e100480">Exit all but William and the marquess.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e100490" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100500">Now marquess must a conqueror at arms</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100510">Disclose himself thralled to unarmed thoughts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100520">And threatened of a shadow, yield to lust:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100530">No sooner had my sparkling eyes beheld</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100540">The flames of beauty blazing on this piece,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100550">But suddenly a sense of miracle</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100560">Imagined on thy lovely mistress' face,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100570">Made me abandon bodily regard,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100580">And cast all pleasures on my wounded soul:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100590">Then gentle marquess tell me what she is,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100600">That thus thou honour'st on thy warlike shield. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100610">And if thy love and interest be such,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100620">As justly may give place to mine,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100630">That if it be: my soul with honour's wings</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100640">May fly into the bosom of my dear. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100650">If not, close them and stoop into my grave. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e100660" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Marquess</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100670">If this be all renowned conqueror:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100680">Advance your drooping spirits, and revive</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100690">The wonted courage of your conquering mind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100700">For this fair picture painted on my shield</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100710">Is the true counterfeit of lovely Blanche</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100720">Princesses and daughter to the King of Danes:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100730">Whose beauty and excess of ornaments</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100740">Deserves another manner of defence</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100750">Pomp and high person to attend her state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100760">Than marquess Lubeck any way presents. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100770">Therefore her virtues I resign to thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100780">Already shrined in thy religious breast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100790">To be advanced and honoured to the full. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100800">Nor bear I this an argument of love:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100810">But to renown fair Blanche my sovereign's child,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100820">In every place where I by arms may do it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e100830" who="A21328-william">
              <pb facs="4"/>
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100840">Ah marquess, thy words bring heaven unto my soul,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100850">And had I heaven to give for thy reward:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100860">Thou shouldst be throned in no unworthy place. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100870">But let my uttermost wealth suffice thy worth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100880">Which here I vow, and to aspire the bliss</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100890">That hangs on quick achievement of my love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100900">Thyself and I will travel in disguise,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100910">To bring this lady to our Britain court. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e100920" who="A21328-denmark">
              <speaker>Marquess.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100930">Let William but bethink what may avail,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100940">And let me die if I deny my aid. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e100950" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100960">Then thus the Duke Dirot and th'earl Dimarch</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100970">Will I leave substitutes to rule my realm,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100980">While mighty love forbids my being here,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e100990">And in the name of sir Robert of Windsor</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101000">Will go with thee unto the Danish court. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101010">Keep William's secrets marquess if thou love him. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101020">Bright Blanche I come, sweet fortune favour me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101030">And I will laud thy name eternally. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e101040">Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e101050">Enter the miller, and Em his daughter.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e101060" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101070">Come daughter we must learn to shake off pomp,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101080">To leave the state that erst beseemed a knight</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101090">And gentleman of no mean descent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101100">To undertake this homely miller's trade:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101110">Thus must we mask to save our wretched lives,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101120">Threatened by conquest of this hapless isle:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101130">Whose sad invasions by the conqueror,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101140">Have made a number such as we subject</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101150">Their gentle necks unto their stubborn yoke,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101160">Of drudging labour and base peasantry. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101170">Sir Thomas Godard now old Goddard is</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101180">Goddard the miller of fair Manchester. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101190">Why should not I content me with this state? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101200">As good sir Edmund Trefford did the flail. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101210">And thou sweet Em must stoop to high estate. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101220">To join with mine that thus we may protect</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101230"><pb facs="5"/> our harmless lives, which led in greater port</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101240">Would be an envious object to our foes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101250">That seek to root all Britain's gentry</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101260">From bearing countenance against their tyranny. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e101270" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101280">Good father let my full resolved thoughts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101290">With settled patience to support this chance</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101300">Be some poor comfort to your aged soul:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101310">For therein rests the height of my estate,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101320">That you are pleased with this dejection,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101330">And that all toils my hands may undertake,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101340">May serve to work your worthiness content. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e101350" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101360">Thanks my dear daughter: these thy pleasant words</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101370">Transfer my soul into a second heaven:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101380">And in thy settled mind, my joys consist,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101390">My state revived and I in former plight. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101400">Although our outward pomp be thus abased,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101410">And thralled to drudging, stayless of the world,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101420">Let us retain those honourable minds</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101430">That lately governed our superior state. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101440">Wherein true gentry is the only mean</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101450">That makes us differ from base millers born:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101460">Though we expect no knightly delicates,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101470">Nor thirst in soul for former sovereignty. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101480">Yet may our minds as highly scorn to stoop</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101490">To base desires of vulgars' worldliness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101500">As if we were in our precedent way. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101510">And lovely daughter, since thy youthful years</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101520">Must needs admit as young affections:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101530">And that sweet love unpartial perceives</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101540">Her dainty subjects thorough every part,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101550">In chief receive these lessons from my lips. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101560">The true discoverers of a virgin's due</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101570">Now requisite, now that I know thy mind</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101580">Something inclined to favour Manville suit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101590">A gentleman, thy lover in protest:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101600">And that thou mayst not be by love deceived,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101610"><pb facs="5"/> but try his meaning fit for thy desert,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101620">In pursuit of all amorous desires,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101630">Regard thine honour. Let not vehement sighs</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101640">Nor earnest vows importing fervent love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101650">Render thee subject to the wrath of lust:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101660">For that transformed to former sweet delight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101670">Will bring thy body and thy soul to shame. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101680">Chaste thoughts and modest conversations</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101690">Of proof to keep out all enchanting vows,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101700">Vain sighs, forced tears, and pitiful aspects,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101710">Are they that make deformed ladies fair,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101720">Poor wretch, and such enticing men,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101730">That seek of all but only present grace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101740">Shall in perseverance of a virgin's due</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101750">Prefer the most refusers to the choice</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101760">Of such a soul as yielded what they thought. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101770">But ho: where is Trotter? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e101780">Here enters Trotter the miller's man to them: and they within call to him for their grist.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e101790" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101800">Where's Trotter? why Trotter is here.</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101810">I'faith, you and your daughter go up and down weeping,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101820">And waymenting and keeping of a waymentation,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101830">As who should say, the mill would go with your waymenting. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e101840" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101850">How now Trotter? why complainest thou so. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e101860" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <p xml:id="A21328-e101870">Why yonder is a company of young men and maids keep such a stir for their grist, that they would have it before my stones be ready to grind it. But i'faith, I would I could break wind enough backward: you should not tarry for your grist I warrant you. <note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A21328-e101880">here he taketh Em about the neck.</note></p>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e101890" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101900">Content thee Trotter, I will go pacify them. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e101910" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101920">Iwis you will when I cannot. Why look,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101930">You have a mill. Why, what's your mill without me? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101940">Or rather mistress, what were I without you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e101950" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101960">Nay Trotter, if you fall a-chiding, I will give you o'er. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e101970" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101980">I chide you dame to amend you. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e101990">You are too fine to be a miller's daughter:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102000"><pb facs="6"/> for if you should but stoop to take up the toll dish</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102010">You will have the cramp in your finger</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102020">At least ten weeks after. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102030" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102040">Ah well said Trotter, teach her to play the good housewife</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102050">And thou shalt have her to thy wife, if thou canst get her good will. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102060" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102070">Ah words wherein I see matrimony come loaden</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102080">With kisses to salute me: now let me alone, to pick the mill,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102090">To fill the hopper to take the toll to mend the sails,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102100">Yea, and to make the mill to go with the very force of my love. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e102110">Here they must call for their grist within.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102120" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102130">I come I come, i'faith now you shall have your grist</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102140">Or else Trotter will trot and amble himself to death. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e102150">They call him again. Exit.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e102160">Enter King of Denmark, with some attendants, Blanche his daughter, Mariana, marquess Lubeck, William disguised.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102170" who="A21328-denmark">
              <speaker>King of Denmark.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102180">Lord marquess Lubeck welcome home,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102190">Welcome brave knight unto the Denmark King:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102200">For William's sake the noble Norman Duke,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102210">So famous for his fortunes and success,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102220">That graceth him with name of conqueror:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102230">Right double welcome must thou be to us. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102240" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Rob. Windsor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102250">And to my lord the King shall I recount</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102260">Your grace's courteous entertainment,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102270">That for his sake vouchsafe to honour me</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102280">A simple knight attendant on his grace. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102290" who="A21328-denmark">
              <speaker>King denmark</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102300">But say sir knight, what may I call your name. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102310" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Robert Windsor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102320">Robert Windsor and like your majesty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102330" who="A21328-denmark">
              <speaker>King denmark</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102340">I tell thee Robert, I so admire the man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102350">As that I count it heinous guilt in him</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102360">That honours not Duke William with his heart. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102370">Blanche, bid this stranger welcome, good my girl. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102380" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102390">Sir, should I neglect your highness' charge herein,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102400">It might be thought of base discourtesy. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102410">Welcome sir knight to Denmark heartily. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102420" who="A21328-william">
              <pb facs="6"/>
              <speaker>Ro. vvinds.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102430">Thanks gentle lady. Lord marquess, what is she? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102440" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102450">That same is Blanche daughter to the King,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102460">The substance of the shadow that you saw. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102470" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Rob. Windsor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102480">May this be she, for whom I crossed the seas? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102490">I am ashamed to think I was so fond. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102500">In whom there's nothing that contents my mind. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102510">Ill hued, worse featured, uncomely, nothing courtly. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102520">Swart and ill favoured, a collier's sanguine skin. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102530">I never saw a harder favoured slut. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102540">Love her? for what: I can no whit abide her. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102550" who="A21328-denmark">
              <speaker>King of Denmark.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102560">Mariana, I have this day received letters</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102570">From Swethia, that lets me understand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102580">Your ransom is collecting there with speed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102590">And shortly shall be hither sent to us. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102600" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102610">Not that I find occasion of mislike</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102620">My entertainment in your grace's court,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102630">But that I long to see my native home. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102640" who="A21328-denmark">
              <speaker>King denmark</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102650">And reason have you madam for the same:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102660">Lord marquess I commit unto your charge</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102670">The entertainment of sir Robert here,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102680">Let him remain with you within the court</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102690">In solace and disport, to spend the time. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e102700">Exit King of Denmark.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102710" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Robert windsor</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102720">I thank your highness, whose bounden I remain. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A21328-e102730">Blanche speaketh this secretly at one end of the stage.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102740">Unhappy Blanche, what strange effects are these</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102750">That works within my thoughts confusedly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102760">That still methinks affection draws me on</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102770">To take, to like, nay more, to love this knight. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102780" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Robert. Windsor</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102790">A modest countenance, no heavy sullen look,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102800">Not very fair, but richly decked with favour:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102810">A sweet face, an exceeding dainty hand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102820">A body were it framed of wax</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102830">By all the cunning artists of the world</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102840">It could not better be proportioned. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102850" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102860">How now sir Robert? in a study man? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102870"><pb facs="7"/>Here is no time for contemplation. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102880" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Robert Windsor.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102890">My lord, there is a certain odd conceit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102900">Which on the sudden greatly troubles me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102910" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102920">How like you Blanche? I partly do perceive</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102930">The little boy hath played the wag with you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102940" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Sir Robert.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102950">The more I look, the more I love to look. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102960">Who says that Mariana is not fair? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102970">I'll gauge my gauntlet 'gainst the envious man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e102980">That dares avow there liveth her compare. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e102990" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103000">Sir Robert, you mistake your counterfeit. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103010">This is the lady which you came to see. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103020" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Sir Robert.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103030">Yea, my lord: she is counterfeit in deed:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103040">For there is the substance that best contents me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103050" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubek.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103060">That is my love. Sir Robert you do wrong me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103070" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Robert.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103080">The better for you sir, she is your love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103090">As for the wrong, I see not how it grows. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103100" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103110">In seeking that which is another's right. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103120" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Robert.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103130">As who should say your love were privileged</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103140">That none might look upon her but yourself. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103150" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103160">These jars becomes not our familiarity,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103170">Nor will I stand on terms to move your patience. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103180" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Robert.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103190">Why my lord, am not I of flesh and blood as well as you? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103200">Then give me leave to love as well as you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103210" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103220">To love sir Robert? but whom? not she I love? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103230">Nor stands it with the honour of my state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103240">To brook corrivals with me in my love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103250" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Robert.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103260">So sir, we are thorough for that lady</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103270">Ladies farewell. Lord marquess, will you go? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103280">I will find a time to speak with her I trow? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103290" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103300">With all my heart. Come ladies will you walk? <stage xml:id="A21328-e103310">Exit.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e103320">Enter Manville alone disguised.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103330" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103340">Ah Em the subject of my restless thoughts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103350">The anvil whereupon my heart doth beat,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103360">Framing thy state to thy desert,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103370">Full ill this life becomes thy heavenly look,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103380">Wherein, sweet love and virtue sits enthroned. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103390"><pb facs="7"/>Bad world, where riches is esteemed above them both,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103400">In whose base eyes naught else is bountiful. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103410">A miller's daughter, says the multitude,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103420">Should not be loved of a gentleman. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103430">But let them breathe their souls into the air:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103440">Yet will I still affect thee as myself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103450">So thou be constant in thy plighted vow. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103460">But here comes one, I will listen to his talk. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e103470">Enter Valingford at another door,<note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A21328-e103480">Manville hiding himself .</note> disguised</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103490" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103500">Go William conqueror and seek thy love. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103510">Seek thou a minion in a foreign land</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103520">Whilst I draw back and court my love at home,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103530">The miller's daughter of fair Manchester</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103540">Hath bound my feet to this delightsome soil:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103550">And from her eyes do dart such golden beams,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103560">That holds my heart in her subjection. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103570" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103580">He ruminates on my beloved choice:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103590">God grant he come not to prevent my hope. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103600">But here's another, him I'll listen to. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e103610">Enter Mountney disguised at another door.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103620" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>L. Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103630">Nature unjust, in utterance of thy art,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103640">To grace a peasant with a prince's fame:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103650">Peasant am I so to misterm my love</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103660">Although a miller's daughter by her birth:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103670">Yet may her beauty and her virtues well suffice</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103680">To hide the blemish of her birth in hell,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103690">Where neither envious eyes nor thought can pierce,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103700">But endless darkness ever smother it. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103710">Go William conqueror and seek thy love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103720">Whilst I draw back and court mine own the while:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103730">Decking her body with such costly robes</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103740">As may become her beauty's worthiness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103750">That so thy labours may be laughed to scorn,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103760">And she thou seekest in foreign regions,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103770">Be darkened and eclipsed when she arrives,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103780">By one that I have chosen nearer home. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103790" who="A21328-manvile">
              <pb facs="8"/>
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103800">What comes he to, to intercept my love? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103810">Then hie thee Manville to forestall such foes. <stage xml:id="A21328-e103820">Exit Manville</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103830" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103840">What now lord Valingford are you behind? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103850">The King had chosen you to go with him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103860" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103870">So chose he you, therefore I marvel much</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103880">That both of us should linger in this sort. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103890">What may the King imagine of our stay? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103900" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103910">The King may justly think we are to blame:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103920">But I imagined I might well be spared</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103930">And that no other man had borne my mind. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103940" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103950">The like did I: in friendship then resolve</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103960">What is the cause of your unlooked for stay? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e103970" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103980">Lord Valingford I tell thee as a friend,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e103990">Love is the cause why I have stayed behind. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104000" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valinford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104010">Love my lord? of whom. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104020" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104030">Em the miller's daughter of Manchester. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104040" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104050">But may this be? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104060" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104070">Why not my lord? I hope full well you know</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104080">That love respects no difference of state</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104090">So beauty serve to stir affection. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104100" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104110">But this it is that makes me wonder most:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104120">That you and I should be of one conceit</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104130">In such a strange unlikely passion. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104140" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104150">But is that true? my lord: I hope you do but jest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104160" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104170">I would I did: then were my grief the less. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104180" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104190">Nay never grieve: for if the cause be such</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104200">To join our thoughts in such a sympathy:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104210">All envy set aside: let us agree</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104220">To yield to either's fortune in this choice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104230" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104240">Content say I, and whatsoe'er befall,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104250">Shake hands my lord and fortune thrive at all. <stage xml:id="A21328-e104260">Exeunt.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e104270">Enter Em and Trotter the miller's man with a kerchief on his head, and an Urinal in his hand.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104280" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104290">Trotter where have you been? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104300" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104310">Where have I been? why what signifies this. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104320" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104330">A kerchief, doth it not? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104340" who="A21328-trotter">
              <pb facs="8"/>
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104350">What call you this I pray? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104360" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104370">I say it is an urinal. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104380" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104390">Then this is mystically to give you to understand</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104400">I have been at the phismicary's house. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104410" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104420">How long hast thou been sick? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104430" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104440">I'faith, even as long as I have not been half well,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104450">And that hath been a long time. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104460" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104470">A loitering time I rather imagine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104480" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trot.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104490">It may be so: but the phismicary tells me that you can help me</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104500" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104510">Why, any thing I can do for recovery of thy health,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104520">Be right well assured of. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104530" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trot.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104540">Then give me your hand</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104550" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104560">To what end. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104570" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trot.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104580">That the ending of an old indenture</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104590">Is the beginning of a new bargain. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104600" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104610">What bargain? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104620" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trot.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104630">That you promised to do any thing to recover my health. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104640" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104650">On that condition I give thee my hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104660" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trot.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104670">Ah sweet Em. <stage xml:id="A21328-e104680">Here he offers to kiss her.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104690" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104700">How now Trotter? your master's daughter? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104710" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trot.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104720">I'faith I aim at the fairest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104730">Ah Em, sweet Em: fresh as the flower:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104740">That hath power to wound my heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104750">And ease my smart, of me poor thief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104760">In prison bound. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104770" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104780">So all your rhyme lies on the ground. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104790">But what means this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104800" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trot.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104810">Ah mark the device,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104820">For thee my love full sick I was, in hazard of my life</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104830">Thy promise was to make me whole, and for to be my wife. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104840">Let me enjoy my love my dear,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104850">And thou possess thy Trottter here. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104860" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104870">But I meant no such matter. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104880" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trot.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104890">Yes woos but you did, I'll go to our parson sir John</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104900">And he shall mumble up the marriage out of hand. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104910" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104920">But here comes one that will forbid the banes. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e104930"><pb facs="9"/>Here enters Manville to them. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104940" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104950">Ah sir you come too late. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104960" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104970">What remedy Trotter. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e104980" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e104990">Go Trotter, my father calls. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105000" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105010">Would you have me go in, and leave you two here? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105020" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105030">Why, darest thou not trust me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105040" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105050">Yes faith, even as long as I see you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105060" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105070">Go thy ways I pray thee heartily. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105080" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105090">That same word (Heartily) is of great force. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105100">I will go: but I pray sir, beware you</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105110">Come not too near the wench. <stage xml:id="A21328-e105120">Exit Trotter.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105130" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105140">I am greatly beholding to you</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105150">Ah mistresses, sometime I might have said my love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105160">But time and fortune hath bereaved me of that,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105170">And I am abject in those gracious eyes</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105180">That with remorse erst saw into my grief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105190">May sit and sigh the sorrows of my heart. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105200" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105210">In deed my Manville hath some cause to doubt,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105220">When such a swain is rival in his love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105230" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105240">Ah Em, were he the man that causeth this mistrust,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105250">I should esteem of thee as at the first. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105260" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105270">But is my love in earnest all this while? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105280" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105290">Believe me Em, it is not time to jest</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105300">When others joys, what lately I possessed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105310" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105320">If touching love, my Manville charge me thus? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105330">Unkindly must I take it at his hands,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105340">For that my conscience clears me of offence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105350" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105360">Ah impudent and shameless in thy ill,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105370">That with thy cunning and defraudful tongue,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105380">Seeks to delude the honest meaning mind:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105390">Was never heard in Manchester before,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105400">Of truer lpove then hath been betwixt us twain:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105410">And for my part how I have hazarded</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105420">Displeasure of my father and my friends</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105430">Thyself can witness. Yet notwithstanding this:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105440">Two gentlemen attending on Duke William</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105450">Mountney and Valingford, as I heard them named,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105460"><pb facs="9"/> oft times resort to see and to be seen,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105470">Walking the street fast by thy father's door,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105480">Whose glancing eyes up to the windows cast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105490">Gives testes of their master's amorous heart. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105500">This Em is noted and too much talked on. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105510">Some see it without mistrust of ill. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105520">Others there are that scorning grin thereat,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105530">And saith, there goes the miller's daughters wooers. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105540">Ah me, whom chiefly and most of all it doth concern</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105550">To spend my time in grief and vex my soul,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105560">To think my love should be rewarded thus,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105570">And for thy sake abhor all women kind. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105580" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105590">May not a maid look upon a man</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105600">Without suspicious judgement of the world? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105610" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105620">If sight do move offence, it is the better not to see. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105630">But thou didst more unconstant as thou art,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105640">For with them thou hadst talk and conference. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105650" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105660">May not a maid talk with a man without mistrust? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105670" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105680">Not with such men suspected amorous. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105690" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105700">I grieve to see my Manville jealousy</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105710" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105720">Ah Em, faithful love is full of jealousy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105730">So did I love thee true and faithfully,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105740">For which I am rewarded most unthankfully. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A21328-e105750">Exit in a rage, manet Em.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105760">And so away? what in displeasure gone? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105770">And left me such a bitter sweet to gnaw upon? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105780">Ah Manville, little wottest thou,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105790">How near this parting goeth to my heart. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105800">Uncourteous love whose followers reaps reward,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105810">Of hate, disdain, reproach and infamy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105820">The fruit of frantic, bedlam jealousy. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A21328-e105830">Here enter Mountney to Em.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105840">But here comes one of these suspicious men:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105850">Witness my god without desert of me:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105860">For only Manville honour I in heart:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105870">Nor shall unkindness cause me from him to start. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105880" who="A21328-mountney">
              <pb facs="10"/>
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105890">For this good fortune, Venus be thou blessed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105900">To meet my love, the mistress of my heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105910">Where time and place gives opportunity</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105920">At full to let her understand my love. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A21328-e105930">He turns to Em, and offers to take her by the hand, and she goes from him.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105940">Fair mistress, since my fortune sorts so well:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105950">Hear you a word. What meaneth this? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105960">Nay stay fair Em. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105970" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e105980">I am going homewards, sir:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e105990" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106000">Yet stay sweet love to whom I must disclose</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106010">The hidden secrets of a lover's thoughts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106020">Not doubting but to find such kind remorse</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106030">As naturally you are inclined to. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106040" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106050">The gentleman your friend sir. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106060">I have not seen him this four days at the least. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106070" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106080">What's that to me? I speak not sweet in person of my friend,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106090">But for myself, whom if that love deserve</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106100">To have regard being honourable love:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106110">Not base affects of loose lascivious love:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106120">Whom youthful wantons play and dally with:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106130">But that unites in honourable bands of holy rites,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106140">And knits the sacred knot that gods. <stage xml:id="A21328-e106150">Here Em cuts him off.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106160" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106170">What mean you sir, to keep me here so long? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106180">I cannot understand you by your signs. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106190">You keep a prattling with your lips,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106200">But never a word you speak that I can hear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106210" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106220">What is she deaf? A great impediment. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106230">Yet remedies there are for such defects. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106240">Sweet Em, it is no little grief to me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106250">To see where nature in her pride of art</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106260">Hath wrought perfections rich and admirable. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106270" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106280">Speak you to me sir? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106290" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106300">To thee my only joy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106310" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106320">I cannot hear you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106330" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106340">O plague of fortune: o hell without compare. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106350">What boots it us to gaze and not enjoy? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106360" who="A21328-em">
              <pb facs="10"/>
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106370">Fare you well sir. <stage xml:id="A21328-e106380">Exit Em. manet Mountney.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106390" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106400">Fare well my love. Nay farewell life and all. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106410">Could I procure redress for this infirmity,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106420">It might be means she would regard my suit. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106430">I am acquainted with the King's physicians:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106440">Amongst the which, there's one mine honest friend,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106450">Signior Alberto, a very learned man. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106460">His judgement will I have to help this ill. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106470">Ah Em, fair Em, if art can make thee whole:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106480">I'll buy that sense for thee, although it cost me dear. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106490">But Mountney: stay, this may be but deceit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106500">A matter feigned only to delude thee. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106510">And not unlike, perhaps by Valingford,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106520">He loves fair Em as well as I. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106530">As well as I? ah no, not half so well. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106540">Put case, yet may he be thine enemy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106550">And give her counsel to dissemble thus. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106560">I'll try the event, and if it fall out so? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106570">Friendship farewell: love makes me now a foe. <stage xml:id="A21328-e106580">Exit Mountney.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e106590">Enter marquess Lubeck, and Mariana.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106600" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106610">Trust me my lord, I am sorry for your hurt. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106620" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106630">Gramercy madam: but it is not great:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106640">Only a thrust, pricked with a rapier's point. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106650" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106660">How grew the quarrel my lord? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106670" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106680">Sweet lady, for thy sake. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106690">There was this last night two masks in one company,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106700">Myself the foremost: the other strangers were:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106710">Amongst the which, when the music began to sound the measures,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106720">Each masker made choice of his lady:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106730">And one more forward than the rest stepped towards thee:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106740">Which I perceiving thrust him aside, and took thee myself. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106750">But this was taken in so ill part,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106760">That at my coming out of the court gate, with justling together,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106770">It was my chance to be thrust into the arm. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106780">The doer thereof because he was the original cause of the disorder</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106790">At that inconvenient time, was presently committed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106800"><pb facs="11"/> and is this morning sent for to answer the matter:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106810"><note anchored="true" place="margin" xml:id="A21328-e106820">here enters sir Robert rr of Windsor for with a jailer</note> and I think here he comes. What sir Robert of Windsor how now? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106830" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Sir Robert.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106840">I'faith my lord a prisoner: but what ails your arm? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106850" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106860">Hurt the last night by mischance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106870" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Sir Robert.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106880">What, not in the mask at the court gate? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106890" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106900">Yes trust me there. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106910" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Sir Rob.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106920">Why then my lord I thank you for my night's lodging. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106930" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106940">And I you for my hurt, if it were so? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106950">Keeper away, I discharge you of your prisoner. <stage xml:id="A21328-e106960">Exit the keeper.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106970" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Sir Robert.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e106980">Lord marquess, you offered me disgrace to shoulder me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e106990" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107000">Sir I knew you not, and therefore you must pardon me</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107010">And the rather it might be alleged to me of</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107020">Mere simplicity, to see another dance with my mistress</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107030">Disguised, and I myself in presence: but seeing it</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107040">Was our haps to damnify each other unwillingly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107050">Let us be content with our harms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107060">And say the fault where it was and so become friends. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107070" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Sir Robert.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107080">I'faith I am content with my night's lodging</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107090">If you be content with your hurt. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107100" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107110">Not content that I have it, but content</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107120">To forget how I came by it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107130" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Sir Robert.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107140">My lord, here comes lady Blanche, let's away. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e107150">Enter Blanche.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107160" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107170">With good will, lady you will stay? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e107180">Exit Lubeck and sir Robert.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107190" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107200">Madam. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107210" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107220">Mariana, as I am grieved with thy presence:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107230">So am I not offended for thy absence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107240">And were it not a breach to modesty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107250">Thou shouldst know before I left thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107260" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107270">How near is this humour to madness</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107280">If you hold on as you begin, you</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107290">Are in a pretty way to scolding. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107300" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107310">To scolding housewife? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107320" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107330">Madam here comes one,</l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e107340">Here enters one with a letter.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107350" who="A21328-blanch">
              <pb facs="11"/>
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107360">There doth in deed. Fellow wouldst thou have any thing with anybody here? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107370" who="A21328-messenger">
              <speaker>Messenger.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107380">I have a letter to deliver to the lady Mariana. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107390" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107400">Give it me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107410" who="A21328-messenger">
              <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107420">There must none but she have it. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A21328-e107430">Blanche snatcheth the letter from him. Et exit messenger.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107440">Go to foolish fellow. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107450">And therefore to ease the anger I sustain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107460">I'll be so bold to open it, what's here? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107470">Sir Robert greets you well? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107480">Your mistresses, his love, his life? O amorous man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107490">How he entertains his new mistresses? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107500">And bestows on Lubeck his old friend</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107510">A horn night cap to keep in his wit. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107520" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107530">Madam though you have discourteously</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107540">Read my letter, yet I pray you give it me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107550" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107560">Then take it there, and there, and there. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e107570">She tears it. Et exit Blanche.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107580" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107590">How far doth this differ from modesty:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107600">Yet will I gather up the pieces, which happily</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107610">May show to me the intent thereof</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107620">Though not the meaning. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e107630">She gathers up the pieces and joins them.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107640" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107650">Your servant and love sir Robert of Windsor</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107660">Alias William the conqueror, wisheth long health and happiness. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107670">Is this William the conqueror, shrouded under</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107680">The name of sir Robert of Windsor? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107690">Were he the monarch of the world</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107700">He should not dispossess Lubeck of his love. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107710">Therefore I will to the court, and there if I can</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107720">Close to be friends with lady Blanche,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107730">And thereby keep Lubeck my love for myself:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107740">And further the lady Blanche in her suit as much as I may. <stage xml:id="A21328-e107750">Exit.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e107760">Enter Em solus.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107770" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107780">Jealousy that sharps the lover's sight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107790">And makes him conceive and construe his intent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107800"><pb facs="12"/> hath so bewitched my lovely Manville senses,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107810">That he misdoubts his Em that loves his soul. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107820">He doth suspect corrivals in his love:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107830">Which how untrue it is, be judge my God. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107840">But now no more: here cometh Valingford:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107850">Shift him off now as thou hast done the other. <stage xml:id="A21328-e107860">Enter Valingford.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107870" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingf</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107880">See how fortune presents me with the hope I looked for. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107890">Fair Em? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107900" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107910">Who is that? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107920" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingf.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107930">I am Valingford thy love and friend. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107940" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107950">I cry you mercy sir: I thought so by your speech. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107960" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingf.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107970">What aileth thy eyes? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e107980" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e107990">O blind sir, blind, stricken blind by mishap on a sudden. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108000" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingf.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108010">But is it possible you should be taken on such a sudden? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108020">Infortunate Valingford to be thus crossed in thy love. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108030">Fair Em, I am not a little sorry to see this thy hard hap:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108040">Yet nevertheless, I am acquainted with a learned physician,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108050">That will do any thing for thee at my request. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108060">To him will I resort, and inquire his judgement,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108070">As concerning the recovery of so excellent a sense. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108080" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108090">Oh lord sir: and of all things I cannot abide physic:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108100">The very name thereof to me is odious. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108110" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108120">No? not the thing will do thee so much good? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108130">Sweet Em, hither I came to parley of love</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108140">Hoping to have found thee in thy wonted prosperity. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108150">And have the gods so unmercifully thwarted my expectation? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108160">By dealing so sinisterly with thee sweet Em? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108170" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108180">Good sir, no more, it fits not me</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108190">To have respect to such vain fantasies,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108200">As idle love presents my ears withal,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108210">More reason I should ghostly give myself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108220">To sacred prayers for this my former sin,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108230">For which this plague is justly fallen upon me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108240">Than to hearken to the vanities of love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108250" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108260">Yet sweet Em accept this jewel at my hand</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108270">Which I bestow on thee in token of my love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108280" who="A21328-em">
              <pb facs="12"/>
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108290">A jewel sir, what pleasure can I have</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108300">In jewels, treasure, or any worldly thing</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108310">That want my sight that should deserve thereof. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108320">Ah sir I must leave you:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108330">The pain of mine eyes is so extreme</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108340">I cannot long stay in a place. I take my leave. <stage xml:id="A21328-e108350">Exit Em.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108360" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108370">Zounds, what a cross is this to my conceit? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108380">But Valingford, search the depth of this device. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108390">Why may not this be feigned subtlety,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108400">By Mountney's invention, to the intent</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108410">That I seeing such occasion should leave off my suit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108420">And not any more persist to solicit her of love. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108430">I'll try the event, if I can by any means perceive</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108440">The effect of this deceit to be procured by his means,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108450">Friend Mountney the one of us is like to repent our bargain. <stage xml:id="A21328-e108460">Exit.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e108470">Enter Mariana and marquess Lubeck.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108480" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108490">Lady, since that occasion forward in our good</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108500">Presenteth place and opportunity:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108510">Let me entreat your wonted kind consent</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108520">And friendly furtherance in a suit I have. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108530" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108540">My lord you know you need not to entreat,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108550">But may command Mariana to her power</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108560">Be it no impeachment to my honest fame. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108570" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108580">Free are my thoughts from such base villainy</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108590">As may in question lady call your name:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108600">Yet is the matter of such consequence</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108610">Standing upon my honourable credit,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108620">To be effected with such zeal and secrecy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108630">As should I speak and fail my expectation</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108640">I would redound greatly to my prejudice. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108650" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108660">My lord wherein hath Mariana given you occasion</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108670">That you should mistrust or else be jealous of my secrecy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108680" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108690">Mariana, do not misconstrue of me:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108700">I not mistrust thee, nor thy secrecy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108710">Nor let my love misconstrue my intent,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108720">Nor think thereof but well and honourable. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108730"><pb facs="13"/>Thus stands the case: thou knowest from England</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108740">Hither came with me Robert of Windsor, a noble man at arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108750">Lusty and valiant, in spring time of his years,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108760">No marvel then though he prove amorous. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108770" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108780">True my lord, he came to see fair Blanche. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108790" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108800">No Mariana, that is not it. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108810">His love to Blanche was then extinct</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108820">When first he saw thy face. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108830">'Tis thee he loves: yea, thou art only she</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108840">That is mistresses and commander of his thoughts. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108850" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108860">Well well my lord, I like you, for such drifts</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108870">Put silly ladies often to their shifts</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108880">Oft have I heard you say, you loved me well:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108890">Yea, sworn the same, and I believed you to. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108900">Can this be found an action of good faith,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108910">Thus to dissemble where you found true love? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e108920" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108930">Mariana, I not dissemble on mine honour:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108940">Nor fails my faith to thee. But for my friend,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108950">For princely William, by whom thou shalt possess</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108960">The title of estate and majesty,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108970">Fitting thy love and virtues of thy mind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108980">For him I speak, for him do I entreat,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e108990">And with thy favour fully do resign</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109000">To him the claim and interest of my love. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109010">Sweet Mariana then deny me not. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109020">Love William, love my friend and honour me</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109030">Who else is clean dishonoured by thy means. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109040" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109050">Borne to mishap, myself am only she,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109060">On whom the sun of fortune never shined:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109070">But planets ruled by retrograde aspect,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109080">Foretold mine ill in my nativity. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109090" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109100">Sweet lady cease, let my entreaty serve</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109110">To pacify the passion of thy grief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109120">Which well I know proceeds of ardent love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109130" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109140">But Lubeck now regards not Mariana:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109150" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109160">Even as my life, so love I Mariana. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109170" who="A21328-mariana">
              <pb facs="13"/>
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109180">Why do you post me to another then? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109190" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109200">He is my friend, and I do love the man. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109210" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109220">Then will Duke William rob me of my love? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109230" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109240">No as his life Mariana he doth love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109250" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109260">Speak for yourself my lord let him alone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109270" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109280">So do I madam, for he and I am one. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109290" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109300">Then loving you I do content you both. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109310" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109320">In loving him you shall content us both. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109330">Me, for I crave that favour at your hands:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109340">He for hopes that comfort at your hands. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109350" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109360">Leave of my lord, here comes the lady Blanche. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e109370">Enter Blanche to them.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109380" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109390">Hard hap to break us of our talk so soon,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109400">Sweet Mariana do remember me. <stage xml:id="A21328-e109410">Exit Lubeck,</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109420" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109430">Thy Mariana cannot choose but remember thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109440" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109450">Mariana well met, you are very forward in your love? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109460" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109470">Madam be it in secret spoken to yourself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109480">If you will but follow the complot I have invented</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109490">You will not think me so forward</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109500">As yourself shall prove fortunate. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109510" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109520">As how? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109530" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109540">Madam as thus: it is not unknown to you</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109550">That sir Robert of Windsor,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109560">A man that you do not little esteem,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109570">Hath long importuned me of love:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109580">But rather than I will be found false</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109590">Or unjust to the marquess Lubeck,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109600">I will as did the constant lady Penelope</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109610">Undertake to effect some great task. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109620" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109630">What of all this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109640" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109650">The next time that sir Robert shall come</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109660">In his wonted sort to solicit me with love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109670">I will seem to agree and like of any thing</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109680">That the knight shall demand so far forth</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109690">As it be no impeachment to my chastity:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109700">And to conclude, point some place for to meet the man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109710"><pb facs="14"/> for my conveyance from the Denmark court:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109720">Which determined upon, he will appoint some certain time</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109730">For our departure: whereof you having intelligence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109740">You may soon set down a plot to were the English crown. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109750">And then? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109760" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109770">What then? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109780" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109790">If sir Robert prove a King and you his Queen</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109800">How then? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109810" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109820">Were I assured of the one, as I am persuaded</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109830">Of the other, there were some possibility in it. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109840">But here comes the man. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109850" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109860">Madam be gone and you shall see</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109870">I will work to your desire and my content. <stage xml:id="A21328-e109880">Exit Blanche.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e109890" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109900">Con. Lady this is well and happily met,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109910">Fortune hitherto hath been my foe,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109920">And though I have oft sought to speak with you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109930">Yet still I have been crossed with sinister haps. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109940">I cannot madam tell a loving tale</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109950">Or court my mistresses with fabulous discourses,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109960">That am a soldier sworn to follow arms:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109970">But this I bluntly let you understand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109980">I honour you with such religious zeal</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e109990">As may become an honourable mind. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110000">Nor may I make my love the siege of Troy</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110010">That am a stranger in this country. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110020">First what I am, I know you are resolved,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110030">For that my friend hath let you that to understand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110040">The marquess Lubeck to whom I am so bound,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110050">That whilst I live I count me only his. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110060" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110070">Surely you are beholding to the marquess,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110080">For he hath been an earnest spokesman in your cause. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110090" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110100">And yields my lady then at his request. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110110">To grace Duke William with her gracious love? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110120" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110130">My lord I am a prisoner, and hard it were</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110140">To get me from the court. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110150" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110160">An easy matter to get you from the court,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110170"><pb facs="14"/> if case that you will thereto give consent. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110180" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110190">Put case I should, how would you use me then? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110200" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110210">Not otherwise but well and honourably. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110220">I have at sea a ship that doth attend,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110230">Which shall forthwith conduct us into England</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110240">Where when we are, I straight will marry thee. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110250">We may not stay deliberating long</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110260">Lest that suspicion, envious of our weal</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110270">Set in a foot to hinder our pretence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110280" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110290">But this I think were most convenient</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110300">To mask my face the better to scape unknown. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110310" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110320">A good device: till then, farewell fair love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110330" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110340">But this I must entreat your grace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110350">You would not seek by lust unlawfully</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110360">To wrong my chaste determinations. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110370" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110380">I hold that man most shameless in his sin</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110390">That seeks to wrong an honest lady's name</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110400">Whom he thinks worthy of his marriage bed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110410" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110420">In hope your oath is true,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110430">I leave your grace till the appointed time. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e110440">Exit Mariana.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110450" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110460">Oh happy William, blessed in thy love:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110470">Most fortunate in Mariana's love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110480">Well Lubeck well, this courtesy of thine</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110490">I will requite if God permit me life. <stage xml:id="A21328-e110500">Exit.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e110510">Enter Valingford and Mountney at two sundry doors, looking angrily each on other with rapiers drawn.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110520" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110530">Valingford, so hardly I digest an injury</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110540">Thou hast proffered me, as were not that I detest to do what stands</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110550">Not with the honour of my name,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110560">Thy death should pay thy ransom of thy fault. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110570" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110580">And Mountney, had not my revenging wrath</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110590">Incensed with more than ordinary love</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110600">Been such for to deprive thee of thy life,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110610">Thou hadst not lived to brave me as thou dost wretch as thou art,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110620">Wherein hath Valingford offended thee? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110630"><pb facs="15"/>That honourable bond which late we did confirm</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110640">In presence of the gods,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110650">When with the conqueror we arrived here</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110660">For my part hath been kept inviolably</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110670">Till now too much abused by thy villainy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110680">I am enforced to cancel all those bands,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110690">By hating him which I so well did love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110700" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110710">Subtle thou art, and cunning in thy fraud,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110720">That giving me occasion of offence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110730">Thou pickest a quarrel to excuse thy shame. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110740">Why Valingford, was it not enough for thee</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110750">To be a rival twixt me and my love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110760">But counsel her to my no small disgrace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110770">That when I came to talk with her of love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110780">She should seem deaf, as feigning not to hear. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110790" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110800">But hath she Mountney used thee as thou sayest? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110810" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110820">Thou knowest too well she hath:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110830">Wherein thou couldst not do me greater injury. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110840" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110850">Then I perceive we are deluded both. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110860">For when I offered many gifts of gold and jewels</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110870">To entreat for love, she hath refused them with a coy disdain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110880">Alleging that she could not see the sun. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110890">The same conjectured I to be thy drift,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110900">That feigning so she might be rid of me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110910" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110920">The like did I by thee. But are not these natural impediments? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110930" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Validgford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110940">In my conjecture merely counterfeit:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110950">Therefore let's join hands in friendship once again,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110960">Since that the jar grew only by conjecture. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110970" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e110980">With all my heart: yet let's try the truth hereof. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e110990" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingf.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111000">With right good will. We will straight unto her father,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111010">And there to learn whither it be so or no. <stage xml:id="A21328-e111020">Exeunt.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e111030">Enter William and Blanche disguised, with a mask over her face.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111040" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111050">Come on my love, the comfort of my life:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111060">Disguised thus we may remain unknown. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111070"><pb facs="15"/>And get we once to seas, I force not then,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111080">We quickly shall attain the English shore. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111090" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111100">But this I urge you with your former oath. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111110">You shall not seek to violate mine honour,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111120">Until our marriage rights be all performed. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111130" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111140">Mariana, here I swear to thee by heaven,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111150">And by the honour that I bear to arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111160">Never to seek or crave at hands of thee</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111170">The spoil of honourable chastity</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111180">Until we do attain the English coast,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111190">Where thou shalt be my right espoused Queen. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111200" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111210">In hope your oath proceedeth from your heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111220">Let's leave the court, and betake us to his power</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111230">That governs all things to his mighty will,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111240">And will reward the just with endless joy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111250">And plague the bad with most extreme annoy. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111260" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111270">Lady, as little tarriance as we may,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111280">Lest some misfortune happen by the way. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e111290">Exit Blanche and William.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e111300">Enter the miller, his man Trotter, and Manville.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111310" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111320">I tell you sir, it is no little grief to me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111330">You should so hardly conceit of my daughter,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111340">Whose honest report, though I say it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111350">Was never blotted with any title of defamation. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111360" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111370">Father miller, the repair of those gentlemen to your house,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111380">Hath given me great occasion to mislike. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111390" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111400">As for those gentlemen, I never saw in them</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111410">Any evil entreaty. But should they have proffered it? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111420">Her chaste mind hath proof enough to prevent it. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111430" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111440">Those gentlemen are as honest as ever I saw:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111450">For i'faith one of them gave me six pence</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111460">To fetch a quart of seck. See master here they come. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e111470">Enter Mountney and Valingford.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111480" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111490">Trotter, call Em, now they are here together,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111500">I'll have this matter thoroughly debated. <stage xml:id="A21328-e111510">Exit Trotter.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111520" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111530">Father, well met. We are come to confer with you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111540" who="A21328-manvile">
              <pb facs="16"/>
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111550">Nay? with his daughter rather. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111560" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111570">Thus it is father, we are come to crave your friendship in a matter. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111580" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111590">Gentlemen as you are strangers to me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111600">Yet by the way of courtesy you shall demand</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111610">Any reasonable thing at my hands. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111620" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111630">What is the matter so forward? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111640">They came to crave his good will. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111650" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valinford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111660">It is given us to understand that your daughter</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111670">Is suddenly become both blind and deaf. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111680" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111690">Mary God for bid, I have sent for her, in deed</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111700">She hath kept her chamber this three days. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111710">It were no little grief to me if it should be so? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111720" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111730">This is God's judgement for her treachery. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e111740">Enter Trotter leading Em.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111750" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111760">Gentlemen I fear your words are too true:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111770">See where Trotter comes leading of her. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111780">What ails my Em, not blind I hope? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111790" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111800">Mountney and Valingford both together? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111810">And Manville to whom I have faithfully vowed my love? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111820">Now Em suddenly help thy self. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111830" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111840">This is no dissembling Valingford. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111850" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111860">If it be? it is cunningly contrived of all sides. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111870" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111880">Trotter lend me thy hand,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111890">And as thou lovest me keep my counsel</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111900">And justify whatsoever I say, and I'll largely requite thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111910" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111920">Ah, that's as much as to say you would tell a monstrous,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111930">Terrible, horrible, outrageous lie,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111940">And I shall soothe it, no byr lady. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111950" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111960">My present extremity wills me, if thou love me Trotter? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111970" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e111980">That same word love makes me to do any thing. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e111990" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112000">Trotter where's my father? </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e112010">He thrusts Em upon her father.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112020" who="A21328-trotter">
              <speaker>Trotter.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112030">Why what a blind dunce are you, can you not see? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112040">He standeth right before you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112050" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112060">Is this my father? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112070">Good father give me leave to sit</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112080"><pb facs="16"/> where I may not be disturbed</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112090">Sith God hath visited me both of my sight and hearing. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112100" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112110">Tell me sweet Em how came this blindness. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112120">Thy eyes are lovely to look on,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112130">And yet have they lost the benefit of their sight. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112140">What a grief is this to thy poor father? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112150" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112160">Good father let me not stand as an open gazing stock to every one,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112170">But in a place a lone as fits a creature so miserable. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112180" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112190">Trotter lead her in, the utter overthrow</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112200">Of poor Goddard's joy and only solace. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e112210">Exit the miller, Trotter and Em.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112220" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112230">Both blind and deaf, then is she no wife for me? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112240">And glad am I so good occasion is happened:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112250">Now will I away to Manchester</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112260">And leave these gentlemen to their blind fortune. <stage xml:id="A21328-e112270">Exit Manville</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112280" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112290">Since fortune hath thus spitefully crossed our hope,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112300">Let us leave this guest and hearken after our King:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112310">Who is at this day landed at Lirpoole. <stage xml:id="A21328-e112320">Exit Mountney.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112330" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112340">Go my lord I'll follow you. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112350">Well, now Mountney is gone</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112360">I'll stay behind to solicit my love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112370">For I imagine that I shall find this but a feigned invention</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112380">Thereby to have us leave off our suits. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e112390">Enter marquess Lubeck and the King of Denmark angrily with some attendants.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112400" who="A21328-ver_life">
              <speaker>Zweno. K.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112410">Well Lubeck well, it is not possible</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112420">But you must be consenting to this act? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112430">Is this the man so highly you extolled? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112440">And play a part so hateful with his friend? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112450">Since first he came with thee into the court</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112460">What entertainment and what countenance</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112470">He hath received, none better knows than thou. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112480">In recompense whereof he quites me well,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112490">To steal away fair Mariana my prisoner,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112500">Whose ransom being lately 'greed upon,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112510">I am deluded of by this escape. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112520"><pb facs="17"/>Besides, I know not how to answer it</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112530">When she shall be demanded home to Swethia. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112540" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112550">My gracious lord, conjecture not I pray</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112560">Worse of Lubeck than he doth deserve. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112570">Your highness knows Mariana was my love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112580">Sole paragon and mistress of my thoughts. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112590">Is it likely I should know of her departure,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112600">Wherein there is no man injured more than I. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112610" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112620">That carries reason marquess I confess. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112630">Call forth my daughter. Yet I am persuaded</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112640">That she poor soul suspected not her going:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112650">For as I hear: she likewise loved the man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112660">Which he to blame did not at all regard. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112670" who="A21328-rocilio">
              <speaker>Rosilio.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112680">My lord here is the Princess Mariana:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112690">It is your daughter is conveyed away. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112700" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112710">What, my daughter gone? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112720">Now marquess your villainy breaks forth. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112730">This match is of your making, gentle sir:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112740">And you shall dear know the price thereof. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112750" who="A21328-lubeck">
              <speaker>Lubeck.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112760">Knew I thereof, or that there was intent</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112770">In Robert thus to steal your highness' daughter:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112780">Let heavens in justice presently confound me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112790" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112800">Not all the protestations thou canst use,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112810">Shall save thy life. Away with him to prison. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112820">And minion, otherwise it cannot be,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112830">But you are an agent in this treachery. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112840">I will revenge it thoroughly on you both. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112850">Away with her to prison. Here's stuff in deed? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112860">My daughter stolen away? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112870">It booteth not thus to disturb myself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112880">But presently to send to English William,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112890">To send me that proud knight of Windsor hither,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112900">Here in my court to suffer for his shame:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112910">Or at my pleasure to be punished there. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112920">Withal, that Blanche be sent me home again,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112930">Or I shall fetch her unto Windsor's cost,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112940"><pb facs="17"/> yea, and William's too if he deny her me?. <stage xml:id="A21328-e112950">Exit Zweno.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e112960">Enter William taken with soldiers.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e112970" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112980">Could any cross, could any plague be worse? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e112990">Could heaven or hell? Did both conspire in one</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113000">To afflict my soul, invent a greater scourge</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113010">Then presently I am tormented with? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113020">Ah Mariana cause of my lament:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113030">Joy of my heart, and comfort of my life. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113040">For thee I breathe my sorrows in the air,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113050">And tire myself: for silently I sigh,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113060">My sorrows afflicts me soul with equal passion. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113070" who="A21328-soldier">
              <speaker>Soldier.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113080">Go to sirrah, put up, it is to small purpose. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113090" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113100">Hence villains hence, dare you lay your hands</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113110">Upon your sovereign? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113120" who="A21328-soldier">
              <speaker>Soldier.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113130">Well sir, we will deal for that. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113140">But here comes one will remedy all this. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e113150">Enter Demarch.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113160" who="A21328-soldier">
              <speaker>Soldier.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113170">My lord, watching this night in the camp,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113180">We took this man, and know not what he is:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113190">And in his company was a gallant dame,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113200">A woman fair in outward show she seemed,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113210">But that her face was masked we could not see</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113220">The grace and favour of her countenance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113230" who="A21328-demarch">
              <speaker>Demarch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113240">Tell me good fellow of whence and what thou art. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113250" who="A21328-soldier">
              <speaker>Soldier.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113260">Why do you not answer my lord? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113270">He takes scorn to answer. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113280" who="A21328-demarch">
              <speaker>Demarch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113290">And takest thou scorn to answer my demand? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113300">Thy proud behaviour very well deserves</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113310">This misdemeanour at the worst be construed. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113320">Why dost thou neither know, nor hast thou heard? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113330">That in the absence of the Saxon Duke,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113340">Demarch is his especial substitute</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113350">To punish those that shall offend the laws. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113360" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113370">In knowing this, I know thou art a traitor. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113380">A rebel, and mutinous conspirator. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113390">Why Demarch, knowest thou who I am? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113400" who="A21328-demarch">
              <pb facs="18"/>
              <speaker>Demarch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113410">Pardon my dread lord the error of my sense,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113420">And misdemeanour to your princely excellency. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113430" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Willi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113440">Why Demarch, what is the cause my subjects are in arms? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113450" who="A21328-demarch">
              <speaker>Demarch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113460">Free are my thoughts my dread and gracious lord</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113470">From treason to your state and common weal,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113480">Only revengement of a private grudge</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113490">By lord Dirot lately proffered me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113500">That stands not with the honour of my name,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113510">Is cause I have assembled for my guard</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113520">Some men in arms that may withstand his force,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113530">Whose settled malice aimeth at my life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113540" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113550">Where is lord Dirot? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113560" who="A21328-demarch">
              <speaker>Demarch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113570">In arms my gracious lord</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113580">Not passed two miles from hence,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113590">As credibly I am ascertained. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113600" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113610">Well, come let us go,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113620">I fear I shall find traitors of you both. <stage xml:id="A21328-e113630">Exit.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e113640">Enter the citizen of Manchester and his daughter Elner and Manville.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113650" who="A21328-citizen">
              <speaker>Citizen.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113660">In deed sir it would do very well</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113670">If you could entreat your father to come hither:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113680">But if you think it be too far,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113690">I care not much to take horse and ride to Manchester,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113700">I am sure my daughter is content with either:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113710">How sayest thou Elner art thou not? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113720" who="A21328-elner">
              <speaker>Elner.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113730">As you shall think best I must be contented. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113740" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113750">Well Elner farewell, only thus much,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113760">I pray make all things in a readiness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113770">Either to serve here or to carry thither with us. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113780" who="A21328-citizen">
              <speaker>Citizen.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113790">As for that sir take you no care,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113800">And so I betake you to your journey. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A21328-e113810">Enter Valingford.</stage>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113820">But soft what gentleman is this? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113830" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingf.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113840">God speed sir, might a man crave a word or two with you</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113850" who="A21328-citizen">
              <speaker>Citizen</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113860">God forbid else sir, I pray you speak your pleasure. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113870" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113880">The gentleman that parted from you, was he not</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113890"><pb facs="18"/> of Manchester, his father lyuing there of good account. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113900" who="A21328-citizen">
              <speaker>Citizen.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113910">Yes marry is he sir: why do you ask? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113920">Belike you have had some acquaintance with him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e113930" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113940">I have been acquainted in times past,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113950">But through his double dealing,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113960">I am grown weary of his company. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113970">For be it spoken to you:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113980">He hath been acquainted with a poor miller's daughter,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e113990">And divers times hath promised her marriage. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114000">But what with his delays and flouts,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114010">He hath brought her into such a taking,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114020">That I fear me it will cost her her life. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114030" who="A21328-citizen">
              <speaker>Citizen.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114040">To be plain with you sir:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114050">His father and I have been of old acquaintance,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114060">And a motion was made,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114070">Between my daughter and his son,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114080">Which is now thoroughly agreed upon</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114090">Save only the place appointed for the marriage,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114100">Whether it shall be kept here or at Manchester,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114110">And for no other occasion he is now ridden. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114120" who="A21328-elner">
              <speaker>Elner.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114130">What hath he done to you? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114140">That you should speak so ill of the man. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114150" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114160">O gentlewoman I cry you mercy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114170">He is your husband that shall be. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114180" who="A21328-elner">
              <speaker>Elner.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114190">If I knew this to be true? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114200">He should not be my husband were he never so good:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114210">And therefore, good father,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114220">I would desire you to take the pains</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114230">To bear this gentleman company to Manchester</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114240">To know whether this be true or no. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114250" who="A21328-citizen">
              <speaker>Citizen.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114260">Now trust me gentleman he deals with me very hardly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114270">Knowing how well I meant to him. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114280">But I care not much to ride to Manchester</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114290">To know whether his father's will be,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114300">He should deal with me so badly. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114310">Will it please you sir to go in, we will presently take horse and away. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114320" who="A21328-valingford">
              <pb facs="19"/>
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114330">If it please you to go in</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114340">I'll follow you presently. <stage xml:id="A21328-e114350">Exit Elner and her father.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114360">Now shall I be revenged on Manville,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114370">And by this means get Em to my wife. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114380">And therefore I will straight to her father's</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114390">And inform them both of all that is happened. <stage xml:id="A21328-e114400">Exit.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e114410">Enter William, the ambassador of Denmark, Demarch, and other attendants.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114420" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114430">What news with the Denmark ambassador? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114440" who="A21328-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114450">Marry thus, the King of Denmark and my sovereign</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114460">Doth send to know of thee what is the cause</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114470">That injuriously against the law of arms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114480">Thou hast stolen away his only daughter Blanche,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114490">The only stay and comfort of his life. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114500">Therefore by me he willeth thee to send his daughter Blanche:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114510">Or else forthwith he will levy such an host,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114520">As soon shall fetch her in despite of thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114530" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114540">Ambassador, this answer I return thy King. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114550">He willeth me to send his daughter Blanche:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114560">Saying I conveyed her from the Danish court,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114570">That never yet did once as think thereof. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114580">As for his menacing and daunting threats</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114590">I nill regard him nor his Danish power. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114600">For if he come to fetch her forth my realm,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114610">I will provide him such a banquet here</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114620">That he shall have small cause to give me thanks. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114630" who="A21328-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114640">Is this your answer then? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114650" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114660">It is and so begone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114670" who="A21328-ambassador">
              <speaker>Ambassador.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114680">I go but to your cost. <stage xml:id="A21328-e114690">Exit ambassador.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114700" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114710">Demarch our subjects erst levied in civil broils,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114720">Mustered forthwith for to defend the realm,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114730">In hope whereof that we shall find you true,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114740">We freely pardon this thy late offence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114750" who="A21328-demarch">
              <speaker>Demarch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114760">Most humble thanks I render to your grace. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e114770">Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e114780"><pb facs="19"/>Enter the miller and Valingford. </stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114790" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114800">Alas gentleman, why should you trouble yourself so much</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114810">Considering the imperfections of my daughter</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114820">Which is able to withdraw the love of any man from her,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114830">As already it hath done in her first choice. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114840">Master Manville hath forsaken her,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114850">And at Chester shall be married to a man's daughter of no little wealth. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114860">But if my daughter knew so much:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114870">It would go very near her heart I fear me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114880" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valing</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114890">Father miller: such is the entire affection to your daughter,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114900">As no misfortune whatsoever can alter. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114910">My fellow Mountney thou seest gave quickly over,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114920">But I by reason of my good meaning</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114930">Am not so soon to be changed</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114940">Although I am borne off with scorns and denial. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e114950">Enter Em to them.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e114960" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114970">Trust me sir I know not what to say,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114980">My daughter is not to be compelled by me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e114990">But here she comes herself: speak to her and spare not:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115000">For I never was troubled with love matters so much before. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115010" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115020">Good lord shall I never be rid of this importunate man? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115030">Now must I dissemble blindness again,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115040">Once more for thy sake Manville thus am I enforced,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115050">Because I shall complete my full resolved mind to thee. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115060">Father where are you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115070" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115080">Here sweet Em, answer this gentleman</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115090">That would so fain enjoy thy love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115100" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115110">Where are you sir? will you never leave</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115120">This idle and vain pursuit of love? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115130">Is not England stored enough to content you? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115140">But you must still trouble the poor</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115150">Contemptible maid of Manchester. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115160" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valing.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115170">None can content me but the fair maid of Manchester. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115180" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115190">I perceive love is vainly described,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115200">That being blind himself,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115210"><pb facs="20"/> would have you likewise troubled with a blind wife,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115220">Having the benefit of your eyes,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115230">But neither follow him so much in folly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115240">But love one, in whom you may better delight. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115250" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115260">Father miller, thy daughter shall have honour</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115270">By granting me her love:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115280">I am a gentleman of King William's court,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115290">And no mean man in King William's favour. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115300" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115310">If you be a lord sir, as you say:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115320">You offer both yourself and me great wrong:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115330">Yours, as apparent in limiting your love so unorderly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115340">For which you rashly endure reproachment:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115350">Mine, as open and evident,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115360">When being shut from the vanities of this world,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115370">You would have me as an open gazing stock to all the world:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115380">For lust, not love leads you into this error:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115390">But from the one I will keep me as well as I can,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115400">And yield the other to none but to my father,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115410">As I am bound by duty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115420" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115430">Why fair Em, Manville hath forsaken thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115440">And must at Chester be married, which,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115450">If I speak otherwise than true,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115460">Let thy father speak what credibly he hath heard. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115470" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115480">But can it be Manville will deal so unkindly,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115490">To reward my justice with such monstrous ungentleness. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115500">Have I dissembled for thy sake? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115510">And dost thou now thus requite it? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115520">In deed these many days I have not seen him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115530">Which hath made me marvel at his long absence. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115540">But father, are you assured of the words he spoke,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115550">Were concerning Manville? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115560" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115570">In sooth daughter, now it is forth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115580">I must needs confirm it. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115590">Master Manville hath forsaken thee,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115600">And at Chester must be married</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115610">To a man's daughter of no little wealth. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115620"><pb facs="20"/>His own father procures it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115630">And therefore I dare credit it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115640">And do thou believe it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115650">For trust me daughter it is so. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115660" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115670">Then good father pardon the injury,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115680">That I have done to you only causing your grief,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115690">By overfond affecting a man so trothless. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115700">And you likewise sir, I pray hold me excused,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115710">As I hope this cause will allow sufficiently for me:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115720">My love to Manville, thinking he would requite it,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115730">Hath made me double with my father and you,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115740">And many more besides,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115750">Which I will no longer hide from you. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115760">That enticing speeches should not beguile me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115770">I have made myself deaf to any but to him. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115780">And lest any man's person should please me more than his,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115790">I have dissembled the want of my sight:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115800">Both which shadows of my irrevocable affections,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115810">I have not spared to confirm before him,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115820">My father, and all other amorous solicitors. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115830">Wherewith not made acquainted, I perceive</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115840">My true intent hath wrought mine own sorrow. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115850">And seeking by love to be regarded,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115860">Am cut of with contempt, and despised. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115870" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115880">Tell me sweet Em hast thou but feigned all this while for his love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115890">That hath so discourteously forsaken thee. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e115900" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115910">Credit me father I have told you the troth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115920">Wherewith I desire you and lord Valingford not to be displeased</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115930">For ought else I shall say,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115940">Let my present grief hold me excused. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115950">But may I live to see that ungrateful man</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115960">Justly rewarded for his treachery? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115970">Poor Em would think herself not a little happy,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115980">Favour my departing at this instant,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e115990">For my troubled thought desires to meditate alone in silence</l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e116000">Exit Em.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116010" who="A21328-valingford">
              <pb facs="21"/>
              <speaker>Valingf</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116020">Will not Em show one cheerful look on Valingford? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116030" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116040">Alas sir, blame her not, you see she hath good cause,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116050">Being so handled by this gentleman:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116060">And so I'll leave you, and go comfort my poor wench</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116070">As well as I may. <stage xml:id="A21328-e116080">Exit the miller.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116090" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116100">Farewell good father. <stage xml:id="A21328-e116110">Exit Valingford.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e116120">Enter Zweno King of Denmark with Rosilio, and other attendants.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116130" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116140">Rosilio, is this the place whereas the Duke William should meet me? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116150" who="A21328-rocilio">
              <speaker>Rosilio.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116160">It is, and like your grace. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116170" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116180">Go captain away, regard the charge I gave:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116190">See all our men be marshalled for the fight. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116200">Dispose the wards as lately was devised. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116210">And let the prisoners under several guards</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116220">Be kept apart until you hear from us.</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116230">Let this suffice, you know my resolution. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116240">If William Duke of Saxon be the man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116250">That by his answer sent us, he would send</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116260">Not words but wounds: not parleys but alarms,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116270">Must be decider of this controversy. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116280">Rosilio, stay with me, the rest begone. <stage xml:id="A21328-e116290">Exeunt.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e116300">Enter William, and Demarch with other attendants</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116310" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116320">All but Demarch go shroud you out of sight,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116330">For I will go parley with the prince myself. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116340" who="A21328-demarch">
              <speaker>Demarch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116350">Should Zweno by this parley call you forth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116360">Upon intent injuriously to deal:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116370">This offereth too much opportunity. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116380" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116390">No no Demarch, that were a breach</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116400">Against the law of arms: therefore begone,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116410">And leave us here alone. <stage xml:id="A21328-e116420">Exeunt.</stage></l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116430">I see that Zweno is master of his word. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116440">Zweno, William of Saxony greeteth thee</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116450"><pb facs="21"/> either well or ill, according to thy intent. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116460">If well thou wish to him and Saxony,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116470">He bids thee friendly welcome as he can. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116480">If ill thou wish to him and Saxony,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116490">He must withstand thy malice as he may. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116500" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116510">William, for other name and title give I none</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116520">To him, who were he worthy of those honours</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116530">That fortune and his predecessors left,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116540">I ought by right and human courtesy</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116550">To grace his style with Duke of Saxony. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116560">But for I find a base degenerate mind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116570">I frame my speech according to the man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116580">And not the state that he unworthy holds. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116590" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116600">Herein Zweno dost thou abase thy state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116610">To break the peace which by our ancestors</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116620">Hath heretofore been honourably kept. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116630" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116640">And should that peace for ever have been kept,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116650">Had not thyself been author of the breach:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116660">Nor stands it with the honour of my state,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116670">Or nature of a father to his child,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116680">That I should so be robbed of my daughter,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116690">And not unto the utmost of my power</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116700">Revenge so intolerable an injury. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116710" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116720">Is this the colour of your quarrel Zweno? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116730">I well perceive the wisest men may err. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116740">And think you I conveyed away your daughter Blanche? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116750" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116760">Art thou so impudent to deny thou didst? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116770">When that the proof thereof is manifest? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116780" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116790">What proof is there? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116800" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116810">Thine own confession is sufficient proof. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116820" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116830">Did I confess I stole your daughter Blanche? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116840" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116850">Thou didst confess thou hadst a lady hence. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116860" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116870">I have and do. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116880" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116890">Why that was Blanche my daughter. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116900" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116910">Nay, that was Mariana,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116920">Who wrongfully thou detainest prisoner. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116930" who="A21328-zweno">
              <pb facs="22"/>
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116940">Shameless persisting in thy ill,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116950">Thou dost maintain a manifest untruth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116960">As she shall justify unto thy teeth. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e116970">Rosilio fetch her and the marquess hither. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e116980">Exit Rosilio for Mariana.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e116990" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117000">It cannot be I should be so deceived. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117010" who="A21328-demarch">
              <speaker>Demarch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117020">I heard this night among the soldiers,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117030">That in their watch they took a pensive lady:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117040">Who at the appointment of the lord Dirot is yet in keeping. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117050">What she is I know not,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117060">Only thus much, I overheard by chance. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117070" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117080">And what of this. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117090" who="A21328-demarch">
              <speaker>Demarch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117100">It may be Blanche the King of Denmark's daughter. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117110" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117120">It may be so: but on my life it is not? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117130">Yet Demarch, go and fetch her straight. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e117140">Enter Rosilio with the marquess.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117150" who="A21328-rocilio">
              <speaker>Rosilio.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117160">Pleaseth your highness, here is the marquess and Mariana. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117170" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117180">See here, Duke William, your competitors</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117190">That were consenting to my daughters scape. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117200">Let them resolve you of the truth herein,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117210">And here I vow and solemnly protest,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117220">That in thy presence they shall lose their heads:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117230">Unless I hear where as my daughter is. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117240" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117250">Oh marquess Lubeck how it grieveth me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117260">That for my sake thou shouldst endure these bonds. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117270">Be judge my soul that feels the martyrdom. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117280" who="A21328-denmark">
              <speaker>Marquess.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117290">Duke William, you know it is for your cause,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117300">It pleaseth thus the King to misconceive of me,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117310">And for his pleasure doth me injury. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e117320">Enter Demarch with the lady Blanche.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117330" who="A21328-demarch">
              <speaker>Demarch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117340">May it please your highness,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117350">Here is the lady you sent me for,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117360" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117370">Away Demarch, what tellest thou me of ladies? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117380"><pb facs="22"/>I so detest the dealing of their sex,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117390">As that I count a lover's state to be the base</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117400">And vildest slavery in the world. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117410" who="A21328-demarch">
              <speaker>Demarch.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117420">What humours are these: here's a strange alteration. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117430" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117440">See Duke William, is this Blanche or no? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117450">You know her, if you see her I am sure. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117460" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117470">Zweno I was deceived, yea utterly deceived,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117480">Yet this is she: this same is lady Blanche. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117490">And for mine error, here I am content</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117500">To do whatsoever Zweno shall set down. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117510">Ah cruel Mariana thus to use</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117520">The man which loved and honoured thee with his heart. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117530" who="A21328-mariana">
              <speaker>Mariana.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117540">When first I came into your highness' court,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117550">And William often importing me of love:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117560">I did devise to ease the grief your daughter did sustain,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117570">She should meet sir William masked as I it were. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117580">This put in proof, did take so good effect,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117590">As yet it seems his grace is not resolved,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117600">But it was I which he conveyed away. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117610" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117620">May this be true? It cannot be but true. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117630">Was it lady Blanche which I conveyed away? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117640">Unconstant Mariana,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117650">Thus to deal with him which meant to thee naught but faith. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117660" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117670">Pardon dear father my follies that are past,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117680">Wherein I have neglected me duty</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117690">Which I in reverence ought to show your grace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117700">For led by love I thus have gone astray,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117710">And now repent the errors I was in. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117720" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117730">Stand up dear daughter though thy fault deserves</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117740">For to be punished in the extremest sort. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117750">Yet love that covers multitude of sins</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117760">Makes love in parents wink at children's faults. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117770">Sufficeth Blanche thy father loves thee so,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117780">Thy follies past he knows but will not know. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117790">And here Duke William take my daughter to thy wife. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117800">For well I am assured she loves thee well. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117810" who="A21328-william">
              <pb facs="23"/>
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117820">A proper conjunction: as who should say,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117830">Lately come out of the fire,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117840">I would go thrust myself into the flame. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117850">Let mistresses nice go saint it where she list,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117860">And coily acquaint it with dissembling face. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117870">I hold in scorn the fooleries that they use,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117880">I being free will never subject myself</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117890">To any such as she is underneath the sun. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117900" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117910">Refusest thou to take my daughter to thy wife? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117920">I tell thee Duke, this rash denial</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117930">May bring more mischief on thee than thou canst avoid. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e117940" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117950">Conceit hath wrought such general dislike</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117960">Through the false dealing of Mariana,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117970">That utterly I do abhor their sex. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117980">They are all disloyal, unconstant, all unjust:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e117990">Who tries as I have tried,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118000">And finds as I have found,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118010">Will say there's no such creatures on the ground. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118020" who="A21328-blanch">
              <speaker>Blanche.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118030">Unconstant knight, though some deserve no trust</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118040">There's others faithful, loving, loyal, and just. </l>
            </sp>
            <stage xml:id="A21328-e118050">Enter to them Valingford with Em and the miller, and Mountney, and Manville, and Elner.</stage>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118060" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>Willi.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118070">How now lord Valingford what makes these women here? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118080" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valing.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118090">Here be two women, may it please your grace,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118100">That are contracted to one man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118110">And are in strife whether shall have him to their husband. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118120" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118130">Stand forth women and say,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118140">To whether of you did he first give his faith. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118150" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118160">To me forsooth. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118170" who="A21328-elner">
              <speaker>Elner.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118180">To me my gracious lord. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118190" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118200">Speak Manville, to whether didst thou give thy faith? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118210" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118220">To say the troth: this maid had first my love. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118230" who="A21328-elner">
              <speaker>Elner.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118240">Yea Manville, but there was no witness by. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118250" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118260">Thy conscience Manville a hundred witnesses. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118270" who="A21328-elner">
              <pb facs="23"/>
              <speaker>Elner.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118280">She hath stolen a conscience to serve her own turn. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118290">But you are deceived, i'faith he will none of you. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118300" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118310">In deed, dread lord, so dear I held her love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118320">As in the same I put my whole delight. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118330">But some impediments which at that instant happened,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118340">Made me forsake her quite,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118350">For which I had her father's frank consent. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118360" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118370">What were the impediments? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118380" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118390">Why she could neither hear nor see. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118400" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118410">Now she doth both. Maiden, how were you cured:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118420" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118430">Pardon my lord, I'll tell your grace the troth,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118440">Be it not imputed to me as discredit. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118450">I loved this Manville so much, that still methought</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118460">When he was absent did present to me</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118470">The form and feature of that countenance</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118480">Which I did shrine an idol in mine heart. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118490">And never could I see a man methought</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118500">That equalled Manville in my partial eye. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118510">Nor was there any love between us lost,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118520">But that I held the same in high regard,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118530">Until repair of some unto our house,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118540">Of whom my Manville grew thus jealous:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118550">As if he took exception I vouchsafed</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118560">To hear them speak, or saw them when they came:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118570">On which I straight took order with myself</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118580">To void the scruple of his conscience,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118590">By counterfeiting that I neither saw nor heard,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118600">Any ways to rid my hands of them. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118610">All this I did to keep my Manville love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118620">Which he unkindly seeks for to reward. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118630" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118640">And did my Em to keep her faith with me</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118650">Dissemble that she neither heard nor saw. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118660">Pardon me sweet Em, for I am only thine. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118670" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118680">Lay off thy hands, disloyal as thou art,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118690">Nor shalt thou have possession of my love,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118700">That canst so finely shift thy matters off. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118710"><pb facs="24"/>Put case I had been blind and could not see,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118720">As often times such visitations falls</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118730">That pleaseth God which all things doth dispose:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118740">Shouldst thou forsake me in regard of that? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118750">I tell thee Manville, hadst thou been blind,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118760">Or deaf, or dumb, or else what impediments</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118770">Might befall to man, Em would have loved and kept,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118780">And honoured thee: yea, begged if wealth had failed</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118790">For thy relief. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118800" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118810">Forgive me sweet Em. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118820" who="A21328-unassigned">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118830">I do forgive thee with my heart,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118840">And will forget thee too if case I can:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118850">But never speak to me, nor seem to know me. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118860" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118870">Then farewell frost:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118880">Well fare a wench that will. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118890">Now, Elner I am thine own my girl. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118900" who="A21328-elner">
              <speaker>Elner.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118910">Mine Manville? thou never shalt be mine. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118920">I so detest thy villainy. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118930">That whilst I live I will abhor thy company. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118940" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118950">Is it come to this? of late, I had choice of twain</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118960">On either side to have me to her husband:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118970">And now am utterly rejected of them both. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e118980" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e118990">My lord this gentleman when time was</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119000">Stood some thing in our light,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119010">And now I think it not a miss</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119020">To laugh at him that sometime scorned at us. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119030" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119040">Content my lord, invent the form. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119050" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119060">Then thus. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119070" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119080">I see that women are not general evils. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119090">Blanche is fair: methinks I see in her,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119100">A modest countenance, a heavenly blush. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119110">Zweno, receive a reconciled foe,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119120">Not as thy friend, but as thy son in law,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119130">If so that thou be thus content. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119140" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119150">I joy to see your grace so tractable. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119160">Here take my daughter Blanche,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119170"><pb facs="24"/> and after my decease the Denmark crown. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119180" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119190">Now sir, how stands the case with you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119200" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119210">I partly am persuaded as your grace is,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119220">My lord, he is best at ease that meddleth least. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119230" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119240">Sir may a man be so bold,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119250">As to crave a word with you? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119260" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119270">Yea, two or three: what are they? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119280" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119290">I say, this maid will have thee to her husband. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119300" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119310">And I say this: and thereof will I lay an hundred pound. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119320" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingf.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119330">And I say this: whereon I will lay as much. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119340" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119350">And I say neither: what say you to that? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119360" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119370">If that be true: then are we both deceived. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119380" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119390">Why it is true, and you are both deceived. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119400" who="A21328-denmark">
              <speaker>Marquess.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119410">In mine eyes, this is the properest wench. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119420">Might I advise thee, take her unto thy wife. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119430" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119440">It seems to me, she hath refused him. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119450" who="A21328-denmark">
              <speaker>Marquess.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119460">Why there's the spite. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119470" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119480">If one refuse him, yet may he have the other. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119490" who="A21328-denmark">
              <speaker>Marquess.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119500">He will ask but her good will, and all her friends. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119510" who="A21328-zweno">
              <speaker>Zweno.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119520">Might I advise thee, let them both alone. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119530" who="A21328-manvile">
              <speaker>Manville.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119540">Yea, that's the course, and thereon will I stand. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119550">Such idle love henceforth I will detest. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119560" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119570">The fox will eat no grapes, and why? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119580" who="A21328-mountney">
              <speaker>Mountney.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119590">I know full well, because they hang too high. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119600" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119610">And may it be a miller's daughter by her birth? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119620">I cannot think but she is better born. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119630" who="A21328-valingford">
              <speaker>Valingford.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119640">Sir Thomas Goddard hight this reverent man,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119650">Famed for his virtues and his good success:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119660">Whose fame hath been renowned through the world. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119670" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119680">Sir Thomas Goddard welcome to thy prince,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119690">And fair Em, frolic with thy good father. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119700">As glad am I to find sir Thomas Goddard</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119710">As good sir Edmund Trefford on the plains:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119720">He like a shepherd, and thou our country miller. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119730" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119740">And longer let not Goddard live a day,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119750">Than he in honour loves his sovereign. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119760" who="A21328-william">
              <pb facs="25"/>
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119770">But say sir Thomas, shall I give thy daughter? </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119780" who="A21328-miller">
              <speaker>Miller.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119790">Goddard and all that he hath,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119800">Doth rest at the pleasure of your majesty. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119810" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119820">And what says Em to lovely Valingford? </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119830">It seemed he loved you well,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119840">That for your sake durst leave his King. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119850" who="A21328-em">
              <speaker>Em.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119860">Em rests at the pleasure of your highness:</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119870">And would I were a wife for his desert. </l>
            </sp>
            <sp xml:id="A21328-e119880" who="A21328-william">
              <speaker>William.</speaker>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119890">Then here lord Valingford,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119900">Receive fair Em.</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119910">Here take her, make her thy espoused wife. </l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119920">Then go we in, that preparation may be made,</l>
              <l xml:id="A21328-e119930">To see these nuptials solemnly performed. </l>
              <stage xml:id="A21328-e119940">Exeunt all. Sound drums and trumpets.</stage>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A21328-e119950">Finis.</trailer>
        <pb facs="25"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A21328"><item xml:id="A21328-william" n="73">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-william</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">73</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-em" n="55">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-em</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">55</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-valingford" n="44">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-valingford</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">44</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-mariana" n="33">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-mariana</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">33</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-lubeck" n="32">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-lubeck</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">32</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-manvile" n="29">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-manvile</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">29</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-mountney" n="28">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-mountney</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">28</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-trotter" n="26">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-trotter</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">26</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A21328-miller" n="21">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-miller</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">21</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-zweno" n="20">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-zweno</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">20</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-blanch" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-blanch</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-demarch" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-demarch</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-denmark" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-denmark</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-elner" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-elner</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-citizen" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-citizen</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-soldier" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-soldier</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-rocilio" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-rocilio</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-ambassador" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-ambassador</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-messenger" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-dirot" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-dirot</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-unassigned" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A21328-ver_life" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A21328-ver_life</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

