<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A15517">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Three Lords and Three Ladies of London <date type="creation_date">1588</date></title>
        <author>Wilson, Robert</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Hannah Bredar</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A15517.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The pleasant and stately morall, of the three lordes and three ladies of London. With the great ioy and pompe, solempnized at their mariages: commically interlaced with much honest mirth, for pleasure and recreation, among many morall obseruations and other important matters of due regard. by R.W.</title>
            <author>Wilson, Robert, d. 1600.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>34 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2005 October (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99847082</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 25783.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 93.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">12092</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15517</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The pleasant and stately morall, of the three lordes and three ladies of London. With the great ioy and pompe, solempnized at their mariages: commically interlaced with much honest mirth, for pleasure and recreation, among many morall obseruations and other important matters of due regard. by R.W.</title>
            <title type="alt">Three lords and three ladies of London</title>
            <title type="alt">Three lordes and three ladies of London</title>
            <title type="alt">Stately morall of the three lords of London.</title>
            <author>Wilson, Robert, d. 1600.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[68] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by R. Ihones, at the Rose and Crowne neere Holburne Bridge,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1590.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>R.W. = Robert Wilson.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Partly in verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>With a title-page woodcut.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A2 B-I4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Running title reads: The stately morall of the three lords of London.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A15517-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A15517-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A15517-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A15517-e100040">The pleasant and stately moral, of the three lords and three ladies of London.</p>
        <p xml:id="A15517-e100050">With the great joy and pomp, solemnised at their marriages: commically interlaced with much honest mirth, for pleasure and recreation, among many moral observations and other important matters of due regard. by R. W.</p>
        <p xml:id="A15517-e100060">
          <figure xml:id="A15517-e100070"/>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="A15517-e100080">London. Printed by R. Jones, at the rose and crown near Holborn bridge. 1590.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A15517-e100090">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>The actors names.</head>
        <list xml:id="A15517-e100100">
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100110">Policy, the thrée lords of London. Wit. their pages. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100120">Pomp, the thrée lords of London. Wealth. their pages. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100130">Pleasure, the thrée lords of London. Will. their pages. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100140">Nemo, a grave old man. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100150">Love, three ladies of London.</item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100160">Lucre, three ladies of London.</item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100170">Conscience, three ladies of London.</item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100180">Honest industry, thrée sages. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100190">Pure zeal, thrée sages. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100200">Sincerity, thrée sages. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100210">Pride, three lords of Spain, shame, their pages,</item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100220">Ambition, three lords of Spain, treachery, their pages,</item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100230">Tyranny, three lords of Spain, terror, their pages,</item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100240">Desire, thrée lords of Lincoln.</item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100250">Delight, thrée lords of Lincoln.</item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100260">Devotion, thrée lords of Lincoln.</item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100270">Sorrow, a jailer. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100280">Simplicity, a poor free man of London.</item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100290">Painful penury, his wife. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100300">Diligence, a post, or an officer. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100310">Fealty, two heralds at arms. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100320">Shealtie, two heralds at arms. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100330">Fraud, four gallants. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100340">Usury, four gallants. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100350">Dissimulation, four gallants. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100360">Simony, four gallants. </item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100370">Falsehood. two that belong to fraud and dissimulation.</item>
          <item xml:id="A15517-e100380">Double dealing. two that belong to fraud and dissimulation.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A15517-e100390">
      <div type="preface" xml:id="A15517-e100400">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e100410">Enter for the preface, a lady very richly attired, representing London, having two angels before her, and two after her with bright rapiers in their hands.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e100420" who="A15517-London">
          <speaker>London speaketh.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A15517-e100430">
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100440">Lo, gentles, thus the lord doth London guard,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100450">Not for my sake, but for his own delight:</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100460">For all in vain the sentinels watch and ward,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100470">Except he keep the city day and night. </l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100480">Now may my foes in vain both spurn and spite,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100490">My foes I mean, that London represent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100500">Guarded from heaven by angels excellent. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A15517-e100510">
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100520">This blessing is not my sole benefit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100530">All England is, and so preserved hath been,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100540">Not by man's strength, his policy and wit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100550">But by a power and providence unseen. </l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100560">Even for the love wherewith God loves our Queen:</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100570">In whom, for whom, by whom we do possess</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100580">More grace, more good, than London can express. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A15517-e100590">
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100600">And that hath bred our plenty and our peace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100610">And they do breed the sports you come to see,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100620">And joy it is, that I enjoy increase,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100630">My former fruits were lovely ladies three,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100640">Now of three lords to talk is London's glee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100650">Whose deeds I wish may to your liking frame,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e100660">For London bids you welcome to the same. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <trailer xml:id="A15517-e100670">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
      <div type="play" xml:id="A15517-e100680">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>The pleasant and stately moral of the three lords of London.</head>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e100690">Enter the three lords and their pages: first, policy with his page wit before him, bearing a shield: the impreze, a tortoise, the word, providens securus. Next pomp, with his page wealth bearing his shield, the word, glory sans peer: the impreze a lily. Last, pleasure, his page Wil, his impreze, a falcon, the word, pour temps: Pol. attired in black, pomp in rich robes, and pleasure in colours. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e100700" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100710">Here I advance my shield and hang it up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100720">To challenge him whoever dare deny,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100730">That one of those thrée London ladies rare</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100740">Ought not of right be matched with policy:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100750">A London lord, the which I represent. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100760">Pom. And pomp provides his challenge in his word,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100770">(Glory sans peer) claiming the one of them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100780">Not by compulsion, but by common right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100790">Yet maugre men my shield is here advanced</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100800">For one matchless, a London lady best</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100810">Beseemeth pomp (A London lord) to have. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e100820" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100830">Pleasure hath soared as doth his impreze show,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100840">To look aloof on earthly ladies all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100850">Yet never could my curious eye discern</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100860">A dame of worth, for London's pleasure's love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100870">But one, and she doth shine as silver dove. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100880">Of self bred soil, of London is her race,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100890">For whom in challenge I my shield advance. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e100900" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100910">Thus each in honour of his mistress</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100920">And in regard of his well daring mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100930">Hath here ymprizde the challenge of his right:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100940">But lordings both, and brothers bred and sworn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100950"><pb facs="4"/> a caution must be had in this conceit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100960">That all our thoughts aspire not to one heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100970">Nor all our ships do sail for one self haven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100980">I mean that all our suits and services</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e100990">We tend and tender to one only dame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101000">All choosing one, refusing th'other two. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101010" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101020">A great mislike amongst us that might breed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101030" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101040">I seek but one and her unto myself.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101050" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101060">And one with I sans partner of my loves.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101070" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101080">It stands with honour to be sole or none.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101090" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101100">Whom lovest thou pleasure? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101110" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101120">Hark ye. <stage xml:id="A15517-e101130">Whisper in his ear.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101140" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101150">Lush, ye lie.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101160" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101170">If my master were a soldier, that word would have the stab.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101180" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101190">Well Will, still you'll be a saucy scab.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101200" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101210">Why pleasure? Pomp hath chosen Lucre's love.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101220" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101230">Why pomp? But pleasure honour's lucre most.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101240" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101250">And policy may lady lucre gain</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101260">Before you both: but let us not contend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101270">For Nemo doth the ladies prisoners keep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101280">Though they were slandered late with liberty</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101290">And marriage to three far born foreigners. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101300">Then first it fits we practise their release,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101310">And see them, and by sight our liking place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101320">For yet we love as gossips tell their tales,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101330">By hearsay: fame, not favour hath us yet inflamed. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101340" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101350">Lord policy with reason hath discuss pleasure consent, and so our love shall hold.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101360" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101370">Ye never found that London's pleasure erred</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101380">From reason, or from pomp and policy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101390" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101400">Come on sir boy, attend you well your charge,<stage xml:id="A15517-e101410">To his page wit.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101420">Wait in this place to watch and ward this shield,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101430">If any man in honour of his love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101440">So hardy be with stroke of sword to attaint</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101450">This shield, and challenge him that hereby challengeth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101460">Say for thy lord as should a trusty page,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101470">That policy doth dare him to perform</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101480">A hardy task than common challengers. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101490">If he demand what policy may be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101500"><pb facs="4"/> a lord of London say, one of the three. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101510" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101520">And you (Sir boy) for pomp perform the like,<stage xml:id="A15517-e101530">To wealth. </stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101540">Bid him that dare this impreze batter once,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101550">Be well advised he be no beggar's brat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101560">Nor base of courage, nor of bad conceit:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101570">To match himself with such magnificence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101580">As fits lord pomp of London for his love:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101590">Call if he come that can encounter me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101600">Or move me not for each envious swad. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101610" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101620">Will, be not wanton nor of wayward mood,<stage xml:id="A15517-e101630">To Will.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101640">Wait as do these, use faith and diligence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101650">And mark him well that dare disdain this shield,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101660">Which London's lord that pleasure hath to name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101670">Hath here advanced in honour of his dame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101680">I bid thee mark him well, whate'er he be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101690">That London's pleasure doth in malice scorn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101700">For he's a rascal, or a stranger born. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101710">Good boy mark well his gesture and his look,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101720">His eye, his gate, his weapon and attire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101730">And dog him to his lodging, or his den,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101740">For I will make him scum and scorn of men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101750">No better boy than Will, when Will is pleased,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101760">Be pleased my boy, and so be my good Will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101770" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101780">And so good boys farewell, look to your charge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101790">Watch well good wit, who scorneth London's policy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e101800">Be wary wit, for thou canst well discern. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101810" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101820">Wealth watch for pomp for thou canst well defend</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101830" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101840">Will can do something too when pleaseth him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101850" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101860">Will is a good boy where better is none. <stage xml:id="A15517-e101870">Exeunt the ●. Lordes. </stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101880" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101890">Nay wit were the best boy if will were gone.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101900" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101910">Nay wealth is the best boy, sirs let that alone.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101920" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101930">I wiss he saith true will, this wealth's a gay lad,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101940" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101950">I care not for him, curmudgeonly swad.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101960" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101970">Well, miss me a while and you'll go near to be sad.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e101980" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e101990">Will, ye are will fool, if of him ye be not glad.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102000" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102010">Nay wit if thou want him, thou'lt go near to be mad.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102020" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Vvea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102030">To keep us still quiet, I would other talk we had,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102040" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102050">I hope we'll not fall out being none but we three.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102060" who="A15517-wealth">
          <pb facs="5"/>
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102070">If wealth were away, wit and will would agree.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102080" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102090">Nay, wit and will are at strife, when there's nobody but we.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102100" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102110">Let pass, and of our shields (Sirs) let's make a little glee,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102120" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil,</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102130">What gives thy master here? A buzzard or a rite.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102140" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102150">Wit, you show yourself a gentleman by g●ssing so right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102160">A buzzard? thou buzyard, wit, hast no more skill</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102170">Than take a falcon for a buzzard. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102180" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102190">O be quiet good will:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102200">It was but for sport, for I know the bird else,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102210" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102220">Thou mightest see it was no buzzard man by the bells:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102230" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102240">What's the reason of this falcon, I pray thee will show.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102250" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102260">Thou knowest that a falcon wares hie, and stoops low,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102270">So doth pleasure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102280" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102290">And what's the word?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102300" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102310">Pour temps, for time.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102320" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102330">A very pretty one, I would it were in rhyme.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102340" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102350">In rhyme wit, why so?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102360" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102370">Because it wants reason.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102380" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102390">Look for my fist wit, if ye rap out such treason.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102400" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102410">Treason, to what, boy?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102420" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102430">To my master's bird.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102440" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102450">Now will my thumb wags, it was but to his word.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102460" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102470">'Tis a pleasant gentleman, this young mast. Wit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102480">Your master hath something too, I pray ye what's it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102490" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102500">Look will, and guess.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102510" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102520">'Tis a load in a shell.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102530" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102540">I had as lief ye had said, a frog in a well.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102550" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102560">Is't not a great butterfly, Will, canst thou tell?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102570" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102580">What is it in sadness?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102590" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102600">A tortoise my boy, whose shell is so hard, that a loaden cart may go over and not break it, and so she is safe within, and wheresoever she goes, she bears it on her back, needing neither other succour or shelter but her shell: the word underneath her is providens securus, the provident is safe, like to the tortoise, armed with his own defence, and defended with his own armour: in shape somewhat round, signifying compass, wherein always the provident foresee to keep themselves within their own compass, my boy.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102610" who="A15517-will">
          <pb facs="5"/>
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102620">Wittily spoken, now wealth's mayst. hath got a daffadowndilly.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102630" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Vvea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102640">If Will had not been wilful, now he might have said a lily, whose glory is without comparison, and beauty matchless. for Salomon the most sumptuous King that ever was, was never comparable in glory with the lily, neither is there any cities matchable with the pomp of London, mistake me not good boys, that this pomp tends to pride, yet London hath enough, but my lord pomp doth rightly represent the stately magnificence and sumptuous estate without pride or vain glory to London accommodate, and therefore the word is well applied to the impreze (Glory sans peer) for that the lily is neither proud of the beauty, nor vainglorious of the pomp: no more is London, but if it be joyful of any thing, it is of the peace and plenty, both flowing from two such fountains as becomes not us to name. Now therefore, my good boys, know that my master is rather magnificence than pomp in bad sense, and rather pomp than pride in the best sense.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102650" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102660">And my lord is not pleasure sprung of voluptuousness, but of such honourable and honest kind conceit, as heaven and humanity well brooks and allows pleasure pleasing not pernicious.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102670" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102680">Who would have thought that will had been philosophous, but what means the word pour temps in the shield, for time?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102690" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102700">Wit, shall I call thee fool? the best pleasure of all lasts but a time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102710">For of all pleasures most pleasing to sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102720">Methinks there is none to the falcon's high slight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102730">Yet diseases end it, the breach of a wing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102740">Nay, the breach of a feather spoils that sweet thing:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102750" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102760">And so my master hath the vantage will ye or no, pomp and pleasure may be ill.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102770" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102780">May not policy be bad?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102790" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Weal.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102800">Wit, well overtaken by Will that crafty lad.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102810" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102820">A crafty goose, the gander gives him health,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102830">Bad policy's seldom found in so christian a common wealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102840">As London is I trust, where my master is a lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102850" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102860">And ours so too.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102870" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wealth</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102880">Well, let us accord, for wit's a good thing, yet may be ill applied</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102890" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102900">And so may wealth, be it employed in pride,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e102910">And will worst of all, when it disdains a guide. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102920" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102930">A jackanapes hath wit. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102940" who="A15517-wit">
          <pb facs="6"/>
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102950">And so he hath will. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102960" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102970">But he never hath wealth: now ye are both still.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e102980" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e102990">Yes, he wears a chain.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103000" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103010">Well spoken, and like a bearward.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103020" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103030">If ye be non plus let the matter fall.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103040" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103050">Wit, dost thou see? thus goes wealth away with all.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103060" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103070">Let's reason no further for we shall have glee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103080">Here is a challenger to our shields, step we aside. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e103090">Enter simplicity in bare black, like a poor citizen.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103100" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103110">He will eat them I think, for he gapes very wide.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103120" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103130">Say nothing to him, and ye shall see the fool go by.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103140" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103150">Sirrah, gape not so wide for fear of a fly.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103160" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103170">Fly, flam flirt: why? Can a fly do hurt?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103180" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103190">Yea, have ye not heard that the fly hath her spleen</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103200">And the ant her gall? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103210" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103220">My uncle hath so I ween, for it's an angry old fellow</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103230">When his gall runs over: children good day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103240">Whose pretty lads are you three? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103250" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103260">Three, are ye sure?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103270" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103280">I'll not swear till I have told you: one, two, three.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103290" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103300">I beshrew thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103310" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103320">Me boy, why? I am beshrewed already, for I am married.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103330" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103340">Then thou hast a wife?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103350" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103360">Yea, I would thou hadst her, if thou couldst stay her tongue,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103370" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103380">I thy wise man? Why, I am too young.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103390" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103400">And I am too old, but in good earnest good boys, be not angry,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103410">That I call you boys, for ye are no men yet, ye have no beards</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103420">And yet I have seen boys angry for being called boys:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103430">Forsooth they would be called youths: well, yet a boy is a boy</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103440">And a youth is a youth: well, if ye be not ashamed of the boy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e103450">Good boys, whose eyes are ye? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103460" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103470">No whit ashamed sir of that that we are, nor ashamed at all of those whom we serve, for boys we be, and as we be, we serve the three lords of London, to weet, policy, pomp, and pleasure. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103480" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103490">A pretty spoken child and of a pretty wit.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103500" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103510">Wit's his name indeed, are ye one of his godfathers, ye hit it so right?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103520" who="A15517-simony">
          <pb facs="6"/>
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103530">It is more than I know, then is thy name wit boy? Now of mine honesty welcome, for I have wanted thee a great while.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103540" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103550">Welcome sir, how so? why do ye entertain me so kindly? I cannot dwell with you for I have a master already.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103560" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103570">So have I too, but she learns me little wit: my wife I mean well, all this while I stand here my wares are not abroad, and so I may lose both my customers and market.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103580" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Vvea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103590">Wares sir, have ye wares? what wares do ye sell?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103600" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103610">Truly child, I sell ballads: soft, whose wares are these that are up already? I paid rent for my standing, and other folks wares shall be placed afore mine, this is wise indeed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103620" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103630">O, the fineness of the wares (Man) deserve to have good place.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103640" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103650">They are fine indeed, who sells them, can ye tell? Is he free?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103660" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103670">Our masters be, we wait on this ware, and yet we are no chapmen.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103680" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103690">Chapmen, no that's true, for you are no men, neither chapmen nor chopmen, nor chipmen nor shipmen, but if ye be chappers, choppers or chippers, ye are but chapboys, and chapboys ye are double.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103700" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103710">Double, how is it? Teach me that and you will make me laugh a little.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103720" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Vvea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103730">And me a little:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103740" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103750">And me a little.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103760" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103770">Then your three little laughs will make one great laugh:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103780" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103790">True, for if three fools were one fool, that were a great fool. But how are we double chapboys? <stage xml:id="A15517-e103800">Point to simplicity.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103810" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103820">Because ye have two chaps, an upper chap and a nether chap.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103830" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103840">Ha, ha, ha.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103850" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103860">Ha, ha, ha.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103870" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wealth</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103880">Ha, ha, ha.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103890" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103900">You said you would laugh but a little, but you laugh a great deal, why do ye laugh so much?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103910" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103920">Because your wit was so great in expounding your meaning</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103930" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103940">Ye, you may see it is a good thing to have wit.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103950" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103960">I thank you sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103970" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wealth</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e103980">And what say you to wealth?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e103990" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104000">Wealth? Marry wealth is better.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104010" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wealth</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104020">I thank you sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104030" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104040">And how say ye to will?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104050" who="A15517-simony">
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104060">Indeed, good will is a great matter,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104070" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104080">Yea between a maid and a bachelor.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104090" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104100">Why? you are not in love boy?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104110" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104120">Yes but I am, and in charity too.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104130" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104140">Charity? alas poor child, thou in charity, ha, ha, now must I laugh.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104150" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104160">But you laugh a great while, and you laugh very loud,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104170" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104180">Then I owe you nothing for laughing, and you hear me the the</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104190" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104200">But now laugh not we.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104210" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104220">No, you may be maddle, coddle: well here's thrée passing fine lads, if a man were able to keep them all: let me see wealth, o that's a sweet lad: then wit, o that's a fine lad: Will, o that's a pretty lad. Will, wit, and wealth, God lend ye health. I would I could guile their masters of two of them. If I had fraud here that served lady Lucre, he would teach me: he would teach me to 'tice one of them from his master: which of them now, if a man should steal one? will? Nay, I care not for will outsep he be good will: wit, a pretty child, but a man can not live by wit: wealth, yea marry sir, I would I could win that wealth, for then I need neither will, nor wit, nor I need sell no ballads but live like a mouse in a mill and have another to grind my meal for me, I'll have a fling at one of them anon.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104230" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104240">Do you not forget yourself gaffer.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104250" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104260">Have you not wares to sell gaffer?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104270" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104280">When do you show gaffer?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104290" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104300">Well remembered pretty lads, ye may see, children can teach old folks, I am an unthrift indeed: well, my wares shall out now. But sir●, how sell ye your wares, how many of these for a groat?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104310" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wealth</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104320">Our wares are not to be sold.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104330" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104340">Not for silver nor gold? why hang they then in the open market?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104350" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104360">To be seen, not bought.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104370" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104380">Then they are like ripe plums upon a rich man's tree that set men's tooth a watering when they be not to be bought: but what call ye these things?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104390" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104400">Scutcheons.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104410" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104420">Cushions, alas it were pity to sit on such fine cushions: but come my boys if you'll buy any of my wares, here's my stall, and I'll open and show straight.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104430" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Vvea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104440">What dainty fine ballad have you now to be sold?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104450" who="A15517-simony">
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104460">Marry child, I have chipping Norton a mile from chapel oath heath, a lamentable ballad of burning the Pope's dog: the sweet ballad of the  Lincolnshire bagpipes, and Peggy and Willy, but now he is dead and gone: mine own sweet Willy is laid in his grave la, la, la, lan ti dan derry, dan da dan, lan ti dan, dan tan derry, dan do. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104470" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit·</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104480">It is a doleful discourse, and sung as dolefully.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104490" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104500">Why, you can not mend it, can ye?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104510" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104520">What will you lay on that? For I myself dare lay six groats to six of your bald ballads, that you yourself shall say I sing better than you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104530" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104540">What a brag boy is this to comparison with a man, but boy boy, I will not lay six ballads to six groats, but I will lay six ballads to six jerks at your buttocks, that you shall not sing so well as I.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104550" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104560">That I shall not? No, possible you will not let me sing.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104570" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104580">I not let you? Is that spoken like wit? It is spoken like a woodcock, how can I stay thee if thou wilt sing out thy throat?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104590" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104600">Well then, to our bargain, six ballads to six stripes, and who shall keep stakes?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104610" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104620">Neither of your companions, for that's ask my fellow if I be a thief.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104630" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104640">Will you keep the stakes yourself?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104650" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104660">Best of all, for I mean plainly and will pay if I lose, here's my six ballads, they be ready: now how shall I come by your six stripes boy?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104670" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104680">Down with your breeches, I'll fetch a rod and deliver them straight.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104690" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104700">Nay then I care not if thou keep stakes.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104710" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104720">You speak too late gaffer, having challenged pre-eminence.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104730" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104740">Then let's lay no wager but sing for good fellowship.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104750" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104760">Agreed, who shall begin?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104770" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104780">O boy, who is the elder? Hast thou not heard give flounders to thy elder?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104790" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104800">You mistake the fish, trust me I am sure 'tis give place, but begin with good grace.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e104810">Here simp. sings first, and wit after, dialoguewise, both to music if ye will.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104820" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104830">Now sirs, which sings best?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104840" who="A15517-simony">
          <pb facs="8"/>
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104850">Tush, your copemates shall not judge: friend, what say you, which of us sings best?<stage xml:id="A15517-e104860">To one of the auditory.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104870" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104880">To say truth there's but had choice, how will you sell the ballad you sang, for I'll not buy the voice.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104890" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104900">Why wilt thou not buy my voice?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104910" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104920">Because it will cost me more money to buy salad oil to keep it from rusting, than it is worth: but I pray ye honest man, what's this?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104930" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104940">Read and then shalt see.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104950" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104960">I cannot read.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104970" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e104980">Not read and brought up in London, wru●st thou never to schols</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e104990" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105000">Yes, but I would not learn.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105010" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105020">Thou wast the more fool: if thou cannot read I'll tell this, this is Tarlton's picture: didst thou never know Tarlton ▪</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105030" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105040">No: what was that Tarlton? I never knew him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105050" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105060">What was be: a prentice in his youth of this honourable city, God be with him: when he was young he was leaning to the trade that my wife useth now, and I have used, vide lice shirt, water-bearing: I wis he hath tossed a tankard in Cornhill ere now, if thou knewest him not I will not call thee ingram, but if thou knewest not him, thou knewest nobody : I warrant here's two crack-ropes knew him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105070" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105080">I dwelled with him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105090" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105100">Didst thou? now give me thy hand, I love thee the better.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105110" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105120">And I too sometime.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105130" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105140">You child, did you dwell with him sometime?</p>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105150">Wit dwelled with him indeed, as appeared by his rhyme,</p>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105160">And served him well, and will was with him now and than, but soft, thy name is wealth, I think in earnest he was little acquainted with thee oh it was a fine fellow as ere was born, there will never come his like while the earth can corn. O passing fine Tarlton I would thou hadst lined yet.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105170" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105180">He might have some, but thou showest small wit, there is no such fineness in the picture that I see.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105190" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105200">And thou art no cinque port man, thou art not wit free,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105210">The fineness was within, for without he was plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105220">But it was the merriest fellow and had such jests in store,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105230">That if thou hadst seen him, thou wouldst have laughed thy heart sore. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105240" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Weal,</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105250">Because of thy praise, what's the price of the picture.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105260" who="A15517-simony">
          <pb facs="8"/>
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105270">I'll tell thee my lad, come hither, if thou wilt be ruled by me thou shalt pay nothing, I'll give it thee, if thou wilt dwell with me, and I promise thee this counsel is for thy prefarming, hadst not thou better serve a free man of the city, and learn a trade to live another day, than to be a serving boy in thy youth and to have no occupation in thine age, I can make thee free if thou wilt be my prentice.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105280" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wealth</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105290">Why, wealth is free everywhere , what need I serve you●. My lord is a freeman if that may do me good.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105300" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105310">I cry ye mercy m. boy, than your master is free of the lords company and you serve him that ye may be a lord when ye come out of your years.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105320" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105330">Wealth is a proud boy, gaffer what say you to me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105340" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105350">Thy name is wit, wilt thou dwell with me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105360" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105370">If I like your name and science, perchance we'll agree</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105380" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105390">Nay, my name and mine honesty is all one, it is well known he's a very fool that cannot beguile me, for my name is simplicity. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105400" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105410">Coads gaffer were not you a mealman once and dwelled with lady Conscience?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105420" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105430">Yes, for want of a better.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105440" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105450">What, a better man?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105460" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105470">No, for want of a better mistress, she was as very a fool as I we dwelled so long together that we went both on begging.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105480" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105490">Indeed they that use a good conscience cannot suddenly be rich, but I'll not dwell with ye, you are too simple a master for me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105500" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105510">Nor I'll not dwell with you for all this world's treasure.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105520" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105530">No, why whom serve you will?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105540" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>W●l. </speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105550">I serve my lord pleasure. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105560" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105570">And whom serve you wit?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105580" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105590">I serve my lord policy</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105600" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105610">And whom serve you wealth?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105620" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wealth</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105630">I serve my lord pomp. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105640" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105650">You should be served all with my lord Birchley if you were well served, these lads are so lordly that louts care not for them: for wealth serves pomp, wit serves policy, and will serves pleasure. wealth, will you buy this picture for your lord? <stage xml:id="A15517-e105660">Show Tarlton's picture,</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105670" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wealth</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105680">No, it's too hase a present for pomp. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105690" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105700">And policy seldom regards such a trifle.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105710" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105720">Come on gaffer, come on, I must be your best chapman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105730"><pb facs="9"/> I'll buy it for pleasure, hold, there is a great:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105740" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105750">Gramercy good will, my wife shall love thee still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105760">And since I can neither get wit nor wealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105770">Let my wife have her will, and let me have my health. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105780">God forgive me, I think I never name her, but it conjures her, look</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105790">Where she comes, be mannerly boys that she knock ye not with her</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105800">Staff: keep your own counsel, and I'll make ye laugh. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105810">What do ye lack, what lack ye. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105820">Stand away these boys from my wares,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105830">Get ye from my stall, or I'll wring you by the ears. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105840">Let my customers see the wares: what lack ye what would ye have bought. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e105850">Enter painful penury, attired like a water-bearing woman with her tankard. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105860" who="A15517-penury">
          <speaker>Pen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105870">You have customers enough and if they were ought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105880">What do ye with these boys here to filch away your ware? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105890">You show all your wit, you'll ne'er have more care. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105900" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105910">Content ye good wife, we do not filch, but buy.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105920" who="A15517-penury">
          <speaker>Pen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105930">I meant not you, young master, god's blessing on your heart</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105940">You have bought indeed sir I see, for your part. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105950">Be these two young gentlemen of your company,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e105960">Buy gentlemen, buy ballads to make your friends merry. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105970" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e105980">To stand long with your burden, methinks you should be weary</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e105990" who="A15517-penury">
          <speaker>Pen.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106000">True gentlemen, but you may see poor painful penury</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106010">Is fain to carry thrée tankards for a penny. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106020">But husband I say, come not home to dinner, its ember day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106030">You must eat nothing till night, but fast and pray. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106040">I shall lose my draught at conduit, and therefore I'll away. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106050">Young gentlemen God be with ye. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106060" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106070">Wife, must I not dine today?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106080" who="A15517-penury">
          <speaker>Pen.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106090">No sir by my say. <stage xml:id="A15517-e106100">Exit penury.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106110" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106120">If I must not eat, I mean to drink the more. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106130">What I spare in bread, in ale I'll set on the score. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106140">How say ye my lad? And do I not speak wisely? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106150" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106160">Methinks ye do, and it's pretty, that simplicity</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106170">Hath gotten to his wife plain painful penury. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106180" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106190">Yea, I thank God though she be poor and scarce cleanly, yet she is homely, careful and comely.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e106200"><pb facs="9"/>One call within. Wit, wealth and will, come to your lords quickly.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106210" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106220">Must the scutcheons hang still? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106230">One within. yea, let them alone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106240" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106250">Farewell master simplicity. <stage xml:id="A15517-e106260">Exeunt.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106270" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106280">Farewell good m. boys e'en heartily, e'en heartily, heartily. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106290">And hear ye will, I thank you for your handsel truly. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106300">Pretty lads, hark ye sirs how? will, wit, wealth. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e106310">Enter Wit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106320" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106330">What's the matter you call us back so suddenly.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106340" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106350">I forgotten to ask you whither your thrée lords of London be courtiers or cittiners?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106360" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106370">Citizens born and courtiers brought up: is this all? Farewell. <stage xml:id="A15517-e106380">Exit.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106390" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106400">Citizens born and courtiers brought up, I think so, for they that be born in London are half courtiers before they see the court, for finesse and mannerliness o passing, my manners and misbehaviour is mended half in half since I gave over being a mealman and came to dwell in London: ye may see time doth much, time wears out iron horseshoes: time tears out millstones: time seasons a pudding well, and time hath made me a free man, as free to bear water and sell ballads, as the best of our copulation: I would have thought once my horse should have been free as soon as myself, and sooner too, for he would have stumbled with a sack of meal and lain along in the channel with it when he had done, and that some calls freedom, but it's but a dirty freedom, but ye may see, bad horses were but jades in those days: but soft, here comes customers: what lack ye, what is't ye lack, what lack ye? Come along and buy nothing: fine ballads, new ballads, what lack ye?</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e106410">Enter Nemo and the three lords.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106420" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106430">My lords come on, what suits have you to me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106440" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106450">Renowned Nemo, the most only one</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106460">That draws no breath but of th'eternal air,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106470">That knowest our suit before we bound to speak</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106480">For thou art the very oracle of thoughts:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106490">Whose virtues do encompass thee about,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106500">As th'air surrounds this massy globe of earth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106510"><pb facs="10"/>Who hast in power whatever pleaseth thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106520">And canst bestow much more than we may crave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106530">To thee we seek, to thee on knees we sue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106540">That thou wilt deign from thraldom to release,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106550">Those lovely dames, that London ladies are. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106560" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106570">What, those thrée caitiefs long ago condemned? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106580">Love, Lucre, conscience, well deserving death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106590">Being corrupt with all contagion:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106600">The spotted ladies of that stately town. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106610" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106620">Love, Lucre, conscience we of thee desire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106630">Which in thyself hast all perfection,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106640">Accomplished with all integrity:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106650">And needest no help so do what pleaseth thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106660">Who holdest fame and fortune both thy slaves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106670">And dost compel the destinies draw the coach:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106680">To thee we sue, sith power thou hast thereto,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106690">To set those ladies at their liberty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106700" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106710">At liberty, thou spotless magistrate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106720">That of the cause dost carry all regard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106730">Careless of bribes, of birth and parentage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106740">Because thyself art only born to bliss,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106750">Bless us so much that lords of London are,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106760">That those thrée ladies born and bred with us</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106770">May by our suits, release of thraldom send. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106780" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106790">Release my lords? why seek ye their release? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106800">That have perpetual prison for their doom. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106810" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106820">But Nemo can from thence redeem them all.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106830" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106840">Their deeds were cause, not Nemo of their thrall.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106850" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106860">Yet Nemo was the judge that sentence gave.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106870" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106880">But Nemo never spilled, whom he could save:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106890" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106900">Thou from perpetual prison mayst revoke.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106910" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106920">Death hath no power 'gainst him to strike a stroke</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106930" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106940">Thou only mild and courteous sir, vouchsafe</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e106950">To grant our suit, and set those ladies free. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106960" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106970">What's your purpose in this earnest suit?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e106980" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e106990">To marry them, and make them honest wives.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107000" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107010">But may it be that men of your regard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107020">Lords of such fortune, and so famous place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107030"><pb facs="10"/> will link yourselves with ladies so forlorn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107040">And so distained with more than common crimes? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107050" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107060">Marriage doth make amends for many amiss.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107070" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107080">And love doth cover hears of cumbrous evils.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107090" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107100">And doth forget the faults that were before.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107110" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107120">Mean as you say, ye need to say no more.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107130" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107140">In token that we mean what we have said,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107150">Lo here our shields the prizes of our love:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107160">To challenge all except thyself that dare</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107170">Deny those ladies to be ours by right. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107180" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107190">Woo them and win them, win them and wear them too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107200">I shall both comfort and discourage you my lords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107210">The comfort's this, of all those former crimes</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107220">Wherewith the world was wont those dames to charge</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107230">I have them cleared and made them all as free</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107240">As they were born: no blemish left to see. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107250">But the discourage (Gentle lords) is this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107260">The time of their endurance hath been long,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107270">Whereby their clothes of cost and curious stuff</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107280">Are worn to rags, and give them much disgrace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107290" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107300">Alas good ladies, was there none that sued</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107310">For their release, before we took't in hand? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107320" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107330">Yes, divers for fair lucre sought release,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107340">And some for love would fain have paid the fees,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107350">But silly conscience sat without regard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107360">In sorrow's dungeon, sighing by herself:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107370">Which when I saw that some did sue for love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107380">And most for lucre, none for conscience:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107390">A vow I made, which now I shall perform,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107400">Till some should sue to have release for all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107410">Judged as they were, they should remain in thrall:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107420">But you that crave their freedoms all at once</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107430">Shall have your suit, and see them here ere long,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107440">A little while you must have patience,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107450">And leave this place: go in my lords before. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107460" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107470">Becometh us to wait on Nemo still,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107480" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107490">Not so: but lordings, the condition more</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107500">You promise me, sith they are in my power,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107510"><pb facs="11"/> I shall dispose them when they are released</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107520">Upon you three, as I shall think it best. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107530" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107540">Do but command and we shall all subscribe.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107550" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107560">Then go your ways, for I have here to do. <stage xml:id="A15517-e107570">Exeunt 3. Lord</stage></l>
          <stage xml:id="A15517-e107580">Enter sorrow. </stage>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107590">Sorrow draw near, tomorrow bring thou forth</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107600">Love, Lucre, conscience, whom thou hast in thrall,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107610">Upon these stones to sit, and take the air,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107620">But set no watch or espial what they do. <stage xml:id="A15517-e107630">Exeunt ambo.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e107640">Enter Fraud, usury, dissimulation, simony and simplicity. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107650" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107660">How happy may we call this merry day my mates, wherein we meet, that once were desperate, I think, ever to have seen one another, when Nemo that upright judge had by imprisoning our mistresses, banished us (By setting such diligent watch for us) out of London, and almost out of the world. But live we yet? And are we met? and near our old seat? Usury is it thou? Let me see, or hath some other stolen thy face? Speakest thou man?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107670" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107680">No fraud, though many have counterfeited both thee and me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107690">We are ourselves yet, and no changelings I see:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107700">And why shouldst thou ask me man if I live:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107710">The silly ass can not feed on harder forage than usury,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107720">She upon thistles, and I upon a brown crust of a month old. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107730" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107740">So that usury and an ass are two of the profitablest beasts that a man can keep, yet th'one hath sharper teeth than th'other.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107750" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107760">But what means dissimulation? He droops methinks , what cheer man? Why cousin, frolic a fit, art thou not glad of this meeting? What's the cause of thy melancholy?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107770" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107780">Not melancholic, but musing how it comes to pass that we are thus fortunate to meet as we do.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107790" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Simony</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107800">I'll tell thee why we met, because we are no mountains.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107810" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107820">But ye are as ill, for ye are monsters.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107830" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Simony</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107840">And men may meet though mountains cannot.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107850" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107860">In token that this meeting is joyful to us all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107870">Let us embrace altogether with heart's joy and affection. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107880" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107890">I see many of these old proverbs prove true, 'tis merry when knaves meet:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107900" who="A15517-fraud">
          <pb facs="11"/>
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107910">How sir, what's that?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107920" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107930">If a man had a casting net, he might catch all you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107940" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e107950">Art not thou simplicity?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e107960" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107970">Goodman Simp. for I am married, and it like your mastership,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107980">And you are mast. Fraud too, a pox on your worship. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e107990">I see, a fox and a false knave have all one luck, the better for banning,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108000">And many of you crafty knaves live merrilier than we honest men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108010" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108020">Sirrah, bridle your tongue if you'll be welcome to our company</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108030">No girds nor old grudges, but congratulate this meeting,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108040">And sirs, if you say it, let's tell how we have lived since our parting. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108050" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108060">O it is great pity.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108070" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108080">What? to tell how we have lived:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108090" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108100">No, that ye do live.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108110" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108120">Yet again sirrah. Usury, as for thee it were folly to ask, for thou livest but too well, but dissimulation and simony, how have you two lived? discourse I pray you heartily.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108130" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108140">Faith even like two mice in an aumbry that eat up all the meat, and when they have done, gnaw holes in the cupboard.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108150" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108160">Fraud, after my scaping away at the sessions where I shifted as thou knowest in thrée sundry shapes, one of a friar, and they can dissemble: another like a woman, and they do little else: the third as a saint and a devil, and so is a woman. I was banished out of London by Nemo, to the country went I, amongst my old friends and never better loved than among the russet coats: once in a month I stole in other market day to leaden-hall and about, and sometime to Westminster hall. Now hearing some speech, that the ladies should be sued for, for I am come in hope of my old entertainment, supposing myself not known of many, and hoping the three lords will prevail in their suit, and I to serve one of them.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108170" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108180">He shall do well that gives thee a coat, but he should do better, that could take of thy skin.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108190" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Simony</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108200">And I have been a traveller abroad in other realms, for here I am so cried out against by preachers (And yet some ministers that be none, could be content to use me) that I was glad to be gone now in some other lands, and not very far off, I am secretly fostered, saving in Scotland, and the low countries, they are reformed, they can not abide me. Well now and then hither I came stealing over sea, and hearing as you here intend as you do.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108210" who="A15517-fraud">
          <pb facs="12"/>
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108220">And for mine own part, amongst artificers and amongst a few bad conscienced lawyers, I have found such entertainment, as doth pass, yet would I with lucre fain be as I was.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108230" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108240">Fraud is as ill as a cutpurse, by the mass.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108250" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108260">And for usury, the longer I live, the greater love I find yet would I be with lucre, again to please my mind.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108270" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108280">Here's a good fellow too, one of our acquaintance, how hast thou lived simplicity?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108290" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108300">More honestly than all the rest of thy company: for when I might beg no longer, as begging was but bad, for you cozened me once of an alms, I fell to tankard bearing ▪ and so ●os a wife of the same science. painful penury, then got I my freedom, and feeling my shoulder grow weary of the tankard, set up an easier trade to sell ballads.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108310" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108320">Hadst thou a stock to set up withal?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108330" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108340">Wise enough to tell you, ay, and yonder's my stal, but beware I lose nothing, for if I do, I'll lay it straight to some of you, for I saw none so like thieves I promise you, since I set up.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108350" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108360">Ye are a wiseman when your nose is in the cup, but soft who comes here? step we close aside, for these be the three ladies for my life brought out of prison by their keeper, let us be whist and we shall hear and see all, sirrah you must say nothing.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e108370">Enter sorrow and the three ladies, he sets them on three stones on the stage. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108380" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108390">Not till ye speak for I am afraid of him that's with thewoman ▪</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108400" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108410">O sorrow when? when sorrow wilt thou cease</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108420">To blow the spark that burns my troubled soul? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108430">To feed the worm that stings my fainting breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108440">And sharp the steel that gores my dying heart? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108450">My thoughts are thorns, my tears hot drops of lead,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108460">I plain, I pine, I die, yet never dead. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108470">If world would end, my woe should but begin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108480">Lo, this the case of conscience for her sin:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108490">And sin the food wherewith my worm was fed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108500">That stings me now to death, yet never dead. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108510" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108520">Yet never dead, and yet love doth not th●●,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108530">Love that to loss in life her folly lent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108540">Folly the food whereon her frailty fed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108550">Frailty the milk that nature's breast did give,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108560"><pb facs="12"/> life, loss and folly, frailty, food and kind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108570">Worm, sting, thorns, fire and torment to the mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108580">Life but a breath, and folly but a flower,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108590">Frailty clay, dust the food, that fancy scorns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108600">Love a sweet bait to cover losses sour. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108610">Flesh breeds the fire that kindles lustful thorns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108620">Lust, fire, bait, scorn, dust, flower, and feeble breath</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108630">Die, quench, deceive, fly, fade, and yield to death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108640">To death? O good, if death might finish all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108650">We die each day, and yet for death we call. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108660" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108670">For death we call, yet death is still in sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108680">Lucre doth sealed in drops of melting gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108690">Accusing rust, calls on eternal might,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108700">Where flames consume, and yet we freeze with cold:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108710">Sorrow adds sulphur unto fury's heat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108720">And chops them ye, whose chattering teeth do beat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108730">But sulphur, snow, flame, frost nor hideous crying</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108740">Can cause them die, that ever are in dying. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108750">Nor make the pain diminish or increase,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108760">Sorrow is slack, and yet will never cease. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108770" who="A15517-sorrow">
          <speaker>Sor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108780">When sorrow ceaseth, Shame shall then begin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108790">With those that wallow senseless in their sin:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108800">But ladies I have drawn you from my den,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108810">To open air to mitigate some moan. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108820">Conscience, sit down upon that sweating stone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108830">And let that flint (Love) serve thee for a seat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108840">And lady lucre, on that stone rest you. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108850">And ladies thus I leave you here alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108860">Mourn ye, but moan not, I shall absent be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e108870">Yet good it were sometime to think on me.<stage xml:id="A15517-e108880">Exit</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108890" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108900">Comfort it is to think on sorrow past.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108910" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108920">Sorrow remains when joy is but a blast.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108930" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108940">A blast of wind is world's felicity,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108950" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108960">A blasting wind and full of misery.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108970" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e108980">O conscience, thou hast most tormented me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e108990" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109000">Me hath thy worm oh conscience, stung too deep.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109010" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109020">But more myself my thoughts tormented have</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109030">Than both of you in sorrows sullen cave. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109040"><pb facs="13"/>From whence drawn forth I find but little rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109050">A seat uneasy, wet, and scalding hot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109060">On this hard stone hath sorrow me assigned,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109070" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109080">And on my seat myself I frozen find. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109090">No flint more hard, no ice more cold than this. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109100" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109110">I think my seat some mineral stone to be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109120">I could from it, it draws heat from me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109130">Lady's consent, and we our seats will view. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109140" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109150">Dare we for shame our stained faces show.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109160" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109170">My double face is single grown again.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109180" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109190">My spots are gone, my skin is smooth and plain.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109200" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109210">Doff we our veils and greet this gladsome light. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109220">The chaser of glome sorrows heavy might. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109230" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109240">Haile cheerful air and clearest crystal sky.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109250" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109260">Haile shining sun and fairest firmament,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109270">Comfort to those that time in woe have spent. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109280" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109290">Upon my weeping stone is set remorse in brazen letters.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109300" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109310">And on this flint in lead is charity. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109320" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109330">In golden letters on my stone is care. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109340" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109350">Then lucre fits upon the stone of care.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109360" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre,</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109370">And conscience on the marble of remorse,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109380" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109390">Love on the flint of frozen charity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109400">Ladies alas, what tattered souls are we? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109410" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109420">Sorrow our hearts, and time our clothes hath torn</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109430" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109440">Then sit we down like silly souls forlorn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109450">And hide our faces that we be not known,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109460">For sorrow's plagues tormented me no more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109470">Than will their fight that knew me heretofore. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109480" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109490">Then will their sight that knew us heretofore</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109500">Draw ruth and help from them for our relief:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109510" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109520">For our relief? for conscience and for love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109530">No help, small ruth that our distress may move:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109540" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109550">O conscience thou wouldst lead me to despair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109560">But that I see the way to hope is fair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109570">And hope to heaven directs a ready way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109580">And heaven to help is pressed, to them that pray. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109590" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109600">That pray with faith, and with unfeigned remorse</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109610">For true belief and tears make prayer of force:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109620" who="A15517-conscience">
          <pb facs="13"/>
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109630">Then ●eile ourselves, and silent let us stay, till heavens shall please to send some friends this way:<stage xml:id="A15517-e109640">Sit all dow●</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109650" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109660">Ladies unmasked, blush not for base attire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109670">Here are none but friends and servants all, dear lady lucre,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109680">Dearer unto us than daily breath we draw from sweetest air;</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109690">Dearer than life, dearer than heaven itself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109700">Deign to discover those alluring lamps,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109710">Those lovely eyes more clear than Venus' star,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109720">Whose bright aspects worlds wonder do produce,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109730">Unveil I say that, beauty more divine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109740">Than nature (Save in thee) did ever paint:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109750">That we sworn slaves unto our mistress, may</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109760">Once more behold those stately lovely looks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109770">And do those duties which us well beseems,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109780">Such duties as we all desire to do. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109790" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109800">I know that tongue Lucre, beware of fraud. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109810" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109820">Of fraud? Indeed by speech it should be he. Fra. what seekest thou</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109830" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109840">Lucre, to honour thee with wit, with worth, with life, with all I have, to be thy servant as I was before, to get thee clothes, and what thou wantest else.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109850" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109860">No fraud, farewell, I must be won no more, to keep such servants as I kept before.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109870" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Simo.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109880">Sweet lady Lucre, me thou mayest accept.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109890" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109900">How art thou called?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109910" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Simo.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109920">Simon. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109930" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109940">I? No, sir, conscience saith.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109950" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109960">No lucre, now beware, false not thy faith,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e109970">For simony's subject to perpetual curse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e109980" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e109990">As you two have sped, I would desire to speed no worse,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110000" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110010">Make you a suit, you may chance to speed better:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110020" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110030">Not I, for of all, my tongue is best known,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110040">But if I speak, it shall be to her that was once mine own:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110050">Good lady love, thou little knowest the grief</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110060">That I thy friend sustain for thy distress,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110070">And less believest what care I have of thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110080">Look up good love, and to supply thy wants,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110090">Ask what thou wilt, and thou shalt have of me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110100">Of me that joy more in thy liberty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110110"><pb facs="14"/> than in this life our light that comforts me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110120" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110130">O gall in honey, serpent in the grass,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110140">Oh bifold fountain of two bitter streams,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110150">Dissimulation fed with viper's flesh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110160">Whose words are oiled, whose deeds the darts of death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110170">Thy tongue I know, that tongue that me be guiled,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110180">Thyself a devil, madest me a monster vild. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110190">From thee well known, well may I bless myself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110200">Dear bought repentance bids me shun thy snare. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110210" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110220">O happy love, if now thou can beware.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110230" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110240">Marry, but hear ye motley-beard, I think this blindfold buzzardly hedge-wench spoke to ye, she knows ye though she see ye not, hark ye, you women, if you'll go to the alehouse, I'll bestow two pots on ye, and we'll get a pair of cards and some company, and win twenty pots more, for you play the best at a game called smelling of the four knaves that ever I saw.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110250" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110260">Four? soft, yet they have not smelled thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110270" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110280">No, I am one more than is in the deck, but you'll be smelled as soon as ye begin to speak, I'll see what they'll say to me: hear ye you women, wives, widows, maids, men's daughters, what shall I call ye? these four fellows (Hark ye, shall I call ye crafty knaves) make me believe that you are the three that were the three fair ladies of London. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110290" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110300">Gentle simplicity we are unhappy they.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110310" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110320">Now ye bad fellows, which of ye had such a word as gentle fir● ▪</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110330" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110340">Bad fellows ye rascal? If ere you bring me pawn I'll pinch ye for that word.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110350" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110360">I cry you mercy m. injury, m. usury I meant not you,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110370" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110380">If you mean us, we may be even with ye too.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110390" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110400">Tut, I knew you an ostler, and a thief beside, you have rubbed my horse heels ere now for all your pri●e: but ladies, if ye be the thrée ladies, which of ye dwelled in Kent street? one of ye did, but I know not which is she, ye look all so like broom-wenches, I was once her servant, I'll ne'er be ashamed of her though I be rich, and I she be poor, yet if she that hath been my dame, or he that hath been my master come in place, I'll speak to them sure, I'll do my duty, which is lady Consc?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110410" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110420">Even I am she simplicity. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110430" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110440">I am glad ye are out of prison, I thought ye had forgotten me,<pb facs="14"/> I went a-begging from you till the beadles snapped me up, now I am free and keep a stall of ballads, I may buy and sell, I would you had as good a gown now as I carried once of yours to pawn to usury here.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110450" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110460">Gramercy good ●imp wilt thou be with me now?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110470" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110480">No I thank you heartily, I'll beg no more, I can not be with ye though I would for I am married to painful penury: look now my proud stately masters, I may if I will, and you would if ye might.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110490" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110500">No, not dwell with such a beggar as conscience. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110510" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110520">No, fraud ne'er loved conscience since he was an ostler.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110530" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110540">Who cares for conscience but dies a beggar?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110550" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110560">That will not usury do, he will first take 3. score pound in the hundred.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110570" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110580">Love, look on me and I will give thee clothes.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110590" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110600">I will no more by thee be so disguised.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110610" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110620">Ye do the wiser, for his face looks like a cloakback:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110630" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110640">In thy affections I had once a place:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110650" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110660">Those fond affections wrought me soul disgrace,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110670" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110680">I'll make amends, if ought amiss were done:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110690" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110700">Who once are burned, the fire will ever shun.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110710" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110720">And yet once burned to warm again may prove:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110730" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110740">Not at thy fire, I will be perfect love?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110750" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110760">I promise you the wenches have learned to answer wittily,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110770">Here's many fair proffers to lucre, and love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110780">But who clothes poor conscience, she may sit long enough. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110790" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e110800">I will clothe her straight:<stage xml:id="A15517-e110810">Usury takes fraud's cloak, and casts it on Cons</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110820" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110830">Will you master usury, that's honestly spoken. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110840">Ha, that's no gramercy to clothe her with another man's cloak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110850">But I see you have a craft in the doing m. usury,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110860">Usury covers conscience with fraud's cloak very cunningly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110870" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110880">Alas who loads my shoulders with this heavy weed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110890">Fie, how it stinks, this is perfumed indeed,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110900" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110910">Marry geppe goody conscience, indeed I do you wrong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110920">But I'll quickly right it, my cloak shall not cumber you long. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e110930" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110940">All this while lucre knows not I am here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110950">But now will I to her, mark how I speed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110960">Lady the fairest that nature ever formed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110970">Lodestone of love, that draws affections darts. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110980">The only object to all human eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e110990"><pb facs="15"/> and sole destred dainty of the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111000">Thy vassal here, a virtue in thy need</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111010">Whom thou by licence of the law mayst use,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111020">Tenders himself, and all his services</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111030">To do thy will in duty as to fore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111040">Glad of thy freedom as his proper life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111050" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e111060">Lady Lucre, you love an apple, take heed the caterpillar consume not your fruit.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111070" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e111080">Why who is it that maketh this latest suit?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111090" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e111100">'Tis usury. <stage xml:id="A15517-e111110">Aloud in her ear. </stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111120" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111130">Great is the service he hath done for me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111140">But usury now I may not deal with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111150" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e111160">The law allows me madam, in some sort.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111170" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e111180">But God and I would have thy bounds cut short.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111190" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111200">For you I reck not, but if God me hate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111210">Why doth the law allow me in some rate? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111220" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111230">Usury slanders both law and state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111240">The law allows not though it tolerate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111250">And thou art sure be shut out at heaven gate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111260" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e111270">You were ever nice, no matter what you pra●e:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111280" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e111290">Then it will be with him as it is at a great man's house in dinner time: he that knocks when the door is shut comes too late,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111300" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111310">Well usury, fraud, and simony</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111320">Dissimulation hearken unto me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111330">My tongue (Although in memory it be green)</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111340">Cannot declare what horrors I have seen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111350">He can it enter into mortal ears</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111360">Unmortified: the furies, fires and fears.</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111370">The shrieks, the groans, the tortures and the pains,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111380">That any soul for each of you sustains. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111390">No pen can write, how conscience hath me scourged. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111400">When with your faults my soul she ever urged:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111410">Arithmetic doth fail to number all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111420">The plagues of sorrow in the den of thrall:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111430">Then tempt me not, nor trouble me no more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111440">I must not use you as I did before,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111450">If you be found within fair London's gate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111460">You must to prison, whence we came of late. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111470"><pb facs="15"/>Conscience will accuse ye if ye be in sight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111480" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e111490">That scurvy conscience works us all the spite:</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e111500">Enter Nemo,</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111510" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e111520">Well lucre, yet in thee we have delight.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111530" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e111540">Yonder come some, we must take our flight. <stage xml:id="A15517-e111550">Exeunt omnes</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111560" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e111570">Birds of a feather will fly together, but when they be taken then are they baken, yonder comes a customer, I'll to my stall:</p>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e111580">Love, Lucre, and conscience, blindman buff to you all.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111590" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111600">Conscience, love, Lucre, ladies all what cheer? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111610">How do ye like the seats you sit upon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111620" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111630">O pure unspotted Nemo sole paragon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111640">Of love, of conscience and perfection,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111650">The marble of remorse I sit upon</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111660">Sweats scalding drops, like bitter brinish tears. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111670" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111680">So should remorse when conscience feels her gilt</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111690">But gentle love how feelest thou thy flint? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111700" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111710">O sharp and cold, I freeze unto my seat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111720">The flint holds fire, and yet I feel no heat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111730">But am benumbed and frozen every joint. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111740" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111750">O love, so cold is charity in these times:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111760">Lucre, how sit you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111770" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111780">Upon a heavy stone, not half so cold, not half so hot as theirs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111790">But of some secret power, for I do find and sensibly I feel,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111800">That I from it exhale an earthly cold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111810">And it from me doth draw a kindly heat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e111820" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111830">Such force hath care of lucre in itself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111840">To cool the heart and draw the vital spirits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111850">And such the true condition of you thrée:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111860">Remorse of conscience, charity of love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111870">And care of lucre, such your uses be:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111880">But ladies now your sorrow lay aside,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111890">Frolic fair dames, an unexpected good</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111900">Is imminent through me unto you all:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111910">Thrée lords there be your native countrymen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111920">In London bred, as you yourselves have been. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111930">Which covet you for honourable wives,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111940">And presently will come to visit you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111950"><pb facs="16"/> be not abashed at your base attire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111960">I shall provide you friends to deck you all. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111970">If I command, stand up, else sit you still. <stage xml:id="A15517-e111980">Enter the 3. Lords. </stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e111990">Lo, where they come: my lords the dames be here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112000" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112010">Why are they wimpled? shall they not unmask theme</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112020" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112030">It is for your sake, for policy they do it:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112040" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112050">Much may their fortune and their feature be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112060">But what it is we cannot thus discern. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112070" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112080">You shall in time lord pomp, be yet consent.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112090" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112100">Their same is more than cause or reason would,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112110">May one of these be pleasures paragon? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112120" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112130">Pleasure, be pleased and use no prejudice. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112140">Madames stand up, mislike not their attire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112150">That shall be mended as your selved desire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112160" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112170">Their port, and their proportion well contented.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112180" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112190">Right stately dames, if they were well attired:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112200" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112210">May we not see their beauty what it is?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112220" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112230">Yes lordings yes, lucre, lift up thy veil.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112240" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112250">Of beauty excellent.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112260" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112270">Of rare perfection.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112280" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112290">A dainty face.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112300" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112310">Unmask love. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112320" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112330">Sweet love indeed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112340" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112350">A lovely face.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112360" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112370">A gallant grace.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112380" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112390">Conscience, uncover.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112400" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112410">Beauty divine.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112420" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112430">A face angelical.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112440" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112450">Sweet creature of the world.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112460" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112470">Enough for once, ladies sit down again:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112480">As cunning chapmen do by curious wares,<stage xml:id="A15517-e112490">To the audience</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112500">Which seldom shown do most inflame the mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112510">So must I deal, being dainty of these dames,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112520">Who seldom seen shall best allure these lords:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112530">A while my lords, I leave you with these thrée,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112540">Converse, confer on good conditions,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112550">I will right soon return with such good friends</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112560">As it concerns to clothe these dainty ones</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112570"><pb facs="16"/> if any in my absence visit them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112580">Know their intent, and use your skill therein.<stage xml:id="A15517-e112590">Exit</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112600" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112610">Ladies, to call to mind your former lives</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112620">Were to recount your sorrows on a row,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112630">Omitting then what you have been or be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112640">What you may be I'll speak, so it please you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112650">Wives to us thrée, ladies to London lords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112660">Pomp, pleasure policy, men of such regard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112670">As shall you guard from evil, once matched with us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112680">And policy presents this good to you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112690" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112700">With London's pomp may one of you be joined,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112710">Possessing more than fortune can afford,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112720">Fortune's a fool, but heavenly providence</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112730">Guards London's pomp, and her that shall be his:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112740" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112750">And London's pleasure, peerless in delights,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112760">Will deign to make one of these dames his own,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112770">Who may with him in more contentment live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112780">Than ever did the Queen of Aethiop. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112790" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112800">Though silence lords, our modesty enforce,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112810">Nemo can tell the secrets of our thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112820">Nemo that women's minds can constant keep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112830">He shall for us you answer good my lords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112840">I speak for all, though ill beseeming me. <stage xml:id="A15517-e112850">Enter falsehood and doub. dealing</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112860" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112870">You speak but well: my lord's step we aside</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112880">To note these fellows, what they do intend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112890" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e112900">Nemo can tell, for he doth follow them. <stage xml:id="A15517-e112910">Enter Nemo.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112920" who="A15517-falsehood">
          <speaker>Falsehood</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112930">Ladies to you, to some of you, we come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112940">Sent from such friends as much affect your good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112950">With garments, and with compliments of cost</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112960">Accordant well to dames of such degree: I come to lucre. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e112970" who="A15517-unassigned">
          <speaker>D. dea.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112980">I to love am sent with no less cost than could be got for coin</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e112990">Which with my message I deliver would,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113000">Could I discern which of these dames were she,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113010" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113020">Friend, I am love, what bringest thou there to me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113030" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113040">Beware good love, from whom and what thou takest.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113050" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113060">No whispering friend, but show it openly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113070">The matter good, you need not be ashamed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113080"><pb facs="17"/> from whom comest thou? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113090" who="A15517-unassigned">
          <speaker>D. dea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113100">That I conceal from any but from love,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113110" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113120">From whom come you sir?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113130" who="A15517-falsehood">
          <speaker>Falsehood</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113140">That shall lucre know, and none but she.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113150" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113160">Then speak aloud, for whispering here is barred.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113170" who="A15517-falsehood">
          <speaker>Falsehood</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113180">Then neither will I do nor speak at all.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113190" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113200">Then I will speak and tell what you are both,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113210">Thyself art falsehood, and art sent from fraud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113220">To compass lucre with a cloak of craft,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113230">With lawn of lies, and call of golden guile. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113240" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113250">Pack you my friend, for if you stay a while</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113260">You shall return no more to him that sent you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113270" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113280">Thou from dissimulation art sent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113290">And bringest a gown of glozing, lived wish lust,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113300">A vardingale of vain boast, and fan of flattery,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113310">A ruff of riot, and a cap of pride,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113320">And double dealing is thy name and office both. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113330" who="A15517-unassigned">
          <speaker>D. dea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113340">Falsehood, let's go, we are deciphered.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113350" who="A15517-falsehood">
          <speaker>Falsehood</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113360">Lucre, thou losest here a princely gift. <stage xml:id="A15517-e113370">Exeunt ambo</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113380" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113390">Lucre censumes being won by fraud or shift,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113400">Thus lords you see how these are qualified,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113410">And how these ladies shun that sharp rebuke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113420">Which some deserve by taking of such toys,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113430">As women weak are tempted soon with gifts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113440">But here they come that must these ladies deck.</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113450">Lucre, arise, come from the stone of care:</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e113460">Enter honest industry, pure zeal, and sincerity. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113470" who="A15517-industry">
          <speaker>Ho. Indust.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113480">Fair lucre, lo what honest industry</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113490">To thee hath brought, to deck thy dainty self,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113500">Lucre by honest industry achieved</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113510">Shall prosper, flourish, and continue long,<stage xml:id="A15517-e113520">Exit Lucre with ho. Industrie.</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113530">Come to thy chamber to attire thee there. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113540" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113550">Thou mayest depart with honest industry. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113560" who="A15517-unassigned">
          <speaker>P. zeal.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113570">And love arise from charity's cold flint,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113580">Pure zeal hath purchased robes to cover love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113590">Whiles love is single, zeal shall her attire</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113600">With kind affection, mortifying lust,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113610"><pb facs="17"/> come love with me these garments to put on:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113620" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113630">Love, follow zeal and take his ornaments. <stage xml:id="A15517-e113640">Exit love with p. zeal</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113650" who="A15517-sincerity">
          <speaker>Sincerity</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113660">Rise conscience from that marble of remorse,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113670">That weeping stone that scalds thy parched skin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113680">Sincerity such robes for thee hath brought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113690">As best beseems good conscience to adorn:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113700">Come follow, that thou mayst go put them on,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113710">For conscience clothed by sincerity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113720">Is armed well against the enemy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113730" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113740">Follow him Consc. fear not, thou art right. <stage xml:id="A15517-e113750">Exit Con. with Si●</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113760" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113770">Most reverend Nemo thanks for this good sight, lucre is clothed by honest industry. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113780" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113790">Love by pure zeal. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113800" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113810">And conscience by sincerity. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113820" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113830">Lordings, thus have you seen them at the first,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113840">And thus you see them, trust me, at the worst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113850">Depart we now, come hence a day or two,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113860">And see them decked as dainty ladies should,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113870">And make such choice as may content you all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113880" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113890">Thanks righteous Nemo we the London lords</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e113900">Only to thee ourselves acknowledge bound. <stage xml:id="A15517-e113910">Exeunt omnes</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e113920">Enter painful penury and simplicity. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113930" who="A15517-penury">
          <speaker>Penury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113940">Come on gentle husband, let us lay our heads together, our purses together, and our reckonings together, to see whether we win or lose, thrive or not, go forward or backward, do you keep a book or a score?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113950" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113960">A score wife? you mean for the alehouse, do you not? I would have her examine me thereof no further, for I am in too far there, more than I would she should know.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113970" who="A15517-penury">
          <speaker>Pen.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e113980">I mean no alehouse score, but a note of your wares, let me see, first you began to set up with a royal, how much money have ye? what ware, and what gain?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e113990" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114000">I have five shillings in money, two shillings in wares, or thereabouts, and I owe two shillings and eight pence upon the score, how much is that? five shillings, two shillings, and two shillings and eight pence.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114010" who="A15517-penury">
          <speaker>Penury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114020">That is nine shillings and eight pence, so we are worse by a<pb facs="18"/> a groat then when we began, well once again I'll set ye up, here is four groats I have got by bearing water this week, make up your stock, and run no more behind ▪ who comes here?</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e114030">Enter fraud like an artificer.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114040" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114050">What lack ye? What do ye lack?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114060" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114070">Me lacke da moons pour de frene very seen Franche knack da feene gold buttoone, de brave bugla lace, a da feene gold ring, you be free man, me un 'Fortiner, you buy a me beware, you gain ten pound by lay out ten shelleng●.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114080" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114090">Wife, what hard luck have we that cannot make x. shillings now to gain x. pound: why, x. pound would set us up for ever.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114100" who="A15517-penury">
          <speaker>Penury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114110">Husband see the ware, and if ten shilling will buy it, it shall go hard but we will make that money: friend, show my husband your wares</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114120" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114130">Look you dear mastra de seen button de la gold, de ring de gold, de bugla sheane, two shelleng une dozen de button, une shellinga une ring, 'tis worth x, shelleng, but mastra and matressa me mussa make money to go over in my own country, but me loose teen● pound pour haste to go next tide or tomorrow.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114140" who="A15517-penury">
          <speaker>Penury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114150">Here is five shillings buy them of this stranger.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114160" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114170">Friend you have not stolen them, but you make them, well, I'll buy them i'the open market, and then I care not, here is ten shillings, deliver me the wares.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114180" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114190">Dear mastra, o pouer necessity maka me selpour grand, grand loss, you shall gein x. pound at least, gour boy.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114200" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114210">What's your name?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114220" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114230">Mechant, I think I am even with ye now for calling me ostler, you'll thrive well with such bargains, if ye buy, ye know not what, fraud hath fitted ye with worse than your ballads.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114240" who="A15517-penury">
          <speaker>Penury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114250">You'll warrant them gold sirrah,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114260" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114270">We, so good goll as you pay for: adieu monster. <stage xml:id="A15517-e114280">Exit.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114290" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114300">Adieu monster: adieu fool, sell such gold buttons and rings for so little money, good lord what pennyworths these strangers can afford: now wife let me see, x. pound, when we have ten pound, we'll have a large shop, and sell all manner of wares, and buy more of these, and get ten pound more, and then ten pound, and ten pound, and twenty pound, than thou shalt have a taffeta hat and a guarded gown, and I a gown and a new cap, and a stik doublet, and a fair house.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114310" who="A15517-penury">
          <pb facs="18"/>
          <speaker>Pen.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114320">I thank ye husband, well, till then look well to your wares, and I'll ply my water-bearing and save and get, and get and save till we be rich, but bring these wares home every night with ye:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114330" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114340">Tush, I shall sell them afore night for ten pound, go wife, go, I may tell you I am glad this French fellow came with these wares, we had fallen to eramining the ale-score else, and then we had fallen cut, and the ale wife and my wife had scolded: well, a man may see, he that's ordained to be rich, shall be rich: go woman.<stage xml:id="A15517-e114350">Exeunt</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e114360">Enter Nemo and the three lords, as though they had been chiding. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114370" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114380">From whence good lords grew this hot argument?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114390" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114400">Thou knowest already, yet if thou wilt hear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114410">For this we strive: fond pleasure makes account</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114420">Summing his bills without an auditory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114430">That lady Lucre ought of right be his. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114440" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114450">So I affirm, and so I will maintain</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114460">That lady Lucre ought of right be his. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114470" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114480">So I affirm, and so I will maintain</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114490">That pleasure ought by right dame Lucre have,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114500">To bear the charge of sports and of delights. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114510" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114520">Nay to support the haughty magnificence</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114530">And lordly pomp of London's excellence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114540">Befits it rather lucre join with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114550">By whom her honour shall be most advanced. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114560" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114570">More fit for pomp than pleasure, but most fit</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114580">That policy with lucre should be matched,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114590">As guerdon of my studies and my cares</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114600">And high employments in the common wealth:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114610" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114620">What pleasure can be fostered without cost:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114630" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom,</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114640">What pomp or port without respect of gaine●</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114650" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114660">What policy without preferment lives?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114670" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114680">Pleasure must have lucre:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114690" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114700">Pomp hath need of lucre:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114710" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114720">Policy merits lucre:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114730" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114740">Pleasure dies without lucre,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114750" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom,</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114760">Pomp decays without lucre,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114770" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114780">Policy droops without lucre:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114790" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114800">Thus lords you show your imperfections:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114810"><pb facs="19"/> subject to passions, straining honours bounds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114820">Be well advised, you promised to be ruled,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114830">And have those dames, by me disposed to you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114840">But since I see that human humours oft</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114850">Makes men forgetful of their greater good. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114860">Be here a while, dame lucre shall be brought</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114870">By me, to choose which lord she liketh best,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114880">So you allow her choice with patience. <stage xml:id="A15517-e114890">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114900" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114910">Go, we abide thy doom till thy return,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114920" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114930">If lucre be not mad she will be mine,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114940" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e114950">If she regard her good she will be mine.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114960" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114970">If she love happy life, she will be mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e114980">Women love pleasure. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e114990" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115000">Women love pomp. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115010" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115020">Women use policy: and here she comes that must decide the doubt.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e115030">Enter Nemo with conscience all in white.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115040" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115050">Conscience content thee with a quaint conceit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115060">Conceal thy name to work a special good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115070">Thou art not known to any of these lords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115080">By face or feature, till they hear thy name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115090">Which must be lucre for a fine device,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115100">And conscience clear indeed's the greatest gain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115110">Lo, lordings here fair lucre whom ye love:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115120">Lucre, the choice is left unto thyself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115130">Which of these three thou wilt for husband choose. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115140" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115150">The modesty that doth our sex beseem</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115160">Forbids my tongue therein to tell my thought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115170">But may it please my lords to pardon me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115180">Which of you three shall deign to make such choice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115190">Him shall I answer to his own content,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115200" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115210">If lucre please to match with policy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115220">She shall be mistress over many men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115230" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115240">If lucre like to match with London's pomp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115250">In stately port all others she shall pass. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115260" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115270">If pleasure may for wife fair lucre gain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115280">Her life shall be an earthly paradise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115290" who="A15517-nemo">
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115300">Lo, lucre, men, and port, and pleasant life</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115310">Are here propounded, which wilt thou accept? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115320" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115330">Lord policy, love were the only choice</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115340">Methinks for you, that all your cares employ</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115350">And studies for the love of common wealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115360">For you lord pleasure, conscience were a wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115370">To measure your delights by reason's rule,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115380">In recreation conscience help to use. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115390" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115400">Were conscience half so sweet as is thyself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115410">Her would I seek with suits and services. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115420" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115430">No less accomplished in perfection</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115440">Is conscience, than this lady I protest,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115450" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115460">But on this dame hath pleasure fixed his heart,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115470">And this or death the period of his love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115480" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115490">Lucre with pomp most aptly might combine</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115500" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115510">Lucre, or love if case thou wilt be mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115520">Let pass thy name, thyself do I desire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115530">Thee will I have except thyself deny,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115540">With thee to live ▪ or else for thee to die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115550" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115560">What if I deny?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115570" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115580">Then will I have her.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115590" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115600">If we deny?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115610" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115620">So much the rather.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115630" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115640">The rather in despight of us? Not so.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115650" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115660">My lords, no quarrel, let this lady go,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115670">And if ye trust me. I'll content ye both,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115680">Pleasure, this is not lucre:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115690" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115700">She's lucre unto me: but be she love or conscience, this is she.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115710" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115720">Whom you will, have?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115730" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115740">Spite of the devil, I will.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115750" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115760">Must it not be my lord if I agree?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115770" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115780">Agree.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115790" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115800">Some further proof it fits of you to see:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115810" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115820">Receive a pawn, my heart, my hand, and oath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115830">To be thy own in love, in faith, and troth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115840" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115850">Thus you are fast, and yet myself am free:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115860" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115870">I know in ruth thou wilt me not refuse:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115880" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115890">I know not that, but other I'll not choose.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115900" who="A15517-nemo">
          <pb facs="20"/>
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115910">It is enough, lord pleasure, do not fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115920">Conscience will use you as becomes her best. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115930" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115940">And art thou conscience? welcomer to me than either love or lucre,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115950" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e115960">God send grace I be,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e115970" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115980">My lords be pleased, ere long shall you be sped,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e115990">As much to your contents as pleasure is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116000">Say but the word ▪ myself shall soon present</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116010">Lucre and love, well worthy such as you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116020" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e116030">Right thankfully those favours we'll receive,</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e116040">Enter Diligence, in haste</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116050" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116060">My lords, if your affairs in present be not great</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116070">Greater than any, save regard of life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116080">Yea even the greatest of the common wealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116090">Prepare ye to withstand a stratagem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116100">Such as this land nor London ever knew. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116110">The Spanish forces lordings are prepared,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116120">In bravery and boast, beyond all bounds</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116130">T'invade, to win, to conquer all this land. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116140">They chiefly aim at London's stately pomp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116150">At London's pleasure, wealth and policy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116160">Intending to despoil her of them all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116170">And over all those lovely ladies three. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116180">Love, lucre, conscience, peerless of the rarest price.</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116190">To tyrannize and carry hardest hand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116200">From Spain they come with engine and intent</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116210">To slay, subdue, to triumph and torment:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116220">Myself (So heaven would) espial of them had,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116230">And diligence, dear lords, they call my name. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116240">If you vouchsafe to credit my report,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116250">You do me right, and to yourselves no wrong,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116260">Provided, that you arm you, being warned. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116270" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116280">Diligence, thy service shall be known,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116290">And well rewarded: Nemo, for a time</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116300">Conceal this dame, and live secure unseen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116310">Let us alone whom most it doth concern,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116320">To meet and match our ever weening foes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116330" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116340">Nemo keep close, and conscience pray for us.</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116350"><pb facs="20"/> been gone and recommend us to our god. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116360" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116370">My lords, if ever, show your honours now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116380">Those proud usurping Spanish tyrants come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116390">To reave from you what you do most regard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116400">To take away your credit and your fame.</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116410">To race and spoil our right renowned town:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116420">And if you love or lucre do regard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116430">Or have of conscience any kind of care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116440">The world shall witness by this action,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116450">And of the love that you to us pretend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116460">In this, your valour shall assurance give:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116470">More would I speak, but danger's in delay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116480">You know my mind, and heavens record my thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116490">When I with prayers for you will penetrate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116500">And will in heart be present in your fight:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116510">Now pleasure, show what you will do for me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116520" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e116530">I will be turned to pain for thy sweet sake.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116540" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116550">Fair conscience fear not, but assure thyself</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116560">What kind affection we soever bear</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116570">To love and lucre, in this action</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116580">Chiefly for thee our service shall be done. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116590" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e116600">For conscience' sake more than for lucre now,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116610" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e116620">For love and conscience, not despising lucre. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116630" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e116640">Only for conscience will I hazard all.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116650" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116660">And I from hence will her convey a space,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116670">Till you return with happy victory. <stage xml:id="A15517-e116680">Exeunt ne. And Con.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116690" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e116700">Farewell my lords, for me my lords, for me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116710" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e116720">Diligence, what number may there be?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116730" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116740">A mighty host, and chiefly led by three,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116750">Who brave it out in show, as men assured</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116760">Of victory, sans venture, or repulse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116770" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e116780">How near be they?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116790" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116800">So near my lords, that each delay is death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116810">Stand on your guard, they come as challengers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116820">To bruise your shields, and bear away your prize,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116830">Mounting the seas, and measuring the land</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116840">With strong imaginations of success,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e116850" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116860">Well, diligence go get in readiness</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116870"><pb facs="21"/> men and munition, bid our pages ply</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116880">To see that all our furniture be well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116890">W●t, wealth and will to further wars be fit,<stage xml:id="A15517-e116900">Exit Dil●●. </stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116910">My lords, I would I might advise ye now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116920">To carry as it were a careless regard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116930">Of these Castilians, and their accustomed bravado:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116940">Lord pomp, let nothing that's magnifical,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116950">Or that may tend to London's graceful state</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116960">Be unperformed. As shows and solemn feasts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116970">Watches in armour, triumphs, cresset-lightes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116980">Bonfires, bells, and peals of ordinance. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e116990">And pleasure, see that plays be published,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117000">May-games and masks, with mirth and minstrelsy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117010">Pageants and school-feastes ▪ bears, and puppet plays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117020">Myself will muster upon Mile-end green,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117030">As though we saw, and feared not to be seen:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117040">Which will their spies in such a wonder set,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117050">To see us reck so little such a foe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117060">Whom all the world admires, save only we:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117070">And we respect our sport more than his spite,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117080">That John the Spaniard will in rage run mad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117090">To see us bend like oaks with his vain breath. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117100" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117110">In this device such liking I conceive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117120">As London shall not lack what pomp can do,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117130">And well I know that worthy citizens</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117140">Do carry minds so frank and bountiful,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117150">As for their honour they will spare no cost:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117160">Especially, to let their enemy know. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117170">Honour in England, not in Spain doth grow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117180" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117190">And for the time that they in pleasure spend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117200">'Tis limited to such an honest end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117210">Namely, for recreation of the mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117220">With no great cost, yet liberal in that kind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117230">That pleasure vows with all delights he can</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e117240">To do them good, till death to be their man. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117250" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117260">Of policy they trial have at large:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117270" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117280">Then let us go and each man to his charge ▪</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e117290">Exeunt the three lords.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e117300"><pb facs="21"/>Enter simplicity led in by usury. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117310" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117320">Ay sir? Why alas I bought them of a stranger, an old French man for good gold, and to be worth ten pound, for so be told me, I have good witness, for my own wife was by, and lent me part of the money.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117330" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117340">And what did they cost you?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117350" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117360">Ten shillings every penny.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117370" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117380">That argues you are guilty: why? could ye buy so many rings and buttons of gold think ye for ten shillings? Of whom did ye buy them?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117390" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117400">Of an old French man, the old French disease take him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117410" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117420">And where dwells that old French man?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117430" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117440">In France I think, for he told me he was to go over the next tide, or the next day, my wife can tell as well as I, if ye think I lie, for she was by.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117450" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117460">A good answer, he dwells in France and you dwell here, and for uttering copper for gold you are like to lose both your ears upon the pillory, and besides lose your freedom.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117470" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117480">Nay, if I lose my ears, I care not for my freedom, keep you my freedom, so I may keep my ears, is there no remedy for this m. usury? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117490" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117500">None, except you can find out that old French man.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117510" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117520">Peradventure I can, if you'll let me go into France to seek him:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117530" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117540">So we may lose you, and never see him, nay that may not be.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117550" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117560">You have a good pawn there, good master usury be good unto me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117570" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117580">Nay, now I'll pinch ye, you villain, ye know how ye have ever used me, but now off goes your ears at least,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117590" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117600">Nay ▪ good master usury take all my goods and let me go,</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e117610">Enter ●raud, dissimulation, simony in canvas coats like sailors.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117620" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117630">What's the matter usury, that this poor knave cries so:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117640" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117650">O master fraud, speak to him to let me go:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117660" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117670">Fraud? Ye villain, call me not by my name, and ye shall see I will speak to him to let ye go free: usury, of all old fellowship let this<pb facs="22"/> poor knave pack, if the matter be not too heinous.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117680" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117690">No sir, his fault is odious, look here what stuff he would utter for gold, flat copper, and he saith, he bought them of an old Frenchman</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117700" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117710">But thou didst not sell them, didst thou?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117720" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117730">No sir, I would have but laid them to pawn for five pounds to him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117740" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117750">That was more than they be worth, I promise thee a foul matter, well, thou must lose thy ware and be glad to escape, so usury, at my request ye shall let the poor man go.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117760" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117770">Well, for this once I will, sirrah, get ye packing, and take heed of such a piece of work again while ye live.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117780" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117790">There is divers pieces of work in that box, pray ye give me some of my goods again, a ring or something.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117800" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117810">Not an inch, and be glad ye scape as ye do,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117820" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117830">Alas, I am undone, there's all the wealth and stock I have.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117840" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117850">Do ye long to lose your ears, be gone ye foolish knave.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117860" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117870">I thank ye master fraud: I'll not go so far, but I'll be near to hear and see what the meaning of these fellows in this canvas should be, for I know fraud, dissimulation, and simony to be those thrée: here I think I am unseen. <stage xml:id="A15517-e117880">Simplicity hides him near them.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117890" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117900">Usury, thank me for this good booty, for it is I that holy ye to it, for I should them to him for gold indeed in the shape of an old French artificer, come give me half for I deserve it, for my part was the first beginning of this comedy, I was ever afraid, lest the fool should have known me, for ye see now though disguised, he calm by my name.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117910" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117920">Did a so? I am glad I have found the French man, now I'll raise the street, but I'll have my wares again, and prove ye as ye were, ever both false knaves I believe. <stage xml:id="A15517-e117930">Exit sim.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117940" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117950">Kill him, stab him, out villain, he will betray us all.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117960" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117970">What a fool were you to speak before he was gone, now you have lost your part of this too, for he will go complain, you will be sought for, and I made to restore these things again.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e117980" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e117990">Not if thou be wise, thou wilt not tarry the reckoning, for seest thou not us three? Dissimulation simony and myself?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118000" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118010">Yes: what means these canvas suits? Will ye be sailors?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118020" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118030">Usury make one, this is our intent: let's see that none hear<pb facs="22"/> us now: the Spaniards are coming thou hearest with great power, here is no living for us in London, men are grown so full of conscience and religion, that fraud, dissimulation and simony are deciphered, and being deciphered are also despised: and therefore we will slip to the sea, and meet and join with the enemy, and if they conquer as they may, for they are a great army by report, our credit may rise again with them, if they fail and retire, we may either go with them and live in Spain, where we and such good fellows are tolerated and used, or come fitly again hither, so long as none knows but friends.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118040" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118050">But will you do thus you two?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118060" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118070">And thou too I hope, why, what should we do?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118080" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118090">Whatsoever ye do, be not traitors to your native country.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118100" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Simo.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118110">'Tis not our native country, thou knowest, I simony am a roman, dissimulation a mongrel, half an Italian, half a Dutchman fraud so too, half French, and half Scottish: and thy parents were both Jews, though thou wert born in London, and here usury thou art cried out against by the preachers: join with us man to better thy state, for in Spain preaching toucheth us not.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118120" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118130">To better my state, nay, to alter my state, for here where I am, I know the government, here can I live for all their threatening, if strangers prevail, I know not their laws nor their usage, they may been oppressor, and take all I have, and it is like they are so, for they seek that's not their own. Therefore here will I stay sure, to keep what I have, rather than be a traitor upon hap and had I wist: and stay you if ye be wise, and pray as I pray, that the preachers and all other good men may die, and then we shall flourish, but never trust to stranger's courtesy.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118140" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118150">We shall trust but to our friends and kin, you'll not go with us, yet for old acquaintance keep counsel, betray us not, for we'll be gone to sea, I am afraid then foolish knave have belayed the streets for us.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118160" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118170">Let me go afore ye, if any such thing be, I'll give ye inkling.<stage xml:id="A15517-e118180">Exit</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118190" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118200">Do, farewell usury: and as he goes one way, we'll go another, follow sirs, never trust a shrinker, if he be your own brother. <stage xml:id="A15517-e118210">Exeunt omnes.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e118220">Enter the three lords with their pages and fealty a Herald before them, his coat having the arms of London before. and an olive tree behind. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118230" who="A15517-policy">
          <pb facs="23"/>
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118240">Fealty, thou faithful herald of our town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118250">Thou true truce-kéeper, and sure friend in peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118260">Take down our shields, and give them to our boys:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118270">Now fealty, prepare thy wits for war,<stage xml:id="A15517-e118280">He delivers them</stage></l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118290">To parley with the proud Castillians</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118300">Approaching fast the frontiers of our coast:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118310">Wit, here, my page in every message shall</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118320">Attend on thee, to note them and their deeds:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118330">I need not tell thee, they are poor and proud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118340">Vaunters, vainglorious, tyrants, truce-breakers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118350">Envious, ireful, and ambitious,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118360">For thou hast found their facing and their brags,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118370">Their backs, their coffers, and their wealth, their rag●,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118380">But let me tell thee what we crave of thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118390">To scan with judgement what their leaders be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118400">To note their presence and observe their grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118410">And truly to advertise what they seem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118420">Whether to be experienced in arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118430">Or men of name those three that led the rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118440">The rest refer we to thy own conceit,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118450" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Feal,</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118460">I hope in this my duty to discharge, as heretofore</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e118470">Simplicity, make a great noise within, and enter with three or four weaponed.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118480" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118490">Clubs, clubs, nay come neighbours come, for here they be, here I left them, arrant thieves, rogues, cozeners, I charge ye as you will answer, prebend them, for they have undone me, and robbed me, and made me the poorest free man that ever kept a ballad stall:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118500" who="A15517-constable">
          <speaker>A constable,</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118510">I charge ye keep the peace and lay down your weapons:<stage xml:id="A15517-e118520">To the three lords.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118530" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pomp,</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118540">Who raised this tumult? Speak, what means this stir?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118550" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118560">O I am undone, robbed, spoiled of all my stock, let me see, where be they? Keep every street and door, 'samine all that comes for fraud that cozener.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118570" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118580">Masters, what mean you in these troublous times to keep this coil?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118590" who="A15517-constable">
          <speaker>Const,</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118600">Alas my lord, here's a poor man robbed, or cozened.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118610" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <pb facs="23"/>
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118620">I am robbed oh my boys, my pretty boys, I am undone, saw ye no thieves, nor no crafty knaves, what be all these?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118630" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118640">Simplicity, away, these be our lords, offend them not for fear.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118650" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118660">I seek not them, I seek for fraud that robbed me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118670" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118680">Go seek else where, for here's no place for such.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118690" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118700">My friends depart, and qualify this stir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118710">And see peace kept within the walls I charge ye. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118720" who="A15517-constable">
          <speaker>Const.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118730">I will my lord, come</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118740" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118750">We came too late to find your losses. <stage xml:id="A15517-e118760">Exeunt.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118770" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118780">Pray for me my boys, I think I shall hang myself I come ever too late to speed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118790" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118800">Now lords, let honour's fire inflame on? thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118810">And let us arm our courage with our cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118820">And so dispose ourselves to welcome them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118830">Do me the favour (If I may entreat)</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118840">To be the first to front the foe in face,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118850">The vanguard let be policies this once,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118860">Pomps the main battle pleasures the rearward:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118870">And so bestow us if you think it good. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118880" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118890">I think it good, and time that it were done.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118900" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e118910">I think it good, and wish the enemy come.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e118920">Enter Diligence. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e118930" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118940">And here they come, as brave as Philip's son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118950">And his Ephestion, wont to be arrayed</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118960">In glittering gold, and party coloured plumes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118970">With curious pendents on their lances exit,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118980">Their shields impressed with gilt copertiments,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e118990">Their pages careless, playing at their backs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119000">As if with conquest they triumphing came. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119010" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119020">If they be conquered greater is their shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119030">But diligence go post alongst the coast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119040">To tell the news, and look to welcome them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119050">Let us alone: my lords you hear the news,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119060">More words were vain, I know ye well resolved. <stage xml:id="A15517-e119070">Exit Dil.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119080" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e119090">And here they come, o proud Castillians.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e119100"><pb facs="24"/>Enter first Shealty the herald: then pride, bearing his shield himself, his impreze, a peacock: the word, non par illi his page shame after him with a lance, having appendent gilt, with this word in it, sur lé ciel, ambition, his impreze, a black horse salliant, with one hinder foot upon the globe of the earth, one for● foot stretching towards the clouds, his word, non sufficit orbis: his page treachery after him, his pendent argent and azure, an armed a●me catching at the sun beams, the word in it, et gloriam phoebi. Last, tyranny, his impreze, a naked child on a spear's point bleeding, his word, pour sangue, his page, terror, his pendent ●uless, in it, a tiger's head out of a cloud, licking a bloody heart: the word in it, cura cruor. March once about the stage, then stand and view the lords of London, who shall march towards them, and they give back, then the lords of London wheel about to their standing, and th'other come again into their places, then policy sends fealty: their herraldes coat must have the arms of Spain before, and a burning ship behind. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119110" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119120">My lords, what mean these gallants to perform,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119130">Come these Castilian cowards but to brave? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119140">Do all these mountains move to breed a mouse? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119150">Fealty, go fetch their answer resolute</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119160">How they dare be so bold, and what they dare do here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119170" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e119180">What wouldst thou herald? <stage xml:id="A15517-e119190">As feal is going towards them, they send forth Sheal.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119200" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Fea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e119210">Parley with those thrée, herald.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119220" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e119230">They scorn to grace so mean a man as thou with parley or with presence.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119240" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Fea:</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119250">Do they scorn? what, are thy masters, monarchs every one? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119260">Or be they gods? or rather be they devils? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119270">Scorn they a herald's presence and his speech? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119280">Name them, that I may know their mightiness,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119290">And so avoid of duties some neglect. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119300" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119310">Monarchs in minds, and gods in high conceits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119320">That scorn you English, as the scum of men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119330">Whom I ne dare without their licence name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119340">Fore whom thy duties all are few and base,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119350" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Fea.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119360">Imperious Spaniard, do a herald right. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119370"><pb facs="24"/>Thyself art one, their trowch man if thou be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119380">Be thou my trunk, that I my message may</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119390">Through thee convey to them from London lords. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119400" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119410">Base English groom, from beggars sent belike,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119420">Who for their mate thee malapert account,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119430">Dare I (Thinkst thou) these lords magnificent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119440">Without their special pleasure understood,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119450">Once move with message, or with show of speech? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119460" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Fea.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119470">More servile thou to lose a herald's due,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119480">That is in field a King's companion,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119490">But if thou dare not my ambassage do,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119500">Stand by and stop not my access to them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119510" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e119520">Rather will I return and know their minds.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119530" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e119540">Now boy, what news. <stage xml:id="A15517-e119550">When Sheal goes to them, wit goes to the 3. Lords of lond.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119560" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit,</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119570">The fearful herald of yon famous crew</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119580">Durst not your message to his masters tell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119590">Till fealty with contumelious words,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119600">(Yet was the Spaniard brave and hot in terms)</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119610">Enforced him for their answer resolute. <stage xml:id="A15517-e119620">The span. whisper with their her.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119630" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119640">Which now belike our herald shall receive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119650">For theirs comes to him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119660" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Sheal.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119670">It pleaseth them to be magnifical,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119680">And of their special graces to vouchsafe</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119690">And counterview of pages, and of shields. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119700">A countermessage by us heralds done:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119710">A favour which they seldom grant to foes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119720">Go thou for those, I meet thee will with these. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119730" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Fea.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119740">My lords then braving Spaniards wish</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119750">A counterview of pages and of shields,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119760">But what they mean or be I know not yet:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119770">Haply you may by their ymprezes view,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119780">Or I by parley some conjecture give,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119790">So please it you your pages and your shields</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119800">With me to send, their herald comes with theirs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119810" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e119820">Our shields I reck not, but to send our wealth</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119830" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Feal.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e119840">Accompanied with wit and will, no peril.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119850" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119860">It is my wealth, but keep him if they dare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119870">I'll fetch him double if they do my lords,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119880" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <pb facs="25"/>
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e119890">Boys, take our shields and spears, for they come on.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119900" who="A15517-wit">
          <speaker>Wit.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e119910">Vail Spaniard, couch thy lance and pendent both, knowest where thou art? Here will we bear no braves</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e119920">When the English boys meet the other, cause them to put down the tops of their lances, but they bear up theirs.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119930" who="A15517-wealth">
          <speaker>Wea.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119940">Down with your point, no loft born lances here</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119950">By any stranger be he foe or friend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119960" who="A15517-will">
          <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119970">Well dost thou note the couching of thy lance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e119980">Mine had ere this else gored your Spanish skin. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e119990" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Feal.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e120000">Well done my boys, but now all reverence.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120010" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e120020">Advance again your lances now my boys<stage xml:id="A15517-e120030">Hold up again</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120040" who="A15517-pride">
          <speaker>S. pride.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e120050">Dicito nobis ideo qui ades, quid sibi velint isthaec emblemata? Dicito (Inquam) lingua materna: nos enim omnes belle intelligimus, quamuis anglicè loqui dedignamur. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120060" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Fea.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120070">Then know Castillian cavalieroes this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120080">The owners of these emblems are three lords</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120090">Those three that now are viewing of your shields,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120100">Of London, our chief city are they lords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120110">Policy, pomp, and pleasure be their names:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120120">And they in honour of their mistresses,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120130">Love, Lucre, conscience, London ladies thrée,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120140">Emblazoned these scutcheons, challenging</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120150">Whom durst compare, or challenge one of them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120160">And policy a tortoise hath impressed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120170">Encompassed with her shell, her native walls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120180">And providens securus is his word:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120190">His page is wit, his mistress lady love.</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120200">Pomp in his shield a lily hath portrayed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120210">As paragon of beauty, and boon grace:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120220">Glory sans peer his word, and true it is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120230">With London's pomp Castille cannot compare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120240">His page is wealth, his mistress lucre hight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120250">Pleasure, the dainty of that famous town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120260">A falcon hath emblazoned, soaring high,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120270">To show the pitch that London's pleasure flies:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120280">His word pour temps, yet never stoops to train,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120290">But unto conscience, chosen for his dear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120300"><pb facs="25"/>His page is will, and thus th'effect you hear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120310" who="A15517-pride">
          <speaker>S. pride.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e120320">Buena bvena per los lutheranos angleses. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120330" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Fea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e120340">Mala, mala per catholicos castillianos. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120350" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e120360">Loqueris anglicè? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120370" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e120380">Maximè dominae. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120390" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120400">Agedum, go too then and declare thy lords, their shields, their pages, and their purpose. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120410">Speak man, fear not, though Spain use messengers ill,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120420">'Tis England's guise to entreat them courteously. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120430" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120440">Three cavalieroes castillianos here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120450">Without compeers in compass of this world:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120460">Are come to conquer, as full well they shall</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120470">This molehill isle, that little England hight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120480">With London that proud paltry market town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120490">And take those dame's love, Lucre, conscience</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120500">Prisoners, to use or force as pleaseth them. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120510">The first (Now quake) is Spanish majesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120520">That for his impreze gives Queen Juno's bird,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120530">Whose train is spanged with Argus hundred eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120540">The Queen of gods scorns not to grace him so. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120550">His word is non par illi, none his like:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120560">Yet is his page or henchman modesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120570">Lucre the lady that shall be his prize:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120580">And in his pendent on his lances point,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120590">Sur le ciel his word, above the heavens. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120600" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120610">Whilom indeed above the heavens he was,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120620">Could be have kept him in that blessed state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120630">From thence for pride he fell to pit of pain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120640">And is he now become the pride of Spain? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120650">And so his page not modesty but shame. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120660">Well, on the rest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120670" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Sheal.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120680">Don honour is the next grand peer of Spain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120690">Whose impreze is a courser salient. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120700">Of colour sables, darkening air and earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120710">Pressing the globe with his disdainful foot. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120720">And sallying to aspire to rolling skies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120730">Non sufficit orbis is his haughty word,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120740">The world sufficeth not high honour's thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120750"><pb facs="26"/> and on the pendent fixed en his lance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120760">A hand is catching at the sunny beams:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120770">Et gloriam phoebi, and the sun's bright coach. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120780">Honour would guide, if he might have his will. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120790">His page is action tempering still with state. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120800" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e120810">Himself ambition, whom the heavens do hate,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120820" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e120830">And love the lady that he hopes to gain,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120840" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120850">His thoughts distract from foul distempered brain</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120860">Proves him the very firebrand of Spain:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120870">And in his shield his black disordered beast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120880">Scaling the skies, scornful to tread the ground,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120890">And both his words, proud words prove perfectly</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120900">Action his page to be but treachery,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120910">Ever attendant on ambition: but to the third. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e120920" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Sheal.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120930">The third ground cavaliero is government,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120940">Severe in justice, and in judgement deep:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120950">His impreze is a naked infant gored</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120960">Upon a lance, signifying, severity. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120970">His word, pour sangue, for blood of enemies</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120980">He bends his sources: on his pendent is</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e120990">A lyger licking of a bleeding heart:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121000">And cura cruor is the word thereon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121010">His care's for blood of those that dare resist:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121020">Yet hight his page that follows him, regard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121030">And he for conscience to this conquest comes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121040" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121050">The government of Spain is tyranny,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121060">As do his impreze and his words declare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121070">His page is terror: for a tyrant fears</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121080">His death, in diet, in his bed, in sleep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121090">In conscience: spite the Spanish tyranny</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121100">Hath shed a sea of most unguilty blood: well, what's the end? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121110" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121120">The end is best you yield, submitting you to mercy of these lords.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121130" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121140">Before we fight? soft sic, ye brave too fast. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121150">Castilians, know that Englishmen will knock, but say. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121160">Doth Spanish pride for London's lucre gape,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121170" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121180">And would their tyranny conscience captive have?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121190" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121200">Doth their ambition London's love affect?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121210" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Sheal.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121220">All this they will, and pray upon your town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121230"><pb facs="26"/> and give your lands away before your face:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121240">Alas, what's England to the power of Spain? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121250">A molehill, to be placed where it pleaseth them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121260" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121270">But in this molehill many pismires be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121280">All which will sting before they be removed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121290">What is thy name? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121300" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Sheal.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121310">Shealty,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121320" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121330">An Irish word, signifying liberty, rather remissness, looseness if ye will, why hath thy coat a burning ship behind?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121340" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121350">To signify theburning of your fleet by us Castillians.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121360" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121370">It rather means your common wealth's on fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121380">About your ears, and you were best look home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121390">A common wealth's compared to a ship,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121400">If yours do flame, your country is hot, beware. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121410" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Feal.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121420">I see Castilians, that you marvel much</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121430">At this same emblem of the olive tree</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121440">Upon my back: lo this it signifies. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121450">Spain is in wars, but London lives in peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121460">Your native fruit doth wither on your soil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121470">And prospers where it never planted was. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121480">This London's fealty doth avouch for truth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121490">Herald of war, and porter of their peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121500">Command ye me no service to my lords. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121510" who="A15517-pride">
          <speaker>S. pride.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121520">Quid tibi cum domini mox servient miseri nobis: discede. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121530" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Feal.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121540">Quid mihi cum dominis servietis miseri meis ▪</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121550" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121560">Shealty, say unto yon Thrasos thrée. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121570">The lords of London dare them to the field,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121580">Witting their pride and their ambition,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121590">Scorning their tyranny, and yet fearing this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121600">That they are come from home and dare not fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121610">But if they dare in joint or several arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121620">Battle or combat, him that lucre seeks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121630">Your Spanish pride, him dare I from the rest. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121640" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121650">That bloody cur, your Spanish tyranny,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121660">That London's conscience would force with cruelty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121670">I challenge him for conscience' sake to fight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121680">A lord of London, and I pleasure height. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121690">And Shealty, when citizens dare them thus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121700"><pb facs="27"/> judge what our nobles and our courtiers dare ▪</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121710" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121720">Say if thou wilt that London's policy</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121730">Discerns that proud ambition of sp●●●e,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121740">And for he comes inflame with London's love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121750">In combat let him conquer me and have her,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121760">This is love's favour, I her servant am. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121770" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121780">This Lucre's favour, pomp for her will fight.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121790" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121800">This conscience favour, she my mistress is.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121810" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121820">You craven English in your dunghill's crow.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121830" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121840">You Spanish pheasants crow upon your perch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121850">But when we fire your coats about your ears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121860">And take your ships before your walled towns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121870">We make a dunghill of your rotten bones,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e121880">And cram our chickens with your grains of gold. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121890" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121900">You will not yield?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121910" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121920">Yes, the last month.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121930" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Shea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121940">Farewell. <stage xml:id="A15517-e121950">Retire heralds with the pages to their places.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121960" who="A15517-pride">
          <speaker>S. pride.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121970">Vade. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e121980" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e121990">Herald, how now?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122000" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Fea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122010">Then proud Castillians look for your service.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122020" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122030">So do we for theirs: but fealty, canst thou declare to me the cause why all their pages follow them, when ours in shows do ever go before.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122040" who="A15517-fealty">
          <speaker>Fea.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122050">In war they follow, and the Spaniard is warring in mind</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122060" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122070">But that's not now the cause, yon three are pride, ambition tyranny.</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122080">Shame follows pride, as we a proverb have,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122090">Pride goes before, and shame comes after,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122100">Treachery ever attends upon ambition. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122110">And terror always with a fearful watch,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122120">Doth wait upon ill conscienced tyranny:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122130">But why stay we to give them space to breathe:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122140">Come, courage, let us charge them all at once. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e122150">Let the three lords pass towards the Spaniards, and the Spaniardes make show of coming forward and suddenly depart.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122160" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122170">What braving cowards these Castillians be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122180">My lordes let's hang our scutcheons up again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122190"><pb facs="27"/> and shroud ourselves but not far off unseen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122200">To prove if that may draw them to some deed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122210">Be it but to batter our impressed shields. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122220" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122230">Agreed, here fealty, hang them up a space.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e122240">They hang up their shields, and step out of sight. The Spaniardes come and flourish their rapiers near them, but touch them not, and then hang up theirs, which the lords of London perceiving, take their own and batter theirs: the Spaniards making a little show to rescue, do suddenly slip away and come no more. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122250" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122260">Facing, faint-hearted, proud and insolent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122270">That bear no edge within their painted sheaths,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122280">That durst not strike our silly patient shields. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122290" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122300">Up have they set their own, see if we dare</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122310">Batter on them, and beat their braving lords. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122320" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122330">Let them not yonder hang unbacked, my lords.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122340" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122350">With good advice, that we be not surprised, and good enough.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122360" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122370">Myself will onset give on prides, at your peacock sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122380" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122390">At tyrannies will I bestow my blow, wishing the master.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122400" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122410">I at ambitions strike, have at his pampered jade.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e122420">Enter s. pride. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122430" who="A15517-pride">
          <speaker>S. pride.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122440">Fuoro viliagos, fuoro lutheranos angleses, fuoro sa, sa, sa. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122450" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122460">Their shields are ours, they fled away with shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122470">But lordings, whiles the stratagem is fresh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122480">And memory of their misfortune green,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122490">Their hearts yet fainting with the novel grief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122500">Let us pursue them flying, if you say it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122510">Haply, we may prevent their passage yet. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122520" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122530">With speed and heed the matter must be done,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122540" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122550">Therefore you policy shall our leader be.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e122560">Exeunt omnes. </stage>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e122570">Enter three ladies and Nemo. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122580" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122590">The day is ours, fair ladies let us joy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122600">The joyful day that all men may rejoice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122610">Yet only I am thankful for this good. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122620">And your good day at hand approacheth fast. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122630">Wherein you shall be joined to thrée such lords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122640"><pb facs="28"/> as all the cities under heavens bright cope,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122650">Cannot with all their glory match in worth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122660">Lucre, lord pomp a victor comes to thee:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122670">Love, look thou for lord policy as well:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122680">And conscience for her well reformed fere,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122690">Pleasure, that only made his choice of her. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122700">Upon that day triumphant shall we feast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122710">Wherein (Madames) your honours nil be least. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122720" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122730">Against their coming might my read be hard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122740">Prepare would we garlands of laurel green,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122750">To welcome them, more for the common good,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122760">Than for affection private that we bear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122770" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122780">To meet them coming will not be amiss,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122790">But what know we how they will take such work,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122800" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122810">Report may be much more than there is cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122820">We may them meet and greet with joyful hearts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122830">And make them garlands when we know their minds. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e122840">Enter the three lords with the Spanish shields and Diligence</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122850" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122860">And here they come with new impressed shields,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122870">My lords well met, and welcome from your foes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122880" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122890">Lord pomp, well met, and welcome home again.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122900" who="A15517-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122910">Lord policy, well met, and welcome home again.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122920" who="A15517-conscience">
          <speaker>Conscience</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122930">Lord pleasure, welcome with unfeigned heart.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122940" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122950">Fair joy and lady xx. thousand thanks.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122960" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e122970">Fair love, and lady, twice as many thanks</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e122980" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e122990">Fair and beloved lucre, though I speak last,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123000">As kindly I thy welcome do accept,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123010">As heart can think, pen write, or tongue can tell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123020" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123030">Now speak my lords, how have ye sped?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123040" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123050">Right well: thanks unto him that gave the day to us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123060">The pride of Spain was cloaked with majesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123070">And shame his page, (Nicknamed) modesty,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123080">Spanish ambition, honour would be called,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123090">And treachery his page, termed action. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123100">Their tyranny was cleped government,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123110">Terror his page, was (Falsely) named regard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123120">But God above hath given them their reward. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123130"><pb facs="28"/>They with dishonour left their shields behind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123140">The only prizes purchased by us now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123150">And those (Fair ladies) we present to you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123160">Love, this is thine, and he that gives it thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123170" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123180">In lieu whereof your gift and her I give</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123190">Again to you, that merit more than both. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123200" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123210">The greatest gift and good could me befall.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123220" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123230">Fair lucre, lo, my present and myself.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123240" who="A15517-lucre">
          <speaker>Lucre.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123250">Which I with Nemo's licence gladly take.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123260" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123270">Take her lord pomp, I give her unto thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123280">Wishing your good may ten times doubled be. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123290" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123300">The wished good this world could give to me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123310" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123320">Of duty I (My dear) must give thee this, that art my comfort and my earthly bliss.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123330" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123340">Now lords, I hope you are contented all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123350">Pomp with his lucre, policy with love:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123360">Pleasure with conscience, joy fall you from above:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123370">And thus to you my promise is performed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123380">And I expect that yours as well be kept,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123390">That present preparation may be made</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123400">To honour those with holy marriage rites,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123410">That I in presence of the world may give</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123420">These as my daughters unto you my sons. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123430" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123440">By my consent one day shall serve us all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123450">Which shall be kept for ever festival. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123460" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123470">And on that day in honour of these dames,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123480">These shields in triumph shall be born about. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123490" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123500">With pageants, plates, and what delights may be to entertain the time and company.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123510" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123520">So it please you lordings, methinks it were meet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123530">That the ladies took care to provide their own toys. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123540">Myself need to help them, who know their minds well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123550">For I can keep women both quiet and constant. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123560" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123570">It pleaseth us well that you will take the pains. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123580">Fair ones, for a while we betake you to your business. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123590" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123600">Ladies, adieu.<stage xml:id="A15517-e123610">The lords bring them to the door, and they go out and ne.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123620" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123630">Beloved, farewell. <stage xml:id="A15517-e123640">Fra. gives Pol. a paper, which he reads and then saie●</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123650" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123660">It seems by this writing sir, you would serve me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e123670">Is your name skill? whom did you serve last? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123680" who="A15517-fraud">
          <pb facs="29"/>
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123690">An ill master, my lord, I served none but myself.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123700" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123710">Have ye never served any heretofore?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123720" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123730">Yes, divers my lord, both beyond sea and here with your patience, my good lord, not offending the same, I think I am your poor kinsman, your lordship, policy, and I skill, if it like ye.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123740" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123750">You say very well, and it is very like, I will answer ye anon.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e123760">Diss. gives plea. A paper which he reads, and says.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123770" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123780">Is your name fair semblance that wish to serve me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123790" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123800">Please it your lordship, fair semblance, I am well seen, though I say it, in sundry languages, meet for your lordship, or any noble service, to teach divers tongues, and other rare things.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123810" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123820">I like ye very well, stay a while for your answer,</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e123830">Enter usury and gives a paper to pomp which he reads, and saith,</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123840" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123850">Master usury, I thank ye that ye offer me your service, it seems to be for your old mistress' sake, lady lucre, stay but a while, I will answer you with reason.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e123860">The three lords go together, and whisper, and call Diligence, Diligence goes out for a marking iron, and returns.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123870" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123880">How now my hearts, think ye we shall speed.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123890" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123900">Diligence, come hither.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123910" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123920">I cannot tell what you shall, but I am sure I shall.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123930" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123940">I am as like as any of ye both.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123950" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123960">Fraud. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123970" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e123980">Whist man, he's skill. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e123990" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124000">Skill, why dost thou seek to serve lady love? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124010">What profit will that he? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124020" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124030">Cut hold thee content, I'll serve but a while, and serve mine own turn and away.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124040" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124050">Master usury come hither, you desire to serve me, you have done lady lucre good service you say, but it was against God and conscience you did it, neither ever in your life did ye any thing for love: well to be short, serve me you shall not, and I would I could banish you from London for ever, or keep you close prisoner, but that is not in me, but what is or may be, that straight you shall see: by policies counsel this shall be done, diligence bring that iron, help me my lords.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e124060"><pb facs="29"/>Enter Diligence. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124070" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124080">Give me the iron pomp, cousin skill help to hold him,</p>
          <stage xml:id="A15517-e124090">Fraud lays hold on him but diss. slip away.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124100">Sirrah, policy gives you this mark, do you see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124110">A little x. standing in the midst of a great. C,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124120">Meaning thereby to let all men understand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124130">That you must not take above bare x. pound in the hundred at any hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124140">And that too much too, and so be packing quietly:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124150">And know that London's pomp is not sustained by usury,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124160">But by well ventured merchandise and honest industry. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124170" who="A15517-usury">
          <speaker>Usury</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124180">I would I had never seen ye, if this be your courtesy.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e124190">Exit usury.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124200" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124210">Now cousin skill, alias, filthy fraud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124220">No kinsman to policy, nor friend to the state. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124230">In steed of serving me, diligence take him to Newgate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124240">Ask not why, sir, but diligence if he do strive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124250">Raise the street he's unweaponed, and thou hast a weapon on:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124260">And now lords when ye will, about our affairs, let's be gone,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124270" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124280">Agreed, but what's become of fair semblance my man.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124290" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124300">A crafty villain, perceiving how we meant to usury, slipped away.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e124310">Enter simplicity in haste, and give the lords a paper to read. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124320" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124330">All hail, all rain, all frost, and all snow, be to you thrée lords of London on a row:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124340">Read my supplantation and my suit ye shall know,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e124350">Even for God's sake above, and three ladies' sakes below. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124360" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124370">M. diligence, do me favour, you know I am a gentleman.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124380" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124390">Step aside till my lords be gone, I'll do for you what I can.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e124400">Slip aside.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124410" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124420">What's here my boy, what's here? pleasure, this suit is sure to you, for it's mad stuff, and I know not what it means.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124430" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124440">Neither do I: sirrah, your writing is so intricate, that you must speak your mind, otherwise, we shall not know your meaning.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124450" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124460">You sue for three things here, and what be they tell them:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124470" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124480">Cannot you thrée tell, and the suit to you thrée? I am glad a simple fellow yet, can go beyond you three great lords of London. <pb facs="30"/>Why my suit, look ye, is such a suit, as you are bound in honour to hear, for it is for the puppet like wealth, I would have no new orders, nor new sciences set up in the city, whereof I am a poor freeman, and please ye, as ye may read in my bill there, simplicity freeman. But my lords, I would have three old trades, which are not for the common wealth, put down.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124490" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Ple.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124500">And after all this circumstance, sir what be they?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124510" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124520">They be not thrée what lack yees, as what do ye lack, fine lockram, fine canvas, or fine holland cloth: or what lack ye, fine ballads, fine sonnets: or what lack ye, a purse or a glass, or a pair of fine knives: but they be three, have ye any's, which methinks are neither sciences nor occupations, and if they be trades, they are very malapert trades, and more than reason.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124530" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124540">As how sir? Name them.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124550" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124560">Will you banish them as readily as I can name them? the first is, have ye any old iron, old male, or old harness?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124570" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124580">And what fault find ye with this?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124590" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124600">What fault? I promise ye a great fault, what have you or any man else to do to ask me if I have any old iron? What if I have, or what if I have not? Why should you be so saucy to ask?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124610" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124620">Why fool, 'tis for thy good to give thee money for that, that might lie and rust by thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124630" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124640">No my lord, no. I may not call you fool: it is to mark the houses where such stuff is, that against rebels rise, there is harness and weapon ready for them in such and such houses, and what then? the rusty weapon doth wound passed surgery, and kills the Queen's good subjects: and the rest of the old trash will make them guns too, so it is good luck to find old iron, but 'tis naught to keep it, and the trade is crafty, and now my l. policy, I speak to you, 'twere well to put it down.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124650" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124660">Wisely said, which is your second? Is that as perilous?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124670" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124680">Yea, and worse: it is, have ye any ends of gold and silver? this is a perilous trade, covetous, and a ticement to murder, for, mark ye, if they that ask this should be evil given, as gods forbad ▪ they see who hath this gold and silver, may not they come in the night break in at their houses, and cut their throats for it? I tell ye, gold and silver hath caused as much mischief to be done as that, down with it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124690" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124700">They that have it need not show it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124710" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim,</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124720">Tush, they need ask no such question, many a man hath delight<pb facs="30"/> to show what he hath, the trade's a ticing trade, down with it:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124730" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124740">Now your third sir:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124750" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim,</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124760">That is the craftiest of all, wherein I am disbus's, for that goes under the colour of simplicity, have ye any wood to clean?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124770" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124780">A perilous thing, what hurt is there in this sir?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124790" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124800">O do you not perceive the subtlety? why sir, the woodmongers hires these poor men to go up and down with their beetles and wedges on their backs, crying, have ye any wood to cleave, and laugh to see them travel so laden with wood and iron: now sir, if the poor men go two or thrée days and be not set a work (As sometimes they do) the woodmongers pay them and gain by it, for then know they there's no wood in the city, then raise they the price of billets so high, that the poor can buy none. Now sir, if these fellows were barred from asking, whether there were wood to cleave or not, the woodmongers need not know but that there were wood, and so billets and faggots would be sold all at one rate, down with this trade, we shall sit a cold else my lords.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124810" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Ple.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124820">I promise you a wise suit, and done with great discretion.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124830" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124840">Yea, is it not? might ye not do well to make me of your counsel I believe I could spy more faults in a week, than you could mend in a month:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124850" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124860">Well, for these three faults the time serves not now to redress:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124870" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124880">No marry, for you three must be married suddenly, and your feast must be dres●:</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124890" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom,</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124900">Against which feast, repair you to diligence, and he shall appoint you furniture and money, and a place in the show, till when farewell. <stage xml:id="A15517-e124910">Exeunt</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124920" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124930">Farewell my lords, farewell my three lords, and remember that I have set each of ye a fault to mend: well, I'll go seek m. diligence that he may give me forty pence against the feast sir reverence:<stage xml:id="A15517-e124940">Exit</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124950" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124960">What is it m. fraud, ye would demand of me? <stage xml:id="A15517-e124970">Dil and Frau. step out</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e124980" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e124990">Sir this you know, though yourself be a man of good reckoning, yet are ye known an officer unto these three lords, and what discredit it were to me, being a noted man to pass through the streets with you being officer, or if any of my friends should suspect me with you, and dog us, and see me committed to Newgate, I were utterly discredited, here is a purse sir, and in it two hundred angels, look sir, you shall tell them.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125000" who="A15517-diligence">
          <pb facs="31"/>
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125010">Here are so indeed, what mean ye by this, I will not take these to let ye escape.<stage xml:id="A15517-e125020">Deliver fraud the purse again.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125030" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125040">I mean not so sir, nor I will not give half of them to be suffered to escape, for I have done no offence, though it please them to imprison me, and it is but on commandment, I shall not stay long, but I will give you this purse and gold in pawn to be true prisoner, only give me leave to go some other way, and home to my lodging, for my boots and other necessaries, for there I'll leave word I am ridden out of town, and with all the haste that possibly I may, I will meet you at Newgate, and give you an angel for your courtesy: there is the purse.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e125050">Fraud gives him a purse like the other.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125060" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125070">I hazard (As you know) my lords displeasure herein, and yet to pleasure you I will venture this once, but I pray ye make haste that I be not shent, I would not for ten angels it were known.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125080" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125090">If I tarry above an hour, take that gold for your tarrying.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e125100">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125110" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125120">I do not fear that you'll forfeit so much for so little cause. <stage xml:id="A15517-e125130">Exit.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e125140">Enter Nemo with desire, delight, and devotion, the three lords of Lincoln. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125150" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125160">My lords of Lincoln, have you such title and such interest</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125170">To love, Lucre, and conscience, as ye say? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125180">Who gave you leave to have access to them? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125190">I am their father by adoption,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125200">I never knew of love twixt them and you:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125210">And to perpetual prison they were doomed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125220">From whence I only might deliver them. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125230">Which at the suit of three most matchless lords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125240">Their countrymen, in London bred as they,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125250">I have performed and freed them from their bonds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125260">And yet have bound them in their freedom too</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125270">To policy, to pleasure, and to pomp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125280">Three lords of London, whose they are in right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125290">Contracted wives, and done by my consent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125300">And even tomorrow is the marriage day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125310">Except your coming stay or break it off,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125320">I will go call their lords to answer you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125330">The (Punder covert baron) meddle not. <stage xml:id="A15517-e125340">Exit.</stage></l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125350" who="A15517-desire">
          <pb facs="31"/>
          <speaker>Desire.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125360">Fetch them lord Nemo, we will here attend.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125370" who="A15517-delight">
          <speaker>Delight.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125380">Attend we may, but unto little end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125390">The ladies are in hucksters handling now,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125400" who="A15517-devotion">
          <speaker>Devo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125410">I would I had my time in praying spent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125420">That I in wooing conscience did consume. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e125430">Enter the three lords of London and Nemo. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125440" who="A15517-desire">
          <speaker>Desire.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125450">Here come the lords, let's show good countenance man.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125460" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125470">Yet more ado before we can enjoy</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125480">The joys of marriage with our mistresses? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125490">Be these the lords that title do pretend? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125500">My lords of Lincoln, so we hear you be. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e125510">What are your names? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125520" who="A15517-delight">
          <speaker>Del.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125530">Devotion, desire, and delight. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125540" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125550">Which comes for lucre?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125560" who="A15517-desire">
          <speaker>Desire.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125570">I desire. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125580" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125590">Which for conscience?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125600" who="A15517-devotion">
          <speaker>Devo.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125610">I devotion. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125620" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125630">Which for love? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125640" who="A15517-delight">
          <speaker>Del.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125650">I delight. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125660" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125670">You shall be answered straight.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125680" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125690">I can answer them quickly: ye cannot have them, nor ye shall not have them.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125700" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125710">Stay pleasure, soft: my lord desire, you lucre seek, desire of lucre (Be it without reproach to you my lord) is covetousness which cannot be separated long from that: read my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e125720">Point to the stone of care.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125730" who="A15517-desire">
          <speaker>Desire.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125740">In golden letters on this stone is written care. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125750" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125760">Care with desire of lucre well agrees, the rather for that London's lucre may not be separated from London's pomp, so you may take that stone if ye will, but the lady you cannot have.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125770" who="A15517-desire">
          <speaker>Desire.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125780">And a stone is a cold comfort instead of lucre. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125790" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125800">Devotion to conscience (I speak now to you my lord that are learned) is sorrow for sin, or in one word read.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e125810">Point to the stone of remorse.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125820" who="A15517-devotion">
          <speaker>Deuot.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125830">On this sweating stone in brass is set remorse. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125840" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125850">And that is your portion, for conscience is bestowed on London's<pb facs="32"/> pleasure, because London makes a conscience what pleasure they use and admit, and what time they bestow therein, and to what end: s● my lord devotion, either that or nothing.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125860" who="A15517-devotion">
          <speaker>Devo.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125870">A stone is a hard lot in stod of a lady.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125880" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125890">My lord delight, that to delight in love, you must I love, for making choice of mine. Love is my portion, and that flint is yours.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125900" who="A15517-delight">
          <speaker>Del.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125910">Here in lead is written, charity: and what of this?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125920" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125930">If you be (As I doubt not) honest delight in love, then in the best sense, you can have but charity, if you be (Which I suspect not) other delight in love, you must be noted for concupiscence, and that you will blush to be: well charity is your best, then that is your portion: for, mark ye, London's policy joins with London's love: to show, that all our policy is for love of London's common wealth: and so our love cannot be separate from our policy, you bear this.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125940" who="A15517-delight">
          <speaker>Delight.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125950">A flint's a hard change for so fair a wife.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125960" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125970">And thus lords, desire of lucre may take care, devotion of conscience may have remorse, and delight of love may have charity, other recompense none.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e125980" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e125990">And so we thrée leave you three with care, remorse, and charity.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e126000">Exeunt.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126010" who="A15517-desire">
          <speaker>Desire.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126020">With care and remorse I swear, ye do leave us, but what charity I cannot tell.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126030" who="A15517-devotion">
          <speaker>Deuot.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126040">Well. yet must we use charity though we fail of our desire, and we are answered with such reason as is not to be gainsaid.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126050" who="A15517-delight">
          <speaker>Del.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126060">Indeed my lord your calling is to persuade to charity, but if I use patience, it shall be perforce.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126070" who="A15517-devotion">
          <speaker>Devo.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126080">Yet being so wisely warned, methinks we should be armed and take this in worth, that the world wonder no further, I will take up my hard burden of remorse and be gone.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e126090">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126100" who="A15517-desire">
          <speaker>Desire.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126110">It is good to follow examples of good, I'll take this heavy burden of care, and follow as I may.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e126120">Exit</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126130" who="A15517-delight">
          <speaker>Del.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126140">Because I'll not be slagular, I'll frame myself to follow, taking this cold portion of charity as my share. <stage xml:id="A15517-e126150">Exit</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e126160">Enter simplicity with Diligence. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126170" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126180">Come on m. diligence, I have been seeking ye, as a man should seek a load of hay in a needle's eye.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126190" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126200">And why hast thou sought me (I pray thee) so earnestly?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126210" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <pb facs="32"/>
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126220">Why? For this ointment, these shells, these pleasure, do ye not know this countua mountus cum this d● mihi?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126230" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126240">What money, why? Do I owe thee any money?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126250" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126260">Owe me? Tush, no man, what do ye talk of owing? Come, and yet I must have some certain sigillatum et deliberatum in praesentia. Do you not understand sir? Forty pence and furniture by my lord pomp's appointment, against the wedding day: to be one of the show-makers, I do not say shoemakers, and yet they be honest men.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126270" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126280">I understand thee now, and thou shalt want neither money nor furniture for that: sawest thou not fraud lately?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126290" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126300">No, a for ferret him, for if I could find him, I would make him fast enough for cozening me of ten shillings for certain copper buttons and rings, I thought to have been a haberdasher, and he hath made me worse than a haymaker.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126310" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126320">I may say to thee in counsel, but I'll have no words of it, he hath overreached me too: but if thou spy him first, let me understand, and if I see him first thou shalt have knowledge, for I'll tell thee, but laugh not, he showed me a purse with a hundred pound in angels, which he would deliver me in pawn to be my true prisoner, because for his credit, he was loath to go with me through the streets to Newgate: I refused it at first, but at last by his entreaty I was content to take his pawn, and thinking he had given me the right purse of gold, he had another like it, which he gave me with counters, and so went away, I never did see him since, but mum, no words of it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126330" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126340">No words quoth 'a, that's a state test, would you be cozened so?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126350" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126360">Well, so it is now, come follow me for thy furniture and money.<stage xml:id="A15517-e126370">Exeunt</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e126380">Enter dissimulation and fraud in caps, and as the rest must be for the show. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126390" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126400">The coast is clear, come follow fraud and fear not, for who can decipher us in this disguise, thus may we shuffle into the show with the rest, and see and not be seen, doing as they do, that are attired like ourselves.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126410" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126420">That is, to stand amongst them, and take as they take, torches or any thing to furnish the show, now if we we can pass but this day unseen, let tomorrow shift for itself as it may, I promise thee dissimulation thou art very formal.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126430" who="A15517-dissimulation">
          <pb facs="33"/>
          <speaker>Dis.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126440">Not more than thyself fraud, I would thou sawest thy picture</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126450" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Frau.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126460">Picture here, picture there, let's follow our business. <stage xml:id="A15517-e126470">Exeunt.</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e126480">Enter a Mench singing.</stage>
        <l xml:id="A15517-e126490">Strow the fair flowers and herbs that be green,</l>
        <l xml:id="A15517-e126500">To grace the gayest wedding that ever was seen. </l>
        <l xml:id="A15517-e126510">If London list to look, the streets were ne'er so clean,</l>
        <l xml:id="A15517-e126520">Except it was when best it might, in welcome of our Queen:</l>
        <l xml:id="A15517-e126530">Three lovely lords of London shall three London ladies wed,</l>
        <l xml:id="A15517-e126540">Strow sweetest flowers upon the stones, perfume the bridal bed. </l>
        <l xml:id="A15517-e126550">Strow the fair flowers. Etc. </l>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e126560">Enter first Diligence with a truncheon, then a boy with policies lance and shield, then policy and love hand in hand: then fraud in a blue gown, red cap and red sleeves, with ambition's lance and shield, then a boy with pomps lance and shield, then pomp and Lucre hand in hand: then dissimulation with pride's lance and shield, then a boy with pleasure's lance and shield: then pleasure and conscience hand in hand: then simplicity with tyrannies lance and shield: they all going out, Nemo stays and speaks. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126570" who="A15517-nemo">
          <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
          <lg xml:id="A15517-e126580">
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126590">These lords and ladies thus to church are gone,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126600">An honoured action to solemnize there,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126610">With greater joy will they return anon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126620">Than Caesar did in Rome his laurel wear. </l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126630">Lord policy hath love unto his fere. </l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126640">Lord pomp hath lucre to maintain his port,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126650">Lord pleasure conscience to direct his sport. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A15517-e126660">
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126670">Usury is marked to be known,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126680">Dissimulation like a shadow fleets,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126690">And simony is out of knowledge grown,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126700">And fraud unfound in London but by fits. </l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126710">Simplicity with painful penury sits. </l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126720">For hospitality that was wont to feed him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126730"><pb facs="33"/> was slain long since and now the poor do need him. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A15517-e126740">
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126750">That hospitality was an honest man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126760">But had few friends (Alas) if he had any,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126770">But usury which cut his throat as than</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126780">Was succoured, and sued for by many. </l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126790">Would liberality had been by thy side,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126800">Than hospitality, thou hadst never died. </l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126810">But what mean I, one of the marriage train,</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126820">To mourn for him will ne'er be had again. </l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126830">His ghost may walk to mock the people rude:</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126840">Ghosts are but shadows, and do sense delude:</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126850">I talk too long, for so this lovely crew</l>
            <l xml:id="A15517-e126860">Are coming back, and have performed their due. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e126870">Return as they went, saving that the blue gowns that bore shields, must now bear torches: simplicity going about, spies fraud, and falleth on his knees before pleasure and conscience, saying. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126880" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity ▪</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e126890">O lady conscience that art married to lord pleasure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e126900">Help thy servant simplicity to recover his lost treasure:</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e126910">A boon my lords, all for love and lucre's sake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e126920">Even as you are true lords, help a false lout to take,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126930" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e126940">Thou shalt have help, speak, what is the matter?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e126950" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e126960">See you yon fellow with the torch in his hand? </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e126970">One the falsest villain that is in this land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e126980">Let him be laid hold on that he run not away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e126990">And than ye shall hear what I have to say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127000" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e127010">Diligence bring him hither, good lords and ladies stay,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127020" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127030">O master fraud, welcome to the butts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127040">Now I'll have my ten shillings in spite of your guts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127050">The French tanker consume ye, you were an old Frenchman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127060">Dam goll button, goll renga, bugla lase, you cozened me then,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127070">My lords I beseech ye that at Tyburn he may totter,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127080">For instead of gold, the villain sold me copper. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127090" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e127100">Is this true m. skill? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127110" who="A15517-fraud">
          <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e127120">It is true in a sort my lord, I thought to be pleasant with him being my old acquaintance, and disguised myself like an old French<pb facs="34"/> artificer and having a few copper knacks, I sold them to him to make sport for ten shillings, which money I am content to pay him again so shall he have no loss though he have made a little sport.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127130" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e127140">First give him an angel before my face. Simplicity, art thou pleased?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127150" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e127160">Truly I am pleased to take a good angel for ten shillings, speciously of such a debtor as m. fraud: but now I am to be pleased otherwise, that is, to see him punished, I promise ye the people love him well, for they would leave work and make half holiday to see him hanged.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127170" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e127180">That his punishment may please thee the better, thou shalt punish him thyself: he shall be bound fast to yon post, and thou shalt be blindfold, and with thy torch shalt run as it were at tilt, charging thy light against his lips, and so (If thou canst) burn out his tongue, that it never speak more guile.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127190" who="A15517-simony">
          <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e127200">O singulariter nominativo, wise lord pleasure: genetivo bind him to that post, dativo, give me my torch, accusat. For I say he's a cozener. Vocat. O give me room to run at him. Ablat. take and blind me. Pluraliter, per omnes casus. Laugh all you to see me in my choler adust to burn and to broil that false fraud to dust.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A15517-e127210">Bind fraud, blind simplicity, turn him thrife about, set his face towards the contrary post, at which he runs, and all to burns it, Dis. standing behind fraud, unbinds him, and whiles all the rest behold Simp. they two slip away: pleasure missing fraud saith.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127220" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e127230">Wisely performed, but soft sirs, where is fraud? O noble villain, gone whiles we beheld the other: who loosed him? Who let him slip? well, one day he will pay for all: unblind simplicity. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127240" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e127250">How now, have I beated his lips? have I warmed his nose? and scorched his face? Let me see, how looks the villain? Have I burned him?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127260" who="A15517-diligence">
          <speaker>Dil.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e127270">Thou hast done more, for thou hast quite consumed him into nothing, look, here is no sign of him, no not so much as his ashes.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127280" who="A15517-simplicity">
          <speaker>Simplicity</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A15517-e127290">Very few ashes if there be any, ye may see what a hot thing anger is, I think that the torch did not waste him so much as my wrath: well, all London, nay, all England is beholding to me, for putting fraud out of this world, I have consumed him and brought him to nothing<pb facs="34"/> and I'll tread his ashes under my feet, thatno more frauds shall ever spring of them: but let me see, I shall have much anger, for the tanners will miss him in their leather, the tailors in cutting out of garments, the shoemaker in closing, the tapsters in filling pots, and the very oistermen to mingle their oysters at Billingsgate, yet it is no matter the world is well rid of such a crafty knave.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127300" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127310">Well now thou art satisfied, I wish all here as well contented,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127320">And we my lords that praise this happy day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127330">Fall we on knees and humbly let us pray. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127340" who="A15517-pomp">
          <speaker>Pom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127350">First that from heaven upon our gracious Queen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127360">All manner blessings may be multiplied,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127370">That as her reign most prosperous hath been,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127380">During world's length so may it still abide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127390">And after that with saints be glorified·</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127400">Lord grant her here health, hearts-ease, joy and mirth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127410">And heaven at last, after long life on earth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127420" who="A15517-policy">
          <speaker>Policy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127430">Her counsel wise, and nobles of this land</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127440">Bless, and preserve oh lord with thy right hand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A15517-e127450" who="A15517-pleasure">
          <speaker>Pleasure</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127460">On all the rest that in this land do dwell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127470">Chiefly in London, lord pour down thy grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127480">Who living in thy fear and dying well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A15517-e127490">In heaven with angels they may have a place. </l>
        </sp>
        <trailer xml:id="A15517-e127500">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A15517"><item xml:id="A15517-policy" n="89">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-policy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">89</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-simony" n="84">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-simony</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">84</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-pleasure" n="74">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-pleasure</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">74</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-simplicity" n="65">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-simplicity</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">65</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-pomp" n="65">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-pomp</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">65</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-wit" n="59">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-wit</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">59</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-nemo" n="52">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-nemo</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">52</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-will" n="49">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-will</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">49</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-fraud" n="45">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-fraud</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">45</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-conscience" n="35">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-conscience</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">35</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-fealty" n="33">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-fealty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">33</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-usury" n="32">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-usury</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">32</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-wealth" n="30">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-wealth</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">30</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A15517-lucre" n="21">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-lucre</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">21</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-love" n="19">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-love</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">19</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-dissimulation" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-dissimulation</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-diligence" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-diligence</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-penury" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-penury</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-delight" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-delight</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-desire" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-desire</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-devotion" n="6">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-devotion</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">6</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-pride" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-pride</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-unassigned" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-unassigned</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-falsehood" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-falsehood</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-constable" n="3">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-constable</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">3</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-sorrow" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-sorrow</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-industry" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-industry</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-sincerity" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-sincerity</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A15517-London" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A15517-London</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

