<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A07247">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Roman Actor <date type="creation_date">1626</date></title>
        <author>Massinger, Philip</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Hannah Bredar</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A07247.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The Roman actor. A tragædie. As it hath diuers times beene, with good allowance acted, at the private play-house in the Black-Friers, by the Kings Majesties Servants. Written by Philip Massinger.</title>
            <author>Massinger, Philip, 1583-1640.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>43 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2003 January (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99847682</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 17642.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, II, 424.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">12736</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07247</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">The Roman actor. A tragædie. As it hath diuers times beene, with good allowance acted, at the private play-house in the Black-Friers, by the Kings Majesties Servants. Written by Philip Massinger.</title>
            <author>Massinger, Philip, 1583-1640.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[80] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed by B[ernard] A[lsop] and T[homas] F[awcet] for Robert Allot, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Beare in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1629.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Printers' names from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-K4.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Variant: texts of H3v and H4r interchanged.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <term>[Paris, -- Roman actor] -- Drama -- Early works to 1800.</term>
          <term>Domitian, -- Emperor of Rome, -- 51-96 -- Drama -- Early works to 1800.</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="A07247-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A07247-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A07247-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A07247-e100040">The roman actor. A tragedy. As it hath divers times been with good allowance acted, at the private playhouse in the Blackfriars, by the King's majesty's servants.</p>
        <p xml:id="A07247-e100050">Written by Philip Massinger. </p>
        <p xml:id="A07247-e100060">London. Printed by 〈◊〉 and ●. F. for Robert allot, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the bear 〈…〉 Church-yard. 1629.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="dramatis_personae" xml:id="A07247-e100070">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <list xml:id="A07247-e100080">
          <head>The persons presented.</head>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100090">Domitianus Caesar. </item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100100">Paris the tragedian.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100110">Parthenius a freeman of Caesar's. </item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100120">Aelius, Lamia, and Stephanos. </item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100130">Junius Rusticus. </item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100140">Aretinus Clemens, Caesar's spy.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100150">Aesopus a player.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100160">Philargus a rich miser.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100170">Palphurius Sura, a senator</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100180">Latinus a player.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100190">3. Tribunes.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100200">2. Lictors.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100210">Domitia the wife of Aelius Lamia. </item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100220">Domitilla cousin germane to Caesar. </item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100230">Julia Titus' daughter.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100240">Caenis, Vespasian's concubine.</item>
        </list>
        <list xml:id="A07247-e100250">
          <head>The principal actors.</head>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100260">John Lowin.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100270">Joseph Taylor.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100280">Richard sharp.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100290">Thomas Pollard.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100300">Robert Benfield.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100310">Eyllardt Swanstone.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100320">Richard Robinson.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100330">Anthony smith.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100340">William Pattricke.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100350">Cvrtise Grevill.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100360">George Vernon.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100370">James horn.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100380">John Tompson.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100390">John Hunnieman.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100400">William Trigge.</item>
          <item xml:id="A07247-e100410">Alexander Gough.</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A07247-e100420">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To my much honoured, and most true friends, sir Philip Knyvet, knight and baronet. And to sir Thomas Jeay, knight. And Thomas Bellingham of Newtimber in Sussex esquire.</head>
        <p xml:id="A07247-e100430">How much I acknowledge myself bound for your so many, and extraordinary favours conferred upon me, as far as it is in my power posterity shall take notice, I were most unworthy of such noble friends, if I should not with all thankfulness, profess, and own 'em. In the composition of this tragedy you were my only supporters, and it being now by your principal encouragement to be turned into the world, it cannot walk safer, than under your protection. It hath been happy<pb facs="3"/> in the suffrage of some learned, and judicious gentlemen when it was presented, nor shall they find cause I hope in the perusal, to repent them of their good opinion of it. If the gravity and height of the subject distaste such as are only affected with jigs, and ribaldry (As I presume it will,) their condemnation of me, and my poem, can no way offend me: my reason teaching me such malicious, and ignorant detractors deserve rather cöntempt, than satisfaction. I ever held it the most perfect birth of my Minerva; and therefore, in justice offer it to those that have best deserved of me, who I hope in their courteous acceptance will render it worth their receiving, and ever, in their gentle construction of my imperfections, believe they may at their pleasure dispose of him, that is wholly, and sincerely</p>
        <signed xml:id="A07247-e100440">Devoted to their service. Philip Massinger.</signed>
      </div>
      <div type="encomia" xml:id="A07247-e100450">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <lg xml:id="A07247-e100460">
          <head>To his dear friend the author.</head>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100470">I am no great admirer of the plays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100480">Poets, or actors, that are now adays:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100490">Yet in this work of thine methinks I see</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100500">Sufficient reason for idolatry. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100510">Each line thou hast taught Ceasar is, as high</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100520">As he could speak, when grovelling flattery,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100530">And his own pride (Forgetting heavens rod)</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100540">By his edicts styled himself great lord and God. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100550">By thee again the laurel crowns his head;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100560">And thus revived, who can affirm him dead? </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100570">Such power lies in this lofty strain as can</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100580">Give swords, and legions to Domitian. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100590">And when thy Paris pleads in the defence</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100600">Of actors, every grace, and excellence</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100610">Of argument for that subject, are by thee</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100620">Contracted in a sweet epitome. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100630">Nor do thy women the tired hearers vex,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100640">With language no way proper to their sex. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100650">Just like a cunning painter thou lets fall</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100660">Copies more fair than the original. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100670">I'll add but this. From all the modern plays</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100680">The stage hath lately born, this wins the bays. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100690">And if it come to trial boldly look</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100700">To carry it clear, thy witness being thy book. </l>
          <signed xml:id="A07247-e100710">T. i.</signed>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A07247-e100720">
          <pb facs="4"/>
          <head>In Philippi massingeri, poetae elegantiss: actorem romanum, typis excusum. <seg xml:lang="unk" xml:id="A07247-e100730">celebrata tragaedia musae</seg>.</head>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100740">Ecce philippinae, celebrata tragaedia musae</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100750">Quam roscus britonum Roscius egit, adest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100760">Semper, frond ambo vireant parnasside, semper</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100770">Libre ab invidrae dentibus esto, libre. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100780">Crebra papyrivori spernas incendia paeti</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100790">Thus, vaenum expositi tegmina suta libri:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100800">Nec metuas raucos, momorum sybila, rhencos</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100810">Tam bardus nebulo si tamen ullus, erit. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100820">Nam toties festis, actum, placuisse theatris</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100830">Quod liquet, hoc, cusum, crede, placebit, opus. </l>
          <signed xml:id="A07247-e100840">Tho. G.</signed>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A07247-e100850">
          <head>To his deserving friend Mr. Philip Massinger, upon his tragedy, the Roman actor.</head>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100860">Paris, the best of actors in his age</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100870">Acts yet, and speaks upon our Roman stage</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100880">Such lines by thee, as do not derogate</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100890">From Rome's proud heights, and her then learned state. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100900">Nor great Domitian's favour; not th'embraces</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100910">Of a fair empress, nor those often graces</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100920">Which from th'applauding theatres were paid</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100930">To his brave action, nor his ashes laid</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100940">In the Flaminian way, where people strowed</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100950">His grave with flowers, and marshal's wit bestowed</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100960">A lasting epitaph, not all these same</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100970">Do add so much renown to Paris name,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100980">As this that thou presentest his history</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e100990">So well to us. For which in thanks would he</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101000">(If that his soul, as thought Pythagoras</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101010">Could into any of our actors pass)</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101020">Life to these lines by action gladly give</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101030">Whose pen so well has made his story live. </l>
          <signed xml:id="A07247-e101040">Tho. may.</signed>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A07247-e101050">
          <pb facs="4"/>
          <head>Upon Mr. Massinger his Roman actor.</head>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101060">To write, is grown so common in our time</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101070">That every one, who can but frame a rhyme</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101080">However monstrous, gives himself that praise</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101090">Which only he should claim, that may wear bays</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101100">By their applause whose judgements apprehend</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101110">The weight, and truth, of what they dare commend. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101120">In this besotted age (Friend) 'tis thy glory</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101130">That here thou hast outdone the Roman story. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101140">Domitian's pride; his wife's lust unabated</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101150">In death; with Paris, merely were related</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101160">Without a soul, until thy abler pen</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101170">Spoke them, and made them speak, nay act again</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101180">In such a height, that here to know their deeds</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101190">He may become an actor that but reads. </l>
          <signed xml:id="A07247-e101200">John ford.</signed>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A07247-e101210">
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101220">Longest thou to see proud Caesar set in state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101230">His morning greatness, or his evening fate? </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101240">With admiration here behold him fall</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101250">And yet outlive his tragic funeral:</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101260">For 'tis a question whether Caesar's glory</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101270">Rose to its height before, or in this story. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101280">Or whether Paris in Domitian's favour</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101290">Were more exalted, then in this thy labour. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101300">Each line speaks him an emperor, every phrase</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101310">Crowns thy deserving temples with the bays;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101320">So that reciprocally both agree</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101330">Thou liv'st in him and he survives in thee. </l>
          <signed xml:id="A07247-e101340">Robert Harvey.</signed>
        </lg>
        <lg xml:id="A07247-e101350">
          <pb facs="5"/>
          <head>To his long known and loved friend, Mr. Philip Massinger, upon his Roman actor.</head>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101360">If that my lines being placed before thy book●s</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101370">Could make it sell, or alter but a look</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101380">Of some sour censurer, who's apt to say</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101390">No one in these times can produce a play</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101400">Worthy his reading, since of late, 'tis true</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101410">The old accepted are more than the new. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101420">Or could I on some spot o'the court work so</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101430">To make him speak no more than he doth know;</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101440">Not borrowing from his flattering flattered friend</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101450">What to dispraise, or wherefore to commend. </l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101460">Then (Gentle friend) I should not blush to be</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101470">Ranked amongst those worthy ones, which here I see</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101480">Ushering this work, but why I write to thee</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101490">Is to profess our love's antiquity,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101500">Which to this tragedy must give my test,</l>
          <l xml:id="A07247-e101510">Thou hast made many good, but this thy best. </l>
          <signed xml:id="A07247-e101520">Joseph Taylor.</signed>
        </lg>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A07247-e101530">
      <div n="1" type="act" xml:id="A07247-e101540">
        <pb facs="5"/>
        <head>The roman actor, a tragedy.</head>
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A07247-e101550">
          <head>Actus, i. Scaena, i.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e101560">Enter Paris, Latinus, Aesopus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e101570" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101580">What do we act today? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e101590" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Latinus.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101600">Agave's frenzy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101610">With Pentheus' bloody end. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e101620" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Paris.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101630">It skills not what</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101640">The times are dull, and all that we receive</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101650">Will hardly satisfy the day's expense. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101660">The Greeks (To whom we owe the first invention</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101670">Both of the buskined scene and humble stock)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101680">That reign in every noble family</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101690">Declaim against us: and our amphitheater. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101700">Great Pompey's work, that hath given full delight</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101710">Both to the eye, and ear of fifty thousand</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101720">Spectators in one day, as if it were</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101730">Some unknown desert, or great room unpeopled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101740">Is quite forsaken. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e101750" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Latin.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101760">Pleasures of worse natures</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101770">Are gladly entertained, and they that shun us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101780">Practice in private sports the stews would blush at. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101790">A litter born by eight Liburnian slaves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101800">To buy diseases from a glorious strumpet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101810">The most censorious of our Roman gentry,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101820">Nay of the guarded robe the senators,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101830">Esteem an easy purchase,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e101840" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Paris</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101850">Yet grudge us</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101860">(That with delight join profit and endeavour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101870">To build their minds up fair, and on the stage</l>
            <pb facs="6"/>
            <pb facs="6"/>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101880"><pb facs="7"/> decipher to the life what honours wait</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101890">On good, and glorious actions, and the shame</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101900">That treads upon the heels of vice. The salary</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101910">Of six sestertij:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e101920" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101930">For the profit Paris,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101940">And mercenary gain they are things beneath us</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101950">Since while you hold your grace, and power with Caesar▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101960">We from your bounty find a large supply,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101970">Nor can one thought of want ever approach us,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e101980" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e101990">Our aim is glory, and to leave our names</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102000">To after times. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102010" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Latin.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102020">And would they give us leave</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102030">There ends all our ambition. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102040" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102050">We have enemies</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102060">And great ones too, I fear. 'tis given out lately</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102070">The consul Aretinus (Caesar's spy)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102080">Said at his table ere a month expired</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102090">(For being galled in our last comedy)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102100">He would silence us for ever. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102110" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102120">I expect</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102130">No favour from him, my strong Aventine is</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102140">That great Domitian, whom we oft have cheered</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102150">In his most sullen moods will once return,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102160">Who can repair with ease, the consoles ruins. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102170" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102180">'Tis frequent in the city, he hath subdued</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102190">The Catti, and the Daci, and ere long,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102200">The second time will enter Rome in triumph. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e102210">Enter two lictors.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102220" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102230">Jove hasten it, with us? I now believe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102240">The consuls threats Aesopus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102250" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Lictor</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102260">You are summoned</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102270">T'appear today in senate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102280" who="A07247-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Lictor</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102290">And there to answer</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102300">What shall be urged against you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102310" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102320">We obey you. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102330">Nay droop not fellows, innocence should be bold</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102340"><pb facs="7"/> we that have personated in the scene</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102350">The ancient heroes, and the falls of princes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102360">With loud applause, being to act ourselves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102370">Must do it with undaunted confidence. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102380">Whate'er our sentence be 'tis in sport. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102390">And though condemned let's hear it without sorrow</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102400">As if we were to live again tomorrow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102410" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Lictor</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102420">'Tis spoken like yourself. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e102430">Enter Aelius / Lamia, Junïus / Rusticus, Palphuris / Sura.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102440" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102450">Whether goes Paris? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102460" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Lictor</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102470">He's cited to the senate. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102480" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102490">I am glad the state is</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102500">So free from matters of more weight and trouble</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102510">That it has vacant time to look on us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102520" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102530">That reverend place, in which the affairs of Kings. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102540">And provinces were determined, to descend</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102550">To the censure of a bitter word, or jest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102560">Dropped from a poet's pen I peace to your lordships</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102570">We are glad that you are safe. <stage xml:id="A07247-e102580">Exeunt lictors, Paris, Latinus, Aesopus.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102590" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102600">What times are these? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102610">To what is Rome fallen? may we being alone</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102620">Speak our thoughts freely of the prince, and state,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102630">And not fear the informer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102640" who="A07247-rusticus">
            <speaker>Rust.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102650">Noble Lamia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102660">So dangerous the age is, and such bad acts</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102670">Are practised everywhere , we hardly sleep</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102680">Nay cannot dream with safety. All our actions</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102690">Are called in question, to be nobly born</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102700">Is now a crime; and to deserve too well</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102710">Held capital treason. Sons accuse their fathers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102720">Fathers their sons; and but to win a smile</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102730">From one in grace in court, our chastest matrons</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102740">Make shipwreck of their honours. To be virtuous</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102750">Is to be guilty. They are only safe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102760">That know to soothe the prince's appetite,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102770">And serve his lusts. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102780" who="A07247-sura">
            <pb facs="8"/>
            <speaker>Sura.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102790">'Tis true; and 'tis my wonder</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102800">That two sons of so different a nature,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102810">Should spring from good Vespasian. We had a Titus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102820">Styled justly the delight of all mankind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102830">Who did esteem that day lost in his life</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102840">In which some one or other tasted not. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102850">Of his magnificent bounties. One that had</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102860">A ready tear when he was forced to sign</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102870">The death of an offender. And so far</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102880">From pride, that he disdained not the converse</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102890">Even of the poorest roman. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102900" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102910">Yet his brother</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102920">Domitian, that now sways the power of things,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102930">Is so inclined to blood, that no day passes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102940">In which some are not fastened to the hook,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102950">Or thrown down from the Gemonies. His freemen</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102960">Scorn the nobility, and he himself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102970">As if he were not made of flesh and blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e102980">Forgets he is a man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e102990" who="A07247-rusticus">
            <speaker>Rust.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103000">In his young years</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103010">He showed what he would be when grown to ripeness:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103020">His greatest pleasure was being a child</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103030">With a sharp pointed bodkin to kill flies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103040">Whose rooms now men supply. For his escape. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103050">In the Vitellian war he raised a temple</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103060">To Jupiter, and proudly placed his figure</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103070">In the bosom of the God. And in his edicts</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103080">He does not blush, or start to style himself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103090">(As if the name of emperor were base)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103100">Great lord, and God Domitian. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e103110" who="A07247-sura">
            <speaker>Sura.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103120">I have letters</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103130">He's on his way to Rome, and purposes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103140">To enter with all glory. The flattering senate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103150">Decrees him divine honours, and to cross it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103160">Were death with studied torments; for my part</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103170">I will obey the time, it is in vain</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103180">To strive against the torrent</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e103190" who="A07247-rusticus">
            <speaker>Rust.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103200">Let's to the curia</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103210"><pb facs="8"/> and though unwillingly grieve our suffrages</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103220">Before we are compelled. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e103230" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103240">And since we cannot</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103250">With safety use the active, let's make use of</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103260">The passive fortitude, with this assurance</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103270">That the state sicke in him, the gods to friend,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103280">Though at the worst will now begin to mend. <stage xml:id="A07247-e103290">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A07247-e103300">
          <head>Actus, i. Scaena, 2.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e103310">Enter Domitia, and Parthenius.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e103320" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103330">To me this reverence? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e103340" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103350">I pay it lady</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103360">As a debt due to her that's Caesar's mistress. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103370">For understand with joy he that commands</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103380">All that the sun gives warmth to, is your servant. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103390">Be not amazed, but fit you to your fortunes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103400">Think upon state, and greatness, and the honours</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103410">That wait upon Augusta, for that name</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103420">Ere long comes to you: still you doubt your vassal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103430">But when you have read this letter, writ, and signed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103440">With his imperial hand, you will be freed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103450">From fear, and jealousy and I beseech you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103460">When all the beauties of the earth bow to you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103470">And senators shall take it for an honour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103480">As I do now to kiss these happy feet;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103490">When every smile you give is a preferment,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103500">And you dispose of provinces to your creatures,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103510">Think on Parthenius. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e103520" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103530">Rise. I am transported,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103540">And hardly dare believe what is assured here. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103550">The means, my good Parthenius, that wrought Caesar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103560">(Our God on earth) to cast an eye of favour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103570">Upon his humble handmaid! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e103580" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103590">What but your beauty? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103600">When nature framed you for her master piece,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103610">As the pure abstract of all rare in woman,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103620"><pb facs="9"/> she had no other ends but to design you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103630">To the most eminent place. I will not say</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103640">(For it would smell of arrogance to insinuate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103650">The service I have done you) with what zeal</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103660">I oft have made relation of your virtues,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103670">Or how I have sung your goodness or how Caesar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103680">Was fired with the relation of your storeys</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103690">I am rewarded in the act, and happy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103700">In that my project prospered. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e103710" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103720">You are modest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103730">And were it in my power I would to be thankful. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103740">If that when I was mistress of myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103750">And in my way of youth, pure, and untainted,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103760">The emperor had vouchsafed to seek my favours,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103770">I had with joy given up my virgin fort</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103780">At the first summons to his soft embraces:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103790">But I am now another's, not mine own. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103800">You know I have a husband, for my honour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103810">I would not be his strumpet, and how law</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103820">Can be dispensed with to become his wife. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103830">To me's a riddle. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e103840" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103850">I can soon resolve it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103860">When power puts in his plea the laws are silenced,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103870">The world confesses one Rome, and one Caesar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103880">And as his rules is infinite, his pleasures</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103890">Are unconfined; this syllable his will</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103900">Stands for a thousand reasons,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e103910" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103920">●ut with safety,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103930">Suppose I should consent, how can I do it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103940">My husband is a senator of a temper,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103950">Not to be jested with. <stage xml:id="A07247-e103960">Enter Lamia.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e103970" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103980">As if he durst</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e103990">Be Caesar's rival. Here he comes, with ease</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104000">I will remove this scruple. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104010" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104020">How! so private! </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104030">Mine own house made a brothel ! sir how durst you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104040">Though guarded with your power in court, and greatness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104050">Hold conference with my wife? as for your minion</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104060"><pb facs="9"/> I shall hereafter treat. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104070" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104080">You are rude, and saucy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104090">Nor know to whom you speak. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104100" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104110">This is fine i'faith! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104120" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104130">Your wife? but touch her, that respect forgotten</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104140">That's due to her, whom mightiest Caesar favours</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104150">And think what 'tis to die. Not to lose time. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104160">She's Caesar's choice. It is sufficient honour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104170">You were his taster in this heavenly nectar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104180">But now must quit the office. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104190" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104200">This is rare. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104210">Cannot a man be master of his wife</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104220">Because she's young, and fair, without a patent. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104230">I in mine own house am an emperor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104240">And will defend what's mine, where are my knaves? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104250">If such an insolence escape unpunished. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104260" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104270">In yourself Lamia. Caesar hath forgotten</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104280">To use his power, and I his instrument,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104290">In whom though absent, his authority speaks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104300">Have lost my faculties. <stage xml:id="A07247-e104310">Stampes.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104320" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104330">The guard! why am I<stage xml:id="A07247-e104340">Enter a centurion with soldiers.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104350">Designed for death? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104360" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104370">As you desire my favour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104380">Take not so rough a course. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104390" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104400">All your desires</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104410">Are absolute commands. Yet give me leave</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104420">To put the will of Caesar into act. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104430">Here's a bill of divorce between your lordship,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104440">And this great lady. If you refuse to sign it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104450">And so as if you did it uncompelled,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104460">Won to it by reasons that concern yourself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104470">Her honour too untainted. Here are clerks. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104480">Shall in your best blood write it new, till torture</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104490">Compel you to perform it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104500" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104510">Is this legal? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104520" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104530">Monarchs that dare not do unlawful things,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104540">Yet bore them out are constables, not Kings</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104550" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104560">Will you dispute? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104570" who="A07247-lamia">
            <pb facs="10"/>
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104580">I know not what to urge</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104590">Against myself, but too much dotage on her</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104600">Love and observance. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104610" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104620">Set it under your hand</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104630">That you are impotent, and cannot pay</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104640">The duties of a husband, or that you are mad</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104650">(Rather than want just cause we'll make you so)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104660">Dispatch, you know the danger else, deliver it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104670">Nay on your knee. Madam you now are free</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104680">And mistress of yourself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104690" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104700">Can you Domitia</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104710">Consent to this? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104720" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104730">'Twould argue a base mind</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104740">To live a servant, when I may command. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104750">I now am Caesar●'s, and yet in respect</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104760">I once was yours, when you come to the palace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104770">(Provided you deserve it in your service)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104780">You shall find me your good mistress, wait me Parthenius</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104790">And now farewell poor Lamia. <stage xml:id="A07247-e104800">Exeunt omnes preter Longinum.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104810" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104820">To the gods</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104830">I bend my knees, (For tyranny hath banished</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104840">Justice from men) and as they would deserve</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104850">Their altars, and our vows, humbly invoke 'em</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104860">That this my ravished wife may prove as fatal</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104870">To proud Domitian, and her embraces</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104880">Afford him in the end as little joy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104890">As wanton Helen brought to him of Troy. <stage xml:id="A07247-e104900">Exit.</stage></l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="scene" xml:id="A07247-e104910">
          <head>Actus, i. Scaena, 3.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e104920">Enter, lictors, Arctinus, Fulcinius, Rusticus, Sura, Paris, Latinus, Aesopus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104930" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Ar●t.. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104940">Father's conscript may this our meeting be</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104950">Happy to Caesar and the common wealth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104960" who="A07247-lictor">
            <speaker>Lictor</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104970">Silence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e104980" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e104990">The purpose of this frequent senate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105000">Is 〈◊〉 to give thanks to the gods of Rome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105010">That for the propagation of the empire,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105020"><pb facs="10"/> vouchsafe us one to govern it like themselves</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105030">In height of courage, depth of understanding,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105040">And all those virtues, and remarkable graces,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105050">Which make a prince most eminent, our Domitian</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105060">Transcends the ancient Romans. I can never</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105070">Bring his praise to a period. What good man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105080">That is a friend to truth, dares make it doubtful,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105090">That he hath Fabius' staidness, and the courage</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105100">Of bold Marcellus, to whom Hannibal gave</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105110">The style of target, and the sword of Rome. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105120">But he has more, and every touch more roman</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105130">As Pompey's dignity, Augustus' state,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105140">Antony's bounty, and great Julius' fortune. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105150">With Cato's resolution. I am lost</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105160">In th'ocean of his virtues. In a word</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105170">All excellencies of good men in him meet,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105180">But no part of their vices. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105190" who="A07247-rusticus">
            <speaker>Rust.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105200">This is no flattery! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105210" who="A07247-sura">
            <speaker>Sur.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105220">Take heed, you'll be observed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105230" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105240">'Tis then most fit</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105250">That we (As to the father of our country,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105260">Like thankful sons, stand bound to pay true service</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105270">For all those blessings that he showers upon us)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105280">Should not connive, and see his government,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105290">Depraved and scandalised by meaner men</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105300">That to his favour, and indulgence owe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105310">Themselves and being. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105320" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105330">Now he points at us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105340" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105350">Cite Paris the tragedian. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105360" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105370">Here. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105380" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Ar●t. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105390">Stand forth. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105400">In thee, as being the chief of thy profession,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105410">I do accuse the quality of treason,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105420">As libellers against the state and Caesar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105430" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105440">Mere accusations are not proofs my lord,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105450">In what are we delinquents? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105460" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105470">You are they</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105480">That search into the secrets of the time,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105490">And under feigned names on the stage present</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105500"><pb facs="11"/> actions not to be touched at; and traduce</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105510">Persons of rank, and quality of both sexes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105520">And with satirical. and bitter jests</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105530">Make even the senators ridiculous</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105540">To the plebeians. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105550" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105560">If I free not myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105570">(And in myself the rest of my profession)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105580">From these false imputations, and prove</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105590">That they make that a libel which the poet</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105600">Writ for a comedy, so acted too,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105610">It is but justice that we undergo</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105620">The heaviest censure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105630" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105640">Are you on the stage</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105650">You talk so boldly? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105660" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105670">The whole word being one</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105680">This place is not exempted, and I am</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105690">So confident in the justice of our cause,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105700">That I could wish Caesar, in whose great name</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105710">All Kings are comprehended sat as judge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105720">To hear our plea, and then determine of us.</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105730">If to express a man sold to his lusts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105740">Wasting the treasure of his time and fortunes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105750">In wanton dalliance, and to what sad end</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105760">A wretch that's so given over does arrive at,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105770">Deterring careless youth, by his example,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105780">From such licentious courses; laying open</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105790">The snares of bawds, and the consuming arts</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105800">Of prodigal strumpets, can deserve reproof,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105810">Why are not all your golden principles</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105820">Writ down by grave philosophers to instruct us</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105830">To choose fair virtue for our guide, not pleasure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105840">Condemn unto the fire? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105850" who="A07247-sura">
            <speaker>Sura.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105860">There's spirit in this. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e105870" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105880">Or if desire of honour was the base</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105890">On which the building of the Roman empire</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105900">Was raised up to this height; if to inflame</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105910">The noble youth with an ambitious heat</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105920">T'indure the frosts of danger, nay of death</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105930"><pb facs="11"/> to be thought worthy the triumphal wreath</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105940">By glorious undertakings, may deserve</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105950">Reward, or favour, from the common wealth. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105960">Actor's may put in for as large a share</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105970">As all the sects of the philosophers;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105980">They which could precepts (Perhaps seldom read)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e105990">Deliver what an honourable thing</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106000">The active virtue is. But does that fire</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106010">The blood, or swell the veins with emulation</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106020">To be both good, and great, equal to that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106030">Which is presented on our theatres? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106040">Let a good actor in a lofty scene</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106050">Show great Alcides honoured in the sweat</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106060">Of his twelve labours; or a bold Cancillus</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106070">Forbidding Rome to be redeemed with gold</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106080">From the insulting Gaul's; or Scipio</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106090">After his victories imposing tribute</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106100">On conquered Carthage. I● done to the life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106110">As if they saw their dangers, and their glories,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106120">And did partake with them in their rewards,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106130">All that have any spark of roman in them</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106140">The slothful arts laid by, contend to be</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106150">Like those they see presented. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e106160" who="A07247-rusticus">
            <speaker>Rust.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106170">He has put</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106180">The consuls to their whisper,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e106190" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106200">But 'tis urged</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106210">That we corrupt youth, and traduce superiors:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106220">When do we bring a vice upon the stage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106230">That does go off unpunished? do we teach</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106240">By the success of wicked undertakings,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106250">Others to tread, in their forbidden steps? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106260">We show no arts of Lydian pandarism,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106270">Corinthian poisons, Persian flatteries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106280">But mulcted so in the conclusion that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106290">Even those spectators that were so inclined,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106300">Go home changed men. And for traducing such</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106310">That are above us, publishing to the world</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106320">Their secret crimes we are as innocent</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106330"><pb facs="12"/> as such as are born dumb. When we present</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106340">An heir, that does conspire against the life</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106350">Of his dear parent, numbering every hour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106360">He lives as tedious to him, if there be</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106370">Among the auditors one whose conscience tells him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106380">He is of the same mould we cannot help it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106390">Or bringing on the stage a loose adultress,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106400">That does maintain the riotous expense</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106410">Of him that feeds her greedy lust, yet suffers</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106420">The lawful pledges of a former bed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106430">To starve the while for hunger, if a matron</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106440">However great in fortune, birth, or titles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106450">Guilty of such a foul unnatural sin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106460">Cry out 'tis writ by me, we cannot help it:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106470">Or when a covetous man's expressed, whose wealth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106480">Arithmetic cannot number, and whose lordships</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106490">A falcon in one day cannot fly over</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106500">Yet he so sordid in his mind, so griping</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106510">As not to afford himself the necessaries</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106520">To maintain life, if a patrician,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106530">(Though honoured with a consulship) find himself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106540">Touched to the quick in this▪ we cannot help it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106550">Or when we show a judge that is corrupt</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106560">And will give up his sentence as he favours,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106570">The person, not the cause, saving the guilty</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106580">If of his faction, and as oft condemning</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106590">The innocent out of particular spleen,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106600">If any in this reverend assembly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106610">Nay e'en yourself my lord, that are the image</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106620">Of absent Caesar feel something in your bosom</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106630">That puts you in remembrance of things past,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106640">Or things intended 'tis not in us to help it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106650">I have said, my lord, and now as you find cause</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106660">Or censure us, or free us with applause. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e106670" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106680">Well pled on my life I never saw him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106690">Act an orators part before. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e106700" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106710">We might have given</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106720">Ten double fees to Regulus, and yet</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106730"><pb facs="12"/> our cause delivered worse. <stage xml:id="A07247-e106740">A shout within, enter Parthenius.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e106750" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106760">What shout is that? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e106770" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106780">Caesar our lord married to conquest, is</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106790">Returned in triumph. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e106800" who="A07247-fulcinius">
            <speaker>Fulcin.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106810">Let's all haste to meet him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e106820" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106830">Break up the court, we will reserve to him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106840">The censure of this cause</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e106850" who="A07247-all">
            <speaker>All.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106860">Long life to Caesar. <stage xml:id="A07247-e106870">Exeunt omnes.</stage></l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="scene" xml:id="A07247-e106880">
          <head>Actus, i. Scaena, 4.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e106890">Enter Julia, Caenis, Domitilla, Domitia.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e106900" who="A07247-caenis">
            <speaker>Caen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106910">Stand back the place is mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e106920" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106930">Yours am I not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106940">Great Titus' daughter, and Domitian's niece</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106950">Dares any claim precedence? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e106960" who="A07247-caenis">
            <speaker>Caen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106970">I was more</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106980">The mistress of your father, and in his right</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e106990">Claim duty from you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107000" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107010">I confess you were useful</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107020">To please his appetite. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107030" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domi●.. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107040">To end the controversy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107050">For I'll have no contending, I'll be bold</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107060">To lead the way myself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107070" who="A07247-domitilla">
            <speaker>Domitil. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107080">You minion▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107090" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domi●. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107100">Yes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107110">And all ere long shall kneel to catch my favours. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107120" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Iul,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107130">Whence springs this flood of greatness? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107140" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107150">You shall know</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107160">To soon for your vexation, and perhaps</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107170">Repent too late, and pine with envy when</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107180">You see whom Caesar favours</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107190" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107200">Observe the sequel. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e107210"><pb facs="13"/>Enter at one door captains with laurels, Domitian, in his triumphant chariot, Parthenius, Paris, Latinus, Aesopus met by Aretinus, Sura, Lamia, Rusticus, Fulcinius, and prisoners led by him. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107220" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107230">As we now touch the height of humane glory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107240">Riding in triumph to the Capitol,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107250">Let these whom this victorious arm hath made</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107260">The scorn of fortune, and the slaves of Rome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107270">Taste the extremes of misery. Bear them off</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107280">To the common prisons, and there let them prove</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107290">How sharp our axes are. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107300" who="A07247-rusticus">
            <speaker>Rust.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107310">A bloody entrance▪</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107320" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107330">To tell you, you are happy in your prince</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107340">Were to distrust your love, or my desert</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107350">And either were distasteful. Or to boast</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107360">How much, not by my deputies, but myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107370">I have enlarged the empire; or what horrors</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107380">The soldier in our conduct hath broke through,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107390">Would better suit the mouth of Plautus' braggart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107400">Than the adored monarch of the world. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107410" who="A07247-sura">
            <speaker>Sura.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107420">This is no boast. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107430" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107440">When I but name the Daci,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107450">And grey eyed Germans whom I have subdued,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107460">The ghost of Julius will look pale with envy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107470">And great Vespasian's, and Titus' triumph,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107480">(Truth must take place of father and of brother)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107490">Will be no more remembered. I am above</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107500">All honours you can give me. And the ●tile</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107510">Of lord, and God, which thankful subjects give me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107520">(Not my ambition) is deserved,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107530" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107540">At all parts</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107550">Celestial sacrifice is fit for Caesar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107560">In our acknowledgement. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107570" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107580">Thanks Aretinus</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107590">Still hold our favour. Now● the god of war,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107600">And famine, blood, and death, Bellona's pages</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107610"><pb facs="13"/> banished from Rome to Thrace in our good fortune. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107620">With justice he may taste the fruits of peace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107630">Whose sword hath ploughed the ground, and reaped the harvest</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107640">Of your prosperity. Nor can I think</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107650">That there is one among you so ungrateful,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107660">Or such an enemy, to thriving virtue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107670">That can esteem the jewel he holds dearest</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107680">Too good for Caesar's use</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107690" who="A07247-sura">
            <speaker>Sur.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107700">All we possess. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107710" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107720">Our liberties. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107730" who="A07247-fulcinius">
            <speaker>Fulcin.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107740">Our children. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107750" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107760">Wealth. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107770" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107780">And throats</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107790">Fall willingly beneath his feet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107800" who="A07247-rusticus">
            <speaker>Rust.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107810">Base flattery. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107820">What roman could endure this? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107830" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107840">This calls on</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107850">My love to all, which spreads itself among you. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107860">The beauties of the time I receive the honour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107870">To kiss the hand, which reared up thus, holds thunder</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107880">To you 'tis an assurance of a calm. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107890">Julia my niece and Caenis the delight</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107900">Of old Vespasian, Domitilla to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107910">A Princess of our blood. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107920" who="A07247-rusticus">
            <speaker>Rust.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107930">'Tis strange his pride</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107940">Affords no greater courtesy to ladies</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107950">Of such high birth and rank. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107960" who="A07247-sura">
            <speaker>Sur.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107970">Your wife's forgotten</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e107980" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e107990">No she will be remembered fear it not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108000">She will be graced and greased. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108010" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108020">But when I look on</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108030">Divine Domitian, methinks we should meet</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108040">(The lesser gods applauding the encounter)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108050">As Jupiter the giants lying dead</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108060">On the Phlegraean plain embraced this Juno</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108070">Lamia 'tis your honour that she's mine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108080" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108090">You are too great to be gainsaid. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108100" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108110">Let all</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108120"><pb facs="14"/> that fear our frown, or do affect our favour,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108130">Without examining the reason why,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108140">Salute her (By this kiss I make it good)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108150">With the title of Augusta. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108160" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108170">Still your servant,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108180" who="A07247-all">
            <speaker>All.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108190">Long live Augusta great Domitian's empress. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108200" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108210">Paris my hand. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108220" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108230">The god's still honour Caesar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108240" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108250">The wars are ended, and our arms laid by</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108260">We are for soft delights. Command the poets</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108270">To use their choicest, and most rare invention</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108280">To entertain the time, and be you careful</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108290">To give it action, we'll provide the people</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108300">Pleasures of all kinds. My Domitia think not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108310">I flatter, though thus fond, on to the Capitol</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108320">'Tis death to him that wears a sullen brow:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108330">This 'tis to be a monarch when alone</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108340">He can command all, but is awed by none</l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e108350">Exeunt.</stage>
          <trailer xml:id="A07247-e108360">The end of the first act.</trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="act" xml:id="A07247-e108370">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A07247-e108380">
          <head>Actus, ii. scaena, 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e108390">Enter Philargus, Parthenius. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108400" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108410">My son to tutor me. Know your obedience</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108420">And question not my will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108430" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108440">Sir were I one</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108450">Whom want compelled to wish a full possession</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108460">Of what is yours. Or had I ever numbered</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108470">Your years, or thought you lived too long, with reason</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108480">You then might nourish ill opinions of me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108490">Or did the suit that I prefer to you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108500">Concern myself, and aimed not at your good</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108510">You might deny, and I sit down with patience,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108520">And after never press you,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108530" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108540">I' the name of Pluto</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108550">What wouldst thou have me do? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108560" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <pb facs="14"/>
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108570">Right to yourself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108580">Or suffer me to do it. Can you imagine</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108590">This nasty hat, this tattered cloak, rent shoe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108600">This sordid linen can become the master</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108610">Of your fair fortunes? whose superfluous means</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108620">(Though I were burdensome) could clothe you in</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108630">The costliest Persian silks, studded with jewels</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108640">The spoils of provinces, and every day</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108650">Fresh change of Tyrian purple. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108660" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108670">Out upon thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108680">My moneys in my coffers melt to hear thee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108690">Purple, hence prodigal. Shall I make my mercer</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108700">Or Taylor my heir, or see my jeweller purchase</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108710">No, I hate pride. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108720" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108730">Yet decency would do well. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108740">Though for your outside you will not be altered,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108750">Let me prevail so far yet, as to win you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108760">Not to deny your belly nourishment;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108770">Neither to think you have feasted when 'tis crammed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108780">With mouldy barley bread, onions, and leeks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108790">And the drink of bondmen water. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108800" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108810">Wouldst thou have me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108820">Be an Apicius, or a Lucullus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108830">And riot out my state in curious sauces? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108840">Wise nature with a little is contented,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108850">And following her, my guide, I cannot err. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108860" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108870">But you destroy her in your want of care</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108880">(I blush to see, and speak it) to maintain her</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108890">In perfect health and vigour, when you suffer</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108900">(Frighted with the charge of physic) rheums, catarrhs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108910">The scurf, ache in your bones to grow upon you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108920">And hasten on your fate with too much sparing. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108930">When a cheap purge, a vomit and good diet</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108940">May lengthen it, give me but leave to send</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108950">The emperor's doctor to you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e108960" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108970">I'll be born first</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108980">Half rotten to the fire, that must consume me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e108990">His pills, his cordials, his electuaries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109000"><pb facs="15"/> his syrups julips, bezerstone nor his</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109010">Imagined unicorn's horn comes in my belly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109020">My mouth shall be a draught first, 'tis resolved. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109030">No; I'll not lessen my dear golden heap. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109040">Which every hour increasing does renew. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109050">My youth, and vigour, but if lessened, then,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109060">Than my poor heartstrings crack. Let me enjoy it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109070">And brood o'er't while I live, it being my life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109080">My soul, my all. But when I turn to dust,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109090">And part from what is more esteemed by me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109100">Then all the gods, Rome's thousand altars smoke to,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109110">Inherit thou my adoration of it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109120">And like me serve my idol. <stage xml:id="A07247-e109130">Exit Philargus.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109140" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109150">What a strange torture</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109160">Is avarice to itself! what man that looks on</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109170">Such a penurious spectacle but must</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109180">Know what the fable meant of Tantalus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109190">Or the ass whose back is cracked with curious viands</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109200">Yet feeds on thistles. Some course I must take,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109210">To make my father know what cruelty</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109220">He uses on himself. <stage xml:id="A07247-e109230">Enter Paris.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109240" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109250">Sir with your pardon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109260">I make bold to inquire the emperor's pleasure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109270">For, being by him commanded to attend</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109280">Your favour may instruct us what's his will. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109290">Shall be this night presented? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109300" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109310">My loved Paris,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109320">Without my intercession you well know</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109330">You may make your own approaches, since his ear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109340">To you is ever open. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109350" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109360">I acknowledge</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109370">His clemency to my weakness, and if ever. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109380">I do abuse it, lightning strike me dead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109390">The grace he pleases to confer upon me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109400">(Without boast I may say so much) was never</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109410">Employed to wrong the innocent, or to incense</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109420">His fury. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109430" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109440">'Tis confessed many men owe you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109450"><pb facs="15"/> for provinces they never hoped for; and their lives</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109460">Forfeited to his anger, you being absent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109470">I could say more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109480" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109490">You still are my good patron. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109500">And lay it in my fortune to deserve it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109510">You should perceive the poorest of your clients</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109520">To his best abilities thankful. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109530" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109540">I believe so. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109550">Met you my father? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109560" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109570">Yes sir, with much grief. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109580">To see him as he is. Can nothing work him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109590">To be himself? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109600" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109610">O Paris 'tis a weight</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109620">Sits heavy here, and could this right hands loss</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109630">Remove it, it should off but he is deaf</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109640">To all persuasion. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109650" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109660">Sir with your pardon,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109670">I'll offer my advice! I once observed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109680">In a tragedy of ours, in which a murder</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109690">Was acted to the life, a guilty hearer</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109700">Forced by the terror of a wounded conscience,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109710">To make discovery of that, which torture</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109720">Could not wring from him. Nor can it appear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109730">Like an impossibility, but that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109740">Your father looking on a covetous man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109750">Presented on the stage as in a mirror</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109760">May see his own deformity, and loathe it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109770">Now could you but persuade the emperor</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109780">To see a comedy we have that's styled</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109790">The cure of avarice, and to command</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109800">Your father to be a spectator of it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109810">He shall be so anatomised in the scene,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109820">And see himself so personated; the baseness</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109830">Of a self torturing miserable wretch</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109840">Truly described that I much hope the object</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109850">Will work compunction in him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109860" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109870">There's your fee</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109880">I never bought better counsel. Be you in readiness</l>
            <pb facs="16"/>
            <pb facs="16"/>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109890"><pb facs="17"/> I will effect the rest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109900" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109910">Sir when you please</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109920">We'll be prepared to enter. Sir the emperor. <stage xml:id="A07247-e109930">Exit. Paris.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e109940">Enter Caesar, Arctinus, guard.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109950" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109960">Repine at us? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e109970" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109980">'Tis, more, or my informers</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e109990">That keep strict watch upon him are deceived</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110000">In their intelligence there is a list</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110010">Of malcontents, as Junius Rusticus</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110020">Palphurius, Sura, and this Aelius, Lamia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110030">That murmur at your triumphs as mere pageants;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110040">And at their midnight meetings tax your justice</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110050">(For so I style what they call tyranny)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110060">For Paetus Thrasea's death, as if in him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110070">Virtue herself were murdered; nor forget they</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110080">Agricola (Who for his service done</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110090">In the reducing Brittany to obedience)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110100">They dare affirm to be removed with poison,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110110">And he compelled to write you a coheir</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110120">With his daughter, that his testament might stand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110130">Which else you had made void. Then your much love</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110140">To Julia your niece, censured as incest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110150">And done in scorn of Titus your dead brother;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110160">But the divorce Lamia was forced to sign</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110170">To her, you honour with Augusta's title,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110180">Being only named, they do conclude there was</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110190">A Lucrece once, a Collatine, and a Brutus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110200">But nothing roman left now, but in you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110210">The lust of Tarquin. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e110220" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110230">Yes. His fire, and scorn</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110240">Of such as think that our unlimited power</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110250">Can be confined, dares Lamia pretend</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110260">An interest to that which I call mine? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110270">Or but remember, she was ever his</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110280">That's now in our possession? fetch him hither. <stage xml:id="A07247-e110290">The guard go of.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110300">I'll give him cause to wish he rather had</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110310"><pb facs="17"/> forgotten his own name then e'er mentioned hers. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110320">Shall we be circumscribed? let such as cannot</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110330">By force make good their actions, though wicked</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110340">Conceal, excuse or qualify their crimes:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110350">What our desires grant leave, and privilege to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110360">Though contradicting all divine decrees,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110370">Or laws confirmed by Romulus, and Numa,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110380">Shall be held sacred. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e110390" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110400">You should else take from</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110410">The dignity of Caesar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e110420" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110430">Am I master</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110440">Of two and thirty legions, that awe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110450">All nations, of the triumphed world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110460">Yet tremble at our frown, yield an account</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110470">Of what's our pleasure to a private man? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110480">Rome perish first, and Atlas' shoulders shrink,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110490">Heavens fabric fall; the sun, the moon, the stars</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110500">Losing their light, and comfortable heat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110510">Ere I confess, that any fault of mine</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110520">May be disputed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e110530" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110540">So you preserve your power</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110550">As you should equal, and omnipotent here,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110560">With Jupiter's above. <stage xml:id="A07247-e110570">Parthenius kneeling whispers to Caesar.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e110580" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110590">Thy suit is granted</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110600">Whate'er it be Parthenius for thy service</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110610">Done to Augusta. Only so? A trifle. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110620">Command him hither. If the comedy fail</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110630">To cure him, I will minister something to him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110640">That shall instruct him to forget his gold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110650">And think upon himself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e110660" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110670">May it succeed well</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110680">Since my intents are pious. <stage xml:id="A07247-e110690">Exit Parthenius.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e110700" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110710">We are resolved</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110720">What course to take, and therefore Aretinus</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110730">Inquire no farther. Go you to my empress,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110740">And say I do entreat (For she rules him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110750">Whom all men else obey) she would vouchsafe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110760">The music of her voice, at yonder window,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110770"><pb facs="18"/> when I advance my hand thus. I will blend<stage xml:id="A07247-e110780">Exit Aretinus.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110790">My cruelty with some scorn, or else 'tis lost. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110800">Revenge, when it is unexpected falling,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110810">With greater violence; and hate clothed in smiles,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110820">Strikes, and with horror dead the wretch that comes not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110830">Prepared to meet it. Our good Lamia welcome. <stage xml:id="A07247-e110840">Enter Lamia with the guard.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110850">So much we owe you for a benefit</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110860">With willingness on your part conferred upon us,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110870">That ''tis our study we that would not live</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110880">Engaged to any for a courtesy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110890">How to return it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e110900" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110910">'Tis beneath your fate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110920">To be obliged that in your own hand grasp</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110930">The means to be magnificent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e110940" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110950">Well put off</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110960">But yet it must not do, the empire, Lamia,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110970">Divided equally can hold no weight,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110980">If balanced with your gift in fair Domitia. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e110990">You that could part with all delights at once,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111000">The magazine of rich pleasures being contained</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111010">In her perfections, uncompelled delivered. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111020">As a present fit for Caesar. In your eyes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111030">With tears of joy, not sorrow, 'tis confirmed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111040">You glory in your act. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e111050" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111060">Derided too! </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111070">Sir this is more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e111080" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111090">More than I can requite</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111100">It is acknowledged Lamia. There's no drop</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111110">Of melting nectar I taste from her lip,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111120">But yields a touch of immortality</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111130">To the blessed receiver; every grace and feature,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111140">Prized to the worth, bought at an easy rate;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111150">If purchased for a consulship. Her discourse. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111160">So ravishing, and her action so attractive,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111170">That I would part with all my other senses</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111180">Provided I might ever see, and hear her. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111190">The pleasures of her bed I dare not trust</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111200">The winds or air with, for that would draw down</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111210"><pb facs="18"/> in envy of my happiness, a war</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111220">From all the gods upon me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e111230" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111240">Your compassion</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111250">To me is your forbearing to insult</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111260">On my calamity which you make your sport,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111270">Would more appease those gods you have provoked</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111280">Then all the blasphemous comparisons,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111290">You sing unto her praise. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e111300" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111310">I sing her praise? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111320">'Tis far from my ambition to hope it. <stage xml:id="A07247-e111330">Music above and a song.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111340">It being a debt she only can lay down,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111350">And no tongue else discharge. Hark. I think prompted</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111360">With my consent that you once more should hear her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111370">She does begin. An universal silence</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111380">Dwell on this place. 'tis death with lingering torments</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111390">To all that dare disturb her. Who can hear this<stage xml:id="A07247-e111400">The song ended Caesar go on.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111410">And falls not down and worships? in my fancy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111420">Apollo being judge on Latino's hill,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111430">Fair haired Calliope on her ivory lute</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111440">(But something short of this) sung Ceres praises</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111450">And grisly Pluto's rape on Proserpine. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111460">The motion of the spheres are out of time</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111470">Her musical notes but heard. Say Lamia, say,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111480">Is not her voice angelical? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e111490" who="A07247-lamia">
            <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111500">To your ear. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111510">But I alas am silent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e111520" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111530">Be so ever,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111540">That without admiration canst hear her. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111550">Malice to my felicity strikes thee dumb,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111560">And in thy hope, or wish to repossess</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111570">What I love more than empire, I pronounce thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111580">Guilty of treason. Off with his head. Do you stare? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111590">By her, that is my patroness, Minerva,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111600">(Whose statue I adore of all the gods)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111610">If he but live to make reply thy life<stage xml:id="A07247-e111620">The guard lead off Lamia slopping his mouth.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111630">Shall answer it. My fears of him are freed now</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111640">And he that lived to upbraid me with my wrong</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111650">For an offence he never could imagine</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111660"><pb facs="19"/> in wantonness removed. Descend my dearest. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111670">Plurality of husbands shall no more</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111680">Breed doubts or jealousies in you. 'tis dispatched</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111690">And with as little trouble here, as if</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111700">I had killed a fly. Now you appear and in<stage xml:id="A07247-e111710">Enter Domitia, ushered in by Aretinus, her train with all state born up by Julia, Caenis, and Domitilla.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111720">That glory you deserve, and these that stoop</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111730">To do you service in the act much honoured. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111740">Julia forget that Titus was thy father,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111750">Canis and Domitilla never remember</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111760">Sabinus, or Vespasian. To be slaves</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111770">To her, is more true liberty then to live</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111780">Parthian or Asian Queens. As lesser stars</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111790">That wait on Phoebe in her full of brightness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111800">Compared to her you are (Thus I seat you)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111810">By Caesar's side. Commanding these that once</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111820">Were the adored glories of the time</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111830">To witness to the world they are your vassals</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111840">At your feet to attend you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e111850" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111860">'Tis your pleasure</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111870">And not my pride. And yet when I consider</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111880">That I am yours, all duties they can pay</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111890">I do receive as circumstances due</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111900">To her you please to honour. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e111910">Enter Parthenius with Philargus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e111920" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111930">Caesar's will</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111940">Commands you hither, nor must you gainsay it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e111950" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111960">Lose time to see an interlude? must I pay to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111970">For my vexation? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e111980" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e111990">Not in the court,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112000">It is the emperor's charge. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112010" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112020">I shall endure</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112030">My torment then the better. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112040" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112050">Can it be</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112060">This sordid thing Parthenius is thy father? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112070">No actor can express him. I had held</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112080">The fiction for impossible in the scene,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112090"><pb facs="19"/> had I not seen the substance. Sirrah sit still,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112100">And give attention, if you but nod</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112110">You sleep for ever. Let them spare the prologue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112120">And all the ceremonies proper to our self</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112130">And come to the last act, there where the cure</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112140">By the doctor is made perfect. The swift minutes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112150">Seem years to me Domitia that divorce thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112160">From my embraces. My desires increasing</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112170">As they are satisfied all pleasures else</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112180">Are tedious as dull sorrows. Kiss me, again:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112190">If I now wanted heat of youth, these fires</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112200">In Priam's veins would thaw his frozen blood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112210">Enabling him to get a second Hector</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112220">For the defence of Troy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112230" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112240">You are wanton? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112250">Pray you forbear. Let me see the play. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112260" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112270">Begin there. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e112280">Enter Paris like a doctor of physic, Aesopus, Latinus brought forth asleep in a chair, a key in his mouth. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112290" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112300">O master doctor he is past recovery</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112310">A lethargy hath ceased him. And however</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112320">His sleep resemble death his watchful care</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112330">To guard that treasure he dares make no use of,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112340">Works strongly in his soul. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112350" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112360">What's that he holds</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112370">So fast between his teeth? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112380" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112390">The key that opens</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112400">His iron chests crammed with accursed gold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112410">Rusty with long imprisonment. There's no duty</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112420">In me his son, nor confidence in friends,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112430">That can persuade him to deliver up</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112440">That to the trust of any. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112450" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112460">He is the wiser</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112470">We were fashioned in one mould. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112480" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112490">He eate● with it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112500">And when devotion calls him to the temple</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112510"><pb facs="20"/> of Mammon, whom of all the gods he kneels to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112520">That held thus still, his orisons are paid;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112530">Or will he though, the wealth of Rome were pawned</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112540">For the restoring of it for one short hour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112550">Be won to part with it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112560" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112570">Still, still myself. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112580">And if like me he love his gold, no pawn</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112590">Is good security. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112600" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112610">I'll try if I can force it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112620">It will not be. His avaritious mind</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112630">(Like men in rivers drowned) makes him gripe fast</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112640">To his last gasp what he in life held dearest. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112650">And if that it were possible in nature</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112660">Would carry it with him to the other world. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112670" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112680">As I would do to hell rather than leave it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112690" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112700">Is he not dead? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112710">Long since to all good actions</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112720">Or to himself, or others, for which wise men</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112730">Desire to live. You may with safety pinch him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112740">Or under his nails stick needle, ● yet he stirs not,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112750">Anxious fear to lose what his soul dotes on</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112760">Renders his flesh insensible. We must use</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112770">Some means to rouse the sleeping faculties</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112780">Of his mind, there lies the lethargy. Take a trumpet</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112790">And blow it into his ears, 'tis to no purpose</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112800">The roaring noise of thunder cannot wake him▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112810">And yet despair not I have one trick yet left</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112820" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112830">What is it? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112840" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112850">I will cause a fearful dream</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112860">To steal into his fancy, and disturb it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112870">With the horror it brings with it, and so free</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112880">His body's organs. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112890" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112900">'Tis a cunning fellow,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112910">If he were indeed a doctor as the play says,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112920">He should be sworn my servant, govern my slumbers</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112930">And minister to me waking. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e112940" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112950">If this fail<stage xml:id="A07247-e112960">A chest brought in.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112970">I'll give him o'er. So with all violence</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112980"><pb facs="20"/> rend open this iron chest. For here is life lies</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e112990">Bound up in fetters, and in the defence</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113000">Of what he values higher, 'twill return</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113010">And fill each vein and artery. Lowder yet. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113020">'Tis open, and already he begins</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113030">To stir, mark with what trouble. <stage xml:id="A07247-e113040">Latinus stretches themselves. </stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113050" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113060">As you are Caesar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113070">Defend this honest thrifty man, they are thieves,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113080">And come to rob him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113090" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113100">Peace the emperor frowns. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113110" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113120">So now pour out the bags upon the table,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113130">Remove his jewels, and his bonds, again. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113140">Ring a second golden peal, his eyes are open. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113150">He stares as he had seen Medusa's head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113160">And were turned marble. Once more. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113170" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113180">Murder, murder,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113190">They us murder, murder. My son in the plot? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113200">Thou worse than parricide if it be death</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113210">To strike thy father's body, can all tortures,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113220">The furies in hell practise, be sufficient</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113230">For thee that dost assassinate my soul? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113240">My gold! my bounds! my jewels! dost thou envy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113250">My glad possession of them for a day? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113260">Extinguishing the taper of my life</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113270">Consumed unto the snuff? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113280" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113290">Seem not to mind him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113300" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113310">Have I to leave thee rich denied myself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113320">The joys of human being? Scraped and hoarded</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113330">A mass of treasure, which had Solon seen</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113340">The Lydian Croesus had appeared to him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113350">Poor as the beggar Irus. And yet I</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113360">Solicitous to increase it, when my entrails</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113370">Were clemed with keeping a perpetual fast,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113380">Was deaf to their loud windy cries, as fearing</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113390">Should I disburse one penny to their use,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113400">My heir might curse me. And to save expense</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113410">In outward ornaments, I did expose</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113420">My naked body to the winter's cold,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113430">And summer's scorching heat. Nay when diseases</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113440"><pb facs="21"/> grew thick upon me, and a little cost</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113450">Had purchased my recovery, I chose rather</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113460">To have my ashes closed up in my urn,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113470">By hasting on my fate, than to diminish</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113480">The gold my prodigal son, while I am living,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113490">Carelessly scatters. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113500" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113510">Would you would dispatch and die once. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113520">Y●●● ghost should feel in hell, that is my slave</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113530">Which was your master. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113540" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113550">Out upon thee varlet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113560" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113570">And what then follows all your cark, and caring,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113580">And self affliction when your starved trunk is</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113590">Turned to forgotten dust? This hopeful youth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113600">Urines upon your monument. Never remembering</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113610">How much for him you suffered. And then tells</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113620">To the companions of his lusts, and riots,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113630">The hell you did endure on earth to leave him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113640">Large means to be an epicure, and to feast</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113650">His senses all at once, a happiness</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113660">You never granted to yourself. Your gold then</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113670">(Got with vexation, and preserved with trouble)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113680">Maintains the public stews, panders, and ruffians</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113690">That quaff damnations to your memory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113700">For living so long here. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113710" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113720">'T will be so, I see it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113730">O that I could redeem the time that's past</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113740">I would live, and die like myself; and make true use</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113750">Of what my industry purchased. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113760" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113770">Covetous men</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113780">Having one foot in the grave lament soever . </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113790">But grant that I by art could yet recover</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113800">Your desperate sickness, lengthen out your life</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113810">A dozen of years, as I restore your body</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113820">To perfect health, will you with care endeavour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113830">To rectify your mind</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113840" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113850">I should so live then</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113860">As neither my heir should have just cause to think</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113870">I lived too long for being close handed to him,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113880"><pb facs="21"/> or cruel to myself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113890" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113900">Have your desires</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113910">Phoebus assisting, me I will repair</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113920">The ruined building of your health, and think not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113930">You have a son that hates you; the truth is</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113940">This means with his consent I practised on you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113950">To this good end, it being a device</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113960">In you to show the cure of avarice. <stage xml:id="A07247-e113970">Exeunt Paris, Latinus, Aesopus.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e113980" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e113990">An old fool to be gulled thus I had he died</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114000">As I resolve to do, not to be altered,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114010">It had gone off twanging. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114020" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114030">How approve you sweetest,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114040">Of the matter, and the actors? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114050" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114060">For the subject</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114070">I like it not, it was filched out of Horace,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114080">Nay I have read the poets but the fellow</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114090">That played the doctor did it well by Venus;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114100">He had a tuneable tongue and neat delivery,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114110">And yet in my opinion he would perform</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114120">A lover's part much better. Prithee Caesar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114130">For I grow weary let us see tomorrow</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114140">Iplus and Anaxerete. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114150" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114160">Any thing</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114170">For thy delight Domitia. To your rest</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114180">Till I come to disquiet you. Wait upon her. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114190">There is a business that I must dispatch</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114200">And I will straight be with you. <stage xml:id="A07247-e114210">Exeunt Aretinus, Domitia, Julia, Canis, Domitilla.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114220" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114230">Now my dread sir</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114240">Endeavour to prevail. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114250" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114260">One way or other. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114270">We'll cure him never doubt it. Now Philargus</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114280">Thou wretched thing, hast thou seen thy sordid baseness? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114290">And but observed what a contemptible creature</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114300">A covetous miser is? dost thou in thyself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114310">Feel true compunction! with a resolution</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114320">To be a new man? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114330" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114340">This crazed bodies Caesars,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114350">But for my mind. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114360" who="A07247-caesar">
            <pb facs="22"/>
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114370">Trifle not with my anger. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114380">Canst thou make good use of what was now presented? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114390">And imitate in thy sudden change of life▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114400">The miserable rich man, that expressed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114410">What thou art to the life. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114420" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114430">Pray you give me leave</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114440">To die as I have lived. I must not part with</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114450">My gold, it is my life. I am past cure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114460" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114470">No; by Minerva thou shalt never more</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114480">Feel the least touch of avarice. Take him hence</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114490">And hang him instantly. If there be gold in hell</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114500">Enjoy it, thine here and thy life together</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114510">Is forfeited. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114520" who="A07247-philargus">
            <speaker>Philarg.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114530">Was I sent for to this purpose? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114540" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114550">Mercy for all my service, Caesar mercy</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114560" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114570">Should Jove plead for him. 'tis resolved he dies,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114580">And he that speaks one syllable to dissuade me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114590">And therefore tempt me not. It is but justice. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114600">Since such as wilfully, will hourly die,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114610">Must tax themselves, and not my cruelty. <stage xml:id="A07247-e114620">Exeunt omnes.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <trailer xml:id="A07247-e114630">The end of the second act.</trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="act" xml:id="A07247-e114640">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A07247-e114650">
          <head>Actus, iii. Scaena, 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e114660">Enter Julia, Domitilla, Stephanos. </stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114670" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114680">No Domitilla, if you but compare</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114690">What I have suffered with your injuries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114700">(Though great ones I confess) they will appear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114710">Like molehills to Olimpus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114720" who="A07247-domitilla">
            <speaker>Domitil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114730">You are tender</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114740">Of your own wounds, which makes you lose the feeling</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114750">And sense of mine. The incest he committed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114760">With you, and publicly professed, in scorn</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114770">Of what the world durst censure may admit</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114780">Some weak defence, as being born headlong to it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114790">But in a manly way to enjoy your beauties. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114800"><pb facs="22"/>Besides won by his perjuries that he would</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114810">Salute you with the title of Augusta,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114820">Your faint denial showed a full consent,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114830">And grant to his temptations. But poor I</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114840">That would not yield, but was with violence forced</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114850">To serve his lusts, and in a kind Tiberius</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114860">At caprae never practised, have not here</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114870">One conscious touch to rise up my accuser</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114880">I in my will being innocent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e114890" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114900">Pardon me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114910">Great Princesses, though I presume to tell you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114920">Wasting your time in childish lamentations,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114930">You do degenerate from the blood you spring from:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114940">For there is something more in Rome expected</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114950">From Titus' daughter, and his uncle's heir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114960">Then womanish complaints after such wrongs</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114970">Which mercy cannot pardon. But you'll say</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114980">Your hands are weak, and should you but attempt</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e114990">A just revenge on this inhuman monster. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115000">This prodigy of mankind bloody Domitian,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115010">Hath ready words at his command as well</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115020">As islands to confine you to remove. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115030">His doubts, and fears, did he but entertain</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115040">The least suspicion you contrived or plotted</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115050">Against his person. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115060" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115070">'Tis true Stephanos. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115080">The legions that sacred Jerusalem</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115090">Under my father Titus are sworn his,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115100">And I no more remembered. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115110" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115120">And to lose</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115130">Ourselves by building on impossible hopes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115140">Were desperate madness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115150" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115160">You conclude too fast. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115170">One single arm whose master does contemn</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115180">His own life holds a full command o'er his,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115190">Spite of his guards. I was your bondman lady,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115200">And you my gracious patroness; my wealth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115210">And liberty your gift, and though no soldier,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115220"><pb facs="23"/> to whom or custom, or example makes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115230">Grim death appear less terrible, I dare die</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115240">To do you service in a fair revenge</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115250">And it will better suit your births and honours</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115260">To fall at once, than to live ever slaves</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115270">To his proud empress that insults upon</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115280">Your patient sufferings. Say but you go on,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115290">And ● will retch his heart, or perish in</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115300">The noble undertaking. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115310" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115320">Your free offer</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115330">Confirms your thankfulness, which I acknowledge</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115340">A satisfaction for a greater debt</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115350">Then what you stand engaged for: but I must not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115360">Upon uncertain grounds hazard so grateful,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115370">And good a servant. The mortal powers</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115380">Protect a prince though sold to impious acts,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115390">And seem to slumber till his roaring crimes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115400">Awake their justice: but then looking down</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115410">And with impartial eyes, on his contempt</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115420">Of all religion, and moral goodness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115430">They in their secrets judgements do determine</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115440">To leave him to his wickedness, which sinks him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115450">When he is most secure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115460" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115470">His cruelty</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115480">Increasing daily of necessity</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115490">Must render him as odious to his soldiers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115500">Familiar friends, and freemen, as it hath done</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115510">Already to the senate; then forsaken</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115520">Of his supporters, and grown terrible</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115530">Even to himself, and her, he now so dotes on,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115540">We may put into act, what now with safety</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115550">We cannot whisper,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115560" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>S●eph. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115570">I am still prepared</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115580">To execute when you please to command me:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115590">Since I am confident he deserves much more</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115600">That vindicates his country from a tyranny,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115610">Than he that saves a citizen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115620" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115630">O here's Caenis. <stage xml:id="A07247-e115640">Enter Caenis.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115650" who="A07247-domitilla">
            <pb facs="23"/>
            <speaker>Domi●il. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115660">Whence come you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115670" who="A07247-caenis">
            <speaker>Caen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115680">From the empress who seems moved</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115690">In that you wait no better. Her pride's grown</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115700">To such a height that she disdains the service</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115710">Of her own women; and esteems herself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115720">Neglected? when the Princesses of the blood</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115730">On every course employment, are not ready</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115740">To stoop to her commands. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115750" who="A07247-domitilla">
            <speaker>Domitil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115760">Where is her greatness? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115770" who="A07247-caenis">
            <speaker>Cae●.. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115780">Where you would little think she could descend</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115790">To grace the room or persons. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115800" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115810">Speak; where is she? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115820" who="A07247-caenis">
            <speaker>Cae●. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115830">Among the players, where all state laid by,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115840">She does inquire who acts this part, who that▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115850">And in what habits? blames the tire-women</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115860">For want of curious dressings; and so taken</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115870">She is with Paris the tragedians shape</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115880">That is to act a lover, I thought once</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115890">She would have courted him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115900" who="A07247-domitilla">
            <speaker>Domitil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115910">In the mean time</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115920">How spends the emperor his hours? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e115930" who="A07247-caenis">
            <speaker>Caen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115940">As ever</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115950">He hath done heretofore in being cruel</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115960">To innocent men, whose virtues he calls crimes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115970">And but this morning if't be possible</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115980">He hath outgone himself, having condemned</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e115990">At Aretinus his informer's suit,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116000">Palphurius Sura, and good Junius Rusticus,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116010">Men of the best repute in Rome for their</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116020">Integrity of life; no fault objected</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116030">But that they did lament his cruel sentence</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116040">On Paetus Thraseas the philosopher</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116050">Their patron and instructor. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116060" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116070">Can Jove see this</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116080">And hold his thunder! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116090" who="A07247-domitilla">
            <speaker>Domitil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116100">Nero and Caligula</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116110">Commanded only mischiefs but our Caesar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116120">Delights to see 'em. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116130" who="A07247-julia">
            <pb facs="24"/>
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116140">What we cannot help,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116150">We may deplore with silence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116160" who="A07247-caenis">
            <speaker>Caen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116170">We are called for</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116180">By our proud mistress. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116190" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116200">We a while must suffer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116210" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116220">It is true fortitude to stand firm against</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116230">All shocks of fate, when cowards faint and die</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116240">In fear to suffer more calamity. <stage xml:id="A07247-e116250">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A07247-e116260">
          <head>Actus, iii. Scaena, 2.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e116270">Enter Caesar, Parthenius.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116280" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116290">They are then in fetters. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116300" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116310">Yes sir. but</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116320" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116330">But? What? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116340">I'll have thy thoughts. Deliver them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116350" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116360">I shall sir. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116370">But still submitting to your godlike pleasure</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116380">Which cannot be instructed? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116390" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116400">To the point. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116410" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116420">Nor let your sacred majesty believe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116430">Your vassal, that with dry eyes looked upon</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116440">His father dragged to death by your command,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116450">Can pity these, that durst presume to censure</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116460">What you decreed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116470" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116480">Well. Forward. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116490" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116500">'Tis my zeal</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116510">Still to preserve your clemency admired</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116520">Tempered with justice, that emboldens me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116530">To offer my advice. Alas I know sir</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116540">These bookmen, Rusticus, and Pulphurius Sura,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116550">Deserve all tortures. Yet in my opinion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116560">They being popular senators, and cried up</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116570">With loud applauses of the multitude,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116580">For foolish honesty, and beggarly virtue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116590">'Twould relish more of policy to have them</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116600">Made away in private, with what exquisite torments</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116610"><pb facs="24"/> you please it skills not, than to have them drawn</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116620">To the degrees in public; for 'tis doubted</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116630">That the sad object may beget compassion</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116640">In the giddy rout, and cause some sudden uproar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116650">That may disturb you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116660" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116670">Hence pale spirited coward</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116680">Can we descend so far beneath ourself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116690">As, or to court, the people's love, or fear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116700">Their worst of hate? Can they that are as dust</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116710">Before the whirlwind of our will and power,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116720">Add any moment to us? Or thou think</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116730">If there are gods above, or goddesses,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116740">(But wise Minerva that's mine own and sure)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116750">That they have vacant hours to take into</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116760">Their serious protection, or care. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116770">This many headed monster? mankind lives</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116780">In few, as potent monarchs, and their peers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116790">And all those glorious constellations</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116800">That do adorn the firmament, appointed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116810">Like grooms with their bright influence to attend</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116820">The actions of Kings, and emperors,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116830">They being the greater wheels that move the less. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116840">Bring forth those condemned wretches let me see</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116850">One man so lost, as but to pity 'em</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116860">And though there lay a million of souls</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116870">Imprisoned in his flesh my hangmens hooks</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116880">Should rend it off and give 'em liberty. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116890">Caesar hath said it. <stage xml:id="A07247-e116900">Exit Parthenius.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e116910">Enter Parthenius, Aretinus, and the guard, hangmen dragging in Junius, Rusticus, and palphurius Sura, bound back to backe▪</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116920" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116930">'Tis great Caesar's pleasure</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116940">That with fixed eyes you carefully observe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116950">The people's looks. Charge upon any man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116960">That with a sigh, or murmur does express</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116970">A seeming sorrow for these traitors deaths,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e116980"><pb facs="25"/> you know his will, perform it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e116990" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117000">A good bloodhound,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117010">And fit for my employments. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117020" who="A07247-sura">
            <speaker>Sur.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117030">Give us leave</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117040">To die fell tyrant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117050" who="A07247-rusticus">
            <speaker>Rust.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117060">For beyond our bodies</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117070">Thou hast no power. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117080" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117090">Yes I'll afflict your souls. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117100">And force them groaning to the Stigian lake</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117110">Prepared for such to howl in, that blaspheme</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117120">The power of princes, that are gods on earth;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117130">Tremble to think how terrible the dream is</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117140">After this sleep of death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117150" who="A07247-rusticus">
            <speaker>Rust.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117160">To guilty men</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117170">It may bring terror, not to us, that know</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117180">What 'tis to die, well taught by his example</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117190">For whom we suffer. In my thought I see</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117200">The substance of that pure untainted soul,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117210">Of Thraseas our master made a star,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117220">That with melodious harmony invites us</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117230">(Leaving this dunghill Rome, made hell by thee,)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117240">To trace his heavenly steps, and fill a sphere</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117250">Above yond crystal canopy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117260" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117270">Do invoke him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117280">With all the aids his sanctity of life</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117290">Have won on the rewarders of his virtue▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117300">They shall not save your dogs do you grin? torment 'em. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117310">So take a leaf of Seneca now and prove</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117320">If it can render you insensible</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117330">Of that which but begins here. Now an oil<stage xml:id="A07247-e117340">The hangmen torment 'em, they still smiling.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117350">Drawn from the Stoics frozen principles</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117360">Predominant over si●e were useful for you. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117370">Again, again. You trifle. Not a groan,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117380">Is my rage lost? What cursed charms defend 'em! </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117390">Search deeper villains. Who looks pale? or thinks</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117400">That I am cruel? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117410" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117420">Over merciful. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117430">All your weakness sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117440" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <pb facs="25"/>
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117450">I dare not show</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117460">A sign of sorrow, yet my sinews shrink</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117470">The spectacle is so horrid. <stage xml:id="A07247-e117480">Aside. </stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117490" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117500">I was never</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117510">O'ercome till now. For my sake roar a little,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117520">And show you are corporeal, and not turned</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117530">Aerial spirits. Will it not do. By Pallas</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117540">It is unkindly done to mock his furl</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117550">Whom the world styles omnipotent. I am tortured</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117560">In their want of feeling torments. Marius' story</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117570">That does report him to have sat unmoved</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117580">When cunning chirurgeons ripped his arteries,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117590">And veins, to cure his gout compared to this</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117600">Deserves not to be named. Are they not dead? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117610">If so, we wash an Aethiop. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117620" who="A07247-sura">
            <speaker>Sur.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117630">No, we live. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117640" who="A07247-rusticus">
            <speaker>Rust.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117650">Live to deride thee, our calm patience treading</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117660">Upon the neck of tyranny. That securely,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117670">(As 'twere a gentle slumber,) we endure</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117680">Thy hangmens studied tortures, is a debt</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117690">We owe to grave philosophy, that instructs us</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117700">The flesh is but the clothing of the soul</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117710">Which growing out of fashion though it be</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117720">Cast of, or rent, or torn, like ours, 'tis then</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117730">Being itself divine, in her best luster. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117740">But unto such as thou, that have no hopes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117750">Beyond the present, every little scar;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117760">The want of rest; excess of heat or, cold</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117770">That does inform them, only they are mortal,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117780">Pierce through, and through them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117790" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117800">We will hear no more,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117810" who="A07247-rusticus">
            <speaker>Rust.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117820">This only, and I give thee warning of it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117830">Though it is in thy will to grind this earth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117840">As small as atoms, they thrown in the sea to. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117850">They shall seem recollected to thy sense,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117860">And when the sandy building of thy greatness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117870">Shall with its own weight totter; look to see me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117880">As I was yesterday, in my perfect shape,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117890"><pb facs="26"/> for I'll appear in horror. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e117900" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117910">By my shaking</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117920">I am the guilty man, and not the judge. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117930">Drag from my sight, these cursed ominous wizards,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117940">That as they are now like to double faced Janus</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117950">Which way soe'er I look, are furies to me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117960">Away with 'em. First show them death▪ then leave<stage xml:id="A07247-e117970">Exeunt hangmen with Rusticus and Sura. Stephanos following. </stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117980">No memory of their ashes I'll mock fate. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e117990">Shall words fright him, victorious army's circle? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118000">No, no, the fever does begin to leave me. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A07247-e118010">Enter Domitia, Julia, Caenis.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118020">Or were it deadly, from this living fountain</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118030">I could renew the vigour of my youth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118040">And be a second Verbius. O my glory! </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118050">My life I command I my all! <stage xml:id="A07247-e118060">Embracing and kissing mutually.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e118070" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118080">As you to me are. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118090">I heard you were sad; I have prepared you sport</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118100">Will banish melancholy. Sirrah, Caesar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118110">(I hug myself for't) I have been instructing</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118120">The players how to act, and to cut off</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118130">All tedious impertinency, have contracted</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118140">The tragedy, into one continued scene. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118150">I have the art of't, and am taken more</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118160">With my ability that way, than all knowledge</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118170">I have but of thy love. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e118180" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118190">Thou art still thyself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118200">The sweetest, wittiest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e118210" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118220">When we are a-bed </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118230">I'll thank your good opinion. Thou shalt see</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118240">Such an Iphis of thy Paris, and to humble</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118250">The pride of Domitilla that neglects me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118260">( howe'er she is your cousin) I have forced her</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118270">To play the part of Anaxerete. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118280">You are not offended with it? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e118290" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118300">Any thing</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118310">That does content thee yields delight to me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118320">My faculties, and powers are thine. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e118330" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118340">I thank you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118350"><pb facs="26"/> prithee let's take our places. Bid 'em enter<stage xml:id="A07247-e118360">After a short flourish, enter Paris as Iphis.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118370">Without more circumstance, how do you like</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118380">That shape? methinks it is most suitable</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118390">To the aspect of a despairing lover. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118400">The seeming late fallen, counterfeited tears</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118410">That hang upon his cheeks, was my device. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e118420" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118430">And all was excellent. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e118440" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118450">Now hear him speak. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e118460" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118470">That she is fair (And that an epithet</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118480">Too foul to express her or descended nobly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118490">Or rich, or fortunate, and certain truth's</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118500">In which poor Iphis glories. But that these</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118510">Perfections, in no other virgin found,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118520">Abused, should nourish cruelty, and pride,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118530">In the divinest Anaxarete,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118540">Is, to my lovesick languishing soul, a riddle,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118550">And with more difficulty to be dissolved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118560">Then that, the monster Sphinx from the steepy rock</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118570">Offered to Oedipus. Imperious love,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118580">As at thy ever flaming altars Iphis</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118590">Thy never tired votary hath presented</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118600">With scalding tears whose hecatombs of sighs,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118610">Preferring thy power, and thy Paphian mothers</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118620">Before the thunderers, Neptunes, or Pluto's</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118630">(That after Saturn did divide the world</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118640">And had the sway of things) yet were compelled</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118650">By thy unsuitable shafts to yield</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118660">And sight under thy ensigns, be auspicious</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118670">To this late trial of my sacrifice</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118680">Of love, and service. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e118690" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118700">Does he not act it rarely? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118710">Observe with what a feeling he delivers</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118720">His orisons to Cupid; I am raped with't. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e118730" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118740">And from thy never emptied quiver take</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118750">A golden arrow, to transfix her heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118760">And force her love like me, or cure my wound</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118770">With a leaden one, that may beget in me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118780">Hate and forgetfulness, of what's now my idol. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118790"><pb facs="27"/>But I call back my prayer, I have blasphemed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118800">In my rash wish. 'tis I that am unworthy,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118810">But she all merit, and may in justice challenge</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118820">From the assurance of her excellencies</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118830">Not love, but adoration. Yet bear witness</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118840">All knowing powers, I bring along with me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118850">As faithful advocates to make intercession</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118860">A loyal heart, with pure, and holy flames</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118870">With the foul fires of lust never polluted. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118880">And as I touch her threshold (Which with tears</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118890">My limbs benumbed with cold, I oft have washed)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118900">With my glad lips I kiss this earth grown proud</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118910">With frequent favours from her delicate feet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e118920" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118930">By Caesar's life he weeps. And I forbear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118940">Hardly to keep him company. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e118950" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118960">Blessed ground thy pardon</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118970">If I profane it with forbidden steps. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118980">I must presume to knock, and yet attempt it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e118990">With such a trembling reverence as if</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119000">My hands held up, for expiation</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119010">To the incensed gods to spare a kingdom. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119020">Within there, ho? something divine come forth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119030">To a distressed mortal. <stage xml:id="A07247-e119040">Enter latinus as a porter. </stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119050" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119060">Ha! who knocks there? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119070" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119080">What a churlish look this knave has</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119090" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119100">Is't you sirrah? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119110">Are you come to pule and whine? avaunt, and quickly. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119120">Dogwhips shall drive you hence else. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119130" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119140">Churlish devil? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119150">But that I should disturb the scene, as I live</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119160">I would tear his eyes out. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119170" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119180">'Tis in jest Domitia,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119190" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119200">I do not like such jesting, if he were not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119210">A flinty hearted slave, he could not use</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119220">One of his form so harshly. How the toad swells</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119230">At the others sweet humility! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119240" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119250">'Tis his part</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119260">Let 'em proceed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119270" who="A07247-domitia">
            <pb facs="27"/>
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119280">A rogue's part, will never leave him</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119290" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119300">As you have gentle sir, the happiness</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119310">(When you please) to behold the figure of</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119320">The master piece of nature, limned to the life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119330">In more than humane Anaxerete,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119340">Scorn not your servant, that with suppliant hands</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119350">Takes hold upon your knees, conjuring you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119360">As you are a man, and did not suck the milk</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119370">Of wolves, and tigers, or a mother of</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119380">A tougher temper, use some means these eyes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119390">Before they are wept out, may see your lady. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119400">Will you be gracious sir? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119410" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119420">Though I lose my place for't</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119430">I can hold out no longer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119440" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119450">Now he melts</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119460">There is some little hope he may die honest</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119470" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119480">Madam. <stage xml:id="A07247-e119490">Enter Domitilla for Anaxerete.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119500" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119510">Who calls? what object have we here? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119520" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119530">Your cousin keeps her proud state still I think</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119540">I have fitted her for a part. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119550" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119560">Did I not charge thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119570">I never might see this thing more? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119580" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119590">I am indeed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119600">What thing you please, a worm that you may tread on,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119610">Lower I cannot fall to show my duty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119620">Till your disdain hath digged a grave to cover</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119630">This body with forgotten dust, and when</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119640">I know your sentence, cruelest of women)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119650">I'll by a willing death remove the object</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119660">That is an eyesore to you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119670" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119680">Wretch thou dar'st not. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119690">That were the last, and greatest service to me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119700">Thy doting love could boast of. What dull fool</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119710">But thou could nourish any flattering hope</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119720">One of my height, in youth, in birth and fortune</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119730">Could e'er descend to look upon thy lowness? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119740">Much less consent to make my lord of one</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119750">I would not accept, though offered for my slave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119760"><pb facs="28"/> my thoughts stoop not so low. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119770" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119780">There's her true nature</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119790">No personated scorn. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119800" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119810">I wrong my worth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119820">Or to exchange a syllable or look,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119830">With one so far beneath me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119840" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119850">Yet take heed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119860">Take heed of pride, and curiously consider</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119870">How brittle the foundation is, on which</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119880">You labour to advance it. Niobe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119890">Proud of her numerous issue durst contemn</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119900">Latona's double burden but what followed? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119910">She was left a childless mother, and mourned to marble. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119920">The beauty you o'erprize so, time, or sickness</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119930">Can change to loathed deformity, your wealth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119940">The prey of thieves; Queen Hecuba Troy fired</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119950">Ulysses bondwoman. But the love I bring you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119960">Nor time, nor sickness, violent thieves, nor fate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119970">Can ravish from you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e119980" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e119990">Could the oracle</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120000">Give better counsel. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120010" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120020">Say will you relent yet? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120030">Revoking your decree that I should die? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120040">Or shall I do what you command? resolve</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120050">I am impatient of delay. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120060" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120070">Dispatch than</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120080">I shall look on your tragedy unmoved,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120090">Peradventure laugh at it, for it will prove</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120100">A comedy to me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120110" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120120">O devil! devil! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120130" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120140">Then thus I take my last leave. All the curses</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120150">Of lovers fall upon you; and hereafter</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120160">When any man like me contemned, shall study</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120170">In the anguish of his soul to give a name</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120180">To a scornful cruel mistress, let him only</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120190">Say this most bloody woman is to me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120200">As Anaxerete was to wretched Iphis. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120210">Now feast your tyrannous mind, and glory in</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120220"><pb facs="28"/> the ruins you have made: for Hymen's bands</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120230">That should have made us one, this fatal halter</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120240">For ever shall divorce us; at your gate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120250">As a trophy of your pride, and my affliction,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120260">I'll presently hang myself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120270" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120280">Not for the world. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120290">Restrain him as you love your lives. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120300" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120310">Why are you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120320">Transported thus Domitia? 'tis a play,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120330">Or grant it serious, it at no part merits. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120340">This passion in you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120350" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120360">I ne'er purposed madam</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120370">To do the deed in earnest, though I bow</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120380">To your care, and tenderness of me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120390" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120400">Let me sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120410">Entreat your pardon, what I saw presented</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120420">Carried me beyond myself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120430" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120440">To your place again</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120450">And see what follows</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120460" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120470">No I am familiar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120480">With the conclusion, besides upon the sudden</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120490">I feel myself much indisposed. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120500" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120510">To bed then</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120520">I'll be thy doctor. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120530" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Areo.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120540">There is something more</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120550">In this then passion, which I must find out,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120560">Or my intelligence freezes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120570" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120580">Come to me Paris</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120590">Tomorrow for your reward</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120600" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120610">Patroness hear me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120620">Will you not call for your share? sit down with this,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120630">And the next action like a Gaditan strumpet</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120640">I shall look to see you tumble. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120650" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120660">Prithee be patient. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120670">I that have suffered greater wrongs bear this</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120680">And that till my revenge my comfort is. <stage xml:id="A07247-e120690">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <trailer xml:id="A07247-e120700">The end of the third act.</trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="act" xml:id="A07247-e120710">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A07247-e120720">
          <pb facs="29"/>
          <head>Actus, iv. Scaena, 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e120730">Enter Parthenius, Julia, Domitilla, Caenis.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120740" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120750">Why 'tis impossible Paris? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120760" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120770">You observed not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120780">(As it appears) the violence of her passion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120790">When personating Iphis, he pretended</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120800">(For your contempt fair Anaxerete)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120810">To hang himself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120820" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120830">Yes, yes, I noted that;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120840">But never could imagine it could work her</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120850">To such a strange intemperance of affection,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120860">As to dote on him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120870" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120880">By my hopes I think not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120890">That she respects though all here saw, and marked it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120900">Presuming she can mould the emperor's will</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120910">Into what form she likes, though we, and all</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120920">Th'informers of the world conspired to cross it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120930" who="A07247-caenis">
            <speaker>Caen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120940">Then with what eagerness this morning urging</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120950">The want of health, and rest, she did entreat</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120960">Caesar to leave her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e120970" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120980">Who no sooner absent</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e120990">But she calls dwarf (So in her scorn she styles me)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121000">Put on my pantofles, fetch pen, and paper</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121010">I am to write, and with distracted looks,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121020">In her smock, impatient of so short delay</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121030">As but to have a mantle thrown upon her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121040">She sealed I know not what but 'twas endorsed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121050">To my loved Paris. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121060" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121070">Add to this I heard her</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121080">Sav, when a page received it; let him wait me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121090">And carefully in the walk, called our retreat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121100">Where Caesar in his fear to give offence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121110">Unsent for never enters. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121120" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121130">This being certain</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121140">(For these are more than jealous suppositions)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121150"><pb facs="29"/> why do not you that are so near in blood</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121160">Discover it? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121170" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121180">Alas you know we dare not. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121190">'Twill be received for a malicious practice</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121200">To free us from that slavery, which her pride</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121210">Imposes on us. But if you would please</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121220">To break the ice on pain to be sunk ever</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121230">We would aver it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121240" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121250">I would second you,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121260">But that I am commanded with all speed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121270">To fetch in Ascletario the Chaldaean</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121280">Who in his absence is condemned of treason</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121290">For calculating the nativity</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121300">Of Caesar, with all confidence foretelling</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121310">In every circumstance when he shall die</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121320">A violent death. Yet if you could approve</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121330">Of my directions I would have you speak</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121340">As much to Aretinus, as you have</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121350">To me delivered. He in his own nature</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121360">Being a spy, on weaker grounds no doubt</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121370">Will undertake it, not for goodness' sake</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121380">(With which he never yet held correspondence)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121390">But to endear his vigilant observings</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121400">Of what concerns the emperor, and a little</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121410">To triumph in the ruins of this Paris<stage xml:id="A07247-e121420">Enter Aretinus.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121430">That crossed him in the senate house. Here he comes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121440">His nose held up, he hath something in the wind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121450">Or I much err already. My designs</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121460">Command me hence great ladies, but I leave</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121470">My wishes with you. <stage xml:id="A07247-e121480">Exit Parthenius.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121490" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121500">Have I caught your greatness</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121510">In the trap my proud Augusta? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121520" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121530">What is't saps him? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121540" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121550">And my fine Roman actor? is't even so? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121560">No courser dish to take your wanton palate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121570">Save that which but the emperor none durst cast off? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121580">'Tis very well. I needs must glory in</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121590">This rare discovery, but the rewards</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121600"><pb facs="30"/> of my intelligence, bid me think even now,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121610">By an edict from Caesar I have power,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121620">To tread upon the neck of slavish Rome,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121630">Disposing offices, and provinces,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121640">To my kinsmen, friends and clients. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121650" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121660">This is more</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121670">Than usual with him,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121680" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121690">Aretinus? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121700" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121710">How? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121720">No more respect and reverence tendered to me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121730">But Aretinus! 'tis confessed that title</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121740">When you were Princesses, and commanded all</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121750">Had been a favour; but being as you are</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121760">Vassals to a proud woman, the worst bondage,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121770">You stand obliged with as much adoration</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121780">To entertain him, that comes armed with strength,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121790">To break your fetters, as tanned galley-slaves</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121800">Pay such as do redeem them from the oar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121810">I come not to entrap you, but aloud</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121820">Pronounce that you are manumised, and to make</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121830">Your liberty sweeter, you shall see her fall,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121840">(This empress, this Domitia, what you will)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121850">That triumphed in your miseries. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121860" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121870">Were, you serious</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121880">To prove your accusation, I could lend</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121890">Some help. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121900" who="A07247-caenis">
            <speaker>Caen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121910">And I. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121920" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121930">And I. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e121940" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121950">No atom to me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121960">My eyes, and ears are everywhere , I know all,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121970">To the line and action in the play that took her;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121980">Her quick dissimulation to excuse</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e121990">Her being transported, with her morning passion;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122000">I bribed the boy that did convey the letter,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122010">And having perused it, made it up again:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122020">Your griefs, and angers, are to me familiar;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122030">That Paris is brought to her, and how far,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122040">He shall be tempted. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122050" who="A07247-domitia">
            <pb facs="30"/>
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122060">This is above wonder. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122070" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122080">My gold can work much stranger miracles</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122090">Than to corrupt poor waiters. Here join with me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122100">'Tis a complaint to Caesar. This is that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122110">Shall ruin her, and raise you. Have you set your hands</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122120">To the accusation. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122130" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122140">And will justify</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122150">What we have subscribed to. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122160" who="A07247-caenis">
            <speaker>Caen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122170">And with vehemency. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122180" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122190">I will deliver it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122200" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122210">Leave the rest to me then</l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e122220">Enter Caesar with his guard.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122230" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122240">Let our lieutenants bring us victory,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122250">While we enjoy the fruits of peace at home,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122260">And being secured from our intestive foes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122270">Far worse than foreign enemies, doubts, and fears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122280">Though all the sky were hung with blazing meteors,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122290">Which fond astrologers give out to be</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122300">Assured presages of the change of empires,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122310">And deaths of monarchs, we undaunted yet</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122320">Guarded with our own thunder, bid defiance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122330">To them, and fate, we being too strongly armed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122340">For them to wound us. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e122350">Aret. Caesar.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122360" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122370">As thou art</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122380">More than a man. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122390" who="A07247-caenis">
            <speaker>Caen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122400">Let not thy passions be</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122410">Rebellious to thy reason. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e122420">The petition delivered.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122430" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122440">But receive</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122450">This trial of your constancy, as unmoved</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122460"><pb facs="31"/> as you go to, or from the Capitol,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122470">Thanks given to love for triumphs? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122480" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122490">Ha! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122500" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122510">Vouchsafe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122520">A while to stay the lightning of your eyes. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122530">Poor mortals dare not look on. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122540" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122550">There's no vein</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122560">Of yours, that rises high with rage, but is</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122570">An earthquake to us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122580" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122590">And if not kept closed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122600">With more than human patience in a moment</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122610">Will swallow us to the centre. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122620" who="A07247-caenis">
            <speaker>Caen.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122630">Not that we</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122640">Repine to serve her, are we her accusers. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122650" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Jul.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122660">But that she's fallen so low. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122670" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122680">Which on sure proofs</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122690">We can make good. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122700" who="A07247-domitilla">
            <speaker>Domitil.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122710">And show she is unworthy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122720">Of the least spark of that diviner fire</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122730">You have conferred upon her. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e122740" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122750">I stand doubtful. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122760">And unresolved what to determine of you. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122770">In this malicious violence you have offered</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122780">To the altar of her truth, and pureness to me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122790">You have but fruitlessly laboured to sully</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122800">A white robe of perfection, black mouthed envy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122810">Could belch no spot on. But I will put off</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122820">The deity, you labour to take from me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122830">And argue out of probabilities with you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122840">As if I wear a man. Can I believe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122850">That she, that borrows all her light from me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122860">And knows to use it, would betray her darkness</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122870">To your intelligence, and make that apparent. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122880">Which by her perturbations in a play</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122890">Was yesterday but doubted and find none,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122900">But you that are her slaves, and therefore hate her</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122910">Whose aids she might employ to make way for her? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122920">Or Aretinus whom long since she knew</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122930"><pb facs="31"/> to be the cabinet counsellor, nay the key</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122940">Of Caesar's secrets? could her beauty raise her</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122950">To this unequalled height to make her fall</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122960">The more remarkable? or must my desires</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122970">To her, and wrongs to Lamia be revenged</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122980">By her, and on herself that drew on both? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e122990">Or she leave our imperial bed to court</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123000">A public actor? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123010" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123020">Who dares contradict</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123030">These more than human reasons, that have power</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123040">To clothe base guilt, in the most glorious shape</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123050">Of innocence? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123060" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123070">To well she knew the strength,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123080">And eloquence of her patron to defend her,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123090">And thereupon presuming fell securely,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123100">Not fearing an accuser, nor the truth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123110">Produced against her, which your love and savour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123120">Will never discern from falsehood. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123130" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123140">I'll not here</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123150">A syllable more that may invite a change</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123160">In my opinion of her. You have raised,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123170">A fiercer war within me by this fable,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123180">(Though with your lives you vow to make it story)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123190">Then i●, and at one instant all my legions</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123200">Revolted from me, and came armed against me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123210">Here in this paper are the swords predestined</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123220">For my destruction; here the fatal stars</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123230">That threaten more than ruin; this the death's head</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123240">That does assure me, if she can prove false</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123250">That I am mortal, which a sudden fever</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123260">Would prompt me to believe, and faintly yield to. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123270">But now in my full confidence what she suffers,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123280">In that, from any witness but myself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123290">I nourish a suspicion she's untrue,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123300">My toughness returns to me. Lead on monsters,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123310">And by the forfeit of your lives confirm</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123320">She is all excellence, as you all baseness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123330">Or let mankind for her fall, boldly swear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123340"><pb facs="32"/> there are no chaste wives now, nor ever were. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e123350">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A07247-e123360">
          <head>Actus, iv. Scaena, 2.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e123370">Enter Domitia, Paris, servants.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123380" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123390">Say we command, that none presume to dare</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123400">On forfeit of our favour, that is life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123410">Out of a saucy curiousness to stand</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123420">Within the distance of their eyes, or ears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123430">Till we please to be waited on. And sirrah<stage xml:id="A07247-e123440">Exeunt servants.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123450">Howe'er you are excepted, let it not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123460">Beget in you an arrogant opinion</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123470">'Tis done to grace you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123480" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123490">With my humblest service</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123500">I but obey your summons, and should blush else</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123510">To be so near you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123520" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123530">'Twould become you rather</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123540">To fear, the greatness of the grace vouchsafed you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123550">May overwhelm you, and 'twill do no less</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123560">If when you are rewarded, in your cups</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123570">You boast this privacy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123580" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123590">That were mightiest empress</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123600">To play with lightning. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123610" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123620">You conceive it right. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123630">The means to kill, or save, is not alone</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123640">In Caesar circumscribed, for if incensed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123650">We have our thunder to, that strikes as deadly. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123660" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123670">'Twould ill become the lowness of my fortune</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123680">To question what you can do, but withal</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123690">Humility to attend what is your will,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123700">And then to serve it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123710" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123720">And would not a secret</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123730">(Suppose we should commit it to your trust)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123740">Scald you to keep it? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123750" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123760">Though it raged within me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123770">Till I turned cinders, it should never have vent. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123780">To be an age a dying, and with torture</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123790"><pb facs="32"/> only to be thought worthy of your counsel,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123800">Or actuate what you command to me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123810">A wretched obscure thing, not worth your knowledge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123820">Were a perpetual happiness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123830" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123840">We could wish</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123850">That we could credit thee, and cannot find</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123860">In reason but that thou whom oft I have seen</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123870">To personate a gentleman, noble, wise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123880">Faithful, and gainsome, and what virtues else</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123890">The poet pleases to adorn you with</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123900">(But that as vessels still partake the odour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123910">Of the sweet precious liquours they contained)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123920">Thou must be really in some degree</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123930">The thing thou dost present. Nay do not tremble,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123940">We seriously believe it, and presume</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123950">Our Paris is the volume in which all</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123960">Those excellent gifts the stage hath seen him graced with</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123970">Are curiously bound up. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e123980" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e123990">The argument</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124000">Is the same great Augusta, that I acting,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124010">A fool, a coward, a traitor or cold cynic</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124020">Or any other weak, and vicious person</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124030">Of force I must be such. O gracious madam,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124040">How glorious soever, or deformed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124050">I do appear in the scene, my part being ended,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124060">And all my borrowed ornaments put off,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124070">I am no more, nor less than what I was</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124080">Before I entered. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e124090" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124100">Come you would put on</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124110">A wilful ignorant, and not understand,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124120">What 'tis we point at. Must we in plain language,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124130">Against the decent modesty of our sex</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124140">Say that we love thee▪ love thee to enjoy thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124150">Or that in our desires thou art preferred</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124160">And Caesar but thy second? thou in justice</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124170">If from the height of majesty we can</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124180">(Look down upon thy lowness and embrace it,)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124190">Art bound with fervour to look up to me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e124200" who="A07247-paris">
            <pb facs="33"/>
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124210">O madam hear me with a patient ear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124220">And be but pleased to understand the reasons</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124230">That do deter me from a happiness</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124240">Kings would be rivals for. Can I that owe,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124250">My life, and all that's mine to Caesar's bounties</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124260">Beyond my hopes, or merits showered upon me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124270">Make payment for them with ingratitude,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124280">Falsehood, and treason? Though you have a shape</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124290">Might tempt Hippolytus, and larger power</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124300">To help, or hurt, then wanton Phaedra had,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124310">Let loyalty, and duty plead my pardon</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124320">Though I refuse to satisfy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e124330" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124340">You are coy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124350">Expecting I should court you, let mean ladies</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124360">Use prayers, and entreaties to their creatures</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124370">To rise up instruments to serve their pleasures;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124380">But for Augusta so to lose herself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124390">That holds command o'er Caesar, and the world,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124400">Were poverty of spirit. Thou must, thou shalt,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124410">The violence of my passions knows no mean,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124420">And in my punishments, and my rewards</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124430">I'll use no moderation. Take this only</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124440">As a caution from me. Threadbare chastity,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124450">Is poor in the advancement of her servants,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124460">But wantonness magnificent; and 'tis frequent</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124470">To have the salary of vice weigh down</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124480">The pay of virtue. So without more trifling</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124490">Thy sudden answer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e124500" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124510">In what a straight am I brought in</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124520">Alas I know that the denial's death</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124530">Nor ●an my grant discovered threaten more. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124540">Yet to die innocent, and have the glory</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124550">For all posterity to report that I</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124560">Refused an empress to preserve my faith</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124570">To my great master, in true judgement must</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124580">Show fairer than to buy a guilty life,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124590">With wealth, and honours. 'tis the base I build on,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124600">I dare not, must not, will not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e124610" who="A07247-domitia">
            <pb facs="33"/>
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124620">How contemned? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124630">Since hopes, nor fears in the extremes prevail not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124640">I must use a mean. Think who 'tis sues to thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124650">Deny not that yet which a brother may</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124660">Grant to his sister: as a testimony<stage xml:id="A07247-e124670">Caesar, Aretinus, Julia, Domitilla, Caenis above. </stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124680">I am not scorned. Kiss me. Kiss me again. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124690">Kiss closer. Thou art now my Trojan Paris</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124700">And I thy Helen. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e124710" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124720">Since it is your will. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e124730" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124740">And I am Menelaus. But I shall be<stage xml:id="A07247-e124750">Caesar descends.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124760">Something I know not yet. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e124770" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124780">Why lose we time</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124790">And opportunity. These are but salads</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124800">To sharpen appetite. Let us to the feast. <stage xml:id="A07247-e124810">Courting Paris wantonly.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124820">Where I shall wish that thou wert Jupiter</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124830">And I Alcmena, and that I had power</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124840">To lengthen out one short night into three,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124850">And so beget a Hercules. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e124860" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124870">While Amphitrio</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124880">Stands by, and draws the curtains. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e124890" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124900">O? —<stage xml:id="A07247-e124910">Falls on his face.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e124920" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124930">Betrayed? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e124940" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124950">No, taken in a not of Vulcan's filing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124960">Wherein myself the theater of the gods</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124970">Are sad spectators, not one of 'em daring</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124980">To witness with a smile he does desire</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e124990">To be so shamed for all the pleasure that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125000">You have sold your being for. What shall I name thee? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125010">Ungrateful, treacherous, insatiate, all</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125020">Invectives, which in bitterness of spirit</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125030">Wronged men have breathed out against wicked women,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125040">Cannot express thee. Have I raised thee from</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125050">Thy low condition to the height of greatness,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125060">Command, and majesty in one base act</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125070">To render me (That was before I hugged thee)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125080">An adder in my bosom, more than man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125090">A thing beneath a boast? did I force these</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125100">Of mine own blood as handmaids to kneel to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125110"><pb facs="34"/> thy pomp, and pride, having myself no thought. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125120">But how with benefits to bind thee mine;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125130">And am I thus rewarded? not a knee? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125140">Nor tear? nor sign of sorrow for thy fault? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125150">Break stubborn silence. What canst thou allege</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125160">To stay my vengeance? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e125170" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125180">This. Thy lust compelled me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125190">To be a strumpet, and mine hath returned it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125200">In my intent, and will, though not in act</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125210">To cuckold thee. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e125220" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125230">O impudence I take her hence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125240">And let her make her entrance into hell. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125250">By leaving life with all the tortures that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125260">Flesh can be sensible of. Yet stay. What power</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125270">Her beauty still holds o'er my soul that wrongs</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125280">Of this unpardonable nature cannot teach me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125290">To tight myself and hate her ● - kill her. - Hold●</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125300">Oh that my dotage should increase from that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125310">Which should breed detestation. By Minerva</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125320">If I look on her longer. I shall melt</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125330">And sue to her. My injuries forgotten</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125340">Again to be received into her favour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125350">Could honour yield to it! Carry her to her chamber,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125360">Be that her prison till in cooler blood</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125370">I shall determine of her. <stage xml:id="A07247-e125380">Exit with Domitia.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e125390" who="A07247-aretinus">
            <speaker>Aret.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125400">Now step I in</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125410">While he's in this calm mood for my rewards</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125420">Sir, if my service hath deserved. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e125430" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125440">Yes. Yes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125450">And I'll reward thee, thou hast robbed me of</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125460">All rest, and peace, and been the principal means</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125470">To make me know that, of which if again<stage xml:id="A07247-e125480">Enter guard.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125490">I could be ignorant of. I would purchase it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125500">With the loss of empire; strangle him, take these hence to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125510">And lodge them in the dungeon, could your reason</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125520">Dull wretches flatter you with hope to think</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125530">That this discovery that hath showered upon me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125540">Perpetual vexation should not fall</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125550"><pb facs="34"/> heavy on you? away with 'em, stop their mouths</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125560">I will hear no reply, oh Paris. Paris<stage xml:id="A07247-e125570">Exeunt guard Aretinus, Julia, Caenis, Domitilla.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125580">How shall I argue with thee? how begin,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125590">To make thee understand before I kill thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125600">With what grief and unwillingness 'tis forced from me? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125610">Yet in respect I have favoured thee. I will here</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125620">What thou canst speak to qualify, or excuse</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125630">Thy readiness to serve this woman's lust. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125640">And wish thou couldst give me such satisfaction</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125650">As I might bury the remembrance of it:</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125660">Look up. We stand attentive;</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e125670" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125680">O dread Caesar,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125690">To hope for life, or plead in the defence</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125700">Of my ingratitude were again to wrong you. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125710">I know I have deserved death. And my suit is</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125720">That you would hasten it: yet that your highness</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125730">When I am dead (As sure I will not live)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125740">May pardon me I'll only urge my frailty,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125750">Her will, and the temptation of that beauty</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125760">Which you could not resist. How would poor I then</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125770">Fly that which followed me, and Caesar sued for? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125780">This is all. And now your sentence. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e125790" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125800">Which I know not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125810">How to pronounce, oh that thy fault had been</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125820">But such as I might pardon; if thou hadst</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125830">In wantonness (Like Nero) sired proud Rome</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125840">Betrayed an army, butchered the whole senate,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125850">Committed sacrilege, or any crime</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125860">The justice of our Roman laws calls death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125870">I had prevented any intercession</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125880">And freely signed thy pardon. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e125890" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125900">But for this</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125910">Alas you cannot nay you must not sir</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125920">Nor let it to posterity be recorded</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125930">That Caesar unrevenged, suffered a wrong,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125940">Which if a private man should sit down with it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125950">Cowards would baffle him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e125960" who="A07247-caesar">
            <pb facs="35"/>
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125970">With such true feeling</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125980">Thou arguest against thyself, that it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e125990">Works more upon me, than if my Minerva</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126000">(The grand protectress of my life, and empire,)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126010">On forfeit of her favour, cried aloud</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126020">Caesar show mercy. And I know not how</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126030">I am inclined to it. Rise. I'll promise nothing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126040">Yet clear thy cloudy fears and cherish hopes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126050">What we must do, we shall do; we remember</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126060">A tragedy, we oft have seen with pleasure,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126070">Called, the false servant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126080" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126090">Such a one we have sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126100" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126110">In which a great lord takes to his protection</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126120">A man forlorn, giving him ample power</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126130">To order, and dispose of his estate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126140">In his absence, he pretending then a journey. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126150">But yet with this restraint that on no terms</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126160">This lord suspecting his wife's constancy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126170">(She having played false to a former husband)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126180">The servant though solicited should consent</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126190">Though she commanded him to quench her flames. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126200" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126210">That was indeed the argument. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126220" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126230">And what</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126240">Didst thou play in it? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126250" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126260">The false servant sir. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126270" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126280">Thou didst indeed. Do the players wait without? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126290" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126300">They do sir and prepared to act the story</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126310">Your majesty mentioned. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126320" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126330">Call 'em in. Who presents</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126340">The injured lord? </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e126350">Enter Aesopus, Latinus, a boy dressed for a lady.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126360" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126370">'Tis my part sir,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126380" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126390">Thou didst not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126400">Do it to the life. We can perform it better. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126410">Off with my robe, and wreath, since Nero scorned not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126420">The public theater, we in private may</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126430"><pb facs="35"/> disport ourselves. This cloak, and hat without</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126440">Wearing a beard, or other property</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126450">Will fit the person. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126460" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126470">Only sir a foil</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126480">The point, and edge rebutted, when you act</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126490">To do the murder. If you please to use this</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126500">And lay aside your own sword. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126510" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126520">By no means. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126530">In jest nor earnest this parts never from me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126540">We'll have but one short scene. That where the lady</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126550">In an imperious way commands the servant</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126560">To be unthankful to his patron when</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126570">My cue's to enter prompt me nay begin</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126580">And do it spritely though but a new actor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126590">When I come to execution you shall find</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126600">No cause to laugh at me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126610" who="A07247-latinus">
            <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126620">In the name of wonder</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126630">What's Caesar's purpose? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126640" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126650">There is no contending. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126660" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126670">Why when? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126680" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126690">I am armed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126700">And stood grim death now within my view and his</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126710">Unevitable dart aimed at my breast</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126720">His cold embraces should not bring an ague</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126730">To any of my faculties, till his pleasures</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126740">Were served, and satisfied, which done Nestor's years,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126750">To me would be unwelcome. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126760" who="A07247-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126770">Must we entreat,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126780">That were born to command, or court a servant</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126790">(That owes his food and clothing to our bounty)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126800">For that, which thou ambitiously shouldst kneel for? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126810">Urge not in thy excuse the favours of</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126820">Thy absent lord, or that thou standst engaged</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126830">For thy life to his charity; nor thy fears</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126840">Of what may follow, it being in my power</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126850">To mould him any way. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126860" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126870">As you may me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126880">In what his reputation is not wounded</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126890"><pb facs="36"/> nor I his creature in my thankfulness suffer. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126900">I know you are young, and fair, be virtuous too</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126910">And loyal to his bed, that hath advanced you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126920">To th'height of happiness. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e126930" who="A07247-boy">
            <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126940">Can my lovesick heart</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126950">Be cured with counsel? or durst reason ever</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126960">Offer to put in an exploded plea</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126970">In the court of Venus. My desires admit not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126980">The least delay. And therefore instantly</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e126990">Give me to understand what I shall trust to. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127000">For if I am refused, and not enjoy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127010">Those ravishing pleasures from thee, I run mad for;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127020">I'll swear unto my lord at his return</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127030">(Making what I deliver good with tears)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127040">That brutishly thou wouldst have forced from me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127050">What I make suit for. And then but imagine</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127060">What 'tis to die with these words slave, and traitor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127070">With burning corrasiues writ upon thy forehead,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127080">And live prepared fort. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127090" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127100">This he will believe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127110">Upon her information. 'tis apparent</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127120">And then I am nothing. And of two extremes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127130">Wisdom says chose the less. Rather than fall</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127140">Under your indignation, I will yield</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127150">This kiss, and this confirms it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127160" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127170">Now. Sir now. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127180" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127190">I must take them at it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127200" who="A07247-aesopus">
            <speaker>Aesop.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127210">Yes sir, be but perfect. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127220" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127230">O villain! thankless villain ! I should talk now▪</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127240">But I have forgotten my part. But I can do,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127250">Thus, thus, and thus. <stage xml:id="A07247-e127260">Kills Paris.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127270" who="A07247-paris">
            <speaker>Par.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127280">O, I am slain in earnest. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127290" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127300">'Tis time, and 'twas my purpose my good Paris</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127310">And yet before life leave thee, let the honour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127320">I have done thee in thy death bring comfort to thee</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127330">If it had been within the power of Caesar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127340">His dignity preserved he had pardoned thee. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127350">But cruelty of honour did deny it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127360"><pb facs="36"/>Yet to confirm I loved thee? 'twas my study</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127370">To make thy end more glorious to distinguish</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127380">My Paris from all others, and in that</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127390">Have shown my pity. Nor would I let thee fall</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127400">By a centurions sword, or have thy limbs</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127410">Rent piece meal by the hangman's hook however</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127420">Thy crime deserved it: but as thou didst live</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127430">Rome's bravest actor, 'twas my plot that thou</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127440">Shouldst die in action, and to crown it die</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127450">With an applause enduring to all times,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127460">By our imperial hand. His soul is freed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127470">From the prison of his flesh, let it mount upward. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127480">And for this trunk when that the funeral pile</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127490">Hath made it ashes, we'll see it enclosed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127500">In a golden urn. Poets adorn his hearse</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127510">With their most ravishing sorrows, and the stage</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127520">For ever mourn him, and all such as were</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127530">His glad spectators weep his sudden death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127540">The cause forgotten in his epitaph. <stage xml:id="A07247-e127550">Exeunt. A sad music the players bearing off Paris body, Caesar and the rest following.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <trailer xml:id="A07247-e127560">The end of the fourth act.</trailer>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="act" xml:id="A07247-e127570">
        <div n="1" type="scene" xml:id="A07247-e127580">
          <head>Actus, v. Scaena, 1.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e127590">Enter Parthenius, Stephanos, guard.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127600" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127610">Keep a strong guard upon him, and admit not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127620">Access to any, to exchange a word,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127630">Or syllable with him, till the emperor pleases</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127640">To call him to his presence. The relation</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127650">That you have made me Stephanos of these late</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127660">Strange passions in Caesar, much amaze me. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127670">The informer Aretinus put to death</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127680">For yielding him a true discovery</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127690">Of th'empress wantonness; poor Paris killed first</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127700">And now lamented; and the Princesses</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127710"><pb facs="37"/> consigned to several islands, yet Augusta</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127720">The machine on which all this mischief moved</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127730">Received again to grace? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127740" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127750">Nay courted to it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127760">(Such is the impotence of his affection)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127770">Yet, to conceal his weakness he gives out</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127780">The people made suit for her, whom they hate more</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127790">Than civil war, or famine. But take heed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127800">My lord, that nor in your consent nor wishes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127810">You lent or furtherance, or favour to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127820">The plot contrived against her, should she prove it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127830">Nay doubt it only you are a loft man</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127840">Her power o'er doting Caesar being now</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127850">Greater than ever. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127860" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127870">'Tis a truth I shake at. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127880">And when there's opportunity. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127890" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127900">Say but do</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127910">I am yours, and sure. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127920" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127930">I will stand one trial more</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127940">And than you shall hear from me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127950" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127960">Now observe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e127970">The fondness of this tyrant, and her pride. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e127980">Enter Caesar and Domitia.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e127990" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128000">Nay all's forgotten. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e128010" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128020">It may be on your part. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e128030" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128040">Forgiven to Domitia 'tis a favour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128050">That you should welcome with more cheerful looks</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128060">Can Caesar pardon what you durst not hope for</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128070">That did the injury, and yet must sue</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128080">To her whose guilt is washed off by his mercy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128090">Only to entertain it? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e128100" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128110">I asked none,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128120">And I should be more wretched to receive</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128130">Remission (For what I hold no crime)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128140">But by a bare acknowledgement then if</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128150">By slighting, and contemning it, as now</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128160"><pb facs="37"/> I dated thy utmost fury. Though thy flatterers</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128170">Persuade thee, that thy murders, lusts, and rapes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128180">Are virtues in thee, and what pleases Caesar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128190">Though never sown just is right, and lawful;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128200">Or work in thee a false belief that thou</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128210">Art more than mortal, yet I to thy teeth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128220">(When circled with thy guards, thy rods, thy axes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128230">And all the ensigns of thy boasted power)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128240">Will say Domitian, nay add to it Caesar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128250">Is a weak feeble man, a bondman to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128260">His violent passions, and in that my slave,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128270">Nay more my slave, than my affections made me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128280">To my loved Paris. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e128290" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128300">Can I live, and hear this? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128310">Or hear and not revenge it? come, you know</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128320">The strength that you hold on me, do not use it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128330">With too much cruelty, for though 'tis granted</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128340">That Lydian Omphale had less command</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128350">O'er Hercules, than you usurp o'er me,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128360">Reason may teach me to shake off the yoke</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128370">Of my fond dotage. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e128380" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128390">Never, do not hope it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128400">It cannot be. Thou bring my beauty's captive</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128410">And not to be redeemed, my empire's larger</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128420">Than thine Domitian, which I'll exercise</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128430">With rigor on thee, for my Paris death. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128440">And when I have forced those eyes now red with fury</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128450">To drop down tears, in vain spent to appease me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128460">I know thy servor such to my embraces</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128470">(Which shall be, though still kneeled for, still denied thee)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128480">That thou with languishment shalt wish my actor</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128490">Did live again, so thou mightst be his second</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128500">To feed upon those delicates, when he's sated. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e128510" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128520">O my Minerva</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e128530" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128540">There she is invoke her</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128550">She cannot arm thee with ability</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128560">To draw thy sword on me, my power being greater</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128570">Or only say to thy centurions</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128580"><pb facs="38"/> dare none of you do what I shake to think on? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128590">And in this woman's death remove the furies</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128600">That every hour afflict me? Lamia's wrongs</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128610">When thy lust forced me from him, are in me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128620">At the height revenged, nor would I outlive Paris</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128630">But that thy love increasing with my hate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128640">May add unto thy torments, so withal</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128650">Contempt I can I leave thee. <stage xml:id="A07247-e128660">Exit Domitia.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e128670" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128680">I am lost</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128690">Nor am I Caesar, when I first betrayed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128700">The freedom of my faculties, and will</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128710">To this imperious Siren, I laid down</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128720">The empire of the world, and of myself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128730">At her proud feet. Sleep all my ireful powers? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128740">Or is the magic of my dotage such</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128750">That I must still make suit to hear those charms</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128760">That do increase my thraldom? wake my anger,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128770">For shame break through this lethargy, and appear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128780">With usual terror, and enable me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128790">(Since I wear not a sword to pierce her heart,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128800">Nor have a tongue to say this let her die)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128810">Though 'tis done with a fever-shaken hand<stage xml:id="A07247-e128820">Pulls out a table book.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128830">To sign her death, assist me great Minerva</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128840">And vindicate thy votary. So she's now</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128850">Among the list of those I have prescribed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128860">And are to free me of my doubts, and fears,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128870">To die tomorrow. <stage xml:id="A07247-e128880">(Writes.)</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e128890" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128900">That same fatal book</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128910">Was never drawn yet, but some men of rank</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128920">Were marked out for destruction. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e128930" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128940">I begin</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128950">To doubt myself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e128960" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128970">Who waits there? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e128980" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e128990">Caesar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e129000" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129010">So. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129020">These that command armed troops quake, at my frowns</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129030">And yet a woman sleights 'em. Where's the wizard</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129040">We charged you to fetch in? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e129050" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <pb facs="38"/>
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129060">Ready to suffer</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129070">What death you please t'appoint him. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e129080" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129090">Bring him in. <stage xml:id="A07247-e129100">Enter Ascletario, tribunes, guard.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129110">We'll question him ourself. Now you that hold</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129120">Intelligence with the stars, and dare prefix</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129130">The day and hour in which we are to part</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129140">With life and empire, punctually foretelling</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129150">The means, and manner of our violent end,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129160">As you would purchase credit to your art</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129170">Resolve me since you are assured of us</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129180">What fate attends yourself? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e129190" who="A07247-ascletario">
            <speaker>Asclet.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129200">I have had long since</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129210">A certain knowledge, and assure as thou</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129220">Shalt die tomorrow being the fourteenth of</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129230">The Kalenda of October, the hour five</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129240">Spite of prevention, this carcase shall be</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129250">Torn and devoured by dogs, and let that stand for a firm prediction. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e129260" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129270">May our body wretch</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129280">Find never nobler sepulchre if this</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129290">Fall ever on thee. Are we the great disposer</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129300">Of life, and death yet cannot mock the stars</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129310">In such a trifle? Hence with the impostor,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129320">And having cut his throat, erect a pile</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129330">Guarded with soldiers, till his cursed trunk</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129340">Be turned to ashes, upon forfeit of</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129350">Your life, and theirs, perform it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e129360" who="A07247-ascletario">
            <speaker>Asclet.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129370">'Tis in vain,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129380">When what I have foretold is made apparent</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129390">Tremble to think what follows. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e129400" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129410">Drag him hence<stage xml:id="A07247-e129420">The guard bear off Ascletario.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129430">And do as I command you. I was never</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129440">Fuller of confidence, for having got●</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129450">The victory of my passions, in my freedom</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129460">From proud Domitia (Who shall cease to live</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129470">Since she disdains to love) I rest unmoved</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129480">And in defiance of prodigious meteors,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129490">Chaldeans vain predictions, jealous fears</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129500">Of my near friends, and freemen, certain hate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129510"><pb facs="39"/> oh kindred, and alliance, or all terrors</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129520">The soldiers doubted faith, or people's rage</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129530">Can bring to shake my constancy I am armed. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129540">That scrupulous thing stilled conscience is seared up</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129550">And I insensible of all my actions</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129560">For which by moral and religious fools</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129570">I stand condemned, as they had never been</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129580">And since I have subdued triumphant love</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129590">I will not deify pale captive scare</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129600">Nor in a thought receive it. For till thou</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129610">Wisest Minerva that from my first youth,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129620">Hast been my sole protectress, dost forsake me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129630">Not Junius Rusticus, threatned apparition,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129640">Nor what this soothsayer but e'en now foretold</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129650">(Being things impossible to humane reason)</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129660">Shall in a dream disturb me. Bring my couch there<stage xml:id="A07247-e129670">Enter with couch. </stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129680">A sudden but a secure drowsiness</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129690">Invites me to repose myself. Let music</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129700">With some choice ditty second it. I the mean time</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129710">Rest there dear book, which opened when I wake<stage xml:id="A07247-e129720">Lays the book under his pillow, the music and song. Caesar sleeps.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e129730">Enter Parthenius and Domitia.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e129740" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129750">Write my name</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129760">In his bloody scroll Parthenius? the fear's idle</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129770">He durst not, could not. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e129780" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129790">I can assure nothing</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129800">But I observed when you departed from him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129810">After some little passion, but much fury,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129820">He drew it out, whose death he signed I know not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129830">But in his looks appeared a resolution</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129840">Of what before he staggered at. What he hath</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129850">Determined o● is uncertain, but too soon</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129860">Will fall on you, or me, or both, or any</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129870">His pleasure known to the tribunes, and centurions. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129880">Who never use to inquire his will but serve it. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129890">Now if out of the confidence of your power,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129900">The bloody catalogue being still about him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129910"><pb facs="39"/> as he sleeps you dare peruse it, or remove it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129920">You may instruct yourself or what to suffer,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129930">Or how to cross it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e129940" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129950">I would not be caught</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129960">With too much confidence. By your leave sir. Ha!</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129970">No motion! you lie uneasy sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e129980">Let me mend your pillow. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e129990" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130000">Have you it? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e130010" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130020">'Tis here. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e130030" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130040">O. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e130050" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130060">You have waked him, softly gracious madam</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130070">While we are unknown, and then consult at leisure. </l>
            <stage xml:id="A07247-e130080">Exeunt Parthenius, and Domitia.</stage>
            <stage xml:id="A07247-e130090">A dreadful music sounding, enter Junius Rusticus, and Palphurius Sura, with bloody swords, they wave them over his head. Caesar in his sleep troubled, seems to pray to the image, they scornfully take it away.</stage>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130100">Defend me goddess, or this horrid dream</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130110">Will force me to distraction. Whether have</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130120">These furies born thee? Let me rise! and follow</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130130">I am bathed o'er with the cold sweat of death,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130140">And am deprived of organs to pursue</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130150">These sacrilegious spirits. Am I at once</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130160">Robbed of my hopes, and being? No, I live<stage xml:id="A07247-e130170">Rises distractedly. </stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130180">Yes live, and have discourse to know myself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130190">Of gods, and men forsaken. What accuser</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130200">Within me cries aloud, I have deserved it,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130210">It being just to neither. Who dares speak this? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130220">Am I not Caesar? how I again repeat it? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130230">Presumptuous traitor thou shalt die, what traitor? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130240">He that hath been a traitor to himself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130250">And stands convicted here. Yet who can sit</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130260">A competent judge o'er Caesar? Caesar. Yes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130270">Caesar by Caesar's, sentenced and must suffer</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130280">Minerva cannot save him. Ha! where is she? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130290">Where is my goddess? vanished! I am lost then</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130300">No 'twas no dream, but a most real truth</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130310"><pb facs="40"/> that Junius Rusticus, and Palphurius Sura,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130320">Although their ashes were cast in the sea</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130330">Whereby their innocence made up again. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130340">And in corporeal forms but now appeared. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130350">Waving their bloody swords above my head,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130360">As at their deaths they threatened. And methought </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130370">Minerva ravished hence whispered that she</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130380">Was for my blasphemies disarmed by Jove</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130390">And could no more protect me. Yes 'twas so,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130400">His thunder does confirm it, against which<stage xml:id="A07247-e130410">Thunder and lightning.</stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130420">Howe'er it spare the laurel, this proud wreath</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130430">Is no assurance. Ha! come you resolved<stage xml:id="A07247-e130440">Enter 3. Tribunes. </stage></l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130450">To be my executioners? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e130460" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130470">Allegiance</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130480">And faith forbid that we should lift an arm</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130490">Against your sacred head. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e130500" who="A07247-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130510">We rather sue</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130520">For mercy. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e130530" who="A07247-yyyy_3">
            <speaker>3. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130540">And acknowledge that in justice</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130550">Our lives are forfeited for not performing</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130560">What Caesar charged us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e130570" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130580">Nor did we transgress it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130590">In our want of will, or care, for being but men</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130600">It could not be in us to make resistance,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130610">The gods fighting against us. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e130620" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130630">Speak in what</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130640">Did they express their anger? we will hear it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130650">But dare not say undaunted. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e130660" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130670">In brief thus sir. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130680">The sentence given by your imperial tongue</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130690">For the astrologer Ascletario's death</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130700">With speed was put in execution. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e130710" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130720">Well. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e130730" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130740">For his throat out, his legs bound, and his arms</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130750">Pinioned behind his back, the breathless trunk</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130760">Was with all scorn dragged to the field of Mars</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130770">And there a pile being raised of old dry wood,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130780">Smeared o'er with oil, and brimstone, or what else</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130790"><pb facs="40"/> could help to feed, or to increase the fire</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130800">The carcase was thrown on it; but no sooner</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130810">The stuff, that was most apt, began to flame;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130820">But suddenly to the amazement of</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130830">The fearless soldier, a sudden flash</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130840">Of lightning breaking through the scattered clouds</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130850">With such a horrid violence forced its passage</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130860">And as disdaining all heat but itself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130870">In a moment quenched the artificial fire. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130880">And before we could kindle it again</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130890">A clap of thunder followed with such noise,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130900">As if then Jove incensed against mankind,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130910">Had in his secret purposes determined</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130920">An universal ruin to the world. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130930">This horror past, not at Deucalion's flood</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130940">Such a stormy shower of rain (And yet that word is</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130950">Too narrow to express it) was e'er seen</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130960">Imagine rather sir, that with less fury</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130970">The waves rush down the cataracts of Nile;</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130980">Or that the sea spouted into the air</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e130990">By the angry ork, endangering tall ships</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131000">But sailing near it, so falls down again,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131010">Yet here the wonder ends not, but begins</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131020">For as in vain we laboured to consume</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131030">The witch's body, all the dogs of Rome</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131040">Howling, and yelling like to famished wolves</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131050">Broke in upon us, and though thousands were</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131060">Killed in th'attempt some did ascend the pile</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131070">And with their eager fangs ceased on the carcase. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131080" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131090">But have they torn it? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131100" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131110">Torn it, and devoured it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131120" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131130">I then am a dead man since all predictions</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131140">Assure me I am lost; oh my loved soldiers</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131150">Your emperor must leave you: yet however</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131160">I cannot grant myself a short reprieve</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131170">I freely pardon you. The fatal hour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131180">Steals fast upon me. I must die this morning</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131190">By five my soldiers, that's the latest hour</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131200"><pb facs="41"/> you e'er must see me living. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131210" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131220">Jove avert it</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131230">In our swords lies your fate, and we will guard it. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131240" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131250">O no, it cannot be, it is decreed,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131260">Above, and by no strengths here to be altered. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131270">Let proud mortality but look on Caesar</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131280">Compassed of late with armies, in his eyes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131290">Carrying both life, and death, and in his arms</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131300">Fadoming the earth; that would be styled a god,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131310">And is for that presumption cast beneath</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131320">The low condition of a common man,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131330">Sinking with mine own weight,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131340" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131350">Do not forsake,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131360">Yourself we'll never leave you. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131370" who="A07247-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131380">We'll draw up</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131390">More cohorts of your guard, if you doubt treason. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131400" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131410">They cannot save me. The offended gods</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131420">That now sit judges on me, from their envy</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131430">Of my power and greatness here, conspire against me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131440" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131450">Endeavour to appease them. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131460" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131470">'Twill be fruitless</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131480">I am past hope of remission. Yet could I</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131490">Decline this dreadful hour of five, these terrors</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131500">That drive me to despair would soon fly from me</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131510">And could you but till then assure me,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131520" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131530">Yes sir,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131540">Or we'll fall with you, and make Rome the urn</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131550">In which we'll mix our ashes. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131560" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131570">'Tis said nobly,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131580">I am something comforted. Howe'er to die</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131590">Is the full period of calamity. <stage xml:id="A07247-e131600">Exeunt.</stage></l>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="scene" xml:id="A07247-e131610">
          <head>Actus, v. Scaena, 2.</head>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e131620">Enter Parthenius, Domitia, Julia, Caenis Domitilla, Stephanos, Sijeius, Entellus.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131630" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131640">You see we are all condemned, there's no evasion,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131650"><pb facs="41"/> we must do or suffer. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131660" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131670">But it must be sudden</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131680">The least delay is mortal. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131690" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131700">Would I were</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131710">A man to give it action. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131720" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit:</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131730">Could I make my approaches though my stature</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131740">Does promise little, I have a spirit as daring</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131750">As hers, that can reach higher. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131760" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131770">I will take</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131780">That burden from you madam. All the art is</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131790">To draw him from the tribunes that attend him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131800">For could you bring him but within my swords reach</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131810">The world should owe her freedom from a tyrant,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131820">To Stephanos. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131830" who="A07247-sigeius">
            <speaker>Sige.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131840">You shall not share alone</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131850">The glory of a deed that will endure</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131860">To all posterity. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131870" who="A07247-entellus">
            <speaker>Entel.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131880">I will put in</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131890">For a part myself. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131900" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131910">Be resolute, and stand close. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131920">I have conceived a way, and with the hazard</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131930">Of my life I'll practise it to fetch him hither. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131940">But then no trifling. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131950" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>St●ph.. </speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131960">We'll dispatch him fear not</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131970">A dead dog never bites. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e131980" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e131990">Thus then at all<stage xml:id="A07247-e132000">Parthenius goes off the res● stand aside</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e132010">Enter Caesar and the tribunes.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132020" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132030">How slow paced are these minutes ● in extremes</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132040">How miserable is the least delay</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132050">Could I jump feathers to the wings of time</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132060">Or with as little ease command the sun</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132070">To scourge his coursers up heaven's Eastern hill</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132080">Making the hour I tremble at past recalling</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132090">As I can move this dial's tongue to six,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132100">My veins, and arteries emptied with fear</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132110">Would fill and swell again. How do I look? </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132120">Do you yet see death about me:</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132130" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <pb facs="42"/>
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132140">Think not of him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132150">There is no danger all these prodigies</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132160">That do affright you rise from natural causes,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132170">And though you do ascribe them to yourself,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132180">Had you never been, had happened</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132190" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132200">'Tis well said,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132210">Exceeding well brave soldier. Can it be</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132220">That I that feel myself in health and strength</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132230">Should still believe I am so near my end,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132240">And have my guards about me? perish all</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132250">Predictions. I grow constant they are false</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132260">And built upon uncertainties. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132270" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132280">This is right. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132290">Now Caesar's hard like Caesar. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132300" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132310">We will to</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132320">The camp, and having there confirmed the soldier</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132330">With a large donative, and increase of pay</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132340">Some shall. I say no more. <stage xml:id="A07247-e132350">Enter Parthenius.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132360" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132370">All happiness</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132380">Security, long life attend upon</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132390">The monarch of the world. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132400" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132410">Thy looks are cheerful,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132420" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132430">And my relation full of joy and wonder. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132440">Why is the care of your imperial body</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132450">My lord neglected the feared hour being passed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132460">In which your your life was threatened. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132470" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132480">Is't past five? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132490" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132500">Past six upon my knowledge, and injustice</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132510">Your clock master should die that hath deferred</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132520">Your peace so long. There is a post new lighted</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132530">That brings assured intelligence, that your legions</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132540">In Siria have won a glorious day,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132550">And much enlarged your empire. I have kept him</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132560">Concealed that you might first partake the pleasure</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132570">In private, and the senate from yourself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132580">Be taught to understand how much they owe</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132590">To you and to your fortune. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132600" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132610">Hence pale fear then</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132620"><pb facs="42"/> lead me Parthenius. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132630" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132640">Shall we wait you? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132650" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132660">No</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132670">After losses guards are useful, know your distance. <stage xml:id="A07247-e132680">Exeunt Caesar and Parthenius. </stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132690" who="A07247-yyyy_2">
            <speaker>2. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132700">How strangely hopes delude men, as I live</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132710">The hour is not yet come. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132720" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132730">Howe'er we are</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132740">To pay our duties, and observe the sequel. <stage xml:id="A07247-e132750">Exeunt Trib.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e132760">Enter Caesar, and Parthenius.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132770" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132780">I hear him coming, be constant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132790" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132800">Where Parthenius is this glad messenger. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132810" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132820">Make the door fast. Here, a messenger of horror. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132830" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132840">How! betrayed? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132850" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132860">No taken tyrant. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132870" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132880">My Domitia in the conspiracy! </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132890" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132900">Behold this book. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132910" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132920">Nay then I am lost. Yet though I am unarmed</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132930">I'll not fall poorly. <stage xml:id="A07247-e132940">O'erthrows Stephanos.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132950" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132960">Help me. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132970" who="A07247-entellus">
            <speaker>Entel.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e132980">Thus, and thus. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e132990" who="A07247-sigeius">
            <speaker>Sije.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133000">Are you so long a falling? </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e133010" who="A07247-caesar">
            <speaker>Caes.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133020">'Tis done, 'tis done basely.<stage xml:id="A07247-e133030">Falls, and dies.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e133040" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133050">This for my father's death. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e133060" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133070">This for my Paris,</l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e133080" who="A07247-julia">
            <speaker>Iul,</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133090">This for thy incest<stage xml:id="A07247-e133100">These severally stab him.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e133110" who="A07247-domitia">
            <speaker>Domit</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133120">This for thy abuse of Domitilla. </l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e133130">Enter tribunes.</stage>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e133140" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133150">Force the doors. O Mars! </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133160">What have you done. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e133170" who="A07247-parthenius">
            <speaker>Parth.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133180">What Rome shall give us thanks for. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e133190" who="A07247-stephanos">
            <speaker>Steph.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133200">Dispatched a monster. </l>
          </sp>
          <sp xml:id="A07247-e133210" who="A07247-yyyy_1">
            <speaker>1. Trib.</speaker>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133220">Yet he was our prince</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133230">However wicked, and in you this murder</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133240">Which whosoever succeeds him will revenge,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133250">Nor will we that served under his command</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133260"><pb facs="43"/> consent that such a monster as thyself</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133270">(For in thy wickedness, Augusta's title</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133280">Hath quite forsook thee) thou that wert the ground</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133290">Of all these mischiefs, shall go hence unpunished. </l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133300">Lay hands on her. And drag her to sentence,</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133310">We will refer the hearing to the senate</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133320">Who may at their best leisure censure you</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133330">Take up his body. He in death hath paid</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133340">For all his cruelties. Here's the difference</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133350">Good Kings are mourned for after life, but ill</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133360">And such as governed only by their will</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133370">And not their reason. Unlamented fall</l>
            <l xml:id="A07247-e133380">No goodman's tear shed at their funeral. <stage xml:id="A07247-e133390">Exeunt omnes.</stage></l>
          </sp>
          <stage xml:id="A07247-e133400">Flourish.</stage>
        </div>
        <trailer xml:id="A07247-e133410">Finis.</trailer>
        <pb facs="43"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A07247"><item xml:id="A07247-caesar" n="97">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-caesar</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">97</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-domitia" n="78">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-domitia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">78</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-paris" n="59">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-paris</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">59</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-parthenius" n="55">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-parthenius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">55</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-aretinus" n="27">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-aretinus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">27</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-lamia" n="19">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-lamia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">19</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-yyyy_1" n="18">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-yyyy_1</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">18</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-julia" n="18">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-julia</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">18</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-philargus" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-philargus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-stephanos" n="16">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-stephanos</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">16</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A07247-aesopus" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-aesopus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-latinus" n="15">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-latinus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">15</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-caenis" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-caenis</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-rusticus" n="12">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-rusticus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">12</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-sura" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-sura</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-domitilla" n="7">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-domitilla</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">7</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-yyyy_2" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-yyyy_2</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-ascletario" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-ascletario</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-boy" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-boy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-entellus" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-entellus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-fulcinius" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-fulcinius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-all" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-sigeius" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-sigeius</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-lictor" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-lictor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A07247-yyyy_3" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A07247-yyyy_3</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

