<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A18589">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chester's Triumph<date type="creation_date">1610</date></title>
        <author>Davies, Richard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Hannah Bredar</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A18589.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Chesters triumph in honor of her prince. As it was performed vpon S. Georges Day 1610. in the foresaid citie.</title>
            <author>Davies, Richard, fl. 1610.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>15 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2004 November (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99840702</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 5118.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 288.</idno>
            <idno type="vid">5229</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18589</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">Chesters triumph in honor of her prince. As it was performed vpon S. Georges Day 1610. in the foresaid citie.</title>
            <author>Davies, Richard, fl. 1610.</author>
            <author>Amerie, Robert.</author>
            <author>Henry Frederick, 1594-1612.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[28] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Printed [by William Stansby] for I. B[rowne] and are to be sold in Saint Dunstanes Church-yard in Fleete-streete,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1610.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-C4 D2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Dedication signed: Ri. Dauies.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Verse by Davies, with a description of the pageant staged in honor of Henry Frederick Prince of Wales by Robert Amerie.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A18589-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A18589-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A18589-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100040">Chester's triumph in honour of her prince.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100050">As it was performed upon s. George's day 1610. in the for said city.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100060">
          <figure xml:id="A18589-e100070">
            <head>Sursum</head>
            <figDesc xml:id="A18589-e100080">printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100090">London printed for I. B. and are to be sold in saint Dunstanes Church-yard in fleet street. 1610.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="blazon" xml:id="A18589-e100100">
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100110">
          <pb facs="2"/>
          <figure xml:id="A18589-e100120">
            <head>Ich dien</head>
            <head>Hp</head>
            <figDesc xml:id="A18589-e100130">blazon of Prince Henry of Wales</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="dedication" xml:id="A18589-e100140">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>To the high and mighty prince, Henry prince of Wales, Duke of Cornwall and Rothsay, Earl of Chester, knight of the most noble order of the garter, etc.</head>
        <head type="sub">Chester to her prince.</head>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100150">Unto the boundless ocean, most dread prince,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100160">Of thy surmounting great magnificence,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100170">Do we (Poor Palatines) from our best hearts,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100180">(Enlarged with love of thine admired parts)</l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100190">Blushing, object to thy deep judgements eye,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100200">The fruit (Though poor) of rich love's industry. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100210">Not that we are ambitious, or that we</l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100220">Can think it worthy; of (Most worthy) thee. </l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100230">But, with our best integrity, to show</l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100240">The awful duty which our loves do owe,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100250">To thy great greatness; who (Beyond compare)</l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100260">Doth shine so bright in our love's hemisphere</l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100270">That, in thy right, our hearts, lives, limbs and swords,</l>
        <l xml:id="A18589-e100280">Shall stretch our actions far beyond our words. </l>
        <closer xml:id="A18589-e100290">
          <signed xml:id="A18589-e100300">Her ill townsman, ri. Davies. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="to_the_reader" xml:id="A18589-e100310">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <head>To the reader.</head>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100320">Reader, to make a large narration of nothing, were scarce worth any thing; yet, since it hath pleased the great giver of all things, to infuse life into poor animals (As well as spirit into more worthy creatures) I have by the importunity of some friends (Upon honest conditions) let slip this prisoner, who like a poor Peregrinator (To purchase enlargement) is contented to pass through the purgatory of the printing-house: where (If by his good behaviour, he do not merit redemption) let him be pressed without pity a god's name, and like a vituperious offender, be stamped and stared at, by the severest corrector, and truest compositor. To be brief, what was done, was so done, as being by the approbation of many, said to be well done, than I doubt not, but it may merit the merciful construction of some few, who may chance to swear was most excellently ill done. Zeal procured it; love devised it; boys performed it; men beheld it, and none but fools dispraised it. As for the further description of the business, I refer to further relation; only thus: the chiefest part of this people-pleasing spectacle, consisted in three bees, viz. boys, beasts, and bells, bells of a strange amplitude and extraordinary proportion; beasts of an excellent shape, and most admirable swiftness, and boys of rare spirit, and exquisite performance. Which glorious triumph, with much more, was merely intended (As it was then thought) for the joyful celebration of Camber's boundless glory.</p>
        <closer xml:id="A18589-e100330">
          <signed xml:id="A18589-e100340">R. D.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
      <div type="description_of_triumphal_procession" xml:id="A18589-e100350">
        <pb facs="3"/>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100360">¶ A brief relation of the most delightful, pleasant and rare shows, the which have been enacted, set forth, and performed, within the most ancient renowned city Caer-leon, now named Chester, upon the festival of our most worthy approved English champion s. George his day, being the 23. of April 1610. and shall remain and continue perpetually to future ages, as a memorable and worthy project, founded, devised, and erected only by the most famous, generous, and well deserving citizen, Mr. Robert Amerie, late sheriff of the said city, redounding to the glory and praise of almighty God for his benefits, immediately and bounteously poured upon us Christians, and also in lieu of the homage, fealty, allegiance, and duty, which we do owe and attribute unto the King's most excellent and magnificent majesty, his crown and dignity, and to the most virtuous and hopeful heir apparent, the prince of Wales, with that noble victor saint George, our aforesaid English champion.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100370">1 a man by strange devises climbing to the top of a very high spire steeple (Standing at the market (Rose, called s. Peter's steeple) carrying an ancient of our colours of s. George, displaying the same upon the said steeple, and fixing the same to the bar of iron, that the vane hangeth upon: likewise, sounding a drum, shooting off a piece, and flourishing a sword, and standing upon the cross of the said bar of iron, stood upon his hands with his feet into the air, very dangerously and wonderfully to the view of the beholders, with casting fireworks very delightful.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100380"><pb facs="4"/>2. Two disguised, called greene-men, their habit embroidered and stitched on with juie-leaves with black-side, having hanging to their shoulders, a huge black shaggy hair, savage-like, with ivy garlands upon their heads, bearing Herculean clubs in their hands, an artificial dragon, very lively to behold, pursuing the savages entering their den, casting fire from his mouth, which afterwards was slain, to the great pleasure of the spectators, bleeding, fainting, and staggering, as though he endured a feeling pain, even at the last gasp, and farewell.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100390">3. One mounted on horseback, bearing the helmet and shield of s. George, attended by three: one leading his horse, a drum sounding before him, with s. George his scutcheon in the forehead of his horse.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100400">4. Fame mounted on horseback, with a trumpet in her hand, pronouncing an oration.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100410">5. Mercury, descending from heaven in a cloud, artificially winged, a wheel of fire burning very cunningly, with other fireworks, mounting to the height of the foresaid steeple upon cords: with most pleasant and melodious harmony at his approach.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100420">6. Another representing the forenamed and most worthy city Chester, mounted on horseback: two drums sounding before him, with the arms of s. George upon a scutcheon in the forehead of his horse.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100430">7. Another with the King's arms, very richly haroldized upon a shield: also mounted on horseback, with the King's arms upon a scutcheon in the horse's forehead.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100440">8. Another, making an oration, in honour of the King his crown and imperial monarchy, likewise mounted on horseback, with the arms correspondent in the forehead of his horse.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100450"><pb facs="4"/>9. Another, mounted on horseback with a great bell double gilt, supported by four lions rampant, standing upon a lesser bell with a clapper in it, the King's arms engraven thereon, carried upon a sceptre, dedicated to the Kings most excellent majesty, with many trumpets sounding cheerfully before him, with the King's arms upon a scutcheon in the horse's forehead.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100460">10 another with the prince's arms upon a shield, very richly haroldized, mounted on horseback, with the prince's arms upon a scutcheon in the horse's foretop.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100470">11. Another mounted on horseback, delivering an oration in honour of the prince his birthright, and magnificent creation, viz. to the high and mighty prince Henry, prince of Wales, Duke of Cornwall and Rothsay, Earl of Chester, etc. with the prince's arms upon a scutcheon in the horse's forehead.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100480">12. Another mounted on horseback, with a massy bell of silver, parcel gilt, with the prince's arms engraven upon it: likewise supported by three lions rampant, standing upon a lesser bell, with a clapper in it, carried upon a sceptre, a noise of cornets before the bell, dedicated to the prince, with the prince's arms upon a scutcheon in the horse's forehead.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100490">13 another mounted on horseback with the arms of s. George upon a shield, with the arms of saint George upon a scutcheon in the forehead of the horse.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100500">14 Rumot mounted on horseback, pronouncing an oration, in honour of the most worthy Christian English champion s. George, mounted on horseback with the arms of s. George, upon a scutcheon in the forehead of the horse.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100510">15. Another mounted on horseback, with the most ancient and famous standard of s. George, with the arms of saint George upon a scutcheon in the horse's forehead.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100520">16. Another mounted on horseback, bearing upon a sceptre<pb facs="5"/> a great piece of plate, parcel gilt, bell fashion, dedicated to the honour of saint George, with the arms of s. George in the horse's forehead.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100530">17. Another, representing s. George, accoutred and armed at all points, attended by two squires: also in complete armour, a noise of drums before them, likewise mounted on horseback, with the arms of s. George upon a scutcheon in the horse's forehead.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100540">18. Another on horseback, representing peace, who made a speech agreeable to her nature.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100550">19. Another on horseback, representing plenty, made likewise a speech, etc. A wreath of wheat-cares upon her head, with a garland of the same athwart her body, casting and strewing wheat abroad amongst the multitude, as she road along. Garb or wheat-sheaf ore, in a scutcheon upon her horse's forehead.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100560">20. Another on horseback, representing envy, with a wreathe of snakes about her head; another in her hand, her face and arms besmeared with blood.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100570">21. After her (On horseback) came one, representing love, who finding envy dismounted from horseback, and mounted on a stage to show her nature, was conjured by love to depart, and not to interrupt (With her detractions) that day's triumph, undertaken and performed through love, which done, love and joy marshal the succeeding sport.</p>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e100580">22. Lastly, joy mounted on horseback, rejoicing at so great a concourse of people, never there before seen, and praising the good meaning of what there was undertaken and performed. Whereupon all departed for a while, to a place upon the river called the Roodes, guarded with one hundred and twenty halberdiers, and a hundred and twenty shot, bravely furnished. The mayor, sheriffs and aldermen of Chester, arrayed<pb facs="5"/> in their scarlet, having seen the said shows, to grace the same, accompanied, and followed the actors unto the said rood, where the ships, barks, and pinnaces, with other vessels harbouring within the river, displaying the arms of s. George, upon their main tops, with several pendants answerable thereunto; discharged many volleys of shot in honour of the day. The bells dedicated (As before is remembered) being presented to the mayor, proclamation being generally made, to bring in horses to run for the said bells, there was run a double race, to the great pleasure and delight of the spectators: men of great worth, running also at the ring for the said cup, dedicated to saint George, and those that won the prizes, according to the articles agreed upon in that behalf, had the same with the honour thereunto belonging: the said several prizes, being with speeches, and several wreaths set on their heads, delivered in ceremonious and triumphant manner, after the order of the Olympian sports, whereof these were an imitation.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A18589-e100590">
      <div type="triumph" xml:id="A18589-e100600">
        <pb facs="6"/>
        <pb facs="6"/>
        <head>Chester's triumph in honour of her prince.</head>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e100610" who="A18589-fame">
          <speaker>Fame.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100620">From blissful bowers of fair Elysian fields,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100630">(The happy harbour of Jove's dearest dear)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100640">From thence these worthies (Noted by their shields</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100650">Are (By my conduct) thus arrived here. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100660">I fame that with a trice, do overfill</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100670">The world's wide ears with what I please to say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100680">Have brought them thus, as 'twere against the hill</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100690">Of highest lets, to celebrate this day! </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100700">This day, that I so far have famoused</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100710">That not a nook of earth's huge globe but knows,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100720">How in great Britain 'tis solemnised</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100730">With divine offices, and glorious shows. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100740">Then for th'increase of this triumphant mirth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100750">I'll invocate the god's ambassador,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100760">To be the precedent of heaven to earth;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100770">And, from the gods, salute your governor. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100780">Then come great nuntius of th'immortal gods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100790">From that all-swaying senate of their state;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100800">Come, I invoke thee, with thy charming-rod</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100810">In glory come, this day to celebrate. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100820">The ninefold orbs of heaven, my words do pierce;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e100830">Descend then, tongues-man of the universe. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e100840" who="A18589-song">
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <stage xml:id="A18589-e100850">A song of eight voices for the show in Chester on s. George's day.</stage>
          <lg xml:id="A18589-e100860">
            <l xml:id="A18589-e100870">Come down thou mighty messenger of bliss,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e100880">Come: we implore thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e100890">Let not thy glory be obscured from us</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e100900">Who most adore thee:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e100910">Then come, oh come great spirit</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e100920">That we may joyful sing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e100930">Welcome, oh welcome to earth</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e100940">Jove's dearest darling. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg xml:id="A18589-e100950">
            <l xml:id="A18589-e100960">Lighten the eyes thou great Mercurian prince,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e100970">Of all that view thee,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e100980">That by the lustre of their optic sense</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e100990">They may pursue thee:</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e101000">Whilst with their voices</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e101010">Thy praise they shall sing,</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e101020">Come away</l>
            <l xml:id="A18589-e101030">Jove's dearest darling. </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e101040" who="A18589-mercury">
          <stage xml:id="A18589-e101050">Mercury comes down in a cloud and speaks thus.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101060">Down from the throne of the immortal gods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101070">From out the glorious everduring heavens,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101080">And from the sacred powers celestial</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101090">From thence I come, commanded by them all</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101100">To visit him whose rare report hath rung</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101110"><pb facs="7"/> his earned fame on earth hath pierced the sky,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101120">Ascending up unto the highest heavens;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101130">And therewithal procured the sacred senate</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101140">In great regard to hold his worthiness:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101150">For which intent, they all (With one accord)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101160">To manifest the love to him they owe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101170">Have sent me Mercury, their messenger,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101180">To bring him joyful tidings of the same. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101190">And to this place, directed by their powers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101200">I am arrived (In happy time I hope)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101210">To find this happy god-beloved man. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101220">And lo behold on sudden where I spy</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101230">This favourite so favoured of the gods:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101240">I will salute him with such courtesy</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101250">As best beseems a wight of such account. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101260">All hail to thee high justice officer;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101270">Mercury, nuntius to the powers divine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101280">Hath brought thee greetings from their deities. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101290">And know (Dear sir) thy deeds and good deserts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101300">Thy well disposed nature, mind, and thought,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101310">Thy zealous care to keep their laws divine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101320">Thy great compassion on poor wights distressed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101330">Thy prudence, justice, temperance, and thy truth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101340">And, to be brief, thy virtue's general,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101350">Have moved them all from heaven, with one assent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101360">To send me down, to let thee understand</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101370">That thou art highly in their favours placed:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101380">And, for the more assurance of the same,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101390">Lo here a favour favourably sent</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101400">From them, by me, to thee, that thou mayst know</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101410">Thy virtues here shall there rewarded be</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101420"><pb facs="8"/> with endless joy, and perfect happiness. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101430">Receive the same, returning naught but thanks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101440">Which is as much as they require of thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101450">My message done, my task thus brought to end,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101460">I must return and to the heavens ascend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e101470" who="A18589-chester">
          <speaker>Chester.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101480">Hail sage spectators, hail ye reverend sires,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101490">Hail younger brutes, whose worth self worth admires. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101500">Whose ardent loves both to the place, and us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101510">Constrains our loves to entertain ye thus. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101520">Welcome ten thousand times ye blissful crew,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101530">Whose light lends luster to the vulgar view. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101540">Whose several virtues, linked with several graces,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101550">Deserves the best, of our best love's embraces. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101560">The Roman Curtius Rome's great favourite,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101570">(Whose daring death did her from scathe acquit)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101580">Was never more welcome to the Romans sights,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101590">Then are yourselves, to these our choice delights. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101600">To which kind purpose our desire intends</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101610">To entertain you as our fastest friends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101620">With such Olympian sports as shall approve</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101630">Our best devotion, and sincerest love. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101640">Such entertain as best beseems your ranks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101650">We'll strive to give you with our heartiest thanks. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101660">And so, to please your nicer appetietes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101670">We'll feast your pains with pleasure's honeyed sweets. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101680">The rarest viands choice itself affords,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101690">Shall o'er abound upon our bounteous boards,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101700">And in the midst of all our jovial solace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101710"><pb facs="8"/> we'll suck sweet nectar from the paps of Pallas. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101720">We'll cozen France of those delicious vines,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101730">Where-hence they drain their brain-enchanting wines</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101740">To cheer our hearts, and make you frolic so</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101750">As you shall swim in joy, though sunk in woe. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101760">We'll banquet you with such variety</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101770">Of dulcet fruits, whose sweet satiety</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101780">Shall seem so pleasing; as it shall entice</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101790">The gods themselves to surfeit on their juice. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101800">Our best pavilions, in their best attire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101810">Remonstrate shall how much we do desire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101820">To satisfy your expectations eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101830">With all that art can possibly devise. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101840">We'll pave our streets, with that eye-pleasing sand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101850">Which is of power whole kingdoms to command:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101860">And for your more delight perfume we will</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101870">The air: nay, it sweet airs shall overfill. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101880">Our verdant pastures three piled green in grain</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101890">Shall wear, to honour so your entertain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101900">And round about the meadows as ye go,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101910">For peeping flowers the grass shall scarcely show</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101920">What may be done, and willing hearts can do</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101930">Shall be effected with advantage too. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101940">We'll furrow up those petty hills or heights,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101950">That lie but in the way of our delights:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101960">And with the surplus of this surquedry,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101970">Fill up the places that too lowly lie</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101980">Within the list or prospect of that place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e101990">Assigned this triumph and triumphant race. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102000">Whatever our more than strained utmost-all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102010">Can possibly perform; perform we shall. </l>
        </sp>
        <pb facs="9"/>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e102020" who="A18589-britain">
          <speaker>Britain.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102030">Illustrious Britain, stately seat of Kings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102040">Whose boundless glories inequivalent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102050">Do so reflect on fame's Oriental wings. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102060">That o'er the world they spread their blandishment. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102070">Whose influence (Past compass of conceit)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102080">Endarts such sunbeams to obscurer places,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102090">That all the world by that resplendent light,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102100">Derives from her their most peculiar graces. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102110">Whose royal, clement, chaste, and bounteous King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102120">(King; oh too base a style for his great worth)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102130">Such radiant luster to the earth doth bring,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102140">That like the sun it cheers the total North. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102150">Then yield him honour Kings that glorious be;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102160">Veil to this (Next the highest) great King of Kings:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102170">Who by his virtues graceth your degree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102180">And to the same immortal glory brings. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102190">Great Britain's greatness (Wonder of the North:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102200">Admired of all whom virtue's height admires)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102210">We do ascribe unto thy matchless worth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102220">Surmounting praise, to mount thy virtues higher. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102230">And while me (Britain) Neptune shall embrace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102240">I'll ruin those, that spite thee, or thy race. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e102250" who="A18589-cambria">
          <speaker>Cambria.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102260">Renowned Camber, Britain's true repose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102270">Whose ardent zeal to her admired prince,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102280">Hath ever been approved to friends and foes</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102290"><pb facs="9"/> to sacrifice her blood in his defence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102300">With high-swollen words of vaunt to thunder forth</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102310">How much we dare to do in this respect,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102320">Were more than merely idle; since our worth</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102330">Shall show itself in such words true effect. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102340">Our hopeful prince whilst Camber's race doth breath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102350">Shall they with fast united might,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102360">In his just cause will their best swords unsheathe</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102370">Against the stoutest opposer of his right. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102380">We scorn that Wales such weaklings should afford,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102390">That dare not bravely front the eager'st foe</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102400">At any weapon (Pistol, pike, or sword)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102410">And (Like stout warriors) give him blow for blow. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102420">But to our prince (Great Britain's matchless heir)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102430">As humbly low, as is his greatness high,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102440">Our lives we'll prostrate with our best devoir,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102450">To do what may undo the enemy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102460">Whose grace is thought upon this present day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102470">Which day saint George hath blissfully created,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102480">To take his birthright; with such great joy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102490">As such a day was never consecrated. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102500">To memorize which more than blissful feast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102510">We are incited by the love we owe him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102520">The same to celebrate, or at the least</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102530">Our great, great joy most thankfully to show him. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102540">Then naught remains but that we all do pray,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102550">God bless prince Henry prop of England's joy. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e102560" who="A18589-rumor">
          <speaker>Rumour.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102570">Saint George for England, is the patron knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102580">Whose ever-conquering, and all-daring hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102590">Did put whole hosts of heathens foes to flight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102600"><pb facs="10"/> that did the vigour of his strength withstand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102610">He that did ever live (A champion stout)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102620">With such undaunted holy-high resolve,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102630">That through the earth his fame did fly about,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102640">Which shall not die till heaven and earth dissolve. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102650">Against the heathen folk his force he proved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102660">By which he did decline their highest pride:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102670">For which of heaven and earth he was beloved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102680">And made a glorious saint whenas he died,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102690">Upon a hideous dragon (Whose thick scales</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102700">Like shields, that naught could pierce by force nor art</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102710">Did bulwark him) so fast his falchion falls,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102720">That he through them made way unto his heart. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102730">Whose rare achievements and whose rich renown</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102740">(Flowing from matchless magnanimity)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102750">Still makes them owners of great Britain's crown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102760">As in this day to crown his memory. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102770">Whose fame's bright splendour, rarely to depaint</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102780">In colours rich according to his worth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102790">Would try the tongue of Hermes, sith this saint</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102800">Thus travels Britain's glory to bring forth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102810">Many a monster he by force subdued,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102820">And many a fiend incarnate he suppressed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102830">Whose sword did still mow down their multitude,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102840">So to imbarn them in hell's restless rest. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102850">When lo at length returning to the soil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102860">Wherein he first received his vital breath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102870">He spent his time religiously awhile,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102880">Till death had slain him, who now conquers death:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102890">So, britain's when they fight with cheer, they say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102900">God and saint George for England to this day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e102910" who="A18589-peace">
          <pb facs="10"/>
          <speaker>Peace.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102920">To bring glad news of future happy years,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102930">Peace is the nuntius that such tidings bears. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102940">Who while the Scotch the English fair entreat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102950">And me embrace withal, I'll make them great. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102960">No foreign nation shall affront their force</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102970">As long as I direct them in that course. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102980">All rash dissensions and litigious braules,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e102990">I shall expel from their unshaken walls. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103000">All civil mutinies shall then surcease,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103010">And peace shall bring them everlasting peace. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103020">Inveterate hate so will I turn to love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103030">As with one motion both shall jointly move. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103040">Brother with brother, nay, the foe with friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103050">For mine and thine shall never more contend. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103060">No massacre nor bloody stratagem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103070">Shall stir in peace's new Jerusalem. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103080">No civil discord, nor domestic strife</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103090">Shall e'er annoy their peace, much less their life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103100">For (Like to olive branches) they shall bear</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103110">Fruit that gives love an appetite to bear. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103120">Which mutual concord dateless shall endure</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103130">As long as love can peace to love procure. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103140">I'll bind their loves with true love's Gordian knot,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103150">That rude dissensions hands undo it not:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103160">And with a wreathe of everduring bays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103170">Crown all your brows with peace-procured praise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103180">I'll rend the close-mouthed rage of emulous strife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103190">And wound distraction, with connexions knife. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103200">And when damned malice comes but once in sight</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103210">I, with a vengeance, will suppress her straight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103220"><pb facs="11"/>I'll send pale envy down to hell with speed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103230">Where she upon her snakes shall only feed. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103240">And with some poisonous and envenomed toad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103250">Her much more poisonous self shall make abode. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103260">Which being done I'll send that base infection</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103270">(Whose only virtue is but base) detraction</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103280">Her to associate; where they both shall live</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103290">As long as hell can life with horror give:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103300">And thus shall peace their joy perpetuate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103310">That love (In love) to stay this blessed state. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103320" who="A18589-plenty">
          <speaker>Plentie.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103330">Since plenty still co-operates with peace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103340">Plenty shall bless your basket of increase. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103350">From whose abundant never exhausted store,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103360">You shall receive much more than had before,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103370">I'll stuff your barns up to the throat with grain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103380">Which shall all yours, and others still sustain. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103390">I'll fructify the earth with rarest fruits</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103400">Of sundry shapes, and several kind of suits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103410">So as the soil (That bears seed timely sown)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103420">Under the burden of their weight, shall groan. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103430">In all abundance I will rear your beasts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103440">Which shall maintain your o'er abounding feasts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103450">Fish, foul, herbs, grass, and all things whatsoever,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103460">Shall at your door be cheap, and nothing dear</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103470">I'll sink into the concaves of earth's mould,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103480">And there hence pull and cull her purest gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103490">And then will dive into the ocean deeps,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103500">To raise the treasure which their neptune keeps. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103510">I'll freight your ships with such o'er-freighting store,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103520">That greediness herself shall seek no more. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103530"><pb facs="11"/>No scarcity shall in your land be found,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103540">As long as I with nature till your ground. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103550">What shall I say? your life-supporting staff,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103560">The staff of bread; I'll throw abroad like chaff. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103570">Then see how graciously the highest hath sent ye</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103580">Peace, in all fullness, in all fullness plenty. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A18589-e103590">Envy and love.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103600" who="A18589-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103610">Hisse. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103620" who="A18589-love">
          <speaker>Love.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103630">Why how now envy? dost thou hiss at Phoebus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103640" who="A18589-envy">
          <speaker>Envy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103650">Yes; and at Cinthia too, if she anger us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103660" who="A18589-love">
          <speaker>L.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103670">Your reason envy? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103680" who="A18589-envy">
          <speaker>Envy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103690">Why? My reason's this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103700">To hear a cat cry mew, who can but hiss. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103710" who="A18589-love">
          <speaker>L.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103720">Out hissing scorpion:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103730" who="A18589-envy">
          <speaker>Envy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103740">Out ye filthy fool,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103750">Envy hath wit, to set such apes to school. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103760" who="A18589-love">
          <speaker>L.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103770">Malicious monster, thou incarnate devil,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103780">Whose base condition, is the source of evil. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103790">Thou envious bandog, speak and do thy worst,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103800">He that regards it; is the most accursed</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103810" who="A18589-envy">
          <speaker>Envy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103820">And he that thinks that love can e'er be wise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103830">Hath neither judgement, wisdom, wit, nor eyes. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103840" who="A18589-love">
          <speaker>L.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103850">Say thou abortive, men-detested slave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103860">Whose only virtue is, but to deprave</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103870">Man's best proceedings, speak thou squint-eyed monster,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103880">What is the cause which makes thee still misconstrue? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103890" who="A18589-envy">
          <speaker>Envy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103900">Because I hate to hear a want-wit preach</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103910">Beyond wits bounds, and wisdom's boundless reach:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103920">To see a superficial sot make show</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103930">Of deeper skill than wit itself doth know. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103940" who="A18589-love">
          <pb facs="12"/>
          <speaker>L.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103950">What is the solace Envy counteth deep? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e103960" who="A18589-envy">
          <speaker>Envy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103970">Marry to see a wolf devour a sheep. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103980">To see men-devils breeding still dissension</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e103990">Is sport ( methinks ) beyond all comprehension:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104000">Or else a rich man hunger-pined with want,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104010">To see an army (When their food is scant)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104020">Eat their own excrements; oh this is sport</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104030">For envy, that without this is all amort. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104040">To see a drove of drunkards like to swine</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104050">Swilling their souls, in soul-overwhelming wine. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104060">To see a city burned, or barns on fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104070">To see a son the butcher of his sire. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104080">To see two swaggerers eagerly to strive,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104090">Which of them both shall make the hangman thrive. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104100">To see a good man poor, or wise man bore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104110">To see dame virtue overwhelmed with care. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104120">To see a ruined church, a preacher dumb,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104130">A King's child perish in the mother's womb. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104140">To see a miser, who to have his pelf,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104150">Will take a rope and (Desperate) hang himself:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104160">To see a virgin by a varlet used,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104170">Till she by him to death be so abused. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104180">Or else to see a father suck the blood</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104190">Of his own spawn, o! these would do me good. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104200">But to behold a rank of rustic boys</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104210">Showing as childish people childish toys</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104220">To grace a day with; oh it grates my gall</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104230">To hear an apish kitling caterwaul. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104240">Is it not harsh to hear a marmoset squeak</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104250">Upon a stage a most unjointed speak? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104260">And then to hear some ignorant baboon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104270">Swear that this monkey did surmount the moon. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104280"><pb facs="12"/> whenas the infants best is too too bad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104290">And which to hear would make a wiseman mad. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e104300" who="A18589-love">
          <speaker>L.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104310">Thou damned infection; damned from thy birth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104320">Abhorred of heaven, and odious to the earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104330">How canst thou ever hope to merit grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104340">When thy delight is but detraction base? </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104350">But since there is no sign of grace in that</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104360">Damned face of thine, which hell doth wonder at,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104370">Love shall conjure thee; that from this time forth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104380">Thou never frequent this island of the North. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104390">Dive to the depth of deepest Stygian flood;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104400">There suck thou snakes, and snakes there suck thy blood. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104410">Or sink thou quite to the infernal deep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104420">Where crawling scorpions may about thee creep. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104430">And there among those vermin vile beneath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104440">Belk up that poison which thou here dost breathe. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104450">Go, I conjure thee, lest I make thee feel</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104460">The keenest edge of wraths revenging steel. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104470">Burden the earth no more, thou hateful toad</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104480">With such a ponderous earth-annoying load,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104490">Go with a vengeance go, and never retire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104500">But we are our time in everlasting fire. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e104510" who="A18589-envy">
          <speaker>Envy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104520">O I could grind and grate thee with my teeth,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e104530" who="A18589-love">
          <speaker>L.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104540">No more thou monster; hence be gone forthwith;</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e104550" who="A18589-envy">
          <speaker>Envy</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104560">Confusion, death, plague, pestilence, and piles,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104570">Confound their souls who at mine anguish smiles,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104580">Yet, ere I go, I'll bid the best farewell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104590">Hoping ere long to meet their ghosts in hell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e104600" who="A18589-love">
          <speaker>L.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104610">Go ugly monster, loves Misanthropos,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104620">Sink down to torture and continual woes. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104630">Heaven excludes thee; earth abhors thy sight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104640">And grieves to bear the burden of thy weight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104650"><pb facs="13"/>Sink to her centre, there's thy native rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104660">And never more be seen to spot her breast:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104670">So, haste thee hence; and henceforth I'll direct</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104680">My speech to those, whom I do best affect:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104690">Love bids you welcome that are come in love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104700">To see our sports that envy doth reprove. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e104710" who="A18589-joy">
          <speaker>Joy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104720">Envy avaunt, thou art no fit compeer</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104730">T'associate these our sweet consociates here. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104740">Joy doth exclude thee, who (To thy disgrace)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104750">Here spits defiance in thy ugly face. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104760">And that is more; thy everlasting shame</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104770">Shall be still blasted by the trump of fame:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104780">The powerful tongue of facund Mercury,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104790">Shall to the world display thy infamy. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104800">Chester abhors thy presence; Britain hates thee;</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104810">And for a damned fury, Camber takes thee. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104820">Peace, as a herald, shall proclaim to all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104830">That thou art damned by justice-general. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104840">Plenty detests thy base society,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104850">Who scorns thy hell-bred gross impiety. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104860">And last of all; my love, in love's defence</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104870">In spite of envy, shall send envy hence. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104880">Wherefore avaunt; that all the I'll may sing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104890">Now envy's gone, in peace w'enioy our King. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e104900" who="A18589-fame">
          <pb facs="13"/>
          <stage xml:id="A18589-e104910">After the running of the horse's fame speaks.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104920">With rich characters of resplendent gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104930">Fame hath your names within her book enrolled:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104940">Which till time stays his course shall glitter bright,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104950">Maugre detraction and fell envy's spite. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e104960" who="A18589-britain">
          <stage xml:id="A18589-e104970">Britain to him that won the best bell.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104980">In sign of victory which thou hast gained,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e104990">This wreathe by thy fair front shall be sustained. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105000">Whose green leaved branches unto fame shall tell</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105010">That thou didst best deserve the better bell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e105020" who="A18589-camber">
          <stage xml:id="A18589-e105030">Camber to the second.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105040">To crown thy temples with a second wreath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105050">Lo here doth Camber unto thee bequeath</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105060">This fragrant garland: sith thou didst excel</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105070">The best that ran but at the second bell. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e105080" who="A18589-rumor">
          <stage xml:id="A18589-e105090">Rumor to him that won the ring.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105100">Thou that by either cunning, or by chance,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105110">Didst take the ring with thy thrice happy lance:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105120">Here take of me (To raise thy virtues up)</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105130">This wreath of balm, and polished silver cup. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e105140" who="A18589-all">
          <stage xml:id="A18589-e105150">All together.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105160">And so we all in all your several graces,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105170">Will with fames o'erfill all times and places. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A18589-e105180" who="A18589-chester">
          <pb facs="14"/>
          <stage xml:id="A18589-e105190">Chesters last speech.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105200">No action, though admired for excellence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105210">No practice, though of highest pre-eminence</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105220">That can escape the Polyphemian eye</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105230">Of envy, that for ever looks awry:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105240">Yet notwithstanding on your love's depending,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105250">Whose patient ears excludes all reprehending. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105260">We here submit ourselves in humblest wise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105270">Before the bar of your judicious eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105280">What we present unto your dainty ears</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105290">Is freed from scandals: so is free from fears. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105300">Only your loves which are our fairest marks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105310">Must muzzle envy, when the fury barks</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105320">Unto the best, we doubt not but our best</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105330">May purchase favour; and for all the rest</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105340">We do expect but this poor kindness from them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105350">That they would speak but what shall well become them. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105360">This being granted: Chester doth invite</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105370">Each noble worthy, and each worthy knight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105380">To close their stomach with a small repast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105390">Which may content a temperate curious taste. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105400">Measure our ardent loves, with such kind measure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105410">As we afford you sport, and give you pleasure:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105420">And so we'll leave you with this solemn vow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105430">That whilst we breathe, our hearts shall honour you. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105440">If any reader shall desire to know</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105450">Who was the author of this pleasing show:</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105460"><pb facs="14"/> let him receive advertisement hereby</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105470">A sheriff (Late of Chester) Amerie. </l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105480">Did thus perform it; who for his reward,</l>
          <l xml:id="A18589-e105490">Desires but love, and competent regard. </l>
        </sp>
        <closer xml:id="A18589-e105500">
          <signed xml:id="A18589-e105510">Robert Amerie.</signed>
        </closer>
        <trailer xml:id="A18589-e105520">Finis.</trailer>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back xml:id="A18589-e105530">
      <div type="illustration" xml:id="A18589-e105540">
        <pb facs="15"/>
        <pb facs="15"/>
        <p xml:id="A18589-e105550">
          <figure xml:id="A18589-e105560">
            <p xml:id="A18589-e105570">A</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A18589"><item xml:id="A18589-love" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-love</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18589-envy" n="9">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-envy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">9</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18589-rumor" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-rumor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18589-fame" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-fame</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18589-chester" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-chester</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18589-britain" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-britain</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A18589-cambria" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-cambria</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18589-mercury" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-mercury</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18589-camber" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-camber</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18589-joy" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-joy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18589-song" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-song</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18589-all" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-all</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18589-peace" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-peace</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A18589-plenty" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A18589-plenty</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

