<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/master/teisimple.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="A13358">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Taming of a Shrew <date type="creation_date">1594</date></title>
        <author>anon.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>

           <edition n="0.1">This early release includes some 500 EEBO-TCP transcriptions of Early Modern plays that have undergone several routines to create an interoperable and algorithmically amenable corpus of Early Modern Drama.  Many incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words have been corrected, including obvious printers' errors,  but the  text has not been proofread word by word. Each word in the text has been identified as a distinct token with its own xml:id and assigned to a lemma, a part of speech, and a standard spelling.  Speech prefixes were mapped  to unique speaker ID's  as "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements. elements</edition>
           <editor>Martin Mueller</editor>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Incompletely or incorrectly transcribed words were reviewed and in many cases fixed by</resp>
              <name>Melina Yeh</name></respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Tokenization and linguistic annotation  using MorphAdorner and NUPOS 2.0 were provided by</resp>
              <name>Philip R. Burns</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>With the help of Thomas L. Berger's Index of Characters in Early Modern English Drama Printed Plays, 1500-1660 speech prefixes were mapped to unique "who" attributes of <gi>sp</gi> elements by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>A provisional, rudimentry, and algorithmically produced castlist was added as a new <gi>div</gi> in the <gi>back</gi> listing each role
              with their number of speeches sorted from high to low by </resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Project co-ordination and review of textual changes and linguistic annotation by</resp>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
           </respStmt>

        </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
           <authority>
              <name>Martin Mueller</name>
              <address>
            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Northwestern University</addrLine>
         <addrLine>Evanston IL 60208</addrLine>
         </address></authority>

           <availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/deed.en_US">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
           <date>2015</date>
           <idno type="SHC">SHC-A13358.xml</idno>
        </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull n="TCP source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A pleasant conceited historie, called The taming of a shrew. As it was sundry times acted by the Right honorable the Earle of Pembrook his seruants.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>27 600dpi TIFF G4 page images</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Michigan, Digital Library Production Service</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, Michigan</pubPlace>
            <date>2009 March (TCP phase 1)</date>
            <idno type="marc">99846538</idno>
            <idno type="stc">STC (2nd ed.) 23667.</idno>
            <idno type="stc">Greg, I, 120(a).</idno>
            <idno type="vid">11514</idno>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13358</idno>
            <availability>
              <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this text, in whole or in part. Please contact project staff at eebotcp-info@umich.edu for further information or permissions.</p>
            </availability>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull n="printed source">
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="_245">A pleasant conceited historie, called The taming of a shrew. As it was sundry times acted by the Right honorable the Earle of Pembrook his seruants.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>[52] p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>By Peter Short and are to be sold by Cutbert Burbie, at his shop at the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
            <date>1594.</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The taming of a shrew.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>In verse.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Signatures: A-F4 G2.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>The connection with Shakespeare's play is obscure.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
This is a very early release with many imperfections. Contact martinmueller@northwestern.edu for corrections and improvement. For more information about the project go to http://scalablereading.northwestern.edu</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl n="4">
        <p>These texts have been encoded in TEI Simple, but retain all the structural distinctions found in the TCP texts fron which they were derived. The facs attributes for each <gi>pb</gi>; and <gi>w</gi>element provide a link to the EEBO pages images. A list of the NUPOS2 tags with descriptiosn and examples can be found at href="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/morphadorner/schemata/nupos2-interpgrp.xml"</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng" xml:id="A13358-e100010">
    <front xml:id="A13358-e100020">
      <div type="title_page" xml:id="A13358-e100030">
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <pb facs="1"/>
        <p xml:id="A13358-e100040">A pleasant conceited history, called the taming of a shrew.</p>
        <p xml:id="A13358-e100050">As it was sundry times acted by the right honourable the Earl of Pembroke his servants.</p>
        <p xml:id="A13358-e100060">
          <figure xml:id="A13358-e100070"/>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="A13358-e100080">Printed at London by Peter short and are to be sold by Cutbert Burbie, at his shop at the royal exchange. 1594.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="A13358-e100090">
      <div type="play" xml:id="A13358-e100100">
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <pb facs="2"/>
        <head>A pleasant conceited history, called the taming of a shrew. </head>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e100110">Enter a tapster, beating out of his doors sly drunken. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e100120" who="A13358-tapster">
          <speaker>Tapster.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100130">You whoreson drunken slave, you had best be gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100140">And empty your drunken paunch somewhere else</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100150">For in this house thou shalt not rest tonight . </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e100160">Exit tapster. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e100170" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100180">Tilly-vally , by crisee tapster I'll feeze you anon. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100190">Fills the tother pot and all's paid for, look you</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100200">I do drink it of mine own instigation,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e100210">Omne bene</stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100220">Here I'll lie a while, why tapster I say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100230">Fills a fresh cushion here. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100240">Heigh ho, here's good warm lying. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e100250">He falls asleep.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e100260">Enter a noble man and his men from hunting.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e100270" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100280">Now that the gloomy shadow of the night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100290">Longing to view Orion's drizzling looks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100300">Leaps from th'antarctic world unto the sky</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100310">And dims the welkin with her pitchy breath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100320">And darksome night o'ershades the crystal heavens,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100330">Here break we off our hunting for tonight ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100340"><pb facs="3"/> couple up the hounds and let us hie us home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100350">And bid the huntsman see them meated well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100360">For they have all deserved it well to day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100370">But soft, what sleepy fellow is this lies here? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100380">Or is he dead, see one what he doth lack? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e100390" who="A13358-servant">
          <speaker>Servant.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100400">My lord, 'tis nothing but a drunken sleep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100410">His head is too heavy for his body,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100420">And he hath drunk so much that he can go no further. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e100430" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100440">Fie, how the slavish villain stinks of drink. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100450">Ho, sirrah arise. What so sound asleep? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100460">Go take him up and bear him to my house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100470">And bear him easily for fear he wake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100480">And in my fairest chamber make a fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100490">And set a sumptuous banquet on the board,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100500">And put my richest garments on his back,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100510">Then set him at the table in a chair:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100520">When that is done against he shall awake,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100530">Let heavenly music play about him still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100540">Go two of you away and bear him hence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100550">And then I'll tell you what I have devised,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100560">But see in any case you wake him not. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e100570">Exeunt two with sly. </stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100580">Now take my cloak and give me one of yours,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100590">All fellows now, and see you take me so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100600">For we will wait upon this drunken man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100610">To see his countenance when he doth awake</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100620">And find himself clothed in such attire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100630">With heavenly music sounding in his ears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100640">And such a banquet set before his eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100650">The fellow sure will think he is in heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100660">But we will be about him when he wakes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100670">And see you call him lord, at every word,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100680">And offer thou him his horse to ride abroad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100690"><pb facs="3"/> and thou his hawks and hounds to hunt the dear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100700">And I will ask what suits he means to wear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100710">And whatsoe'er he saith, see you do not laugh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100720">But still persuade him that he is a lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e100730">Enter one.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e100740" who="A13358-messenger">
          <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100750">And it please your honour your players be come</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100760">And do attend your honour's pleasure here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e100770" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100780">The fittest time they could have chosen out,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100790">Bid one or two of them come hither straight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100800">Now will I fit myself accordingly,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100810">For they shall play to him when he awakes. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e100820">Enter two of the players with packs at their backs, and a boy.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100830">Now sirs, what store of plays have you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e100840" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100850">Marry my lord you may have a tragical</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100860">Or a commodity, or what you will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e100870" who="A13358-other">
          <speaker>The other.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e100880">A comedy thou shouldst say, 'zounds thou'lt shame us all.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e100890" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e100900">And what's the name of your comedy?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e100910" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100920">Marry my lord 'tis called the taming of a shrew:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100930">'Tis a good lesson for us my lord, for us y' are married men</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e100940" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100950">The taming of a shrew, that's excellent sure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100960">Go see that you make you ready straight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100970">For you must play before a lord tonight ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100980">Say you are his men and I your fellow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e100990">He's something foolish, but whatsoe'er he says,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101000">See that you be not dashed out of countenance. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101010">And sirrah go you make you ready straight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101020">And dress yourself like some lovely lady,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101030">And when I call see that you come to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101040">For I will say to him thou art his wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101050">Dally with him and hug him in thine arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101060">And if he desire to go to bed with thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101070"><pb facs="4"/> then fain some 'scuse and say thou wilt anon. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101080">Be gone I say, and see thou dost it well. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101090" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101100">Fear not my lord, I'll dandell him well enough</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101110">And make him think I love him mightily. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e101120">Ex. boy.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101130" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101140">Now sirs go you and make you ready to,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101150">For you must play as soon as he doth wake. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101160" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101170">O brave, sirrah Tom, we must play before</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101180">A foolish lord, come let's go make us ready,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101190">Go get a dishclout to make clean your shoes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101200">And I'll speak for the properties, my lord, we must</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101210">Have a shoulder of mutton for a property,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101220">And a little vinegar to make our devil roar. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101230" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e101240">Very well: sirrah see that they want nothing.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e101250">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e101260">Enter two with a table and a banquet on it, and two other, with sly asleep in a chair, richly apparelled, and the music playing.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101270" who="A13358-one">
          <speaker>One.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101280">So: sirrah now go call my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101290">And tell him that all things is ready as he willed it. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101300">Another. Set thou some wine upon the board</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101310">And then I'll go fetch my lord presently. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e101320">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e101330">Enter the lord and his men.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101340" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e101350">How now, what is all things ready?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101360" who="A13358-one">
          <speaker>One.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e101370">I my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101380" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101390">Then sound the music, and I'll wake him straight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101400">And see you do as erst I gave in charge. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101410">My lord, my lord, he sleeps soundly: my lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101420" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e101430">Tapster, gis a little small ale. Heigh ho,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101440" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e101450">Here's wine my lord, the purest of the grape.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101460" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e101470">For which lord?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101480" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e101490">For your honour my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101500" who="A13358-sly">
          <pb facs="4"/>
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e101510">Who I, am I a lord? Jesus what fine apparel have I got.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101520" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101530">More richer far your honour hath to wear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101540">And if it please you I will fetch them straight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101550" who="A13358-will">
          <speaker>Will</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101560">And if your honour please to ride abroad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101570">I'll fetch you lusty steeds more swift of pace</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101580">Then winged Pegasus in all his pride,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101590">That ran so swiftly over the Persian plains. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101600" who="A13358-tom">
          <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101610">And if your honour please to hunt the dear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101620">Your hounds stands ready coupled at the door,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101630">Who in running will o'ertake the row,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101640">And make the long breathed tiger broken winded. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101650" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101660">By the mass I think I am a lord indeed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101670">What's thy name? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101680" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e101690">Simon and it please your honour.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101700" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101710">Simon, that's as much to say Simion or Simon</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101720">Put forth thy hand and fill the pot. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101730">Give me thy hand, Sim. am I a lord indeed? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101740" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101750">I my gracious lord, and your lovely lady</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101760">Long time hath mourned for your absence here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101770">And now with joy behold where she doth come</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101780">To gratulate your honours safe return. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e101790">Enter the boy in woman's attire.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101800" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e101810">Sim. Is this she?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101820" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e101830">I my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101840" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e101850">Mass 'tis a pretty wench, what's her name?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101860" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101870">O that my lovely lord would once vouchsafe</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101880">To look on me, and leave these frantic fits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101890">Or were I now but half so eloquent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101900">To paint in words what I'll perform in deeds,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101910">I know your honour then would pity me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101920" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101930">Hark you mistress, will you eat a piece of bread,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101940"><pb facs="5"/> come sit down on my knee, Sim drink to her Sim,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101950">For she and I will go to bed anon. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101960" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101970">May it please you, your honour's players be come</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e101980">To offer your honour a play. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e101990" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e102000">A play Sim, oh brave, be they my players?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102010" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e102020">I my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102030" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e102040">Is there not a fool in the play?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102050" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e102060">Yes my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102070" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e102080">When will they play Sim? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102090" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e102100">Even when it please your honour, they be ready.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102110" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e102120">My lord I'll go bid them begin their play.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102130" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e102140">Do, but look that you come again.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102150" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e102160">I warrant you my lord, I will not leave you thus.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e102170">Exit boy.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102180" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102190">Come Sim, where be the players? Sim stand by</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102200">Me and we'll flout the players out of their coats. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102210" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e102220">I'll call them my lord. Ho where are you there?</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e102230">Sound trumpets.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e102240">Enter two young gentlemen, and a man and a boy.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102250" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102260">Welcome to Athens my beloved friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102270">To Plato's schools and Aristotle's walks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102280">Welcome from Cestus famous for the love</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102290">Of good Leander and his tragedy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102300">For whom the Hellespont weeps brinish tears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102310">The greatest grief is I cannot as I would</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102320">Give entertainment to my dearest friend. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102330" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102340">Thanks noble Polidor my second self,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102350">The faithful love which I have found in thee</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102360">Hath made me leave my father's princely court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102370">The Duke of Cestus thrice renowned seat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102380">To come to Athens thus to find thee out,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102390"><pb facs="5"/> which since I have so happily attained,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102400">My fortune now I do account as great</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102410">As erst did Caesar when he conquered most,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102420">But tell me noble friend where shall we lodge,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102430">For I am unacquainted in this place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102440" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102450">My lord if you vouchsafe of scholars fare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102460">My house, myself, and all is yours to use,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102470">You and your men shall stay and lodge with me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102480" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102490">With all my heart, I will requite thy love,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e102500">Enter Simon, Alphonsus, and his three daughters.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102510">But stay; what dames are these so bright of hue</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102520">Whose eyes are brighter than the lamps of heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102530">Fairer than rocks of pearl and precious stone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102540">More lovely far than is the morning sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102550">When first she opens her Oriental gates. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102560" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102570">Daughters be gone, and hie you to the church,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102580">And I will hie me down unto the key,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102590">To see what merchandise is come ashore. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e102600">Ex. omnes.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102610" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102620">Why how now my lord, what in a dump,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102630">To see these damsels pass away so soon? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102640" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102650">Trust me my friend I must confess to thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102660">I took so much delight in these fair dames,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102670">As I do wish they had not gone so soon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102680">But if thou canst, resolve me what they be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102690">And what old man it was that went with them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102700">For I do long to see them once again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102710" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102720">I cannot blame your honour good my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102730">For they are both lovely, wise, fair and young,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102740">And one of them the youngest of the three</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102750">I long have loved (Sweet friend) and she loved me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102760">But never yet we could not find a means</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102770">How we might compass our desired joys. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102780" who="A13358-aurel">
          <pb facs="6"/>
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e102790">Why, is not her father willing to the match?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102800" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102810">Yes trust me, but he hath solemnly sworn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102820">His eldest daughter first shall be espoused,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102830">Before he grants his youngest leave to love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102840">And therefore he that means to get their loves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102850">Must first provide for her if he will speed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102860">And he that hath her shall be fettered so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102870">As good be wedded to the devil himself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102880">For such a scold as she did never live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102890">And till that she be sped none else can speed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102900">Which makes me think that all my labours lost,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102910">And whosoe'er can get her firm good will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102920">A large dowry he shall be sure to have,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102930">For her father is a man of mighty wealth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102940">And an ancient citizen of the town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102950">And that was he that went along with them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e102960" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102970">But he shall keep her still by my advice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102980">And yet I needs must love his second daughter</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e102990">The image of honour and nobility,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103000">In whose sweet person is comprised the sum</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103010">Of nature's skill and heavenly majesty. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103020" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103030">I like your choice, and glad you chose not mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103040">Then if you like to follow on your love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103050">We must devise a means and find some one</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103060">That will attempt to wed this devilish scold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103070">And I do know the man. Come hither boy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103080">Go your ways sirrah to Ferando's house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103090">Desire him take the pains to come to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103100">For I must speak with him immediately. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103110" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e103120">I will sir, and fetch him presently.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103130" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103140">A man I think will fit her humour right,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103150">As blunt in speech as she is sharp of tongue,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103160">And he I think will match her every way,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103170">And yet he is a man of wealth sufficient,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103180"><pb facs="6"/> and for his person worth as good as she,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103190">And if he compass her to be his wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103200">Then may we freely visit both our loves. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103210" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103220">O might I see the centre of my soul</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103230">Whose sacred beauty hath enchanted me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103240">More fair than was the Grecian Helena</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103250">For whose sweet sake so many princes died,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103260">That came with thousand ships to Tenedos,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103270">But when we come unto her father's house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103280">Tell him I am a merchant's son of Cestus,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103290">That comes for traffic unto Athens here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103300">And here sirrah I will change with you for once,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103310">And now be thou the Duke of Cestus' son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103320">Revel and spend as if thou wert myself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103330">For I will court my love in this disguise. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103340" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103350">My lord, how if the Duke your father should</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103360">By some means come to Athens for to see</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103370">How you do profit in these public schools,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103380">And find me clothed thus in your attire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103390">How would he take it then think you my lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103400" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103410">Tush fear not Valeria let me alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103420">But stay, here comes some other company. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e103430">Enter Ferando and his man Saunders with a blue coat.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103440" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e103450">Here comes the man that I did tell you of.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103460" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103470">Good morrow gentlemen to all at once. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103480">How now Polidor, what man still in love? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103490">Ever wooing and canst thou never speed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103500">God send me better luck when I shall woo. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103510" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e103520">I warrant you master and you take my council.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103530" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e103540">Why sirrah, are you so cunning?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103550" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103560">Who I, 'twere better for you by five mark</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103570">And you could tell how to do it as well as I. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103580" who="A13358-polydore">
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103590">I would thy master once were in the vain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103600">To try himself how he could woe a wench. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103610" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e103620">Faith I am even now a going.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103630" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e103640"> i'faith sir, my master's going to this gear now.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103650" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e103660">Whither in faith Ferando, tell me true.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103670" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103680">To bony Kate, the patientest wench alive</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103690">The devil himself dares scarce venture to woo her,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103700">Signior Alfonso's eldest daughter,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103710">And he hath promised me six thousand crowns</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103720">If I can win her once to be my wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103730">And she and I must woo with scolding sure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103740">And I will hold her toot till she be weary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103750">Or else I'll make her yield to grant me love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103760" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103770">How like you this Aurelius, I think he knew</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103780">Our minds before we sent to him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103790">But tell me, when do you mean to speak with her? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103800" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103810">Faith presently, do you but stand aside,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103820">And I will make her father bring her hither,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103830">And she, and I, and he, will talk alone. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103840" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103850">With all our hearts, come Aurelius</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103860">Let us be gone and leave him here alone. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e103870">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103880" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e103890">Ho signior Alfonso, who's within there?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103900" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103910">Signior Ferando your welcome heartily,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103920">You are a stranger sir unto my house. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103930">Hark you sir, look what I did promise you</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103940">I'll perform, if you get my daughter's love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e103950" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103960">Then when I have talked a word or two with her,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103970">Do you step in and give her hand to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103980">And tell her when the marriage day shall be,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e103990">For I do know she would be married fain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104000">And when our nuptial rites be once performed</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104010">Let me alone to tame her well enough,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104020">Now call her forth that I may speak with her. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e104030">Enter Kate. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104040" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <pb facs="7"/>
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104050">Ha Kate, come hither wench and list to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104060">Use this gentleman friendly as thou canst. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104070" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104080">Twenty good morrows to my lovely Kate. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104090" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104100">You jest I am sure, is she yours already?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104110" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104120">I tell thee Kate I know thou lovest me well.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104130" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104140">The devil you do, who told you so?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104150" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104160">My mind sweet Kate doth say I am the man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104170">Must wed, and bed, and marry bonny Kate. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104180" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104190">Was ever seen so gross an ass as this?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104200" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104210">Ay, to stand so long and never get a kiss.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104220" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104230">Hands off I say, and get you from this place;</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104240">Or I will set my ten commandments in your face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104250" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104260">I prithee do Kate; they say thou art a shrew,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104270">And I like thee the better for I would have thee so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104280" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104290">Let go my hand, for fear it reach your ear.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104300" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104310">No Kate, this hand is mine and I thy love.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104320" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104330">In faith sir no the woodcock wants his tail.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104340" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104350">But yet his bill will serve, if the other fail.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104360" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104370">How now Ferando, what says my daughter?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104380" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104390">She's willing sir and loves me as her life.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104400" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104410">'Tis for your skin then, but not to be your wife.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104420" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104430">Come hither Kate and let me give thy hand</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104440">To him that I have chosen for thy love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104450">And thou tomorrow shalt be wed to him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104460" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104470">Why father, what do you mean to do with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104480">To give me thus unto this brainsick man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104490">That in his mood cares not to murder me? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104500">She turns aside and speaks. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104510">But yet I will consent and marry him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104520">For I methinks have lived too long a maid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104530">And match him to, or else his manhoods good. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104540" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104550">Give me thy hand Ferando loves thee well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104560">And will with wealth and ease maintain thy state. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104570">Here Ferando take her for thy wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104580"><pb facs="8"/> and Sunday next shall be your wedding day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104590" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104600">Why so, did I not tell thee I should be the man</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104610">Father, I leave my lovely Kate with you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104620">Provide yourselves against our marriage day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104630">For I must hie me to my country house</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104640">In haste, to see provision may be made,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104650">To entertain my Kate when she doth come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104660" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104670">Do so, come Kate, why dost thou look</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104680">So sad, be merry wench thy wedding days at hand. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104690">Son fare you well, and see you keep your promise. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e104700">Exit Alfonso and Kate. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104710" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104720">So, all thus far goes well. Ho Saunder. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e104730">Enter Saunder laughing.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104740" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104750">Sander, i'faith your a beast, I cry God heartily</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104760">Mercy, my heart's ready to run out of my belly with</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104770">Laughing, I stood behind the door all this while,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104780">And heard what you said to her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104790" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104800">Why didst thou think that I did not speak well to her?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104810" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104820">You spoke like an ass to her, I'll tell you what,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104830">And I had been there to have wood her, and had this</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104840">Cloak on that you have, chud have had her before she</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104850">Had gone a foot further, and you talk of woodcocks</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104860">With her, and I cannot tell you what. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104870" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e104880">Well sirrah, and yet thou seest I have got her for all this.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104890" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104900">I marry 'twas more by hap then any good cunning</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104910">I hope she'll make you one of the head men of the parish shortly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e104920" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104930">Well sirrah leave your jesting and go to Polidor's house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104940">The young gentleman that was here with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104950">And tell him the circumstance of all thou knowest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104960">Tell him on Sunday next we must be married,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104970">And if he ask thee whither I am gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104980">Tell him into the country to my house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e104990">And upon Sunday I'll be here again. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e105000">Ex. Ferando,</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105010" who="A13358-sander">
          <pb facs="8"/>
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105020">I warrant you master fear not me</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105030">For doing of my business. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105040">Now hang him that has not a livery coat</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105050">To slash it out and swash it out amongst the proudest</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105060">On them. Why look you now I'll scarce put up</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105070">Plain Saunder now at any of their hands, for and anybody</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105080">Have any thing to do with my master, straight</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105090">They come crouching upon me, I beseech you good m.</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105100">Saunder speak a good word for me, and then am I so</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105110">Stout and takes it upon me, and stands upon my pantofles</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105120">To them out of all cry, why I have a life like a giant</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105130">Now, but that my master hath such a pestilent mind</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105140">To a woman now a late, and I have a pretty wench</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105150">To my sister, and I had thought to have preferred my</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105160">Master to her, and that would have been a good</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105170">Deal in my way but that he's sped already. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e105180">Enter Polidor's boy.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105190" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105200">Friend, well met.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105210" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105220">'Zounds, friend well met. I hold my life he sees</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105230">Not my master's livery coat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105240">Plain friend hop of my thum, know you who we are. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105250" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105260">Trust me sir it is the use where I was born,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105270">To salute men after this manner, yet notwithstanding</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105280">If you be angry with me for calling of you friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105290">I am the more sorry for it, hoping the style</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105300">Of a fool will make you amends for all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105310" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105320">The slave is sorry for his fault, now we cannot be</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105330">Angry, well what's the matter that you would do with us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105340" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105350">Marry sir, I hear you pertain to signior Ferando. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105360" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105370">I and thou beest not blind thou mayst see, ecce signum, here.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105380" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105390">Shall I entreat you to do me a message to your master?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105400" who="A13358-sander">
          <pb facs="9"/>
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105410">Ay, it may be, and you tell us from whence you come.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105420" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105430">Marry sir I serve young Polidor your master's friend.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105440" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105450">Do you serve him, and what's your name?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105460" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105470">My name sirrah, I tell thee sirrah is called Catapie.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105480" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105490">Cake and pie, oh my teeth waters to have a piece of thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105500" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105510">Why slave wouldst thou eat me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105520" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105530">Eat thee, who would not eat cake and pie?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105540" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105550">Why villain my name is Catapie,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105560">But wilt thou tell me where thy master is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105570" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105580">Nay thou must first tell me where thy master is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105590">For I have good news for him, I can tell thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105600" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105610">Why see where he comes.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e105620">Enter Polidor, Aurelius and Valeria. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105630" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105640">Come sweet Aurelius my faithful friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105650">Now will we go to see those lovely dames</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105660">Richer in beauty than the orient pearl,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105670">Whiter than is the Alpine crystal mould,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105680">And far more lovely than the terrean plant,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105690">That blushing in the air turns to a stone. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105700">What Sander, what news with you? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105710" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105720">Marry sir my master sends you word</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105730">That you must come to his wedding tomorrow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105740" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105750">What, shall he be married then?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105760" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105770">Faith I, you think he stands as long about it as you do.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105780" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105790">Whither is thy master gone now?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105800" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105810">Marry he's gone to our house in the country,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105820">To make all things in a readiness against my new</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105830">Mistress comes thither, but he'll come again to morrow. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105840" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105850">This is suddenly dispatched belike,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105860">Well, sirrah boy, take Saunder in with you</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105870"><pb facs="9"/> and have him to the buttery presently. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105880" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e105890">I will sir: come Saunder. </p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e105900">Exit Saunder and the boy.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105910" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105920">Valeria as erst we did devise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105930">Take thou thy lute and go to Alfonso's house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105940">And say that Polidor sent thee thither. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e105950" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105960">I Valeria for he spoke to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105970">To help him to some cunning musician,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105980">To teach his eldest daughter on the lute,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e105990">And thou I know will fit his turn so well</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106000">As thou shalt get great favour at his hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106010">Begun Valeria and say I sent thee to him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106020" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Valer</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e106030">I will sir and stay your coming at Alfonso's house.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e106040">Exit Valeria</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106050" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106060">Now sweet Aurelius by this device</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106070">Shall we have leisure for to court our loves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106080">For whilst that she is learning on the lute,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106090">Her sisters may take time to steel abroad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106100">For otherwise she'll keep them both within,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106110">And make them work whilst she herself doth play,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106120">But come let's go unto Alfonso's house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106130">And see how Valeria and Kate agrees,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106140">I doubt his music scarce will please his scholar,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106150">But stay here comes Alfonso. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e106160">Enter Alfonso</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106170" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfonso.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106180">What m. Polidor you are well met,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106190">I thank you for the man you sent to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106200">A good musician I think he is,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106210">I have set my daughter and him together,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106220">But is this gentleman a friend of yours? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106230" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106240">He is, I pray you sir bid him welcome,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106250">He's a wealthy merchant's son of Cestus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106260" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfonso.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106270">Your welcome sir and if my house afford</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106280"><pb facs="10"/> you any thing that may content your mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106290">I pray you sir make bold with me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106300" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106310">I thank you sir, and if what I have got,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106320">By merchandise or travel on the seas,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106330">Satins or lawns or azure coloured silk,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106340">Or precious fiery pointed stones of Indy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106350">You shall command both them myself and all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106360" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106370">Thanks gentle sir, Polidor take him in,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106380">And bid him welcome to unto my house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106390">For thou I think must be my second son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106400">Ferando, Polidor dost thou not know</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106410">Must marry Kate, and tomorrow is the day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106420" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e106430">Such news I heard, and I came now to know.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106440" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106450">Polidor 'tis true, go let me alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106460">For I must see against the bridegroom come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106470">That all things be according to his mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106480">And so I'll leave you for an hour or two. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e106490">Exit.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106500" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106510">Come then Aurcleus come in with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106520">And we'll go sit a while and chat with them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106530">And after bring them forth to take the air. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e106540">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e106550">Then sly speaks.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106560" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e106570">Sim, when will the fool come again?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106580" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e106590">He'll come again my lord anon.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106600" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106610">Gis some more drink here, 'zounds where's</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106620">The tapster, here Sim eat some of these things. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106630" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e106640">So I do my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106650" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e106660">Here Sim, I drink to thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106670" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e106680">My lord here comes the players again,</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106690" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e106700">O brave, here's two fine gentlewomen.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e106710">Enter Valeria with a lute and Kate with him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106720" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Vale.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106730">The senseless trees by music have been moved</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106740">And at the sound of pleasant tuned strings,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106750"><pb facs="10"/> have savage beasts hung down their listening heads,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106760">As though they had been cast into a trance. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106770">Then it may be that she whom naught can please,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106780">With music's sound in time may be surprised,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106790">Come lovely mistress will you take your lute,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106800">And play the lesson that I taught you last? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106810" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106820">It is no matter whether I do or no,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106830">For trust me I take no great delight in it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106840" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Vale.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106850">I would sweet mistress that it lay in me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106860">To help you to that thing that's your delight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106870" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106880">In you with a pestilence, are you so kind? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106890">Then make a night cap of your fiddles case,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106900">To warm your head, and hide your filthy face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106910" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106920">If that sweet mistress were your heart's content,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106930">You should command a greater thing than that,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106940">Although it were ten times to my disgrace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106950" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106960">Your so kind 'twere pity you should be hanged,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e106970">And yet methinks the fool doth look asquint. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e106980" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e106990">Why mistress do you mock me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107000" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107010">No, but I mean to move thee.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107020" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107030">Well, will you play a little?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107040" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107050">Ay, give me the lute.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e107060">She plays.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107070" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107080">That stop was false, play it again.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107090" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107100">Then mend it thou, thou filthy ass.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107110" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107120">What, do you bid me kiss your arse?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107130" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107140">How now jack sauce, your a jolly mate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107150">Your best be still lest I cross your pate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107160">And make your music fly about your ears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107170">I'll make it and your foolish coxcomb meet. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107180">She offers to strike him with the lute. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107190" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107200">Hold mistress, souns will you break my lute?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107210" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107220">I on thy head, and if thou speak to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107230"><pb facs="11"/> there take it up and fiddle somewhere else,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107240">She throws it down. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107250">And see you come no more into this place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107260">Lest that I clap your fiddle on your face. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e107270">Ex. Kate.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107280" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107290">'Zounds, teach her to play upon the lute? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107300">The devil shall teach her first, I am glad she's gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107310">For I was ne'er so 'fraid in all my life,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107320">But that my lute should fly about mine ears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107330">My master shall teach her his self for me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107340">For I'll keep me far enough without her reach,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107350">For he and Polydor sent me before</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107360">To be with her and teach her on the lute,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107370">Whilst they did court the other gentlewomen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107380">And here methinks they come together. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e107390">Enter Aurelius, Polidor, Emelia, and Philena. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107400" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107410">How now Valeria, where's your mistress?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107420" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107430">At the vengeance I think and nowhere else.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107440" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107450">Why Valeria, will she not learn apace?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107460" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107470">Yes byr lady she has learned too much already,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107480">And that I had felt had I not spoke her fair,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107490">But she shall ne'er be learned for me again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107500" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107510">Well Valeria go to my chamber,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107520">And bear him company that came to day</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107530">From Cestus, where our aged father dwells. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e107540">Ex. Valeria.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107550" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107560">Come fair Emelia my lovely love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107570">Brighter than the burnished palace of the sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107580">The eyesight of the glorious firmament,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107590">In whose bright looks sparkles the radiant fire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107600">Wily Prometheus slily stole from Jove,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107610">Infusing breath, life, motion, soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107620">To every object stricken by thine eyes. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107630">O fair Emelia I pine for thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107640">And either must enjoy thy love, or die. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107650" who="A13358-emel">
          <pb facs="11"/>
          <speaker>Eme.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107660">Fie man, I know you will not die for love:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107670">Ah Polidor thou needst not to complain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107680">Eternal heaven sooner be dissolved,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107690">And all that pierceth Phoebus' silver eye,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107700">Before such hap befall to Polidor. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107710" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107720">Thanks fair Emelia for these sweet words,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107730">But what saith Phylena to her friend? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107740" who="A13358-philema">
          <speaker>Phyle.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107750">Why I am buying merchandise of him.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107760" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107770">Mistress you shall not need to buy of me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107780">For when I crossed the bubbling Canibey,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107790">And sailed along the crystal Hellespont,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107800">I filled my coffers of the wealthy mines,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107810">Where I did cause millions of labouring Moors</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107820">To undermine the caverns of the earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107830">To seek for strange and new found precious stones,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107840">And dive into the sea to gather pearl,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107850">As fair as Juno offered Priam's son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107860">And you shall take your liberal choice of all. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107870" who="A13358-philema">
          <speaker>Phyle.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107880">I thank you sir and would Phylena might</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107890">In any courtesy requite you so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107900">As she with willing heart could well bestow. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e107910">Enter Alfonso. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107920" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107930">How now daughters, is Ferando come?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107940" who="A13358-emel">
          <speaker>Eme.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107950">Not yet father, I wonder he stays so long.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107960" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e107970">And where's your sister that she is not here?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e107980" who="A13358-philema">
          <speaker>Phyle.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e107990">She is making of her ready father</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108000">To go to church and if that he were come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108010" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e108020">I warrant you he'll not be long away.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108030" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108040">Go daughters get you in, and bid your</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108050">Sister provide herself against that we do come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108060">And see you go to church along with us. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e108070">Exit Philena and Emelia. </stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108080">I marvel that Ferando comes not away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108090" who="A13358-polydore">
          <pb facs="12"/>
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108100">His tailor it may be hath been too slack,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108110">In his apparel which he means to wear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108120">For no question but some fantastic suits</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108130">He is determined to wear today,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108140">And richly powdered with precious stones,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108150">Spotted with liquid gold, thick set with pearl,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108160">And such he means shall be his wedding suits. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108170" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108180">I cared not I what cost he did bestow,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108190">In gold or silk, so he himself were here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108200">For I had rather lose a thousand crowns,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108210">Then that he should deceive us here to day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108220">But soft I think I see him come. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e108230">Enter Ferando basely attired, and a red cap on his head.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108240" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108250">Good-morrow father, Polidor well met,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108260">You wonder I know that I have stayed so long. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108270" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108280">I marry son, we were almost persuaded,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108290">That we should scarce have had our bridegroom here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108300">But say, why art thou thus basely attired? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108310" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108320">Thus richly father you should have said,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108330">For when my wife and I am married once,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108340">She's such a shrew, if we should once fall out,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108350">She'll pull my costly suits over mine ears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108360">And therefore am I thus attired awhile,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108370">For many things I tell you's in my head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108380">And none must know thereof but Kate and I,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108390">For we shall live like lambs and lions sure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108400">Nor lambs to lions never was so tame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108410">If once they lie within the lions paws</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108420">As Kate to me if we were married once,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108430">And therefore come let us to church presently. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108440" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108450">Fie Ferando not thus attired for shame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108460">Come to my chamber and there suit thyself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108470"><pb facs="12"/> of twenty suits that I did never were </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108480" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108490">Tush Polidor I have as many suits</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108500">Fantastic made to fit my humour so</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108510">As any in Athens and as richly wrought</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108520">As was the massy robe that late adorned,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108530">The stately legate of the Persian King,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108540">And this from them have I made choice to wear. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108550" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108560">I prithee Ferando let me entreat</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108570">Before thou ghost unto the church with us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108580">To put some other suit upon thy back. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108590" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108600">Not for the world if I might gain it so,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108610">And therefore take me thus or not at all,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e108620">Enter Kate. </stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108630">But soft see where my Kate doth come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108640">I must salute her: how fares my lovely Kate? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108650">What art thou ready? shall we go to church? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108660" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108670">Not I with one so mad, so basely tired,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108680">To marry such a filthy slavish groom,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108690">That as it seems sometimes is from his wits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108700">Or else he would not thus have come to us. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108710" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108720">Tush Kate these words adds greater love in me</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108730">And makes me think thee fairer then before,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108740">Sweet Kate the lovelier than Diana's purple robe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108750">Whiter than are the snowy Apenis,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108760">Or icy hair that grows on Boreas chin. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108770">Father I swear by Ibis' golden beak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108780">More fair and radiant is my bony Kate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108790">Than silver Zanthus when he doth embrace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108800">The ruddy simies at Ida's feet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108810">And care not thou sweet Kate how I be clad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108820">Thou shalt have garments wrought of Median silk,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108830">Enchased with precious jewels fetched from far,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108840">By Italian merchants that with Russian stems,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108850">Ploughs up huge sorrows in the terren main,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108860"><pb facs="13"/> and better far my lovely Kate shall wear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108870">Then come sweet love and let us to the church,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108880">For this I swear shall be my wedding suit. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e108890">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108900" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108910">Come gentlemen go along with us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108920">For thus do what we can he will be wed. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e108930">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e108940">Enter Polidor's boy and Sander. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108950" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e108960">Come hither sirrah boy.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e108970" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108980">Boy; o disgrace to my person, 'zounds boy</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e108990">Of your face, you have many boys with such</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109000">Pickadevantes I am sure, 'zounds would you</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109010">Not have a bloody nose for this? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109020" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109030">Come, come, I did but jest, where is that</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109040">Same piece of pie that I gave thee to keep. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109050" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109060">The pie? I you have more mind of your belly</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109070">Then to go see what your master does. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109080" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109090">Tush 'tis no matter man I prithee give it me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109100">I am very hungry I promise thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109110" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109120">Why you may take it and the devil burst</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109130">You with it, one cannot save a bit after supper,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109140">But you are always ready to munch it up. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109150" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109160">Why come man, we shall have good cheer</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109170">Anon at the bridehouse, for your masters gone to</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109180">Church to be married already, and there's</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109190">Such cheer as passeth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109200" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109210">O brave, I would I had eat no meat this week,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109220">For I have never a corner left in my belly</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109230">To put a venison pastry in, I think I shall burst myself</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109240">With eating, for I'll so cram me down the tarts</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109250">And the marchpanes, out of all cry. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109260" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109270">Ay, but how wilt thou do now thy master's</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109280">Married, thy mistress is such a devil, as she'll make</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109290">Thee forget thy eating quickly, she'll beat thee so. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109300" who="A13358-sander">
          <pb facs="13"/>
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109310">Let my master alone with her for that, for</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109320">He'll make her tame well enough ere long I warrant thee</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109330">For he's such a churl waxen now of late that and he be</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109340">Never so little angry he thumbs me out of all cry,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109350">But in my mind sirrah the youngest is a very</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109360">Pretty wench, and if I thought thy master would</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109370">Not have her I'd have a fling at her</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109380">Myself, I'll see soon whither 'twill be a match</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109390">Or no: and it will not I'll set the matter</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109400">Hard for myself I warrant thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109410" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109420">'Zounds you slave will you be a rival with</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109430">My master in his love, speak but such</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109440">Another word and I'll cut off one of thy legs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109450" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109460">O, cruel judgement, nay then sirrah,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109470">My tongue shall talk no more to you, marry my</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109480">Timber shall tell the trusty message of his master,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109490">Even on the very forehead on thee, thou abusious</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109500">Villain, therefore prepare thyself. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109510" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109520">Come hither thou imperfectious slave in</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109530">Regard of thy beggary, hold thee there's</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109540">Two shillings for thee? to pay for the</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109550">Healing of thy left leg which I mean</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109560">Furiously to invade or to maim at the least. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109570" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109580">O supernodical foul? well I'll take your</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109590">Two shillings but I'll bar striking at legs. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109600" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e109610">Not I, for I'll strike anywhere .</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109620" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109630">Here here take your two shillings again</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109640">I'll see thee hanged ere I'll fight with thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109650">I got a broken shin the other day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109660">'Tis not, whole yet and therefore I'll not fight</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109670">Come come why should we fall out? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109680" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109690">Well sirray your fair words hath something</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109700">Allayed my collar: I am content for this once</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109710">To put it up and be friends with thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109720"><pb facs="14"/> but soft see where they come all from church,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109730">Belike they be married already. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e109740">Enter Ferando and Kate and Alfonso and Polidor and Emelia and Aurelius and Philema. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109750" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109760">Father farewell, my Kate and I must home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109770">Sirrah go make ready my horse presently. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109780" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109790">Your horse! what son I hope you do but jest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109800">I am sure you will not go so suddenly. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109810" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109820">Let him go or tarry I am resolved to stay,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109830">And not to travel on my wedding day. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109840" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109850">Tut Kate I tell thee we must needs go home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109860">Villain hast thou saddled my horse? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109870" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e109880">Which horse, your curtal?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109890" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109900">'Zounds you slave stand you prating here? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109910">Saddle the bay gelding for your mistress. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109920" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e109930">Not for me: for I'll not go.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109940" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109950">The ostler will not let me have him, you owe ten pence </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e109960">For his meat, and 6 pence for stuffing my mistress saddle. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109970" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e109980">Here villain go pay him straight.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e109990" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e110000">Shall I give them another peck of lavender.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110010" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e110020">Out slave and bring them presently to the door</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110030" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e110040">Why son I hope at least you'll dine with us.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110050" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e110060">I pray you master let's stay till dinner be done.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110070" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110080">'Zounds villain art thou here yet? </l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e110090">Ex. Sander.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110100">Come Kate our dinner is provided at home. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110110" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110120">But not for me, for here I mean to dine. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110130">I'll have my will in this as well as you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110140">Though you in madding mood would leave your friends</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110150">Despite of you I'll tarry with them still. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110160" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110170">I Kate so thou shalt but at some other time,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110180">Whenas thy sisters here shall be espoused,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110190">Than thou and I will keep our wedding day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110200">In better sort than now we can provide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110210"><pb facs="14"/> for here I promise thee before them all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110220">We will ere long return to them again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110230">Come Kate stand not on terms we will away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110240">This is my day, tomorrow thou shalt rule,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110250">And I will do whatever thou commands. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110260">Gentlemen farewell, we'll take our leaves,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110270">It will be late before that we come home. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e110280">Exit Ferando and Kate.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110290" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e110300">Farewell Ferando since you will be gone.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110310" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e110320">So mad a couple did I never see.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110330" who="A13358-emel">
          <speaker>Emel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e110340">They're even as well matched as I would wish.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110350" who="A13358-philema">
          <speaker>Phile.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110360">And yet I hardly think that he can tame her. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110370">For when he has done she will do what she list. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110380" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e110390">Her manhood then is good I do believe.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110400" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110410">Aurelius or else I miss my mark,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110420">Her tongue will walk if she doth hold her hands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110430">I am in doubt ere half a month be past</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110440">He'll curse the priest that married him so soon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110450">And yet it may be she will be reclaimed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110460">For she is very patient groan of late. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110470" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110480">God hold it that it may continue still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110490">I would be loath that they should disagree,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110500">But he I hope will hold her in a while. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110510" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110520">Within this two days I will ride to him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110530">And see how lovingly they do agree. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110540" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110550">Now Aurelius what say you to this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110560">What have you sent to Cestus as you said,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110570">To certify your father of your love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110580">For I would gladly he would like of it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110590">And if he be the man you tell to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110600">I guess he is a merchant of great wealth. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110610">And I have seen him oft at Athens here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110620">And for his sake assure thee thou art welcome. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110630" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e110640">And so to me whilst Polidor doth live.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110650" who="A13358-aurel">
          <pb facs="15"/>
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110660">I find it so right worthy gentlemen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110670">And of what worth your friendship I esteem,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110680">I leave censure of your several thoughts,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110690">But for requital of your favours past,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110700">Rests yet behind, which when occasion serves</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110710">I vow shall be remembered to the full,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110720">And for my father's coming to this place,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110730">I do expect within this week at most. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110740" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110750">Enough Aurelius? but we forget</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110760">Our marriage dinner now the bride is gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110770">Come let us see what there they left behind. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e110780">Exit omnes</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e110790">Enter sanders with two or three serving men</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110800" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110810">Come sirs provide all things as fast as you can,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110820">For my masters hard at hand and my new mistress</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110830">And all, and he sent me before to see all things ready. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110840" who="A13358-tom">
          <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110850">Welcome home Sander sirrah how looks our</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110860">New mistress they say she's a plaguy shrew. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110870" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110880">I and that thou shalt find I can tell thee and thou</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110890">Dost not please her well, why my master</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110900">Has such a do with her as it passeth and he's even</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110910">Like a madman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110920" who="A13358-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e110930">Why Sander what dos he say.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e110940" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110950">Why I'll tell you what: when they should</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110960">Go to church to be married he puts on an old</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110970">Jerkin and a pair of canvas breeches down to the</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110980">Small of his leg and a red cap on his head and he</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e110990">Looks as thou wilt burst thyself with laughing</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111000">When thou seest him: he's e'en as good as a</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111010">Fool for me: and then when they should go to dinner</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111020">He made me saddle the horse and away he came. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111030">And never tarried for dinner and therefore you had best</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111040">Get supper ready against they come, for</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111050"><pb facs="15"/> they be hard at hand I am sure by this time. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111060" who="A13358-tom">
          <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e111070">'Zounds see where they be all ready.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e111080">Enter Ferando and Kate.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111090" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111100">Now welcome Kate: where is these villains</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111110">Here, what? not supper yet upon the board:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111120">Nor table spread nor nothing done at all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111130">Where's that villain that I sent before. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111140" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e111150">Now, adsum, sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111160" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111170">Come hither you villain I'll cut your nose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111180">You rogue: help me of with my boots: wilt please</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111190">You to lay the cloth? 'zounds the villain</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111200">Hurts my foot? pull easily I say; yet again. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e111210">He beats them all. They cover the board and fetch in the meat.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111220">'Zounds? burned and scorched who dressed this meat? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111230" who="A13358-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111240">Forsooth John cook. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111250">He throws down the table and meat</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111260">And all, and beats them. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111270" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111280">Go you villains bring you me such meat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111290">Out of my sight I say and bear it hence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111300">Come Kate we'll have other meat provided,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111310">Is there a fire in my chamber sir? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111320" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e111330">I forsooth.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e111340">Exit Ferando and Kate.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e111350">Manent serving-men and eat up all the meat.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111360" who="A13358-tom">
          <speaker>Tom.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111370">'Zounds? I think of my conscience my masters</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111380">Mad since he was married. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111390" who="A13358-will">
          <speaker>Will.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111400">I laughed what a box he gave Sander</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111410">For pulling of his boots. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e111420">Enter Ferando again.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111430" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e111440">I hurt his foot for the nonce man.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111450" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111460">Did you so you damned villain. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e111470">He beats them all out again.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111480">This humour must I hold me to a while,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111490"><pb facs="16"/> to bridle and hold back my headstrong wife,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111500">With curbs of hunger: ease: and want of sleep,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111510">Nor sleep nor meat shall she enjoy tonight ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111520">I'll mew her up as men do mew their hawks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111530">And make her gently come unto the lure,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111540">Were she as stubborn or as full of strength</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111550">As were the Thracian horse Alcides tamed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111560">That King Egeus fed with flesh of men,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111570">Yet would I pull her down and make her come</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111580">As hungry hawks do fly unto there lure. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e111590">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e111600">Enter Aurelius and Valeria. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111610" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111620">Valeria attend: I have a lovely love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111630">As bright as is the heaven crystalline,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111640">As fair as is the milk white way of Jove,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111650">As chaste as Phoebe in her summer sports,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111660">As soft and tender as the azure down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111670">That circles Citherea's silver doves. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111680">Her do I mean to make my lovely bride,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111690">And in her bed to breathe the sweet content,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111700">That I thou knowest long time have aimed at. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111710">Now Valeria it rests in thee to help</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111720">To compass this, that I might gain my love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111730">Which easily thou mayst perform at will,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111740">If that the merchant which thou toldst me of,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111750">Will as he said go to Alfonso's house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111760">And say he is my father, and there with all</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111770">Pass over certain deeds of land to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111780">That I thereby may gain my hearts desire,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111790">And he is promised reward of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111800" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111810">Fear not my lord I'll fetch him straight to you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111820">For he'll do any thing that you command,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111830">But tell me my lord, is Ferando married then? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111840" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111850">He is: and Polidor shortly shall be wed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111860">And he means to tame his wife erelong. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111870" who="A13358-valeria">
          <pb facs="16"/>
          <speaker>Vale.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e111880">He says so.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111890" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e111900">Faith he's gone unto the taming school.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111910" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e111920">The taming school  why is there such a place?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111930" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e111940">I: and Ferando is the master of the school.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111950" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e111960">That's rare: but what decorum dos he use?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e111970" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111980">Faith I know not: but by some odd device</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e111990">Or other, but come Valeria I long to see the man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112000">By whom we must comprise our plotted drift,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112010">That I may tell him what we have to do. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112020" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e112030">Then come my lord and I will bring you to him straight.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112040" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e112050">Agreed, then let's go.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e112060">Exeunt</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e112070">Enter Sander and his mistress. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112080" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e112090">Come mistress.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112100" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112110">Sander I prithee help me to some meat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112120">I am so faint that I can scarcely stand. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112130" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112140">I marry mistress but you know my master</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112150">Has given me a charge that you must eat nothing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112160">But that which he himself giveth you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112170" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e112180">Why man thy master needs never know it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112190" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112200">You say true indeed: why look you mistress,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112210">What say you to a piece of beef and mustard now? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112220" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e112230">Why I say 'tis excellent meat, canst thou help me to some?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112240" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112250">Ay, I could help you to some but that</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112260">I doubt the mustard is too choleric for you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112270">But what say you to a sheep's head and garlic? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112280" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e112290">Why any thing, I care not what it be.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112300" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112310">I but the garlic I doubt will make your breath</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112320">Stink, and then my master will course me for letting</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112330">You eat it: but what say you to a fat capon? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112340" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112350">That's meat for a King sweet Sander help</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112360">Me to some of it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112370" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112380">Nay byr lady then 'tis too dear for us, we must</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112390"><pb facs="17"/> not meddle with the King's meat. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112400" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112410">Out villain dost thou mock me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112420">Take that for thy sauciness. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e112430">She beats him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112440" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112450">'Zounds are you so light fingered with a murrain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112460">I'll keep you fasting for it this two days. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112470" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112480">I tell thee villain I'll tear the flesh of</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112490">Thy face and eat it and thou prates to me thus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112500" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e112510">Here comes my master now he'll course you.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e112520">Enter Ferando with a piece of meat upon his dagger's point and Polidor with him.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112530" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112540">See here Kate I have provided meat for thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112550">Here take it: what is't not worthy thanks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112560">Go sirrah? take it away again you shall be</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112570">Thankful for the next you have. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112580" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e112590">Why I thank you for it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112600" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112610">Nay now 'tis not worth a pin go sirray and take</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112620">It hence I say. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112630" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112640">Yes sir I'll carry it hence: master let her</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112650">Have none for she can fight as hungry as she is. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112660" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112670">I pray you sir let it stand, for I'll eat</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112680">Some with her myself. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112690" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e112700">Well sirrah set it down again.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112710" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112720">Nay nay I pray you let him take it hence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112730">And keep it for your own diet for I'll none,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112740">I'll ne'er be beholding to you for your meat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112750">I tell thee flatly here unto thee thy teeth</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112760">Thou shalt not keep me nor feed me as thou list,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112770">For I will home again unto my father's house. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112780" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112790">Ay, when you're meek and gentle but not</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112800">Before, I know your stomach is not yet come down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112810">Therefore no marvel thou canst not eat,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112820">And I will go unto your father's house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112830">Come Polidor let us go in again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112840"><pb facs="17"/> and Kate come in with us I know ere long,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112850">That thou and I shall lovingly agree. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e112860">Ex. omnes</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e112870">Enter Aurelius Valeria and Phylotus the merchant. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112880" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112890">Now senior Phylotus, we will go</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112900">Unto Alfonso's house, and be sure you say</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112910">As I did tell you, concerning the man</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112920">That dwells in Cestus, whose son I said I was,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112930">For you do very much resemble him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112940">And fear not: you may be bold to speak your mind. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112950" who="A13358-phylotus">
          <speaker>Phylo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112960">I warrant you sir take you no care,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112970">I'll use myself so cunning in the cause,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e112980">As you shall soon enjoy your heart's delight. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e112990" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113000">Thanks sweet Phylotus, then stay you here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113010">And I will go and fetch him hither straight. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113020">Ho, signior Alfonso: a word with you. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e113030">Enter Alfonso. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113040" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113050">Who's there? what Aurelius what's the matter</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113060">That you stand so like a stranger at the door? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113070" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113080">My father sir is newly come to town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113090">And I have brought him here to speak with you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113100">Concerning those matters that I told you of,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113110">And he can certify you of the truth. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113120" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e113130">Is this your father? you are welcome sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113140" who="A13358-phylotus">
          <speaker>Phylo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113150">Thanks Alfonso, for that's your name I guess,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113160">I understand my son hath set his mind</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113170">And bent his liking to your daughter's love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113180">And for because he is my only son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113190">And I would gladly that he should do well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113200">I tell you sir, I not mislike his choice,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113210">If you agree to give him your consent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113220">He shall have living to maintain his state,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113230"><pb facs="18"/> three hundred pounds a year I will assure</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113240">To him and to his heirs, and if they do join,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113250">And knit themselves in holy wedlock band,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113260">A thousand massy in gets of pure gold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113270">And twice as many bars of silver plate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113280">I freely give him, and in writing straight,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113290">I will confirm what I have said in words. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113300" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113310">Trust me I must commend your liberal mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113320">And loving care you bear unto your son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113330">And here I give him freely my consent,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113340">As for my daughter I think he knows her mind,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113350">And I will in large her dowry for your sake. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113360">And solemnise with joy your nuptial rites,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113370">But is this gentleman of Cestus too? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113380" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113390">He is the Duke of Cestus thrice renowned son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113400">Who for the love his honour bears to me:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113410">Hath thus accompanied me to this place. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113420" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfonso.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113430">You wear to blame you told me not before,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113440">Pardon me my lord, for if I had known</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113450">Your honour had been here in place with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113460">I would have done my duty to your honour. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113470" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113480">Thanks good Alfonso: but I did come to see</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113490">Whenas these marriage rites should be performed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113500">And if in these nuptials you vouchsafe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113510">To honour thus the prince of Cestus' friend,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113520">In celebration of his spousal rites,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113530">He shall remain a lasting friend to you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113540">What says Aurelius father. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113550" who="A13358-phylotus">
          <speaker>Phylo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113560">I humbly thank your honour good my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113570">And ere we part before your honour here:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113580">Shall articles of such content be drawn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113590">As twixt our houses and posterities,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113600">Eternally this league of peace shall last,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113610">Inviolate and pure on either part:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113620" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <pb facs="18"/>
          <speaker>Alfonso.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113630">With all my heart, and if your honour please,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113640">To walk along with us unto my house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113650">We will confirm these leagues of lasting love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113660" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e113670">Come then Aurelius I will go with you.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e113680">Ex. omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e113690">Enter Ferando and Kate and Sander. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113700" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113710">Master the haberdasher has brought my</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113720">Mistress home her cap here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113730" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e113740">Come hither sirrah: what have you there?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113750" who="A13358-habar">
          <speaker>Habar.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e113760">A velvet cap sir and it please you.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113770" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e113780">Who spoke for it? didst thou Kate? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113790" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113800">What if I did, come hither sirrah, give me</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113810">The cap, I'll see if it will fit me. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e113820">She sets it one her head.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113830" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113840">O monstrous: why it becomes thee not,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113850">Let me see it Kate: here sirrah take it hence,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113860">This cap is out of fashion quite. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113870" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113880">The fashion is good enough: belike you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113890">Mean to make a fool of me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113900" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113910">Why true he means to make a fool of thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113920">To have thee put on such a curtailed cap,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113930">Sirrah begone with it. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e113940">Enter the tailor with a gown.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113950" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e113960">Here is the tailor too with my mistress gown.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e113970" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113980">Let me see it tailor: what with cuts and jags? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e113990">'Zounds you villain, thou hast spoilt the gown. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114000" who="A13358-tailor">
          <speaker>Tailor.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114010">Why sir I made it as your man gave me direction,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114020">You may read the note here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114030" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114040">Come hither sirrah: tailor read the note.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114050" who="A13358-tailor">
          <speaker>Tailor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114060">Item a fair round compassed cape.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114070" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114080">I that's true.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114090" who="A13358-tailor">
          <speaker>Tailor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114100">And a large trunk sleeve.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114110" who="A13358-sander">
          <pb facs="19"/>
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114120">That's a lie master, I said two trunk sleeves.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114130" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114140">Well sir go forward.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114150" who="A13358-tailor">
          <speaker>Tailor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114160">Item a loose bodied gown.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114170" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114180">Master if ever I said loose body's gown,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114190">Sew me in a seam and beat me to death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114200">With a bottom of brown thread. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114210" who="A13358-tailor">
          <speaker>Tailor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114220">I made it as the note bade me.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114230" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114240">I say the note lies in his throat and thou too,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114250">And thou sayst it. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114260" who="A13358-tailor">
          <speaker>Tailor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114270">Nay nay ne'er be so hot sirrah, for I fear you not.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114280" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114290">Dost thou hear tailor, thou hast braved</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114300">Many men: brave not me. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114310">Thou'st fast many men. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114320" who="A13358-tailor">
          <speaker>Tailor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114330">Well sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114340" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114350">Face not me I'll neither be fast nor braved</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114360">At thy hands I can tell thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114370" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114380">Come come I like the fashion of it well enough,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114390">Here's more ado then needs I'll have it,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114400">And if you do not like it hide your eyes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114410">I think I shall have nothing by your will. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114420" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114430">Go I say and take it up for your master's use.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114440" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114450">'Zounds: villain not for thy life touch it not,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114460">'Zounds, take up my mistress gown to his</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114470">Master's use? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114480" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114490">Well sir: what's your conceit of it.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114500" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114510">I have a deeper conceit in it than you</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114520">Think for, take up my mistress gown</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114530">To his master's use? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114540" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114550">Tailor come hither: for this time take it</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114560">Hence again, and I'll content thee for thy pains. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114570" who="A13358-tailor">
          <speaker>Tailor.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114580">I thank you sir.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e114590">Exit Taylor.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114600" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114610">Come Kate we now will go see thy father's house</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114620">Even in these honest mean abiliments,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114630">Our purses shall be rich, our garments plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114640"><pb facs="19"/> to shroud our bodies from the winter rage,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114650">And that's enough, what should we care for more. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114660">Thy sisters Kate tomorrow must be wed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114670">And I have promised them thou shouldst be there</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114680">The morning is well up let's haste away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114690">It will be nine o'clock ere we come there. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114700" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114710">Nine o'clock , why 'tis already passed two</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114720">In the afternoon by all the clocks in the town. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114730" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114740">I say 'tis but nine o'clock in the morning.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114750" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e114760">I say 'tis tow o'clock in the afternoon .</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114770" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114780">It shall be nine then ere we go to your fathers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114790">Come back again, we will not go today. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114800">Nothing but crossing of me still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114810">I'll have you say as I do ere you go. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e114820">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e114830">Enter Polidor, Emelia, Aurelius and Philema. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114840" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114850">Fair Emelia summers sun bright Queen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114860">Brighter of hue then is the burning clime,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114870">Where Phoebus in his bright aequator sits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114880">Creating gold and precious minerals,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114890">What would Emelia do? if I were forced</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114900">To leave fair Athens and to range the world. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114910" who="A13358-emel">
          <speaker>Eme.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114920">Should thou assay to scale the seat of love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114930">Mounting the subtle airy regions</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114940">Or be snatched up as erst was Ganymede,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114950">Love should give wings unto my swift desires,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114960">And prune my thoughts that I would follow thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114970">Or fall and perish as did Icarus. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e114980" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e114990">Sweetly resolved fair Emelia,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115000">But would Phylema say as much to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115010">If I should ask a question now of thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115020">What if the Duke of Cestus only son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115030">Which came with me unto your father's house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115040">Should seek to git Phylemas love from me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115050"><pb facs="20"/> and make thee Duchess of that stately town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115060">Wouldst thou not then forsake me for his love? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115070" who="A13358-philema">
          <speaker>Phyle.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115080">Not for great neptune, no nor Jove himself,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115090">Will Phylema leave Aurelius' love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115100">Could he install me empres of the world,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115110">Or make me Queen and guideress of the heavens,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115120">Yet would I not exchange thy love for his,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115130">Thy company is poor Philemas heaven,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115140">And without thee, heaven were hell to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115150" who="A13358-emel">
          <speaker>Eme.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115160">And should my love as erst did Hercules</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115170">Attempt to pass the burning vaults of hell,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115180">I would with piteous looks and pleasing words,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115190">As once did Orpheus with his harmony,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115200">And ravishing sound of his melodious harp,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115210">Entreat grim Pluto and of him obtain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115220">That thou mightest go and safe return again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115230" who="A13358-philema">
          <speaker>Phyle.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115240">And should my love as erst Leander did,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115250">Attempt to swim the boiling Hellespont</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115260">For Heros love: no towers of brass should hold</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115270">But I would follow thee through those raging floods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115280">With locks dishevered and my breast all bare,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115290">With bent knees upon Abidas shore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115300">I would with smoky sighs and brinish tears,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115310">Importune Neptune and the watery gods,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115320">To send a guard of silver scaled dolphins,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115330">With sounding Tritons to be our convoy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115340">And to transport us safe unto the shore,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115350">Whilst I would hang about thy lovely neck,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115360">Redoubling kiss on kiss upon thy cheeks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115370">And with our pastime still the swelling waves. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115380" who="A13358-emel">
          <speaker>Eme.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115390">Should Polidor as great Achilles did,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115400">Only employ himself to follow arms,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115410">Like to the warlike Amazonian Queen,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115420">Pentheselea Hector's paramour,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115430"><pb facs="20"/> who foiled the bloody Pyrrhus murderous Greek,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115440">I'll thrust myself amongst the thickest throngs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115450">And with my utmost force assist my love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115460" who="A13358-philema">
          <speaker>Phyle.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115470">Let Eole storm: be mild and quiet thou,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115480">Let Neptune swell, be Aurelius calm and pleased,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115490">I care not I, betide what may betide,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115500">Let fates and fortune do the worst they can,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115510">I reck them not: they not discord with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115520">Whilst that my love and I do well agree </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115530" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115540">Sweet Phylema beauties mineral,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115550">From whence the sun exhales his glorious shine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115560">And clad the heaven in thy reflected rays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115570">And now my liefest love, the time draws nigh,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115580">That Hymen mounted in his saffron robe,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115590">Must with his torches weight upon thy train,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115600">As Helen's brothers on the horned moon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115610">Now Juno to thy number shall I add,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115620">The fairest bride that ever merchant had. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115630" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115640">Come fair Emelia the priest is gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115650">And at the church your father and the rest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115660">Do stay to see our marriage rites performed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115670">And knit in sight of heaven this Gordian knot. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115680">That teeth of fretting time may ne'er untwist,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115690">Then come fair love and gratulate with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115700">This days content and sweet solemnity. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e115710">Ex. omnes</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115720" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e115730">Sim must they be married now?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115740" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e115750">I my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e115760">Enter Ferando and Kate and Sander. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115770" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e115780">Look Sim the fool is come again now.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115790" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115800">Sirrah go fetch our horses forth, and bring</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115810">Them to the back gate presently. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115820" who="A13358-sander">
          <speaker>San.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e115830">I will sir I warrant you,</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e115840">Exit Sander.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115850" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e115860">Come Kate the moon shines clear tonight methinks.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115870" who="A13358-kate">
          <pb facs="21"/>
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115880">The moon? why husband you are deceived</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115890">It is the sun. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115900" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115910">Yet again: come back again it shall be</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e115920">The moon ere we come at your fathers. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115930" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e115940">Why I'll say as you say it is the moon.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115950" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e115960">Jesus save the glorious moon.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115970" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e115980">Jesus save the glorious moon.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e115990" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116000">I am glad Kate your stomach is come down,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116010">I know it well thou knowest it is the sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116020">But I did try to see if thou wouldst speak,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116030">And cross me now as thou hast done before,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116040">And trust me Kate hadst thou not named the moon,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116050">We had gone back again as sure as death,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116060">But soft who's this that's coming here. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e116070">Enter the Duke of Cestus alone.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116080" who="A13358-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116090">Thus all alone from Cestus am I come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116100">And left my princely court and noble train,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116110">To come to Athens, and in this disguise,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116120">To see what course my son Aurelius takes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116130">But stay, here's some it may be travels thither,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116140">Good sir can you direct me the way to Athens? </l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e116150">Ferando speaks to the old man.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116160">Fair lovely maid young and affable,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116170">More clear of hue and far more beautiful,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116180">Then precious sardonix or purple rocks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116190">Of amethysts or glistering hyacinth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116200">More amiable far than is the plain,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116210">Where glistering Cepherus in silver bowers,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116220">Gazeth upon the giant Andromede,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116230">Sweet Kate entertain this lovely woman. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116240" who="A13358-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e116250">I think the man is mad he calls me a woman.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116260" who="A13358-kate">
          <pb facs="21"/>
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116270">Fair lovely lady, bright and crystalline,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116280">Bewteous and stately as the eye-trained bird,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116290">As glorious as the morning washed with dew,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116300">Within whose eyes she takes her dawning beams,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116310">And golden summer sleeps upon thy cheeks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116320">Wrap up thy radiations in some cloud,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116330">Lest that thy beauty make this stately town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116340">Inhabitable like the burning zone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116350">With sweet reflections of thy lovely face. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116360" who="A13358-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116370">What is she mad to? or is my shape transformed </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116380">That both of them persuade me I am a woman,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116390">But they are mad sure, and therefore I'll begone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116400">And leave their companies for fear of harm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116410">And unto Athens haste to seek my son. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e116420">Exit Duke.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116430" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116440">Why so Kate this was friendly done of thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116450">And kindly too: why thus must we two live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116460">One mind, one heart, and one content for both,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116470">This good old man dos think that we are mad,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116480">And glad he is I am sure, that he is gone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116490">But come sweet Kate for we will after him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116500">And now persuade him to his shape again. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e116510">Ex. omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e116520">Enter Alfonso and Phylotus and Valeria, Polidor, Emelia, Aurelius and Phylema. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116530" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116540">Come lovely sons your marriage rites performed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116550">Let's hie us home to see what cheer we have,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116560">I wonder that Ferando and his wife</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116570">Comes not to see this great solemnity. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116580" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116590">No marvel if Ferando be away,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116600">His wife I think hath troubled so his wits,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116610"><pb facs="22"/> that he remains at home to keep them warm,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116620">For forward wedlock as the prover be says,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116630">Hath brought him to his night cap long ago. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116640" who="A13358-phylotus">
          <speaker>Phylo.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116650">But Polidor let my son and you take heed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116660">That Ferando say not ere long as much to you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116670">And now Alfonso more to show my love,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116680">If unto Cestus you do send your ships,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116690">Myself will fraught them with Arabian silks,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116700">Rich Afric spices arras counter poines,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116710">Musk Cassia: sweet smelling ambergris,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116720">Pearl, coral  crystal, jet, and ivory,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116730">To gratulate the favours of my son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116740">And friendly love that you have shone to him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116750" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Vale.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116760">And for to honour him and this fair bride,</l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e116770">Enter the Duke of Cestus. </stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116780">I'll yearly send you from my father's court,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116790">Chests of refined sugar severally,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116800">Ten ton of Tunis wine, sucket sweet drudges,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116810">To celebrate and solemnise this day,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116820">And custom free your merchants shall converse:</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116830">And interchange the profits of your land,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116840">Sending you gold for brass, silver for lead,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116850">Casses of silk for packs of will and cloth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116860">To bind this friendship and confirm this league. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116870" who="A13358-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116880">I am glad sir that you would be so frank,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116890">Are you become the Duke of Cestus' son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116900">And revels with my treasure in the town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116910">Base villain that thus dishonourest me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116920" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116930">'Zounds it is the Duke what shall I do,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116940">Dishonour thee why, knowest thou what thou sayest? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116950" who="A13358-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116960">Here's no villain: he will not know me now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e116970">But what say you? have you forgotten me too? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e116980" who="A13358-phylotus">
          <speaker>Phylo.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e116990">Why sir, are you acquainted with my son?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117000" who="A13358-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117010">With thy son? no trust me if he be thine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117020"><pb facs="22"/> I pray you sir who am I? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117030" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117040">Pardon me father: humbly on my knees,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117050">I do entreat your grace to hear me speak. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117060" who="A13358-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117070">Peace villain: lay hands on them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117080">And send them to prison straight. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e117090">Phylotus and Valeria runs away. Then sly speaks.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117100" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e117110">I say we'll have no sending to prison.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117120" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e117130">My lord this is but the play, their but in jest.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117140" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117150">I tell thee Sim we'll have no sending,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117160">To prison that's flat: why Sim am not I don Christo vary? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117170">Therefore I say they shall not go to prison. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117180" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117190">No more they shall not my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117200">They be run away. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117210" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117220">Are they run away Sim? that's well,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117230">Then gis some more drink, and let them play again. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117240" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e117250">Here my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e117260">Sly drinks and then falls asleep .</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117270" who="A13358-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117280">Ah treacherous boy that durst presume,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117290">To wed thyself without thy father's leave,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117300">I swear by fair Cinthia's burning rays,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117310">By Merops head and by seven mouthed Nile,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117320">Had I but known ere thou hadst wedded her,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117330">Were in thy breast the world's immortal soul,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117340">This angry sword should rip thy hateful chest,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117350">And hewed thee smaller than the Libyan sands,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117360">Turn hence thy face: o cruel impious boy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117370">Alfonso I did not think you would presume,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117380">To mach your daughter with my princely house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117390">And ne'er make me acquainted with the cause </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117400" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117410">My lord by heavens I swear unto your grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117420">I knew none other but Valeria your man,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117430">Had been the Duke of Cestus noble son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117440"><pb facs="23"/> nor did my daughter I dare swear for her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117450" who="A13358-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117460">That damned villain that hath deluded me </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117470">Whom I did send guide unto my son,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117480">O that my furious force could cleave the earth,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117490">That I might muster bands of hellish fiends,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117500">To rack his heart and tear his impious soul. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117510">The ceaseless turning of celestial orbs,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117520">Kindles not greater flames in flitting air,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117530">Then passionate anguish of my raging breast,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117540" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117550">Then let my death sweet father end your grief,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117560">For I it is that thus have wrought your woes,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117570">Then be revenged on me for here I swear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117580">That they are innocent of what I did,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117590">O had I charge to cut of Hydra's head,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117600">To make the topless Alps a champion field,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117610">To kill untamed monsters with my sword,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117620">To travel daily in the hottest sun,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117630">And watch in winter when the nights be cold,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117640">I would with gladness undertake them all,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117650">And think the pain but pleasure that I felt,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117660">So that my noble father at my return,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117670">Would but forget and pardon my offence,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117680" who="A13358-philema">
          <speaker>Phile.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117690">Let me entreat your grace upon my knees,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117700">To pardon him and let my death discharge</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117710">The heavy wrath your grace hath vowed 'gainst him. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117720" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117730">And good my lord let us entreat your grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117740">To purge your stomach of this melancholy,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117750">Taint not your princely mind with grief my lord,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117760">But pardon and forgive these lovers faults,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117770">That kneeling crave your gracious favour here. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117780" who="A13358-emel">
          <speaker>Emel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117790">Great prince of Cestus, let a woman's words,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117800">Entreat a pardon in your lordly breast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117810">Both for your princely son, and us my lord. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117820" who="A13358-duke">
          <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117830">Aurelius stand up I pardon thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117840"><pb facs="23"/> I see that virtue will have enemies,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117850">And fortune will be thwarting honour still,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117860">And you fair virgin too I am content,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117870">To accept you for my daughter since 'tis done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117880">And see you princely used in cestus court. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117890" who="A13358-philema">
          <speaker>Phyle.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117900">Thanks good my lord and I no longer live,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117910">Than I obey and honour you in all:</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117920" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117930">Let me give thanks unto your royal grace,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117940">For this great honour done to me and mine,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117950">And if your grace will walk unto my house,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117960">I will in humblest manner I can, show</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117970">The eternal service I do owe your grace. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e117980" who="A13358-duke">
          <speaker>Duke</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e117990">Thanks good Alfonso: but I came alone,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118000">And not as did beseem the Cestian Duke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118010">Nor would I have it known within the town,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118020">That I was here and thus without my train,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118030">But as I came alone so will I go,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118040">And leave my son to solemnise his feast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118050">And ere't be long I'll come again to you,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118060">And do him honour as beseems the son</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118070">Of mighty Jerobell the Cestian Duke,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118080">Till when I'll leave you, farewell Aurelius. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118090" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e118100">Not yet my lord, I'll bring you to your ship.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e118110">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e118120">Sly sleeps.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118130" who="A13358-lord">
          <speaker>Lord.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118140">Who's within there? come hither sirs my lords</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118150">Asleep again: go take him easily up,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118160">And put him in his one apparel again,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118170">And lay him in the place where we did find him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118180">Just underneath the alehouse side below,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118190">But see you wake him not in any case. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118200" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e118210">It shall be done my lord come help to bear him hence,</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e118220">Exit.</stage>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e118230"><pb facs="24"/>Enter Ferando, Aurelius and Polidor and his boy and Valeria and Sander. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118240" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118250">Come gentlemen now that suppers done,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118260">How shall we spend the time till we go to bed? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118270" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118280">Faith if you will in trial of our wives,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118290">Who will come sownest at their husbands call. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118300" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118310">Nay then Ferando he must needs sit out,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118320">For he may call I think till he be weary,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118330">Before his wife will come before she list. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118340" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118350">'Tis well for you that have such gentle wives,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118360">Yet in this trial will I not sit out,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118370">It may be Kate will come as soon as yours. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118380" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e118390">My wife comes soonest for a hundred pound.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118400" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118410">I take it: I'll lay as much to yours,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118420">That my wife comes as soon as I do send. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118430" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e118440">How now Ferando you dare not lay belike.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118450" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118460">Why true I dare not lay indeed;</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118470">But how, so little money on so sure a thing,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118480">A hundred pound: why I have laid as much</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118490">Upon my dog, in running at a deer,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118500">She shall not come so far for such a trifle,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118510">But will you lay five hundred marks with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118520">And whose wife soonest comes when he doth call,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118530">And shows herself most loving unto him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118540">Let him enjoy the wager I have laid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118550">Now what say you? dare you adventure thus? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118560" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118570">I wear it a thousand pounds I durst presume</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118580">On my wife's love: and I will lay with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e118590">Enter Alfonso. </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118600" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118610">How now sons what in conference so hard,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118620">May I without offence, know whereabouts . </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118630" who="A13358-aurel">
          <pb facs="24"/>
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118640">Faith father a weighty cause about our wives</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118650">Five hundred marks already we have laid,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118660">And he whose wife doth show most love to him,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118670">He must enjoy the wager to himself. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118680" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118690">Why then Ferando he is sure to lose,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118700">I promise thee son thy wife will hardly come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118710">And therefore I would not wish thee lay so much. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118720" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118730">Tush father were it ten times more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118740">I durst adventure on my lovely Kate,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118750">But if I lose I'll pay, and so shall you. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118760" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e118770">Upon mine honour if I lose I'll pay.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118780" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e118790">And so will I upon my faith I vow.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118800" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e118810">Then sit we down and let us send for them.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118820" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e118830">I promise thee Ferando I am afraid thou wilt lose</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118840" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118850">I'll send for my wife first, Valeria</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118860">Go bid your mistress come to me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118870" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e118880">I will my lord.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e118890">Exit Valeria.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118900" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118910">Now for my hundred pound. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118920">Would any lay ten hundred more with me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118930">I know I should obtain it by her love. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118940" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e118950">I pray God you have not laid too much already.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e118960" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118970">Trust me Ferando I am sure you have,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e118980">For you I dare presume have lost it all. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e118990">Enter Valeria again.</stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119000">Now sirrah what says your mistress? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119010" who="A13358-valeria">
          <speaker>Val.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119020">She is something busy but she'll come anon.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119030" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119040">Why so, did not I tell you this before,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119050">She is busy and cannot come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119060" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119070">I pray God your wife send you so good an answer</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119080">She may be busy yet she says she'll come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119090" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119100">Well well: Polidor send you for your wife.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119110" who="A13358-polydore">
          <pb facs="25"/>
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119120">Agreed boy desire your mistress to come hither.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119130" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119140">I will sir</p>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e119150">Ex. boy.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119160" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119170">I so so he desires her to come.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119180" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119190">Polidor I dare presume for thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119200">I think thy wife will not deny to come. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119210">And I do marvel much Aurelius,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119220">That your wife came not when you sent for her. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e119230">Enter the boy again </stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119240" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119250">Now where's your mistress?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119260" who="A13358-boy">
          <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119270">She bade me tell you that she will not come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119280">And you have any business, you must come to her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119290" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119300">O monstrous intolerable presumption,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119310">Worse than a blazing star, or snow at midsummer,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119320">Earthquakes or any thing unseasonable,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119330">She will not come: but he must come to her. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119340" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119350">Well sir I pray you let's hear what</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119360">Answer your wife will make. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119370" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119380">Sirrah, command your mistress to come</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119390">To me presently. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e119400">Exit Sander.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119410" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119420">I think my wife for all she did not come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119430">Will prove most kind for now I have no fear,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119440">For I am sure Ferando's wife, she will not come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119450" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119460">The moors the pity: than I must lose. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e119470">Enter Kate and Sander. </stage>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119480">But I have won for see where Kate doth come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119490" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119500">Sweet husband did you send for me?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119510" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119520">I did my love I sent for thee to come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119530">Come hither Kate, what's that upon thy head</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119540" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119550">Nothing husband but my cap I think.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119560" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119570">Pull it of and tread it under thy feet,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119580">'Tis foolish I will not have thee wear it. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e119590">She takes of her cap and treads on it.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119600" who="A13358-polydore">
          <pb facs="25"/>
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119610">O wonderful metamorphosis.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119620" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119630">This is a wonder: almost passed belief.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119640" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119650">This is a token of her true love to me,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119660">And yet I'll try her further you shall see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119670">Come hither Kate where are thy sisters. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119680" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119690">They be sitting in the bridal chamber.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119700" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119710">Fetch them hither and if they will not come,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119720">Bring them perforce and make them come with thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119730" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119740">I will.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119750" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119760">I promise thee Ferando I would have sworn,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119770">Thy wife would ne'er have done so much for thee. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119780" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119790">But you shall see she will do more than this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119800">For see where she brings her sisters forth by force. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e119810">Enter Kate thrusting Phylema and Emelia before her, and makes them come unto their husbands call.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119820" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119830">See husband I have brought them both.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119840" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119850">'Tis well done Kate. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119860" who="A13358-emel">
          <speaker>Eme.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119870">I sure and like a loving piece, your worthy</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119880">To have great praise for this attempt. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119890" who="A13358-philema">
          <speaker>Phyle.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119900">I for making a fool of herself and us.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119910" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119920">Beshrew thee Phylema, thou hast</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119930">Lost me a hundred pound tonight . </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119940">For I did lay that thou wouldst first have come. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119950" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e119960">But thou Emelia hast lost me a great deal more.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e119970" who="A13358-emel">
          <speaker>Eme.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119980">You might have kept it better than,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e119990">Who bade you lay? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120000" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120010">Now lovely Kate before there husbands here,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120020">I prithee tell unto these headstrong women,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120030">What duty wives do owe unto their husbands. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120040" who="A13358-kate">
          <speaker>Kate.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120050">Then you that live thus by your pompered wills,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120060">Now list to me and mark what I shall say,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120070">Th'eternal power that with his only breath,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120080">Shall cause this end and this beginning frame,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120090"><pb facs="26"/> not in time, nor before time, but with time, confused,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120100">For all the course of years, of ages, months,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120110">Of seasons temperate, of days and hours,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120120">Are tuned and stopped, by measure of his hand,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120130">The first world was, a form, without a form,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120140">A heap confused a mixture all deformed,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120150">A gulf of gulfs, a body bodilesses,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120160">Where all the elements were orderless,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120170">Before the great commander of the world </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120180">The King of Kings the glorious god of heaven </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120190">Who in six days did frame his heavenly work,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120200">And made all things to stand in perfect course. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120210">Then to his image he did make a man. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120220">Old Adam and from his side asleep ,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120230">A rib was taken, of which the lord did make,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120240">The woe of man so termed by Adam then,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120250">Woman for that, by her came sin to us,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120260">And for her sin was Adam doomed to die,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120270">As Sara to her husband, so should we,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120280">Obey them, love them, keep, and nourish them,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120290">If they by any means do want our helps,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120300">Laying our hands under their feet to tread,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120310">If that by that we, might procure there ease,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120320">And for a precedent I'll first begin,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120330">And lay my hand under my husband's feet</l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e120340">She lays her hand under her husband's feet.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120350" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120360">Enough sweet, the wager thou hast won,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120370">And they I am sure cannot deny the same. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120380" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120390">I Ferando the wager thou hast won,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120400">And for to show thee how I am pleased in this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120410">A hundred pounds I freely give thee more,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120420">Another dowry for another daughter,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120430">For she is not the same she was before. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120440" who="A13358-ferando">
          <speaker>Feran.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120450">Thanks sweet father, gentlemen goodnight</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120460"><pb facs="26"/> for Kate and I will leave you forto night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120470">'Tis Kate and I am wed, and you are sped. </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120480">And so farewell for we will to our beds. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e120490">Exit Ferando and Kate and Sander.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120500" who="A13358-alfonso">
          <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e120510">Now Aurelius what say you to this?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120520" who="A13358-aurel">
          <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120530">Believe me father I rejoice to see,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120540">Ferando and his wife so lovingly agree. </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e120550">Exit Aurelius and Phylema and Alfonso and Valeria.</stage>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120560" who="A13358-emel">
          <speaker>Eme.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e120570">How now Polidor in a dump, what sayst thou man?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120580" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e120590">I say thou art a shrew.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120600" who="A13358-emel">
          <speaker>Eme.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e120610">That's better than a sheep.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120620" who="A13358-polydore">
          <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120630">Well since 'tis done let it go, come let's in. </l>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e120640">Exit Polidor and Emelia.</stage>
          <stage xml:id="A13358-e120650">Then enter two bearing of sly in his<lb xml:id="A13358-e120660"/> own apparel again, and leaves him<lb xml:id="A13358-e120670"/> where they found him, and then goes out. <lb xml:id="A13358-e120680"/>then enter the tapster. </stage>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120690" who="A13358-tapster">
          <speaker>Tapster.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120700">Now that the darksome night is overpast,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120710">And dawning day appears in crystal sky,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120720">Now must I haste abroad: but soft who's this? </l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120730">What sly o wondrous hath he lain here all night,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120740">I'll wake him, I think he's starved by this,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120750">But that his belly was so stuffed with ale,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120760">What how sly, awake for shame. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120770" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120780">Sim gis some more wine: what's all the</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120790">Players gone: am not I a lord? </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120800" who="A13358-tapster">
          <speaker>Tapster.</speaker>
          <p xml:id="A13358-e120810">A lord with a murrain: come art thou drunken still?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120820" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120830">Who's this? Tapster, o lord sirrah, I have had</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120840">The bravest dream tonight , that ever thou</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120850">Hardest in all thy life. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120860" who="A13358-tapster">
          <pb facs="27"/>
          <speaker>Tapster.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120870">I marry but you had best get you home,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120880">For your wife will course you for dreaming here tonight ,</l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120890" who="A13358-sly">
          <speaker>Sly</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120900">Will she? I know now how to tame a shrew,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120910">I dreamt upon it all this night till now,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120920">And thou hast waked me out of the best dream</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120930">That ever I had in my life, but I'll to my</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120940">Wife presently and tame her too</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120950">And if she anger me. </l>
        </sp>
        <sp xml:id="A13358-e120960" who="A13358-tapster">
          <speaker>Tapster.</speaker>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120970">Nay tarry sly for I'll go home with thee,</l>
          <l xml:id="A13358-e120980">And hear the rest that thou hast dreamt tonight . </l>
        </sp>
        <stage xml:id="A13358-e120990">Exeunt omnes.</stage>
        <trailer xml:id="A13358-e121000">Finis.</trailer>
        <pb facs="27"/>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="machine-generated_castlist"><list n="A13358"><item xml:id="A13358-ferando" n="80">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-ferando</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">80</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-sander" n="59">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-sander</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">59</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-polydore" n="47">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-polydore</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">47</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-kate" n="44">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-kate</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">44</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-aurel" n="42">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-aurel</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">42</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-alfonso" n="39">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-alfonso</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">39</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-lord" n="28">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-lord</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">28</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-boy" n="27">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-boy</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">27</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-sly" n="26">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-sly</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">26</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-valeria" n="24">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-valeria</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">24</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-emel" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-emel</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-duke" n="11">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-duke</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">11</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-philema" n="10">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-philema</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">10</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-tailor" n="8">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-tailor</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">8</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-tapster" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-tapster</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-phylotus" n="5">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-phylotus</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">5</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-tom" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-tom</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-will" n="4">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-will</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">4</seg>
  </item>
<item xml:id="A13358-one" n="2">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-one</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">2</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-habar" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-habar</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-other" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-other</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-messenger" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-messenger</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  <item xml:id="A13358-servant" n="1">
    <seg type="character_name">A13358-servant</seg>
    <seg type="speech_count">1</seg>
  </item>
  </list>
  </div>
      <div type="textual_notes">
        <head>Textual Notes</head>
        <p>The textual notes below aim at making textual corrections  readable in their immediate context and facilitating access to the source text. A five-dit number preceded by 'A' or 'B' represents an EEBO-TCP filenumber.  A notation like "6-b-2890" means "look for EEBO page image 6 of that text, word 289 on the right side of the double-page image." That reference is followed by the corrupt reading. A black dot stands for an unidentified letter, a black square for an unidentified punctuation mark, a diamond for a missing word, and the ellipsis for a short span of undefined length. The corrected reading is displayed as a kewyord in context.

</p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>

